<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Plutus</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">William James Hickie</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>William James Hickie (1853). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg011.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">CARIO (servant of Chremylus)</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="2">CHORUS OF COUNTRY-PEOPLE.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="3">PLUTUS (the god of riches).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="4">"THE Plutus, according to an indubitable tradition, was twice brought upon the stage; first, in the year 408, B. c., in the Archon ship of Diodes, and then, in the year 388, B. c., in the Archonship of Antipater. In its second representation, the Plutus contended successfully against the " Lacedæmonians” of Nicochares, the " Admetus " of Aristomenes, the " Adonis " of Nicophon, and the “ Pasiphaë ” of Alcæus. The Greek Scholiasts frequently assert that our present text is the first Plutus. This view is in decided con tradiction to the play itself, which contains numerous allusions to the times of the Archon Antipater. The opinion of later philologers, which has been sanctioned by the great authority of Hemsterhuis, represents our present text as a riffaccimento of the two editions. But recent investigations have completely refuted this position. We therefore may confidently assume that the Plutus we have be fore us is just in the state in which Aristophanes in the latter years of his life brought it on the stage." Droysen. See the Scholiast on vs. 173. The argument is simply this:—Chremylus, a poor, but just man, consults the Delphic oracle about his son, whether he ought not to be instructed in injustice and knavery, and the other arts whereby worldly men acquired riches. The god answered him nothing plainly, but merely told him he was to follow whomsoever he should first light upon on leaving the temple. The first person he meets with is a blind old man. This turns out to be Plutus, the god of riches, whom Jupiter had deprived of his eyesight in order that he might no longer distinguish between the just and the un just. By the help of Æsculapius, Plutus is restored to the use of his eyes. Whereupon all the just are made rich, and the unjust reduced to indigence. In an artistic point of view, the Plutus must rank as by far the lowest of the existing works of Aristophanes. In its absence of personal interest, and its sparingness of personal satire, it approximates more nearly to a whimsical allegory than a proper comedy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.15"/>
          <p n="5">CARIO. How troublesome1 a thing it is, 0 Jupiter and ye gods, to be the slave of a crazy master ! For if the servant should happen to have given the best advice, and it should seem fit to his master not to do this, it must be that the ser vant share the evils;2 for fortune suffers not the natural owner to be master of his person, but the purchaser. And so much for this.3 But Loxias 4 who prophesies from his tripod of beaten gold I censure with this just censure, because being a physician and a clever soothsayer, as they say, he has sent away my master melancholy-mad,5 who is following behind6 a blind man, acting contrary to what it became him to do ; for we who see lead the blind ; whereas he follows him, and compels me besides ; and that too without even7 answering a syllableS at all. Therefore it is not possible for me to hold my tongue, unless you tell me, master, for what in the world we are following this man, but I'll give you trouble; for you will not beat1 me while I wear the chaplet.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.15"/>
          <p n="6">CHR. No, by Jove, but if you trouble me in any way, I'll do it when I have taken away your chaplet, that you may grieve the more.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.24"/>
          <p n="7">CA. Nonsense ! for I will not cease until you tell me who in the world this is; for I ask it, being exceedingly well2 dis posed to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.24"/>
          <p n="8">CHR. Well then, I will not hide it from you, for I do believe you to be the most faithful of my domestics, and-the arrantest thief.3 I, though a religious and just man, was unprosperous and poor.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.24"/>
          <p n="9">CA. In truth I know it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.24"/>
          <p n="10">CHR. While others, sacrilegious persons, demagogues, and informers, and villains, were rich.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.32"/>
          <p n="11">CHR. So I went to the god to consult him, thinking that my own life,5 unhappy man, had now nearly been wasted away, but to ask about my son,6 who is my only one,7 if he ought to change his habits and be knavish, unjust, nothing good ;1 since I thought this very thing to be advantageous for life.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.40"/>
          <p n="12">CA. What then did Phoebus proclaim from amongst his chaplets ? 2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.40"/>
          <p n="13">CHR. You shall hear: for the god told me this plainly; whomsoever I should first meet with3 on going out,4 him he bid med never let go, but prevail on him to accompany me home.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.40"/>
          <p n="14">CA. And whom then did you first meet with ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.40"/>
          <p n="15">CA. Then did you not understand the meaning of the god, when it directed you, 0 most stupid, in the plainest terms, to educate6 your son after the fashion of the country ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.48"/>
          <p n="16">Cup. By what7 do you judge of this ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.48"/>
          <p n="17">CA. It is evident that even a blind man fancies he knows this,8 that it is very advantageous to practise no virtue in these times.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.48"/>
          <p n="18">CHR. It is not possible that the oracle inclines to this,9 but to something else of greater moment. But if this fellow tell us who in the world he is, and on account of what, and in want of what he came hither with us, we might under stand what our oracle10 means.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="19">CA. (to Plutus). Come now, do you declare yourself, who you are, before I do what comes next.1 You must be very quick about speaking.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="20">PLU. A plague take you ! 2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="21">CA. (to Chrem.). Do you understand whom he professes himself to be ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="22">CHR. He says this to you, not to me ; for you inquire of him uncouthly and roughly. But [to Plutus] if you take any pleasure in the manners of a man of honour, tell me !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="23">PLU. Go, hang yourself!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <p n="24">CA. Take3 the man, and omen of the god.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="25">CHR. By Ceres, you certainly shall not any longer escape4 unpunished!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="26">CA. For unless you will tell us, I will kill you, you wretch, in a wretched way.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="27">PLU. Good sirs, depart from me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="28">CA. Well now, what I say, is best, master: I’ll kill this fel low in a most wretched way; for I will set him up on7 some precipice and leave him and go away, that he may fall and break his neck.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="29">CHR. Well, up with him quickly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="30">CHR. Will you not tell us then ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="31">PLU. But if you learn who I am, I well know that you will do me some mischief, and not let me go.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="32">CHR. By the gods will we, if you wish it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="33">PLU. Then first let me go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="34">CHR. Lo ! we let you go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="35">PLU. Hear now; for, as it seems, I must speak what I was2 prepared to conceal: I am Plutus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="36">CHR. 0 most abominable of all men! did you hold your tongue then, you Plutus ?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="37">CA. You Plutus, so wretchedly circumstanced ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="38">Cup. 0 Phœbus Apollo, and ye gods and dæmons, and Jove, what do you say ? Are you really he ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="39">PLU. His very self.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="40">CHR. Whence then, tell us, come you so squalid ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="41">PLU. I come from the house of Patrocles,5 who has not washed himself since he was born.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="42">CHR. But how did you suffer this mishap?6 Declare it to me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="43">PLU. Jupiter treated me in this manner through envy to wards mankind. For when I was a boy,7 I threatened that I would1 go to the just, and wise, and well-behaved alone. So he made me blind, that I might not distinguish any of these. So much does he envy the good.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="44">CHR. And yet he is honoured by the good and the just alone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="45">CHR. Come, what then ? if you were to recover your sight again, just as formerly,3 would you now shun the wicked ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="46">CHR. But would you go to the just ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="47">PiU. Most assuredly; for I havenot seen4 them for a long time.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="48">CHR. And no wonder too; for neither have I, whosee.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="49">PLU. Now let me go; for now you know all about me.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="50">CHR. No, by Jove! but so much the more will we keep hold of you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="51">PLU. Did I not say that you would7 cause me trouble ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="52">CHR. And do you, I beseech you, comply, and do not abandon me; for you will never8 find a man better in his morals than I, if you search. No, by Jove ! for there is no other 9 save me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="53">PLU. They all say this: but when they actually get pos session of me, and become wealthy, they absolutely exceed all bounds in their wickedness.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="54">CHR. So it is : yet all are not wicked.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="55">PLU. No, by Jove, not all, but all without exception.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="56">CA. You shall suffer2 for it severely.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="57">CHR. And that you may know how many blessings you will have, if you stay with us, give your attention,' that you may hear. For I think, I think,-with god's permission3 it shall be spoken,-that I shall free you from this4 blindness' having made you see.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="58">PLU. By no means do this; for I do not wish to recover my sight again.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.114"/>
          <p n="59">CHR. W fiat do you say ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.114"/>
          <p n="60">CA. This fellow is a born5 miserable.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.114"/>
          <p n="61">PLU. I know indeed that Jupiter would destroy me, if he were to hear of the follies of these men.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.114"/>
          <p n="62">CHR. But does he not do this now, who suffers you to go about stumbling ? 7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.114"/>
          <p n="63">PLU. I know not; but I dread him exceedingly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <p n="64">CHR. What really, 0 you most cowardly of all deities ?1 For do you suppose the sovereignty2 of Jove and his thunder bolts would be worth a three-obol piece,3 if you should reco ver your sight, if it were but for a short time ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <p n="65">PLU. Ah ! say not so, you wretch !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <p n="66">CHR. Be quiet ;4 for I will demonstrate you to be farmore powerful than Jupiter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <p n="67">CHR. Aye, by heaven. For, for example,6 through whom does Jupiter rule the gods ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="68">CA. Through money, for he has most of it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="69">CHR. Come, who then is it that supplies 7 him with this ? CA. This person here.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="70">CHR. And through whom do men sacrifice to him ? is it not through him ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="71">CA. And, by Jupiter, they pray openly8 to be rich.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="72">CHR. Is not he then the cause, and might he not easily put an end to this, if he wished ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="73">PLU. Why so ?9 why pray ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <p n="74">CHR. Because 10 no man would any longer sacrifice, either ox or barley-cake, or any thing else whatever, if you were not willing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.140"/>
          <p n="75">CHR. How? it is not possible for him to purchase it, I weed, unless you yourself be present1 and give him the money i so that you alone will put down the power of Jove, if he annoy you in any way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.140"/>
          <p n="76">PLU. What do you say ? do they sacrifice to him through me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.140"/>
          <p n="77">CHR. Certainly. And, by Jupiter, if there be any thing magnificent and beautiful or agreeable to men,2 it is through you : for all things are subservient3 to riches.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.140"/>
          <p n="78">CA. I, in truth, have become a slave on account of a tri fling sum of money,4 because I was not equally rich as others.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.149"/>
          <p n="79">CHR. And they say that the Corinthian courtesans, when any poor man tries them, do not even pay any attention to him, but if a rich man try, that they immediately turn any thing to 5 him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.157"/>
          <p n="80">CA. And they say that the boys do this very thing, not for their lovers', but the money's sake.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.157"/>
          <p n="81">CHR. Not the better sort, but the catamites; for the better sort do not ask for money.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.157"/>
          <p n="82">CHR. One asks for a good horse, another hunting dogs.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.157"/>
          <p n="83">CA. For, perhaps, being ashamed to ask for money, they gloss overs their wickedness by a false name.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.165"/>
          <p n="84">CHR. And all arts and clever contrivances among men have been invented through you. For one of them sits and makes shoes ; and some other one is a smithy and another a carpen ter ; another is a goldsmith, having received gold from you; another, by Jove, steals clothes; another is a housebreaker; another is a fuller;2 another washes fleeces; another is a tanner; another sells onions; another, having been detected as an adulterer, is depillated through you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.165"/>
          <p n="85">PLU. Ah me, miserable ! this has been unknown to me this long while.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.173"/>
          <p n="86">CA. And does not the Great King pride himself through him ? And is not the Assembly held through him ? But how? -do you not man the triremes ? tell me. And does not he support the mercenaries in Corinth ?3 And will not Pamphi lus4 suffer through him? And will not the “Needle-seller”5 along with Pamphilus ? And does not Agyrrhius 6 fart through him ? And [to Plutus] does not Philepsius1 relate fables on account of you ? And is not the alliance2 with the Egyptians through you. And does not Lais, through you, love Phi lonides ?3 And the tower of Timotheus4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="87">CHR. May it fall upon you. And [to Plutus] are not all our affairs transacted through you? For you alone5 are the cause of all, both of our miseries and our blessings, be well assured.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="88">CA. At any rate, in wars also, they always conquer, upon whom he only sits down.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="89">PLU. Am I able, single as I am, to effect so many things ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="90">CHR. And, by Jupiter, far more than these; so that no one 7 has ever at any time been sated of you. For of all the rest there is1 a satiety. Of love,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="91">CHR. Of manly virtue,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="92">CHR. Of military command,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="93">CA. Of lentil-broth.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.194"/>
          <p n="94">CHR. But of you3 no one has ever at anytime been sated. But if any one get thirteen talents, so much the more does he desire to get sixteen. And if he accomplish this, he wishes for forty, or he says his life is not worth4 living.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.194"/>
          <p n="95">PLU. In truth you appear to me to speak exceedingly well; but one thing only I fear.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.194"/>
          <p n="96">CHR. Tell us, what about.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.194"/>
          <p n="97">PLU. How I shall become master of this power which5 you say I have.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.202"/>
          <p n="98">CHR. Yes, by Jove, you shall! But even all say1 that wealth is a most2 timid thing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.202"/>
          <p n="99">PLU. By no means; but some housebreaker has calumni ated me. For having once crept into the 3 house, he was not able to get any thing, having found every thing locked up ; so then he called my forethought cowardice.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.202"/>
          <p n="100">CHR. Let nothing trouble you4 now ; for if you be a zeal ous man yourself in the business, I'll make you more sharp- sighted than Lynceus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="101">PLU. How then will you be able to do this, mortal as you are ? CHR. I have some good hope from what Phoebus himself told me, having shaken the Pythian laurel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="102">PLU. And was he then privy to this ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="103">CHR. Do not be at all concerned, my good sir ; for I, be well assured of this, will accomplish this myself, even if I must die for it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="104">CA. And I too, if you wish it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="105">CHR. And many others5 will be our allies, as many as had no bread, though they were just.”</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.220"/>
          <p n="106">PLU. Deary'meT you tell us of miserable allies.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.220"/>
          <p n="107">CHR. Not so, if they become rich again as before. But do you [to Cario] go and run quickly</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.220"/>
          <p n="108">CA. What am I to do? Tell me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.220"/>
          <p n="109">CHR. Call my fellow-labourers,—and you will probably find them working hard in the fields,—that each, being pre sent here, may share an equal portion with us of this Plutus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.220"/>
          <p n="110">CA. Well now, I am going. But let some one of the servants from within take and carry in this small bit of meat.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.229"/>
          <p n="111">CHR. (taking the meat). This shall be my care: but run quickly.1 [Exit Cario. ] And do you, 0 Plutus, most ex cellent of all gods, go in this way with me ; for this is the house which you must to-day fill with riches, by fair means or by foul.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.237"/>
          <p n="112">PLU. But, by the gods, I am exceedingly loth to be always going into other people's houses. For I never at any time got any good from it.4 For if I chance to go into the house of a miser, he immediately buries5 me deep in the earth : and if any good man, his friend, come to him asking to get some small sum of money, he denies that he has ever at any time even seen me. But if I chance to go into the house of a mad fellow, I am exposed to harlots and dice and driven out of doors naked in a moment of time.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.245"/>
          <p n="113">CHR. Yes; for you never at any time met with7 a moder ate man. But I am somehow always of this character.8 For I both take pleasure in saving, as never man did, and again in spending,9 whenever there is occasion for it. But let us go in; for I wish both my wife to see you10 and my only son, whom I love most of all-next to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.253"/>
          <p n="114">CHR. For why should one not tell the truth to you?1 [Exeunt Chremylus and Plutus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.253"/>
          <p n="115">CA. Oh you who have often eaten of the same thyme2 with my master, his friends, and fellow-tribesmen, and lovers of labour, come, make haste, hurry, since the time docs not ad mit delay, but it is at the very crisis at which you ought to be present3 and lend your aid.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.253"/>
          <p n="116">CHORUS OF COUNTRY-PEOPLE.4 Don't you see then that we have been actively hastening this long while, as is reason able those should who are now feeble old men ? But you, perhaps, expect that I should run, before you even tell me this,5 on what account your master has called me hither.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.261"/>
          <p n="117">CA. Have I not then, I ween, been telling you this long while ? It is you yourself that don't hear. For my master says that you shall all of you live pleasantly, freed from your dreary and unpleasant mode of life.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.261"/>
          <p n="118">CiO. But what, pray, and whence, is this thing which he speaks of?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.261"/>
          <p n="119">CA. He has come hither with a certain old man, ye wretches, who is filthy, crooked, miserable, wrinkled, bald, and tooth less ; and, by heaven, I think be is circumcised,6 too.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="120">CHO. 0 you who have announced golden tidings,7 how say you? tell me again! For you plainly show that he is come with a heap of money.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="121">CA. Nay, rather, with1 a heap of the ills of age.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="122">CHO. Do you expect, after humbugging us, to get off un punished, and that, too, when I have a staff ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="123">CA. Why, do you consider me to be altogether such a man by nature in all respects, and do you think that I would say2 nothing true ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="124">CiO. How haughty the rascals is ! Your legs are crying out, “Oh ! Oh ! ” longing for the stocks and fetters.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.277"/>
          <p n="125">CA. But are you not for going, when now your letter 4 has assigned5 you to administer justice in the tomb, and Charon 6 gives you your ticket?7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.277"/>
          <p n="126">CHO. Split you!8 What an impudent fellow you are, and arrant knave by nature, who9 humbug us, and have not yet had the patience to tell us on what account your master has called me hither, who,10 after labouring much, have come hither readily, though we had no leisure, passing over 11 many roots of thyme.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.277"/>
          <p n="127">f CA. Well then, I will not conceal it any longer ; for, sirs, my master has come with Plutus, who will make you rich.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.286"/>
          <p n="128">CHO. Why, is it really possible for us all to be rich ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.286"/>
          <p n="129">CA. Nay, rather, by the gods, all Midases,12 if you get ass's ears.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.286"/>
          <p n="130">CHO. How I am delighted and gladdened, and wish to dance for joy, if you are really speaking I this truly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.290"/>
          <p n="131">CA. Well now, I should like2 to lead you, imitating3 the Cyclops, threttanelo ! and moving thus to and fro with my feet. But come, my children, crying out frequently, and bleating4 the strains5 of sheep and stinking goats, follow me lewdly, and you shall breakfast like6 goats.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.290"/>
          <p n="132">CiO. And we, on the other hand, bleating, when we have caught you, this Cyclops, threttanelo! dirty, with a wallet and dewy, wild potherbs, having a drunken head-ache, lead ing your sheep, and carelessly asleep some where, will take a great lighted, sharp stake and try to blind you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.302"/>
          <p n="133">CA. And I will imitate in all her ways Circe, who mixed up the drugs, who once in Corinth1 persuaded the companions )f Philonides, as if they were boars, to eat kneaded dung; while the herself kneaded it for them. But do you, grunting for lelight, follow, like swine, your mother.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.302"/>
          <p n="134">CiO. Therefore we, having caught you, the Circe, who nixed up the drugs and bewitched and defiled our com panions, imitating for delight the son of Laertes, will hang rou up2 by your testicles, and besmear your nostrils with lung, like a goat's; while you, gaping like3 Aristyllus, shall ay, " Follow, like swine, your mother."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.316"/>
          <p n="135">CA. But come now, do you now have done with your jests ,nd turn yourselves into another shape;4 while I should like low to go unknown to my master and take some bread and neat and eat it, and so afterwards to join in the work. [Exit Cario. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.322"/>
          <p n="136">CHREMYLUS (entering and addressing the Chorus). To bid you “ hail,”5 my fellow-tribesmen, is now old-fashioned and obsolete ; so I “ embrace you," because you have come readily ,nd eagerly, and not tardily. But see that you be7 my co-adjutors in the rest as well, and truly preservers of the god.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.322"/>
          <p n="137">CHO. Be of good courage ! for you shall think I look down right martial.1 For it would be absurd,2 if we constantly jostle one another in the Assembly for the sake of three obols, while I were to yield up Plutus himself to any one to take away.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.332"/>
          <p n="138">CHR. Well now, I see also Blepsidemus here approaching: and 'tis plain 4 from his gait and haste that he has heard some thing of the affair. [Enter Blepsidemus. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.332"/>
          <p n="139">BL. (talking to himself). What then can the affair be? whence and in what way has Chremylus suddenly become rich ? I don't believe it: and yet, by Hercules, there was much talk among those who sat in the barbers' shops,5 that the man has suddenly become wealthy. But this very thing is marvellous to me, that he, being well off, sends for his friends. In truth he does not6 do a thing fashionablein the country.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.340"/>
          <p n="140">CHR. (aside). Well then, by the gods, I '11 tell him, without concealing any thing.7 0 Blepsidemus, we are better off than yesterday, so that it is permitted you to share; for you are of the number of my friends.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="141">BL. But have you really become1 rich, as people say ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="142">CHR. Nay, but I shall be very soon, if God please ;2 for there is-there is some hazard in the affair.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="143">BL. Of what sort ? 3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="144">BL. Tell me quickly 4 what in the world you mean.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="145">CHR.—that, if we succeed, we shall be always well off;6 but if we be foiled, we shall be utterly undone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="146">BL. This load7 looks bad, and does not please me. For your suddenly becoming so excessively rich, and, again, your fearing, is in character with a man 8 who has done nothing good.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.348"/>
          <p n="147">Cup. How nothing good ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.356"/>
          <p n="148">BL. If, by Jove, you have come from thence, having stolen my silver or gold from the god, and then, perhaps, repent.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.356"/>
          <p n="149">CHR. 0 Apollo, averter of evil! not I, by Jove !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.356"/>
          <p n="150">BL. Cease talking nonsense, my good sir; for I know it for certain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.356"/>
          <p n="151">CHR. Do you suspect nothing of the kind 9 of me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.356"/>
          <p n="152">BL. Alas! how there is absolutely no good10 in any one mut all are slaves11 of gain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="153">CHR. By Ceres, you certainly do not appear to me to be in your right senses.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="154">BL. (aside). How much he has altered 1 from the charac ter 2 he formerly had !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="155">CHR. By heaven, fellow, you are mad !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="156">BL. (aside). But not even does his glance itself keep3 in its place, but is like 4 to one who has committed some villany.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="157">CUR. I know what you are croaking5 about: you seek to get a share, as if I had stolen something.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="158">BL. I seek to get a share ? of what ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.364"/>
          <p n="159">CHR. Whereas 6 it is not of such nature, but different.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="160">BL. Have you not stolen, but snatched it away ?8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="161">CHR. You are possessed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="162">BL. But have you, in truth, not even defrauded any one ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="163">CHR. Not I, indeed !9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="164">BL. 0 Hercules, come, whither can10 one turn himself? for you will not tell the truth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="165">CHR. For you accuse me before you know my case.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="166">BL. My good friend, I will settle this for you at a very trifling expense, before the city hear of it, by stopping the orators' mouths2 with small coin.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="167">CHR. And verily, by the gods, methinks you would3 in a friendly way lay out three minæ and set down twelve.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="168">BL. I see a certain person4 who will sit at the Bema, holding the suppliant's bought with his children and his wife; and who will not differ at all, not even in any way,6 from the Heraclidæ of Pamphilus.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="169">CHR. Not so, you wretch, but on the contrary,8 Iwill cause the good alone, and the clever and discreet, to become rich.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="170">BL. What doyou say ?have you stolen so very much ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="171">CHR. Ah me, what miseries ! you will destroy me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="172">BL. Nay, rather, you will destroy yourself, as it seems to me.9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="173">CHR. Certainly not; for I have got Plutus, you sorry wretch.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="174">BL. You, Plutus ? what1 Plutus ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="175">CHR. The god himself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="176">BL. Why, where is he ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="177">BL. Go to the devil! Plutus at your house ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="178">CHR. Yes, by the gods !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="179">BL. Are you speaking truth ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="180">CHR. Yea, by Neptune !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="181">BL. Do you mean the sea Neptune ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="182">CHR. Aye, and t'other Neptune, if there be any other.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="183">BL. Then are you not for sending him round to us also, your friends ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="184">CHR. The affair is not yet come to this point.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="185">BL. What do you say ? not to the sharing3 point—eh ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="186">CHR. No, by Jupiter ! for we must first</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="187">CHR. Cause him to see..</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="188">BL. Whom to see ? tell me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="189">CHR. Plutus, as before, in some way or other.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="190">BL. Why, is he really blind ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="191">CHR. Yes, by heaven !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="192">BL. No wonder,5 then, he never atany time came to me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="193">CHR. But, if the gods please, he shall come now.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="194">BL. Ought1 you not then to call in some physician?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="195">CHR. What physician then is there now in the city ? For neither is the fee of any valuer nor the profession.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="196">CHR. But there is none.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="197">BL. Neither do I think so.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="198">CHR. No, by Jupiter ; but ’tis best to lay him ona couch in3 the temple of Æsculapius,4 as I was intending this long while.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="199">BL. Nay, rather, far thebest, by the gods. "Do not then delay, but make haste and do something or other.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="200">1 CHR. Well now, I am going.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="201">CHR. I am doing this very thing. [Enter Poverty.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="202">Pov. 0 you pitiful mannikins, who dare to do a hasty and unholy and unlawful deed ! whither ? whither ? why do you fly ? will you not remain ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.413"/>
          <p n="203">Pov. I will destroy you, you wretches, in a wretched7 way; for you are venturingon adaring act not tobe borne, but such as no otherperson even at any time, either8 god or man, has ventured on; therefore you are undone.9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="204">CHR. But who are you ? fol' you appear to me to be ghastly pale.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="205">BL. Perhaps 'tis some Fury from tragedy :1 at least she certainly looks very mad and tragic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="206">CHR. But she has no torches.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="207">BL. Then she shall suffer for it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="208">Pov. Whom do you think me to be?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="209">Cap. Some hostess2 or pulse-porridge-seller: for otherwise you would not have cried out so loud against us, having been wronged4 in no way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.422"/>
          <p n="210">Pov. What, really ? for have you not acted, most shame fully in seeking to banish me from every place ? 5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <p n="211">CHR. Is not then the Barathrum left you ? But you ought to tell me immediately who you are.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <p n="212">Pov. One who will make you to-day give satisfaction, be cause you seek to expel me from hence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <p n="213">BL. Is it the tavern-keeper of our neighbourhood,6 who is always cheating7 me grossly with her half-pints?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <p n="214">Pov. Nay,8 but I am Poverty, who have been dwelling with you many years.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <p n="215">BL. (running away). 0 King Apollo, and ye gods! Whi ther must one fly ? 9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="216">CHR. Hollo ! what are you about? O you most cowardly.10 beast, will you not stay ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="217">CHR. Will you not stay ? What! shall we two men fly from one woman ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="218">BL. Yes, for 'tis Poverty, you wretch, than whom there is no living being any where more ruinous.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="219">CHR. Stand, I beseech you, stand !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="220">BL. No, by Jove, not I.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <p n="221">CHR. Well now, I tell you, we shall do a deed by far the most shameful of all deeds, if we shall leave the god unprotected and fly1 any whither, through fear of her, and not fight it out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.449"/>
          <p n="222">BL. Relying on what sort of arms or strength ? For what sort of breast-plate and what sort of shield does not the most abominable wretch put in pawn ? 2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.449"/>
          <p n="223">CHR. Be of good courage; for this god alone, I well know, can set up a trophy over her ways.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.449"/>
          <p n="224">Pov. And do you also dare to mutter, you scoundrels, when you have been detected in the very act of doing shameful things ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.449"/>
          <p n="225">CHR. But why do you, the devil take you,4 come against us and revile us, being wronged not5 even in any way ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.458"/>
          <p n="226">Pov. For do you think, oh, by the gods !.6 that you wrong me in no way, in endeavouring to make. Plutus see again ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.458"/>
          <p n="227">CHIt. What wrong tHen do we do you in this, if we contrive good for all men ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.458"/>
          <p n="228">Pov. But what good could you devise ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.458"/>
          <p n="229">CHR. What ? by banishing you from Greece in the first place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.458"/>
          <p n="230">Pov. By banishing me ? and what greater evil do you snp pose you could do to men ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="231">CHR. What ? if we were 7 to delay to do this and forget it. Pov. Well now, I wish first to render you an account of this very matter.8 And if I prove that I am the sole cause of all blessings to you, and that you live through is well;1 but if not, now do this, whatever seems good to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="232">CHR. Do you dare to say this, 0 most abominable ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="233">Pov. Aye, and do you suffer yourself to be taught.2 For I think I shall very easily prove that you are altogether in the wrong, if you say you will make the just wealthy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="234">CHR. 0 cudgels and pillories,3 will you not aid me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="235">Pov. You ought not to complain angrily and cry out before you know.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.466"/>
          <p n="236">BL. Why, who would be able not to cry out " oh ! oh ! " at hearing such things ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="237">Pov. He who is in his right senses.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="238">CHR. What penalty, then, shall I set down5 in the title of the suit for you, if you be cast ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="239">Pov. Whatever seems good to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="240">Pov. For you also must suffer the same, if you lose your cause.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="241">BL. Do you think then twenty deaths6 sufficient ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="242">CHR. Yes, for her; but two only will suffice for us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="243">Pov. You cannot be too quick in doing7 this: for what just plea could any one any longer bring8 against me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="244">CHO. Well, you ought now to say something clever, by which you shall conquer her, opposing her in argument, and not effeminately give in.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.487"/>
          <p n="245">CHR. I think that this is plain for all alike to understand,' that it is just that the good men should be prosperous, but the wicked and the ungodly, I ween, the contrary3 of this. We therefore desiring that this4 should take place, have with dif ficulty found out a plan, excellent, and noble, and useful for every5 enterprise. For if Plutus now should have the use of his eyes, and not go about blind, he will go to the good. men,6 and not leave them, but will fly from the wicked and the un godly ; and then he will make all to be good and rich, I ween, and to reverence7 things divine. And yet, who could ever devise a better thing than this8 for men ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="246">BL. No one : I am your witness in this ; don’t1 ask her.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="247">CHR. For as life is at present circumstanced for us men, who would not think it to be madness, or rather still a de moniacal possession ? For many men who are wicked are rich, having accumulated them 2 unjustly; while many who are very good, are badly off, and suffer hunger, and live3 with you [to Poverty] for the most part. I say, then,4 that there is a way, proceeding upon which5 a person might procure greater benefits for men, namely, if Plutus were ever to have the use of his eyes and put a stop to her.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.507"/>
          <p n="248">Pov. Nay, 0 you two old dotards, partners in nonsense and folly, of all men the most easily persuaded not to be in your right senses, if this were to happen, which you desire, I deny that it would profit you. For if Plutus were to have the use of his eyes again and portion himself6 out equally, no man would practise either art or science; and when both these have disappeared through you, who will be willing to be a smith, or to build ships, or to sew, or to make wheels, or to make shoes, or to make bricks, or to wash, or to tan hides, or who will be willing to break up the soil of the earth with ploughings and reap the fruits7 of Ceres, if it be possible for you to live in idleness, neglecting all these ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="249">CHR. You talk nonsense ;8 for our servants shall toil at all these things for us, as many as you have now enumerated.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="250">Pov. Whence then will you have servants ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="251">CHR. We will buy them for money, to be sure.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="252">Pov. But first, who will be the seller, when he too has money ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="253">CHR. Some one wishing to make gain, having come as a merchant1 from Thessaly, from amongst very many kid nappers.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="254">Pov. But first of all, there will not even be any one, not even a kidnapper, according to the statement, I ween, which you mention. For whothat is wealthy will be willing to do this3 at the hazardof his own lifer So that, having been compelled to plough, and dig, and toil at the other labours yourself, you will spend a much more painful life than the present one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.517"/>
          <p n="255">CHR. May it fall on your own head !4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.525"/>
          <p n="256">Pov. Moreover you will not be able to sleep either in a bed,-for there will be none,-or in carpets ; for who will be willing to weave them when he has gold ? Nor, when you lead home a bride, to anoint her with dropping unguents; nor to adorn her with sumptuous 5 garments, dyed, and variegated. And yet, what advantage will it be to you to be rich, when in want6 of all these ? But from me all these which you stand in needof are easily obtained ; for I sit, compelling the artisan, like a mistress, through his want and his poverty, to seek whence he shall have subsistence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.535"/>
          <p n="257">CHR. Why,what good could you procure, except a swarm of blisters7 from the bath, and of children beginning to be hungry, and of old women ? and1 the quantity of lice, and gnats, and fleas, I don't even mention2 to you, by reason of their multitude, which buzz3 about my head and torment me, wakening me and saying, " You will suffer hunger; come, get up." 4 Moreover to have a rag instead of a garment; and in stead of a bed, a mattress of rushes, full of bugs, which wakens5 the sleepers ; and to have a rotten mat instead of a carpet; and a good-sized stone against one's head instead of a pillow; and to eat shoots of mallow instead of bread; and leaves of withered radish instead of barley-cake ; and to have the head of a broken jar instead of a bench; and the side of a cask, and that too6 broken, instead of a kneading-trough. Do I not7 demonstrate you to be the cause of many blessings to all men ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.548"/>
          <p n="258">Pov. You have not mentioned my way of life, but have at tacked that of beggars.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.548"/>
          <p n="259">CHR. Therefore we say,I ween, that poverty is sister9 of beggary.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.548"/>
          <p n="260">POV. Aye, you who also say that Dionysius is like Thrasy bulus. But my mode of life is not thus circumstanced, no, by Jove, nor will it.1For aBeggar's mode of life, which, you describe, is to live possessed of nothing; but that of a poor man to live sparingly, and attentive to his work; and not to have any superfluity, nor yet, however, to have a deficiancy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.548"/>
          <p n="261">CHR. 0 Ceres ! how blessed is his life which 2 you have set forth, if after sparing and toiling he shall leave behind him not even wherewith to be buried.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.557"/>
          <p n="262">Pov. You are trying to scoff at and ridicule me, heedless of being earnest, not knowing that I render men better both inmind and body than Plutus4 does. For with him5 they are gouty in their feet, and pot-bellied, and thick-legged, and extravagantly fat; but with me they are thin and slender, and grievous to their foes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="263">CHR. For, no doubt,6 you bring about the slenderness for them by hunger.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="264">Pov. Now therefore I will discourse to you respectingso briety, and will demonstrate that orderly behaviour dwells with me, but that riotousness belongs to Plutus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="265">- CHR. In sooth it is very orderly to steal and to dig through walls.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="266">BL. Yes, by Jove ;7 how is it not orderly, if he must escape notice ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="267">Pov. Consider thereforethe orators in the States, how, when they are poor, theyarejust to wards the people and the state:but when they have become rich out of the public purse, they immediately become unjust, and plot against the commons, and make war upon the democracy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="268">CHR. Well, you don't speak falsely in any of these things, although 1 you areexceedingly slanderous. But you shall suf fer none the less—don't pride 2 yourself on thIs-because you seek to convince usof this, that poverty is better than riehes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="269">Pov. And you too are -not yeTable to refute me about this, but talk nonsense and flap your wings.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="270">CHR. Why how is it that allshunyou ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="271">Pov. Because I make them better. But you may see it best in 3 children; for they shun their fathers who are very well-dis posed towards them. So difficult a matter is it to distinguish what is right.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="272">CHR. You will say then4 that Jupiter does not correctly dis tinguish what is best; for he too has wealth.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="273">BL. And despatches 6 her to us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.583"/>
          <p n="274">Pov. Nay, 0 you who are both of you purblind in your minds with old-fashioned prejudices, Jupiter is certainly poor ; and I will now teaeh you this clearly. For if he was rieh, how would he,when eelebrating the Olympic games himself, where he assembles all the Greeks every fifth year, have pro claimed as conquerors the vie tori ous athletes, having erowned them with a chaplet of wild olive?7 And yet he ought8 rather to crown them, with gold, if he was rich ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.583"/>
          <p n="275">CHR. By this therefore he certainly shows that he honours riches. For through parsimony and a wish to spend none of it, he crowns the victors with trifles and lets his wealth re main by him.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.592"/>
          <p n="276">Pov. You seek to fix upon him a much more disgraceful thing than poverty, if he, though rich, be so stingy and avaricious.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.592"/>
          <p n="277">CHR. Well, may Jupiter utterly destroy you, having crown ed you with a chaplet of wild olive !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.592"/>
          <p n="278">Pov. To think of your daring 2 to contradict me, that all your blessings are not through poverty!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.592"/>
          <p n="279">CHR. One may learn this from Hecate, whether to be rich or to suffer hunger is better. For she says that those who have property and are wealthy send a dinner every month, while the poor people snatch it away before3 one has set it down. But go and be hanged,4 and don't mutter any thing more whatever. For you shall notconvince me, even if you should convince me.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="280">Pov. " O city of Argos you hear what he says !"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="281">CHR. Call Pauson, your messmate.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="282">Pov. What7 shall I do, unhappy woman !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="283">CHR. Go to the devil quickly from us !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="284">Pov. But whither on earth shall I go ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="285">CHR. To the pillory; you ought not to delay, but to make haste.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.608"/>
          <p n="286">Pov. Assuredly you will have to send for me hither some time.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.608"/>
          <p n="287">CHR. Then you shall return ; but now go and be banged! For it is better for me to be rich, and to leave you to wail loudly in your head.1 [Exit Poverty.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.608"/>
          <p n="288">BL. By Jove, then, I wish, when I am rich, to feast along with my children and my wife; and going sleek from the bath, after I have bathed, to fart at the artisans and Poverty.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.619"/>
          <p n="289">CHR. This cursed wretch is gone. But let you and me convey the god as soon as possible to the temple of Æsculapius to put him to bed in it.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.619"/>
          <p n="290">BL. And let us not delay, lest again some one come and hinder us from doing something useful.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.619"/>
          <p n="291">CHR. Boy Cario, you must bring out the bed-clothes, aud convey Plutus himself, as is customary, and the other things, as many as are ready prepared in the house. [-Exeunt Chremylus and Blepsidemus.] 4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.627"/>
          <p n="292">CARIO (returning from the temple). 0 you old men, who very often at the festival of Theseus5 have sopped up soup to very little bread, how prosperous you are, how happily you are circumstanced, and the rest of you, as many as have any claim to a good character !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.627"/>
          <p n="293">CHO. But what news is there, 0 good sir, about6 your friends ? for you appear to have come as a messenger of some good news.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.627"/>
          <p n="294">— CA. My master is most prosperously circumstanced,—or rather Plutus himself; for instead of being blind, he has been1 restored to sight, and has been made clear-sighted in the pupils of his eyes, having found Æsculapius a friendly physi cian.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.627"/>
          <p n="295">CHO. You tell me a matter for joy, you tell me a matter for shouting.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.627"/>
          <p n="296">CA. 'Tis your lot to rejoice, whether you wish it or no. CiO. I will loudly praise AEsculapius blest in his children, and3 a great light to mortals. [Enter wife of Chremylus. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.637"/>
          <p n="297">WIFE. What in the world means the shout ? Is some good news announced ? for, longing for this, I have been sitting in the house this long while, waiting for this fellow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.637"/>
          <p n="298">CA. Quickly, quickly, bring wine, mistress, in order that you yourself also may drink,-and you are very fond4 of doing it, for I bring you all blessings in a lump.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="299">WIFE. Why, where are they ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="300">CA. You will soon learn by what is said.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="301">WIFE. Be quick and finish then some time or other what you are for saying.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="302">CA. Hear then ; for I will tell you the whole affair from the foot to the head.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="303">WIFE. Nay, not on my head, pray.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="304">CA. Not the blessings .which have now taken place ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="305">WIFE. Nay, rather, not the troubles.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="306">CA. As soon as we came to the god, conveying a man, at that time most miserable, but now blessed and fortunate, if there ever was one,2 we first conveyed him to the sea, an then washed him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="307">WIPE. By Jupiter, then he was fortunate, an old man washed in the cold sea !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="308">CA. Then we went to the temple of the god. And when our wafers and preparatory sacrifices were offered on the altar, and our cake in the flame of Vulcan,3 we laid Plutus on a couch, as was proper, while each of us began putting his mattress in order.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="309">WIFE. And were there any others also in need of the god ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="310">CA. Yes, there was one Neoclides,4 who is indeed blind, but out-does5 in stealing those who see : and many others having all sorts of diseases. But when the sacrist6 of the god put out the lamps and ordered us to sleep, telling us if any one should hear a noise, he must be silent, we all laid down in an orderly manner. And I could not sleep; but a pot of porridge which was lying a little way off from the head of an old woman strongly affected me, towards which I desired exceedingly to creep. Then on looking up I see the priest snatching away7 the cakes and dried figs from the sacred table. And after this he went round to all the altars round about, if any where a cake might be left; and then he consecrated these-into a sack.8 And I, supposing9 there was great piety in the thing, got up towards the pot of por ridge.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.667"/>
          <p n="311">WIFE. 0 most daring1 of men, were you not afraid of the god?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.667"/>
          <p n="312">CA. Yes, by the gods, lest he might get to the pot before me, with his garlands on ; for his priest taught me that before hand.2 But the old woman, when she heard my noise, stretched forth3 her hand ; and then I hissed and seized it with my teeth, as if I were an Æsculapian4 snake. But she immediately drew back her hand again, and lay down, having wrapped herself up quietly, farting for fear more offensively - than a weasel. And then I swallowed greedily the greater part of the porridge :1 and then, when I was full, I rested.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.667"/>
          <p n="313">WIFE. But did not the god come to you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.676"/>
          <p n="314">CA. Not yet. And after this now I did a very laughable thing indeed ; for as he was approaching, I farted very loudly ; for my belly,- had been blown out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="315">WIFE. Doubtless he was immediately disgusted at you on account of this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="316">CA. No ; but a certain Iaso,7 who was following along with him, blushed a little, and Panacea took hold of her nose and turned away her head ; for I fart no frankincense.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="317">WIFE. But he himself?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="318">CA. No, by Jove, he did not even take notice of it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="319">WIFE. Then you represent the deity to be boorish.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.684"/>
          <p n="320">CA. No, by Jove, not I ; but a dung-eater.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.694"/>
          <p n="321">WIFE. Ha, you wretch !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.704"/>
          <p n="322">CA. After this I immediately covered myself up for fear ; while he went round in a circuit inspecting all the maladies very regularly. Then a servant set before bim a small stone mortar and a pestle and a small chest.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.704"/>
          <p n="323">CA. No, by Jove, certainly not, not3 the little chest.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.704"/>
          <p n="324">WIFE. But bow did you see, the devil take4 you! who say you were wrapped up ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.712"/>
          <p n="325">CA. Through my little tbreadbare cloak ; for, by Jupiter,5 it has6 no few holes. First of all he began to pound up a plaster7 for Neoclides, having thrown in three heads of Tenian8 garlic. Then he beat them up in the mortar, mixing9 along with them gum and squill ; and then be moistened it with Sphettian10 vinegar, and spread it over, having turned his eyelids inside out, that he might be pained the more. And he crying out and bawling, jumped up and ran away, while the god laughed and said : “ Sit there now,11 plastered over, that I may Stop12 your excusing yourself on oath from the Assembly.”13</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.724"/>
          <p n="326">WIFE. How very14 patriotic and wise the god is !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.724"/>
          <p n="327">CA. After this he sat down beside Plutus:1 and first he handled his head, and then he took a clean napkin and wiped his eyelids all round: and Panacea covered his head and the whole of his face with a purple cloth. Then the god whistled; then two snakes rushed forth from the temple, prodigious in size.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.724"/>
          <p n="328">WIFE. 0 ye friendly gods !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.733"/>
          <p n="329">CA. And these two gently crept under the purple cloth and began to lick his eyelids all round, as it appeared to me. And before you could have drank up ten half-pints of wine, mistress, Plutus was standing up having the use of his eyes: and I clapped my hands for joy, and began to wake my master. But the god immediately took himself4 out of sight, and the snakes took themselves into the temple; while those who were lying in bed near him, you can't think how5 they began embracing Plutus, and kept awake the whole night, until day dawned. But I praised the god very much, be cause he had quickly caused Plutus to see, while he made Ncoclides more blind than before.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.742"/>
          <p n="330">WIFE. How much6 power you possess, 0 king and master! But [to Cario] tell mc, where is Plutus ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.750"/>
          <p n="331">CA. He is coming. But there was a prodigious7 crowd about him. For all those who were formerly just, and had a scanty subsistence, were embracing him and shaking hands with him for joy; but as many as were rich, and had much property, not having acquired their subsistence justly, were' contracting their browse and at the same time looking an- gry. But the others were following behind with garlands on, laughing and shouting in triumph; and the shoe of the old men was resounding1 with their steps in good time' But come, do you all together with one accord dance, and leap, and form a chorus ; for no one will announce to you when you go in that there is no meal in the bag.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="332">WIFE. And I, by Hecate, wish to crown you for your good news3 with a string of cracknels,4 who have announced such tidings.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="333">CA. Do not then delay any longer, for the men are now near to the door.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="334">WIFE. Come then, let me go in and fetch some sweet meats5 to be showered as it were over his newly purchased eyes. [ Exit wife of Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="335">CA. But I wish to go to meet them. [Exit Cario.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.771"/>
          <p n="336">PLU. (entering, accompanied by Chremylus and a great crowd of people). And first I salutes the sun, and then the illustrious soil7 of the august Pallas, and the whole land of Cecrops, which received me. I am- ashamed of my misfor tunes, because I associated with such mens without know ing it, but shunned those who were wortHyof my society, knowing nothing, oh, unhappy me ! How wrongly I acted both In. that case9 and in this ! But I will reverse them all again, and henceforth show to all men that I unwillingly gave myself up to the wicked.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.779"/>
          <p n="337">CHR. (to some by-stander). Go to the devil! How trou blesome a thing arc the friends who appear immediately, when one is prosperous ! For they nudge me with their elbows, and bruise1 my shins, each of them exhibiting2 some good will. For who did not address me ? What a crowd of old men was there not around me in the market-place ? [Enter wife of Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.788"/>
          <p n="338">WIFE. 0 dearest of men ! Welcome, both you, and you ! Come now, for it is the custom, let me take and pour these sweetmeats over you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.788"/>
          <p n="339">PLU. By no means ; for on my first entry into the house, and when I have recovered my eye-sight, it is in no wise be coming to carry out any thing, but rather to carry in.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.788"/>
          <p n="340">WIFE. Then, pray, will you not accept my sweetmeats ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.796"/>
          <p n="341">PLU. Yes, in the house, by the fireside, as is the custom. Then also we may avoid the vulgarity of the thing ; for it is not becoming for the dramatic poet4 to throw dried figs and sweetmeats to the spectators and then force them to laugh at this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.796"/>
          <p n="342">WIFE. You say very well; for see ! there's Dexinicus5 standing up, with the intention of snatching at the dried figs ! [Exeunt PlutuM, Chremylus, wife, and attendants.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.802"/>
          <p n="343">CA. (coming out of the house). How delightful it is, sirs, to fare prosperously ! especially if one has brought out nothing from home.6 For a heap7 of blessings has rushed into our house, without our committing any injustice. these circumstances 9 wealth-is- a very delightful thing. Our meal- chest is full of wheaten flour, and our wine-jars of dark wine with a high perfume.1 And all our vessels are full of silver and gold, so that I wonder. And our oil-jar is full of oil; and our flasks are full of unguents, and our garret of dried figs. And every vinegar-cruet, and platter, and pot has be come of brass ; and our rotten, fishy chargers you may see of silver. And our lantern has suddenly become of ivory. And we servants play at even and odd with golden staters ; and we no longer wipe ourselves with stones,2 but always with garlic, through luxury. And at present my master is sacrificing within a swine, and a goat, and a ram, with a chaplet on : but the smoke drove me out; for I was not able to remain within ; for it stung my eye-lids. [Enter a Just Man attended by his servant.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="344">J. M. Follow with me,3 my little boy, that we may go to the god. [Enter Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="345">CHR. Ha ! who is this who approaches ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="346">J. M. Aman, formerly wretched, but nowprosperous.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="347">CHR. It is evident that you are one of the good, as it appears.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="348">J. M. Most certainly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.810"/>
          <p n="349">CHR. Then, what do youwant ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.819"/>
          <p n="350">J. M. I have come to the god: for he is the author of great blessings to me. For having received a considerable property from my father, I used to assist those of my friends4 who were in want, thinking it to be useful for life.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.819"/>
          <p n="351">CHR. Doubtless your money soon failed1 you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.819"/>
          <p n="352">CHR. Therefore after this you were wretched.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.827"/>
          <p n="353">J. M. Just so. And I thought I should have as really irm friends, if ever I might want them, those whom I had )efore done kindness to when they were in want: but they &gt;egan to avoid me, and pretended not to see me any longer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.827"/>
          <p n="354">CHR. And also3 laughed at you, I well know.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.827"/>
          <p n="355">J. M. Just so. For the dearth4 which was in my vessels uined me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.827"/>
          <p n="356">J. M. Wherefore with good reason I have come hither to he god, to offer up my vows.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="357">CHR. But what has the threadbare cloak to do with the ;od,5 which this servant is carrying in your retinue ?6 tell ne.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="358">J. M. This also I am coming to the god to dedicate.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="359">CHR. Were you initiated,7 then, in the Great Mysteries n it?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="360">J. M. No; but I shivered in it for thirteen years.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="361">CHR. But your shoes ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="362">J. M. These also have weathered the storm along with me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="363">CHR. Then were you bringing these also to dedicate them ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="364">J. M. Yes, by Jupiter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="365">CHR. You have come with very pretty1 presents for the god. [Enter an informer attended by his witness.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="366">INF. Ah me, unhappy! How I am undone, miserable man, and thrice unhappy,2 and four times, and five times, and twelve times, and ten thousand times! alas! alas! with so powerful3 a fate have I been mingled.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.853"/>
          <p n="367">CHR. 0 Apollo, averter of evil, and ye friendly gods ! what in the world is the misfortune which the man has suffered ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.853"/>
          <p n="368">INF. Why, have I not now suffered chocking things, who havelost every thing out of my house through this god, who shall be blind again, unless law-suits be wanting.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.861"/>
          <p n="369">J. M. I imagine I pretty nearly see into the matter; for a man is approaching who is badly off; and he seems to be of the bad stamp.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.861"/>
          <p n="370">CHR. By Jupiter, then, he is rightly5 ruined.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.861"/>
          <p n="371">INF. Where, where is this fellow who singly promised he would immediately make us all rich, if he were to recover his sight again6 as before ? On the contrary, he has7 ruined some much more.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.861"/>
          <p n="372">CHR. And whom, pray, has he treated thus ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.869"/>
          <p n="373">CHR. Were you of the number of the wicked ones and housebreakers ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.869"/>
          <p n="374">INF. By Jove, there is certainly8 no good in any of you, and it must be that you have9 my money.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.869"/>
          <p n="375">CA. 0 Ceres, how insolently the informer has come in ! It is evident that he is ravenously hungry.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.869"/>
          <p n="376">INF. You cannot be too2 quick in going speedily to the market-place ; for you must there be racked upon the wheel and declare your villanies.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.869"/>
          <p n="377">CA. Then you'll suffer for it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.877"/>
          <p n="378">J. M. By Jupiter the Preserver, this god is of great value to all the Greeks, if he shall utterly destroy the informers, the wretches,4 in a wretched way.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.877"/>
          <p n="379">INF. Ah me, miserable! Are you also laughing at me, who are an accomplice ? for whence have you got this garment ? But yesterday I saw you with a threadbare cloak on.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.877"/>
          <p n="380">J. M. I care nothing for you : for see ! I wear this ring,6 having purchased it from Eudemus7 for a drachma.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="381">CHR. But it is not possible to wear one against an in former’s 8 bite.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="382">INF. Is not this great insolence ? You mock me, but you have not stated what you are doing here. For you are here for no good.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="383">CHR. Certainly not, by Jove, for your good; be well assured.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="384">INF. For, by Jove, you will dine at my cost.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="385">CHR. For the sake of truth1 may you burst, together with your witness, filled with nothing.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="386">INF. Do you deny it ? There is a great quantity3 of slices of salt-fish and roast meat within, you most abominable fel lows. [Sniffs.] uhu, uhu, uhu, uhu, uhu, uhu.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="387">CHR. Do you smell any thing,5 you poor wretch ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="388">J. M. The cold, perhaps ; since he has ons such a thread bare cloak.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="389">INF. Is this bearable7 then, 0 Jupiter and ye gods, that these should commit outrages upon me ? Ah me ! how grieved I am-that, good and patriotic as I am, I fare badly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="390">CHR. You patriotic and good ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="391">INF. As never man was.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="392">CHR. Well now, answer me when asked- INF. What ?8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="393">CHR. Are you a husbandman ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="394">INF. Do you suppose me to be so mad ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="395">CHR. Or a merchant?9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="396">INF. Yes, I pretend to be,10 upon occasion.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="397">CHR. Well then, did you learn any trade ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="398">CHR. How then, or whence, did you live,11 if you do no thing ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="399">INF. I am manager of all the affairs of the state and private affairs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="400">CHR. YOU? Wherefore?1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="401">INF. I please to do so.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="402">J CHR. How then, you house-breaker,2 can you be good, if,, when it in no wise concerns you.3 you are then hated ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="403">INF. Why, does it not concern me,4 you booby, to benefit my own city as far as I be able ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="404">CHR. Then is to be a meddlingbusybody to benefit it?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="405">INF. Nay, rather, to aid the established5 laws, and,if any one do wrong, not to permit it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="406">CHR. Does not the state, then, purposely appoint judges to preside ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="407">( INF. But who is the accuser ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="408">\ CHR. Any one who pleases.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="409">INF. Then I am he; so that the affairs of the state have devolved on me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="410">CHR. Then, by Jove, it has a sorry patron. But would you not prefer that,6 to keep quiet and live idle ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="411">INF. Nay, you are describing the life of a sheep, if there shall appear no amusement in life.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="412">CHR. And would you not learn better ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="413">INF. Not even if you were to give7 me Plutus himself, and the silphium of Battus.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="414">CHR. Quickly lay down your cloak.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.918"/>
          <p n="415">CA. (to the informer). Ho you ! he is speaking to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="416">CHR. Next take off your shoes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="417">CA. (to the informer). He says all this to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="418">INF. Well now, let any of you that pleases come hither against me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="419">CA. " Then I am he.” [Seizes the informer and strips him of his cloak and shoes.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="420">INF. Ah me, miserable! I am stripped in the day time.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="421">CA. For you do not hesitate to get a livelihood by meddling with -other people’s business.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="422">INF. (to his witness). Do you see what he is doing? I call you to witness this.2 [His witness runs off.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="423">CHR. But the witness whom3 you brought is running away.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="424">INF. Ah me, I have been caught alone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="425">CA. Do you bawl now ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="426">INF. Ah me, again and4 again!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="427">CA. Do you [to the Just Man] give me your threadbare cloak, that I may put it on this informer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="428">J. M. Certainly not; for it has been this long while con secrated to Plutus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="429">CA. Where then will it be better dedicated than around a knavish man and house-breaker ? But Plutus it is fitting to adorn with grand dresses.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.934"/>
          <p n="430">J. M. But what shall one make of the shoes ? tell me. CA. These also I will instantly nail fast to this man's fore head, as if to a wild5 olive.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.942"/>
          <p n="431">INF. I'll begone ; for I perceive I am much weaker than you. But if I find a comrade, even of fig-tree wood,6 I will to-day make this powerful god give me satisfaction, because he singly and alone is manifestly putting down the democracy, having neither prevailed upon the Senate of the citizens nor the Assembly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="432">J. M. Well now, since you are marching with my panoply on, run to the bath, and then stand there in the front and warm1 yourself. For I also once held this post. [Exit informer. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="433">CHR. But the bath-man will take and drag him2 out of doors by the testicles ; for when he has seen him he will per ceive that he is of that bad stamp. But let us two go in, that you may offer up your vows to the god.4 [Exeunt Chremylus and Just Man.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="434">OLD WOMAN (entering and bearing some cakes on a platter). 0 dear old men, have we really come to the houses of this new god, or have we altogether missed the road ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="435">CHO. Nay, know that you have come to the very door,6 my little girl; for you ask seasonably.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="436">OLD WOM. Come then, let me summons some one of those within. [Enter Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="437">CHR. Certainly not ;9 for I myself have come out. But 'rou must tell me for what in particular you have come.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="438">OLD WOM. 0 dearest sir, I have suffered dreadful and un just things : for since what time this god began10 to have the use of his eyes, he has made my life to be insupportable.11</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="439">CHR. What's the matter ? I suppose you also were an informeress12 amongst women ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="440">OLD WOM. No, by Jupiter, not I.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="441">CHR. Or did you not drink in your letter,13 having obtained it by lot ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.975"/>
          <p n="442">OLD WOM. You are mocking me ; but I burn with love,1 unhappy woman.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.975"/>
          <p n="443">CHR. Will you not then quickly tell me what is your love</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.975"/>
          <p n="444">OLD WOM. Hear then ! I had a dear youth, poor, indced, but, for the rest,2 good looking, and handsome, and good. For if I wanted any thing, he used to perform every thing for me decently and well, while I assisted him in all his wants in the same manner.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.975"/>
          <p n="445">CHR. But what was it he especially wanted of you, on each occasion ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.984"/>
          <p n="446">OLD WOM. Not much ; for he was marvellously respectful to me. But he used to ask for3 twenty drachmae of silver for a mantle, and eight for shoes ; and he used to entreat me to purchase a tunic4 for his sisters, and a little mantle for his mother ; and he used to beg for four medimni of wheat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.984"/>
          <p n="447">CHR. Certainly, by Apollo, this is not much which5 you have mentioned ; but it is evident that he respected you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.984"/>
          <p n="448">OLD WOM. And these moreover he said he asked of me, not on account of lewdness,6 but for affection, that while wearing my mantle, he might think on7 me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.984"/>
          <p n="449">Cap. You describe a man most marvellously8 in love with you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.992"/>
          <p n="450">OLD. WOM. But the abominable fellow now no longer has the same mind, but has changed very much. For when I sent him this cheese-cake here and the other1 sweetmeats which are upon the plate, and whispered2 that I would come in the evening-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.992"/>
          <p n="451">CHR. What did he do to you ? tell me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.992"/>
          <p n="452">OLD WOM. He sent back to us besides this milk-cake here, on condition3 that I never came thither any more ; and be sides, in addition to this, when4 sending it off he said, " Once in olden time the Milesians5 were brave."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1003"/>
          <p n="453">CHR. It is evident that he was not very bad6 in his cha racter. So then,7 being rich, he no longer takes pleasure in lentil-porridge : but formerly, through his poverty, he used to eat every thing as a relish.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1003"/>
          <p n="454">OLD WOM. And yet formerly, by the two goddesses,9 he used always to come to my door every day.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1003"/>
          <p n="455">CHR. For your burial ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1003"/>
          <p n="456">OLD WOM. No, by Jupiter, but merely through a desire to hear my voice.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1003"/>
          <p n="457">CHR. Nay, rather, for the sake of getting something.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="458">OLD WOM. And, by Jove, if he perceived me afflicted, he used to call me coaxingly his little duck and little dove.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="459">CHR. And then, perhaps, he used to ask1 you for money for shoes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="460">OLD WOM. And when any one looked at me when riding in my carriage at the Great Mysteries, I was beaten on ac count of this the whole day; so very jealous was the young man.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="461">CHR. For he took pleasure, as it seems, in eating alone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="462">OLD IVM. And he said I had very beautiful3 hands.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1012"/>
          <p n="463">CHR. Aye, whenever they offered twenty drachmæ.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="464">OLD WOM. And he said I smelt5 sweet in my skin-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="465">CHR. Aye, like enough, by Jove, if you poured in Thasian 6 wine for him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="466">OLD WOM. And that I had a gentle and beautiful look.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="467">CHR. The man was no fool, but knew how to devour the bstance of a lustful old woman.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="468">OLD WOM. In this therefore, O dear sir, the god does not act rightly, who professes to succour whoever happen to be wronged.8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1020"/>
          <p n="469">CHR. Why, what must he do ?9 speak, and it shall be done immediately.10</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="470">OLD WOM. It is just, by Jove, to compel him who has been benefitedby meto benefit me in turn ;or he deserves to possess no blessingwhatever.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="471">CHR. Did he not then repay you every night ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="472">OLD WOM. But hesaid, he would never desert me while I lived.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="473">CHR. Aye, rightly ; but now1 he thinks you no longer alive.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="474">OLD WOM. For I am wasting away through grief, 0 dear est friend.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1028"/>
          <p n="475">CHR. No, but you have rotted away, as it appears 2 to me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="476">OLD WOM. Indeed, then, you might draw me through a ring.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="477">CHR. Yes, if the ring were the hoop of a sieve.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="478">OLD WOM. Well now, see ! here's the youth approaching,4 whom I have been accusing this long while; and he seems to be going to a revel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="479">CHR. He appears so: at least he is certainly coming with a chaplet and a torch.5 [Enter a young man with a lighted torch in his hand and followed by a band of revellers. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="480">OLD WOM. (to Chremylus). What says he ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="481">You. My ancient sweetheart, by heaven, you have quickly become gray.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1036"/>
          <p n="482">OLD WOM. Unhappy me, for the insult with which6 I am insulted!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="483">CHR. He seems to have seen you after a long time.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="484">OLD WOM. Since7,what time, 0 most audacious, who8 was at my house yesterday ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="485">CHR. Then he is affected in a manner opposite to most people ; for, as it seems, he sees sharper when he's drunk.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="486">OLD WOM. No, but he is always saucy in his manners.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="487">You. (holding the torch close to her face). 0 Sea-Poseidon2 and ye elderly gods, how many wrinkles3 she has in her face!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="488">OLD WOM. Ah ! ah ! don't bring the torch near me !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="489">CHR. Upon my word she says rightly ; for if only a single spark catch her, it will burn her like an old harvest-wreath.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1044"/>
          <p n="490">You. Will you'play with me for a4 while?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="491">OLD WOM. Where, wretch?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="492">You. Here, having taken some nuts.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="493">OLD WOM. What game ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="494">You. How many teeth5 you have.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="495">CHR. Come, I also will have a guess; for she has three, perhaps, or four.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="496">YOU. Pay up ! for she carries only one grinder.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1052"/>
          <p n="497">OLD.WOM. Most audacious of men, you don't appear to me bein your right senses, who make a wash-pot of me in the presence of so many men.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1060"/>
          <p n="498">YOU. Upon my word you'd be the better for it, if one were to wash you clean.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1060"/>
          <p n="499">CHR. Certainly not, for now she is playing the cheat: 2 but if this white-lead 3 shall be washed off, you'll see the wrinkles in her face quite plain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1060"/>
          <p n="500">OLD WOM. You don't appear4 to me to be in your right senses, old man as you are.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1060"/>
          <p n="501">You. Perhaps, indeed, he is tempting you, and is touching your breasts, fancying that he escapes my notice.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="502">OLD WOM. No, by Venus, not mine, you abominable fellow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="503">CHR. No, by Hecate, certainly not! for I should be mad. But, young man, I won't suffer you to hate this girl.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="504">You. Nay, I love her beyond measure.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="505">CHR. And yet she accuses you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="506">You. What does she accuse me of?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="507">CHR. She says that you are an insolent person, and that you tell her, " Once in olden time the Milesians were brave."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="508">You. I will not quarrel with you about her.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="509">You. Out of respect for your age; for I would never have suffered another to do so; but now go in peace, having taken the girl along with you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="510">CHR. I know, Iknow your meaning; perhaps you no longer deign to be with her.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="511">OLD WOM. But who is there to permit him ? 5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="512">You. I would not have to do 1 with one who has been em braced by thirteen2 thousand years.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="513">CHR. But yet, since you thought proper to drink the wine, you must also drink 3 up the dregs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="514">You. But the dregs are altogether old and fusty.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="515">CHR. Then a straining-cloth will cure all this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="516">You. Come, go within ! for I wish to go and dedicate to the god these chaplets which I have on.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="517">OLD WOM. And I also wish to say something to him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="518">You. But I will not go in.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="519">CHR. Be of good courage, don't be afraid! for she shan't ravish you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="520">You. Now you say very well: for I have been pitching her up long enough already.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="521">OLD WOM. Go in, and I'll enter after you. [Exeunt Old Woman and Young Man.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="522">CHR. How forcibly, 0 King Jove, the old woman sticks to the youth like a limpet.5 [Exit Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1097"/>
          <p n="523">CARIO (from within). Who's that knocking6 at the door? [Comes out and looks about.] What's this?7 It appears to be nobody. Then certainly the door shall suffer 8 for creaking without cause. [Retires again.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1097"/>
          <p n="524">MER. (running out of his hiding-place). Cario! You, I say! stop!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1097"/>
          <p n="525">.CA. (coming out again). Hollo, you! Tell me, did you knock at the door so violently ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1097"/>
          <p n="526">MER. No, by Jove; but I. was a going to; and then you anticipated me by opening it. Come, run quickly and call out your master, then his wife and children, then his servants, then the do-, then yourself, then the sow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="527">CA. Tell me, what's the matter ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="528">MER. Jupiter, you rascal, intends to mix you up in the same bowl and cast you all together into the Barathrum.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="529">CA. The tongue 2 is givento the herald of these tidings. But on what account, pray, does he purpose to do this to us ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="530">MER. Because you have done the most dreadful of all deeds. For since what time Plutus began to have the use of his eyes as before,3 no one any longer offers to us gods either4 frankincense, or laurel, or barley-cake, or victim, or any thing else.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1117"/>
          <p n="531">CA. No, by Jupiter, nor will he offer them. For you took bad care of us aforetime.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1117"/>
          <p n="532">MER. And for the other gods I care less; but I am undone, and am ruined.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1117"/>
          <p n="533">MER. For formerly I used to enjoy all good things in the female innkeepers' shops as soon as it was morning, wine cake, honey, dried figs, as many as 'tis fitting that Mercury should eat: but now I go to bed hungry with my legs ly ing up.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1117"/>
          <p n="534">CA. Is it not then with justice, who sometimes2 caused their loss, although you enjoyed such good things.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="535">MER. Ah me, miserable! Ah me, for the cheese-cake 3 that was baked on the fourth day !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="536">CA. " You 1 long for the absent, and call in vain.”</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="537">MER. Ah me for the ham which I used to devour!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="538">CA. Leap upon the bottle5 there in the open air.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="539">MER. And for the warm entrails which I used to devour !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="540">CA. A pain about your entrails seems to torture you. 7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="541">MER. Ah me, for the cup that was mixed 8 half-and-half !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="542">CA. You cannot be too quick in drinking this 9 besides and running away.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="543">MER. Would you assist your own friend in any way ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="544">CA. Yes ; if you want any of those things in which 10 I am able to assist you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="545">MER. If you were to procure me a well-baked loaf and give it me to eat, and a huge11 piece of meat from the sacrifices you are offering within.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="546">CA. But there is no carrying out. 1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="547">MER. And yet whenever you stole2 any little vessel from your master, I always used 3 to cause you to be undetected.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="548">CA. On condition that you also shared yourself, you house breaker. For a well-baked cake used to come to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="549">MER. And then you used to devour this yourself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="550">CA. For you had not an equal share4 of the blows with me, whenever I was caught in any knavery.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="551">MER. Don't bear malice,5 if you have got possession of Phyle; but, by the gods, receive me as a fellow-inmate.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="552">CA. Then will you abandon the gods and stay here ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="553">MER. Yes; for your condition is much better.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="554">CA. How then ? do you think desertion a fine thing ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="555">MER. Yes; “ for his country is every country, wherever a man is well off.” 6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="556">CA. What use then would you be to us, if you were here ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="557">MER. Post me beside the door as turnkey.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="558">CA. As turnkey ? but we have no need of turns.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="559">MER. As merchant, 8 then.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="560">CA. But we are rich: what need then for us to maintain a huckstering Mercury?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1158"/>
          <p n="561">MER. Well, as deceiver, then.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1158"/>
          <p n="562">CA. As deceiver? By no means. For we have no need of deception now, but of simple manners.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1158"/>
          <p n="563">MER. As conductor, then.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1158"/>
          <p n="564">CA. But the god now has the use of his eyes; so we shall no longer want a conductor.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1158"/>
          <p n="565">MER. Then I will be president of the games. And what further will you say ? For this is most convenient for Plutus, to celebrate musical and gymnastic 1 contests.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1166"/>
          <p n="566">CA. What a good thing it is to have many 2 surnames ! for this fellow has found out a scant living for himself by this means. No wonder all the judges often seek eagerly to be inscribed in many letters.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1166"/>
          <p n="567">MER. Then shall I go in upon these terms ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1166"/>
          <p n="568">CA. Aye, and go yourself to the well and wash4 the pud dings, that you may immediately be thought to be serviceable. [Exeunt Mercury and Cario.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="569">PRIEST OF JUPITER (entering hastily). Who can tell me for certain where Chremylus is ? [Enter Chremylus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="570">CHR. What is the matter, my good air ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="571">PRIEST. Why, what else but:; bad? For since what time this Plutus began to have the use of his eyes, I perish with hunger. For I have nothing to eat; and that too, though I am the priest 6 of Jupiter the Preserver.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="572">CHR. Oh ! by the gods, what is the cause ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="573">PRIEST. No one deigns to sacrifice any longer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="574">CHR. On what account ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="575">PRIEST. Because they are all rich. And yet, at that time, when they had nothing, the one, a merchant, used 7 to come and sacrifice some victim for his safety ; and some other one, be causehe had been acquitted on his trial; and some other one used to sacrifice with favourable omens, and invite me too, the priest. But now not even a single person sacrifices any thing at all, or enters the temple, except it be more than a myriad to ease themselves.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1171"/>
          <p n="576">CHR. Do you not then receive your lawful share of these ? 1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="577">PRIEST. Therefore I also am resolved2 to bid farewell 3 to. Jupiter the Preserver and stay here in this placed</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="578">CHR. Be of good courage ! for it will be well,5 if the god please. For6 Jupiter the Preserver is present here, having come of his own accord.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="579">PRIEST. Then you tell me all good news.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="580">CHR. We will therefore immediately establish-but 7 stay here—Plutus where he was before established, always guard ing the inner cell8 of the goddess. But let some one give me out here9 lighted torches, that you may hold them and go be fore the god.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="581">PRIEST. Yes, by all means we must do this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="582">CHR. Call Plutus out, some of you.10 [Enter Old Woman.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="583">OLD WOM. But what am I to do ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="584">CHR. Take the pots with which we are to establish11 the god, and carry them on your head in a stately manner, for you came yourself with a party-coloured dress on.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="585">OLD WOM. But on what account I came ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="586">CHR. All shall be immediately done for you. For the young man shall come to you in the evening.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1202"/>
          <p n="587">OLD WOM. Well, by Jove, ifl2 indeed you promise me that he shall come to me, I'll carry the pots. [ Takes up the pots and puts them on her head.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1202"/>
          <p n="588">CHR. (to the spectators). Well now, these pots act very differently from the other pots. For in the other pots the scum1 is on the top; but now the pots are on the top of this old woman.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1208"/>
          <p n="589">CHO. Therefore 'tis fitting that we delay no longer, but go) back to the rear; for we must follow after these, singing. [ Exeunt omnes.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
