<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moschus, Idylls</title>
        <author>Moschus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0035.tlg002.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.37"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.46"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.55"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.63"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.72"/>
          <p n="1.0">VENUS once sent upon Europa a sweet dream, what time the third portion of night sets in, and dawn is near; what time sleep sweeter than honey settling on the eyelids, limb-relaxing though it is, fetters down the eyes with soft bond; 2what time moreover the tribe of truthful dreams is roving abroad. Then as she slumbered in a chamber next the roof, the daugh ter of Phoenix, yet a maiden, Europa, fancied 3 that two conti nents were contending for her, Asia and the opposite coast, and they were in shape as women. Now of these the one had the form of a foreign woman, whilst the other in truth re sembled a native, and hugged her more closely as her own child; and kept saying that she-was her mother, and that herself had nurtured her. But the other, using violence with strong hands, was drawing her away, nothing loth: for she said that 'twas fated by ægis-bearing Jove that Europa should be her prize. She then started in affright from 4her strown couch, quak in- at heart, for she had beheld the dream as a real appear ance ; and seating herself she kept silence a long time, yet still had she before her waking eyes both the women. And late at length the maiden uplifted a timid voice, Who of the ce lestials has sent upon me such phantoms ? What manner of dreams are these which have exceedingly scared me, as I slumbered right sweetly in my chamber on my strown couch ? And who was that foreign woman, whom I beheld in my sleep? How did a yearning toward her strike me at heart! How graciously did she too welcome me, and regard me as her own child! But may the blessed gods decide the dream to me for good.' Thus saying, she sprang up; and went to seek her dear companions, in the prime of life, 'her equals in years, well-pleasing, and nobly-born, with whom she was ever wont to sport, 5when she was making ready for the choir, or when she might be washing her skin at the mouths of 6the Anaurus, or whensoever 7 she might be culling odorous lilies from the mead. And these quickly showed themselves to her, and they had each in their hands a basket for-holding-flowers; and they proceeded to go to the meadows by-the-shore, where too they were ever wont to gather themselves in one troop, delighting both in the growth of the roses and in the roaring of the sea. But Europa herself was carrying a basket wrought of gold, and ad mirable, a great wonder, a great work of Hephæstus, which he had bestowed on 8 Libya as a gift, when she went to the bed of the Earth-shaker; and she gave it to very-beauteous Telephas sa, who was of near kin to her; and upon Europa, yet unwed ded, her mother, Telephassa, bestowed it as a famous present. Whereon many sparkling curious-works had been wrought; on it indeed was wrought 9 of gold Io the daughter of Inachus, while still a heifer, and she had not the figure of a woman. And frantic she was going afoot over the briny paths, like unto one swimming; and a sea had been wrought of dark blue. And aloft, upon the brow of the shore, were standing two men together, and they were watching the sea-traversing heifer. On it moreover was 10Jupiter, son of Saturn, patting gently with his hand the heifer daughter of Inachus, whom beside seven-mouthed Nile he was transforming again to a woman from a horned cow. Of silver indeed was the stream of Nile; and the heifer, I ween, of brass; but Jove himself was fashioned of gold. 11 And about the crown of the rounded basket Hermes had been formed ; and near to him Argus had been represented stretched, distinguished by his sleepless eyes ; and from his deep-red blood was springing up a bird exulting in the many-hued colour of his wings, having spread wide the plumage of his tail, and like some ship speeding through the sea, he was covering all round with feathers the rims of the golden basket. Such was very-beauteous Europa's basket. Now these, when in truth they had entered the flowery meads, were then pleasing their fancy each with various kinds of flowers; one of them was plucking odorous narcissus, another hyacinth, another the violet, and another the creeping thyme: and on the ground were falling many leaves of spring-nursed 12 meadows. But others again were culling in rivalry incense-laden tufts of yellow crocus; in the midst however stood the princess, gathering with her hands the beauty of the bright-red rose, 13like as foam-born Venus shone conspicuous among the Graces. Not long however was she destined to please her fancy on flowers, or to 14 preserve, I wot, her virgin zone undefiled. For of a truth the son of Saturn, when he observed her, had then been smitten at heart, subdued by the unforeseen darts of Venus, who alone can overcome even Jove: wherefore now, both as desiring-to- avoid the wrath of jealous Here, and wishing to beguile the young fancy of the maiden, he concealed the god, and trans formed his body, 15 and became a bull; not such a one as feeds in the stalls, nor indeed such a one as cleaves a furrow, drag ging the curved plough; nor like one that grazes in the herds, no, nor of such a kind as the bull that is tamed and draws the heavy-laden wain. But of a truth the rest of his body was chestnut-coloured, whilst a silvery ring was gleaming on his mid forehead, and his eyes were 16 sparkling from under, flashing through desire; and horns equal one to the other were branching up from his head, like orbs of the horned moon, her disc cut in half; so came he into the meadow, and did not alarm the maidens by his appearance: 17but a longing to draw near to him arose in all, and to touch the lovely bull; for his divine scent from afar surpassed even the sweet odour of the meadow. And he stood before the feet of faultless Europa, and began to lick her neck, and to soften the maiden's heart. Then would she stroke him, and gently with her hands wipe off from his lips much foam, and she kissed the bull. But he 18 lowed softly: you might say that you heard a 19Mygdonian flute, uttering distinctly a clear sound; then he bent the knee before her feet, and began to look keenly on Europa, with his neck turned towards her, and to display to her his broad back. Then she bespoke her maidens with-thick-falling hair thus, ‘ Come, dear playmates of like age, that we may delight ourselves in sitting on the bull here; for in sooth he will spread his back beneath us, and take us all up, even as a ship; mild is he to look upon, and gentle, nor is he at all like to other bulls ; 20 and a right mind, as of a man, surrounds him, and he wants but speech.' Thus saying, 21 she took her seat smilingly on his back ; and the rest were about to do so; when straightway the bull sprang up, having carried off her whom he wished, and speedily he came to the sea. But she having turned her round began to call her dear companions, outstretching her hands; and they could not reach her, for having set foot on the strand he ran forward as a dolphin, and the Nereids emerged from out the brine, ay, the whole of them, I wot, arrayed themselves in line, 22 sitting on the backs of whales. And moreover heavily-roaring Earth-shaker himself above the sea, levelling the waves, led the briny way for his brother; and 23 the Tritons, dwellers in deep-flowing ocean, were gathered round him, sounding on long conches a nuptial melody.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.84"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.93"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.101"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.111"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.120"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.129"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.139"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.149"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.157"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.9"/>
          <p n="1.1">But she truly, sitting on the bull-like shoulders of Jupiter, with one hand indeed kept holding the bull's long horn, whilst in the other hand she was drawing back the folds of her purple-flowing robe, in order that the countless spray of the hoary brine might not wet the skirt of it when drawn towards her. Now the deep robe of Europa had been formed into loose folds at the shoulders, like the sail of a ship, and was wont to lighten the maiden. But when at length she was far from her fatherland, and 24 there appeared neither any sea- dashed shore, nor tall mountain, but air indeed above, and boundless ocean beneath, peering round about her, she gave vent to words like these: ‘ Whither bearest thou me, divine bull ? Who art thou ? Or how dost thou traverse the way 25 with untiring feet, and yet not shudder at the sea ? For by swift ships the sea is overrun, but bulls dread the briny path. What kind of drink is sweet to thee ? what food wilt thou get from the sea ? Art thou in truth, I wonder, some god ? For 26 thou dost acts beseeming the gods. Neither do marine dolphins walk upon land, nor bulls in any wise on the sea. But thou rushest unwetted over land and sea, and thine 27 hoofs are oars to thee. Nay, haply also lifted aloft above the azure air, thou wilt take flight, resembling swift birds. Ah me! ill-fated assuredly in a high degree; 28even I who, having left afar my father's house, and followed this bull, am pursuing a strange voyage, and roaming alone. But mayest thou, earth-shaking regent of the hoary sea, graciously light upon me ! I hope to behold this god directing my voyage, as my forerunner. For not without a god's help do I traverse these watery paths.' Thus spake she; and her the broad homed bull addressed thus: 'Take heart, maiden, fear not ocean's billow: I myself, look you, am Jove, though near at hand I seem to be a bull; yes, for I am able to appear whatso ever I choose. Now desire of thee hath impelled me to measure so much sea, taking the appearance of a bull: but Crete shall receive thee presently, Crete, which reared even myself; where shall be thy nuptials: and by me thou shalt bear illustrious sons, who shall all of them be sceptre-bearers among the dwellers upon earth. So said he: and what he said found fulfilment: Crete indeed at length appeared: and Jove again assumed his own form. And he loosed her girdle, and the 29 Hours prepared her bed, and she who was aforetime a maiden became presently bride of Jove. 30 And she bore sons to Jove and became a mother forthwith. [In connexion with this Idyll, Ovid Met. vi. 103, and Fast. v. 605— 612, may be read with advantage. See Chapman's notes.]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
