<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bion of Phlossa, Idylls</title>
        <author>Bion of Phlossa</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0036.tlg003.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.13"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.23"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.31"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.39"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.54"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="1.0">I WAIL for Adonis ; beauteous Adonis is dead. ‘Dead is beauteous Adonis;' the Loves join in the wail. Sleep no more, Venus, in purple vestments ;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.91"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.10"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.18"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.3.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.3.9"/>
          <p n="1.1">rise, wretched goddess, in thy robes of woe, 1and beat thy bosom, and say to all, ‘Beau teous. Adonis hath perished.' I wail for Adonis: the Loves join in the wail.' Low lies beauteous Adonis on the moun tains, having his white thigh smitten by a tusk, a white tusk, and he inflicts pain on Venus, as he breathes out his life faintly ; but adown his white skin trickles the black blood ; and his eyes are glazed neath the lids, and the rose flies from his lip; and round about it dies also the kiss, which Venus will never relinquish. To Venus, indeed, his kiss, even though he lives not, is pleasant, yet Adonis knew not that she kiss ed him as he died. I wail for Adonis: the Loves wail in concert. A cruel, cruel wound hath Adonis in his thigh, 2 but a greater wound doth Cytherea bear at her heart. Around that youth 3indeed faithful hounds whined, and Oread Nymphs weep; but Aphrodite, having let fall her braided hair, wanders up and down the glades, sad, unkempt, 4 unsandaled, and the brambles tear her as she goes, and 5cull her sacred blood: then wailing piercingly she is borne through long valleys, crying for her 6 Assyrian spouse, and calling on her youth. But around him dark blood was gushing up about his navel, and his breasts were empurpled from his thighs, and to Adonist the parts beneath his breasts, white before, became now deep-red. Alas, alas for Cytherea, the Loves join in the wail. She hath lost her beauteous spouse, she hath lost with him her divine beauty. Fair beauty had Venus, when Adonis was living ; but with Adonis perished the fair form of Venus, alas, alas ! All mountains, and the oaks say, ‘Alas for Adonis.' 7 And rivers sorrow for the woes of Aphrodite; and springs on the mountains weep for her Adonis, and 8 flowers redden from grief; whilst Cytherea sings mournfully along all 9 woody-mountain-passes, and along cities. Alas, alas for Cytherea, beauteous Adonis bath perished. And Echo cried in response, 'Beauteous Adonis bath perished.' 10 Who would not have lamented the dire love of Venus ? alas ! alas ! When she saw, when she perceived the wound of Adonis, which none might stay, when she saw gory blood about his wan thigh, unfolding wide her arms, she sadly cried, ' Stay, ill- fated Adonis, Adonis, stay : that I may find thee for the last time, that I may enfold thee around, and mingle kisses with kisses. Rouse thee a little, Adonis, and again this last time kiss me : kiss me just so far as there is life in thy kiss, 11till from thy heart thy spirit shall have ebbed into my lips and soul, and I shall have drained thy sweet love-potion, and 12have drunk out thy love: and I will treasure this kiss, even as if it were Adonis himself, since thou, ill-fated one, dost flee from me. Thou flyest afar, 0 Adonis, 13and comest unto Acheron, and its gloomy and cruel king ; but wretched I live, and 14 am a goddess, and cannot follow thee. Take, Proserpine, my spouse : for thou art thyself far more power ful than I, 15and the whole of what is beautiful falls to thy share ; yet I am all-hapless, and feel insatiate grief, and mourn for Adonis, since to my sorrow he is dead, and I am afraid of thee. Art thou dying, 0 thrice-regretted ? 16 Then my longing is fled as a dream ; and widowed is Cytherea, and idle are the Loves along my halls : and with thee has my charmed-girdle been undone ; nay, why, rash one, didst thou hunt ? Beauteous as thou wert, wast thou mad enough to contend with wild beasts ?' Thus lamented Venus ; the Loves join in the wail. Alas, alas for Cytherea, beauteous Adonis has perished. The Paphian goddess sheds as many tears as Adonis pours forth blood: and these all, on the ground, become flowers : 17 the blood begets a rose, and the tears the anemone. I wail for Adonis : beauteous Adonis hath perish ed. Lament no more, Venus, thy wooer in the glades : there is a goodly couch, there is a bed of leaves ready for Adonis ; this bed of thine, Cytherea, dead Adonis occupies; and though a corpse, he is beautiful, a beautiful corpse, as it were sleeping. Lay him down on the 18 soft vestments in which he was wont to pass the night: in which with thee along the night he would take his holy sleep, on a couch all-of-gold; yearn thou for Adonis, sad-visaged though he be now: and lay him 19 amid chaplets and flowers ; all with him, since he is dead, 20 ay, all flowers have become withered : but sprinkle him with myrtles, sprinkle him with unguents, with perfumes : perish all perfumes, thy perfume, Adonis, hath perished. Delicate Adonis reclines in purple vestments ; and about him weeping Loves set up the wail, 21 having their locks shorn for Adonis :-and one was trampling on his arrows, another on his bow, and 22 another was breaking his well-feathered quiver ; and one has loosed the sandal of Adonis, while an other is carrying water in golden ewers, and a third is bathing his thighs ; and another behind him is fanning Adonis with his wings. The Loves join in the wail for Cytherea herself: Hy menæus has quenched every torch at the door-posts, and shredded the nuptial wreath; and no more is 23 Hymen, no more Hymen the song that is sung, alas ! alas ! is chanted: alas, alas for Adonis, wail the Graces, far more than Hy menæus, for the son of Cinyras, saying one with another, ‘ Beauteous Adonis hath perished and far more piercingly speak they, than thou, 24 Dione. The Muses too strike up the lament for Adonis, and invoke him by song, but he heeds them not; not indeed that he is unwilling, but Proserpine does not release him. Cease, Cytherea, thy laments, refrain this day from thy dirges. 25 Thou must wail again, and weep again, another year.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.4.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.4.12"/>
          <p n="1">A BIRD-CATCHER, yet a boy, hunting birds in a leafy grove, spied Eros, 1from whom men-turn-away, perched on the branch of a box-tree ; and when he had observed him, in delight because in sooth it seemed to him a great bird,2 fitting together one on another his rods all at once, he proceeded to lay a trap for Eros, as he hopped 3 hither and thither. And the lad, being chagrined that no success befell him, threw down-his rods, and went to an old rustic, who had taught him this art; and spoke to him, and showed him Eros perch ing. 4 But the old man, gently smiling, wagged his head, and answered the boy: ' Beware of thy sport, and come not at yon bird ; fly far from it; 'tis an evil brute; happy will you be, 5 so long as you shall not have caught it; but if you shall have reached to man's stature, yon bird that now flees, and hops away, will come himself of his own accord, on a sudden, 6 and settle upon your head.'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.5.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.5.9"/>
          <p n="1">THE mighty Venus stood beside me, when I was yet 1 in youth's prime, leading with her fair hand infant Eros, nodding towards the ground; and addressed me as follows, ‘ Prythee, good herdsman, take and teach Eros to sing.' Thus said she, and herself went away; but I, witless as I was, began to teach Eros, as though he wished to learn, as many pastorals as I knew ; namely, how 2Pan invented the cross-flute, how Athena the pipe, how 3 Hermes the lyre, and how sweet Apollo the cithern. These I began to teach him; but he did not take heed to my words, but himself kept singing me love- ditties, and teaching me 4 the desires of mortals and immortals, and his mother's doings. And I forgot indeed all the strains which I was teaching Eros, but whatsoever love-ditties Eros taught me, I learned them all.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.6.1"/>
          <p n="1">THE Muses fear not the savage Eros, but love him from their hearts, and follow him close behind. And if haply one follow them having an unloving spirit, out of that man's way they fly, and are not willing to teach him. But if a man agitated in mind by Eros sing sweetly, to him every one of them hasten 1 in flowing stream. I am witness that this state ment is 2 universally true ; for if indeed I sing of any other mortal or immortal, my tongue 3 stutters, and sings no longer as before; but if again I warble any ditty to Eros, and to Lycidas, 4why then the strain flows joyously through my lips.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="5">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.7.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.7.9"/>
          <p n="1">1 I KNOW not how, nor is it fitting I should, to labour at what I have not learned. If my ditties are beautiful, then these only, which the 2 Muse has presented to me aforetime, will give me renown. But if these be not to men's taste, what boots it me to labour at more ? For if indeed Saturn's son or shifting fate had given to us a twofold life-time, so that one term might be spent on pleasure and delights, and the other in toil, 'twere possible perhaps for one, having first laboured, at some after-period to receive the fruits. But since the gods have allowed but one time for living to come to men, 3 and this a short space, and too brief for all, 4 how long, ah wretched men, do we toil over labours and works ? And how far are we to throw our whole souls upon gains and upon arts. longing ever for much more wealth ? Surely we have all forgotten that we were born mortal, and how brief a time we have had assigned to us by fate.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="6">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.8.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.9.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.10.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.11.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.12.1"/>
          <p n="1.0">Cleodamus. 1 OF spring, good Myrson, or winter, or autumn, or summer, what is pleasant to you ? And what do you desire most to come ? Is it summer, when all things, as many as we labour at, are completed ? Or sweet autumn, when hunger comes but lightly on men ? Or is it even 2idle winter ? since 'tis e'en in winter that many, while they warm themselves, 3 are overpowered by laziness and sloth. Or is beauteous spring more agreeable to you ? Tell me what your inclination prefers ; for our leisure has given us leave to speak. Myrson. For mortals to judge divine works is unmeet; for all these are holy and sweet; yet for your sake, Cleodamus, I will speak out which is to me more sweet than all the rest. I would not it were summer, 4for then the sun scorches me. I would not it were 5 autumn, for then ripe fruits breed disease. I dread to endure terrible winter, its falling snow and frosts. Come spring to me thrice-welcome in the 6 whole year, when there is neither frost, nor does sun oppress us. In spring every thing is fruitful. All sweet things burst forth in spring, 7 and night is equal to men, and morning the same. PERPLEXITY seized on 1 Phœbus experiencing so great grief; he began to seek every remedy, and strove to obtain a cunning art. And with ambrosia and nectar he anointed, he anointed all the wound; but for the fates all remedies are remediless. BLESSED are they who love, 2whensoever they are loved equally in return. Blest was 3 Theseus, when Pirithous was with him, even though he had descended to the abode of re lentless Hades. Blest was Orestes among the 4 churlish inhospitables, because Pylades had chosen common paths with him. 5 Achilles, grandson of Æacus, was fortunate in his friend's life-time, blessed was he in his death, because he warded off from him dire fate. IT is pot well, my friend, on every occasion to have re course to a craftsman, nor at all in every matter to have need of another, but 1do you even yourself fashion a Pan's pipe ; and it is an easy task for you. MAY Eros invite the Muses, may the Muses bring Eros : and to me, always yearning after it, may the Muses give song, the sweet song, than which 2 no charm is sweeter. 3 FROM the frequent drop, as the saying is, ever falling, even the stone is bored into a hollow. BUT I will go on my way to yon slope, 4 warbling at the sands of the shore, whilst I supplicate cruel Galatea : for I will not relinquish my sweet hopes even till extreme old-age. NEITHER leave me unrewarded, since even Phoebus gave a reward to song. And honour makes the things we do better. 5 BEAUTY is woman's grace: but man's is courage. Myrson. Are you willing now, Lycidas, sweetly to sing me 2 a Sicilian melody, delightsome, charming the mind, and amorous, such as the. Cyclops Polyphemus sung on the sea- shore to Galatea ? Lycidas. And if, Myrson, it be agreeable to me to sing to my pipe, then what shall my song be ? Myrs. I admire, Lycidas, the Scyrian strain, sweet love, the stolen kisses, the 3 stolen embrace of the son of Peleus. How he, a boy, put on a maiden's mantle, and how he belied his form, and how among the daughters of Lycomedes, Deidamia, 4 holding him in her arms, gratified Achilles, son of Peleus. Lycid. Once on a day, the herdsman carried off Helen ; and led her to Ida, a sore grief to Ænone ; then Lacedæmon was wroth, and gathered all the Achæan host. Nor did any man of Hellas, of Mycenæ, or Elis, or of the Laconians, stay behind in his home, 5bearing as vengeance dread war. But only Achilles was lying concealed among the daughters of Ly comedes, and was learning skill in wool, instead of arms, and in his white hand was holding a maiden's 6task; and in ap pearance he was as a girl; for he was equally womanish with them, and as fresh a colour as theirs blushed on his snowy cheeks; and he was wont to walk with the step of maiden hood, and to cover his hair with a veil; yet had he the spirit of Mars, and possessed the love of a man, and from dawn to nightfall would he sit beside Deidamia ; and at times indeed he would kiss her hand, and often 7 would he raise her beau teous mouth, and the sweet tears would flow forth. But with no other of like age did he eat; and he kept doing every thing in eagerness for a sleep in common. Then he spoke also a word to her, ‘ With one another other sisters slumber, but I remain alone, and thou sleepest 8 apart from me; we two, vir gins of like age, we twain beautiful. Yet sleep we alone in our several beds, and this evil and troublesome partition-wall 9 wickedly separates me from you. For not of you am I—’10 HESPER! 'golden light of the lovely Foam-born ! Hesper, dear friend, sacred ornament of dark night, hail, thou friend, 2as much more faint than the moon, as thou art eminent above the stars;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.13.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.14.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.15.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.16.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.17.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.18.1"/>
          <p n="1.1">and give thou me, as I go a merry-making to a shep herd, light instead of the moon : because she, beginning her course to-day, went down too quickly. I am not going forth for theft, nor to molest a wayfarer in the night: but I am a lover; and 'tis meet to return a lover love for love. GENTLE Cyprus-born goddess, child of Jove and the sea, why art thou so wroth with mortals and immortals ? I have said but little; rather, why dost thou so much hate them, and why, prythee, shouldest thou have given birth to Eros, so great a plague to all, cruel as he is, without natural affection, in mind nowise resembling his form ? And to what end hast thou given him to us 3 winged and a far-darter, that we might not be able to escape him, bitter as he is.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
