<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bion of Phlossa, Idylls</title>
        <author>Bion of Phlossa</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0036.tlg001.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.13"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.23"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.31"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.39"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.54"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="1.0">I WAIL for Adonis ; beauteous Adonis is dead. ‘Dead is beauteous Adonis;' the Loves join in the wail. Sleep no more, Venus, in purple vestments ;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.91"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.10"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.18"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.3.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.3.9"/>
          <p n="1.1">rise, wretched goddess, in thy robes of woe, 1and beat thy bosom, and say to all, ‘Beau teous. Adonis hath perished.' I wail for Adonis: the Loves join in the wail.' Low lies beauteous Adonis on the moun tains, having his white thigh smitten by a tusk, a white tusk, and he inflicts pain on Venus, as he breathes out his life faintly ; but adown his white skin trickles the black blood ; and his eyes are glazed neath the lids, and the rose flies from his lip; and round about it dies also the kiss, which Venus will never relinquish. To Venus, indeed, his kiss, even though he lives not, is pleasant, yet Adonis knew not that she kiss ed him as he died. I wail for Adonis: the Loves wail in concert. A cruel, cruel wound hath Adonis in his thigh, 2 but a greater wound doth Cytherea bear at her heart. Around that youth 3indeed faithful hounds whined, and Oread Nymphs weep; but Aphrodite, having let fall her braided hair, wanders up and down the glades, sad, unkempt, 4 unsandaled, and the brambles tear her as she goes, and 5cull her sacred blood: then wailing piercingly she is borne through long valleys, crying for her 6 Assyrian spouse, and calling on her youth. But around him dark blood was gushing up about his navel, and his breasts were empurpled from his thighs, and to Adonist the parts beneath his breasts, white before, became now deep-red. Alas, alas for Cytherea, the Loves join in the wail. She hath lost her beauteous spouse, she hath lost with him her divine beauty. Fair beauty had Venus, when Adonis was living ; but with Adonis perished the fair form of Venus, alas, alas ! All mountains, and the oaks say, ‘Alas for Adonis.' 7 And rivers sorrow for the woes of Aphrodite; and springs on the mountains weep for her Adonis, and 8 flowers redden from grief; whilst Cytherea sings mournfully along all 9 woody-mountain-passes, and along cities. Alas, alas for Cytherea, beauteous Adonis bath perished. And Echo cried in response, 'Beauteous Adonis bath perished.' 10 Who would not have lamented the dire love of Venus ? alas ! alas ! When she saw, when she perceived the wound of Adonis, which none might stay, when she saw gory blood about his wan thigh, unfolding wide her arms, she sadly cried, ' Stay, ill- fated Adonis, Adonis, stay : that I may find thee for the last time, that I may enfold thee around, and mingle kisses with kisses. Rouse thee a little, Adonis, and again this last time kiss me : kiss me just so far as there is life in thy kiss, 11till from thy heart thy spirit shall have ebbed into my lips and soul, and I shall have drained thy sweet love-potion, and 12have drunk out thy love: and I will treasure this kiss, even as if it were Adonis himself, since thou, ill-fated one, dost flee from me. Thou flyest afar, 0 Adonis, 13and comest unto Acheron, and its gloomy and cruel king ; but wretched I live, and 14 am a goddess, and cannot follow thee. Take, Proserpine, my spouse : for thou art thyself far more power ful than I, 15and the whole of what is beautiful falls to thy share ; yet I am all-hapless, and feel insatiate grief, and mourn for Adonis, since to my sorrow he is dead, and I am afraid of thee. Art thou dying, 0 thrice-regretted ? 16 Then my longing is fled as a dream ; and widowed is Cytherea, and idle are the Loves along my halls : and with thee has my charmed-girdle been undone ; nay, why, rash one, didst thou hunt ? Beauteous as thou wert, wast thou mad enough to contend with wild beasts ?' Thus lamented Venus ; the Loves join in the wail. Alas, alas for Cytherea, beauteous Adonis has perished. The Paphian goddess sheds as many tears as Adonis pours forth blood: and these all, on the ground, become flowers : 17 the blood begets a rose, and the tears the anemone. I wail for Adonis : beauteous Adonis hath perish ed. Lament no more, Venus, thy wooer in the glades : there is a goodly couch, there is a bed of leaves ready for Adonis ; this bed of thine, Cytherea, dead Adonis occupies; and though a corpse, he is beautiful, a beautiful corpse, as it were sleeping. Lay him down on the 18 soft vestments in which he was wont to pass the night: in which with thee along the night he would take his holy sleep, on a couch all-of-gold; yearn thou for Adonis, sad-visaged though he be now: and lay him 19 amid chaplets and flowers ; all with him, since he is dead, 20 ay, all flowers have become withered : but sprinkle him with myrtles, sprinkle him with unguents, with perfumes : perish all perfumes, thy perfume, Adonis, hath perished. Delicate Adonis reclines in purple vestments ; and about him weeping Loves set up the wail, 21 having their locks shorn for Adonis :-and one was trampling on his arrows, another on his bow, and 22 another was breaking his well-feathered quiver ; and one has loosed the sandal of Adonis, while an other is carrying water in golden ewers, and a third is bathing his thighs ; and another behind him is fanning Adonis with his wings. The Loves join in the wail for Cytherea herself: Hy menæus has quenched every torch at the door-posts, and shredded the nuptial wreath; and no more is 23 Hymen, no more Hymen the song that is sung, alas ! alas ! is chanted: alas, alas for Adonis, wail the Graces, far more than Hy menæus, for the son of Cinyras, saying one with another, ‘ Beauteous Adonis hath perished and far more piercingly speak they, than thou, 24 Dione. The Muses too strike up the lament for Adonis, and invoke him by song, but he heeds them not; not indeed that he is unwilling, but Proserpine does not release him. Cease, Cytherea, thy laments, refrain this day from thy dirges. 25 Thou must wail again, and weep again, another year.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
