<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moschus, Idylls</title>
        <author>Moschus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0035.tlg003.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.19"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.28"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.36"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.45"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.53"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.62"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.70"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.78"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.86"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.98"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.107"/>
          <p n="1.0">PLAINTIVELY groan at my bidding, ye woodland dells, and thou Dorian water, and weep, rivers, the lovely Bion; now wail at my bidding, ye plants, and now, groves, utter a wail ; now may ye flowers breathe forth your life in sad clusters ; 1 blush now sorrowfully, ye roses, now, thou anemone ; 2 now, hyacinth, speak thy letters, and with thy leaves lisp ‘ ai,' ‘ ai,' more than is thy wont: a noble minstrel is dead. Begin Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Ye nightingales, that wail in the thick foliage, tell the news to the Sicilian waters of 3Arethusa, that Bion the herdsman is dead, that with him both the song is dead, and perished is Doric minstrelsy. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Plaintively wail beside the waters, Strymonian swans, and with mournful voices sing a sorrowful ode, with as sweet a sound as was that of old, wherewith he used to sing to your lips. 4 And tell, again, to Æagrian maids, tell to all Bistonian nymphs, that the Dorian Orpheus has perished. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. That darling of the herds no longer sings: no longer does he warble, as he reclines beneath the solitary oaks: but in Pluto's realm he chants 5 a song of forgetfulness. And voice less are the hills; and the heifers, which roam with the bulls, lament and will not go to pasture. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Thy sudden fate, 0 Bion, even Apollo bewailed, and the , Satyrs grieved, and the dark-robed Priapi; and Pans sigh for thy melody, whilst the fountain nymphs through the wood mourned for thee, 6 and their tears became waters ; and Echo amid the rocks laments, because thou art mute, and mimics no more thy lips ; and at thy death the trees have cast off their fruit, and the flowers have all withered; good milk bath not flowed from ewes; nor honey from hives; but it has perished in the wax wasted with grief; for no longer is it meet, now that thy honey is lost, to gather that. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. 7Not so much did the dolphin lament beside the shores of the sea, nor so sang the nightingale ever on the rocks, no, nor* so much complained the swallow along the high mountains 8neither did Ceyx wail so much over the griefs of Halcyon. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. ' Neither did Cerylus sing so much in the gray-green waves, nor so much 9did the bird of Memnon, fluttering around his tomb, deplore the son of Aurora in the valleys of the East, as they have bewailed Bion, having perished. Begin, Silician Muses, begin the lament. Nightingales, and all swallows, which once he was wont to delight, which he was teaching to speak, sitting on the branches, of trees, kept wailing opposite to each other, whilst the other birds kept responding, Grieve, ye doves, but we will do so too. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Who shall sing to thy pipe, 0 thrice-regretted ? And who shall apply his lip to thy reeds ? Who so bold ? For even yet they breathe of thy lips and thy breath: and Echo amid the reeds feeds upon thy songs. To Pan I bear 10the pipe : haply even he would fear to set his mouth to it, lest he should carry off a second prize after thee. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. 11 Galatea too weeps for thy lay, she whom of old thou didst lelight, as she sat in thy company along the sea-beach. For lot like Cyclops didst thou sing: from him indeed the fair Galatea used to fly; but thee she was wont to regard 12with ore sweetness than the sea. And now, forgetful of the ve, she sits on the lonely sands, and even yet leads thy n to pasture. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. All along with thee, 0 herdsman, have perished the Muses' gifts, charming kisses of maidens, lips of boys : and around thy tomb weep sad-visaged Loves. Venus loves thee far more than the kiss, with which lately she kissed dying Adonis. This is a second grief to thee, most musical of rivers ! This, 3 0 Meles, is a fresh grief; to thy sorrow perished Homer foretime, that 14 sweet mouth of Calliope, and men say thou lidst deplore thine illustrious son in streams of much weeping, and didst fill all the sea with thy voice: now again thou deepest another son, and pinest over a fresh woe. Both were beloved by the fountains; the one indeed was wont to drink )f the Pegasean .spring ; the other, to enjoy a draught of the Arethusa. And the one sang the fair daughter of Tyndarus, and the mighty son of Thetis, and Menelaus, son of Atreus: but the other would sing not of wars, nor tears, but Pan; and would sound the praise of herdsmen, and feed the herd as he sang : and he was wont to fashion Pan's-pipes, and to milk the sweet heifer, and to teach the lips of youths, and to cherish Eros in his bosom, 'and rouse a passion in Aphrodite. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Every famous city laments thee, 0 Bion, as do all the towns: 16Ascra indeed wails for thee, far more than for Hesiod : not so much does Bœotian Hylæ regret Pindar ; nor so much did pleasant Lesbos weep about Alcæus: no, nor bath the Ceian town wept for her bard so much. Pares regrets thee more than Archilochus ; and Mitylene yet plaintively utters thy melody instead of Sappho's. All, as many as have a clear-sounding voice, all singers of pastorals by the Muses' favour, weep for thy fate, now thou art dead. 17 Sicelidas, the glory of Samos, weeps; and among the Cydonians, he who was aforetime cheerful to look on with his smiling eye, Ly cidas, yet sheds tears as he wails : whilst among the citizens of Cos, Philetas mourns beside the river Halens ; and among Syracusans, Theocritus : but I sing for thee a strain of 18 Au sonian sorrow, I, no stranger to the pastoral song, but heir to the Doric Muse, which thou didst teach thy scholars : honouring me, to others indeed thou didst leave thy wealth, but to me thy song. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Alas, alas, when once in a garden the mallows have died, or the green parsley, or blooming crisp dill, they live again after, and spring up another year. But we, the great, and brave, or wise of men, after we have once died, unheard of in hollow earth, sleep a right long and boundless slumber, from which none are roused.19 And in the earth thou indeed wilt be covered in silence, but it has seemed good to the Nymphs that the frog should croak for ever. Yet I envy him not: for 'tis no pretty song he sings. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Poison came, 0 Bion, to thy lip: thou knewest poison. How did it find access to thy lips, yet not become sweet ? or what mortal was so far ruthless, as to mix for thee, or to give thee the poison, if thou didst speak ? He shunned the power of song. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. But justice has overtaken all. And I, shedding tears over this woe, bewail thy fate; yet were I able, like 20 Orpheus, having gone down to Tartarus, like Ulysses once, or as Al cides in days of yore, I too would haply descend to the home of Pluto, that I might see thee, and, if thou singest to Pluto, that I might hear what thou singest. Nay, but in the pre sence of the damsel (Proserpine) warble some Sicilian strain, sing some pleasant pastoral. She too, being Sicilian, 21 sport - ed on the Ætnæan shores, and knew the Doric song: nor will thy strain be unhonoured;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.121"/>
          <p n="1.1">and as of old to Orpheus, sweetly singing to his lyre, she gave Eurydice to return, so will she send thee, Bion, to thy hills. Yes, if even I could avail aught by singing to my pipe, I too would sing before Pluto.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
