<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Acharnians</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">William James Hickie</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>William James Hickie (1853). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg001.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">CHORUS OF ACHARNIANS.</p>
          <p n="2">DAUGHTER OF DICÆOPOLIS.</p>
          <p n="3">SERVANT OF EURIPIDES.</p>
          <p n="4">DAUGHTERS OF THE MEGARIAN</p>
          <p n="5">SCENE.—At first the General Assembly, at the Pnyx; afterwards the house of Dicaeopolis, in the country.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="6">THIS Comedy takes its name from the natives of Acharnæ, who constitute the Chorus. In order of time, it is the first entire play which has come down to us. It was brought out in January, a. c. 425, 01. lxxxviii. 4, at the Lenæan feast of Bacchus, in the sixth year of the Peloponnesian war. It obtained the first prize, the of Cratinus the second, and the of Eupolis the third. Musgrave and Scaliger, deceived by the cor rupt reading, , in the argument, have ascribed it to B. c. 437, although the play itself, vs. 266, mentions the sixth year of the war, and quotes the Philoctetes of Euripides, vs. 424; and although the archonship of this Euthymenes is referred to as a distant date, vs. 67.—See Clinton's Fast. Hell. p. 69, second edition.</p>
          <p n="7">The plot is simply this:—Dicæopolis, an Athenian citizen, but an Acharnian by birth, tired at the continuance and miseries of the war, determines, if he cannot persuade the Athenians to adopt his measures, to make a peace for himself and family. The Athenians, elated by success, and urged on by the factious demagogues of the day, refuse to hear of it. Dicæopolis, therefore, despatches Amphi theüs to Sparta, on his own account. A private peace is, concluded, and its happy results are enumerated with all the festivity and license conceded to the old Comedy. For the political importance of Acharnæ, see Thucydides, book ii. c. xix. xx; and for other par ticulars, Anacharsis' Travels, vol. iv, 314, &amp;c., octavo edition. As tending to elucidate many passages, it may be observed, that Acharnæ abounded in charcoal works. This was the author's third play, the two preceding it, the (B. c. 427, under the name of Philonicles), and (B. c. 426, at the Great Dionysia, under the name of Callistratus), not having come down to us entire.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.28"/>
          <p n="8">How many things truly have I been vexed at in my heart; and with how few have I been pleased, how very few, some four! while the things I have suffered are countless. Come, let me see ; at what was I pleased that was worthy of exulta tion ? I know at what I was gladdened in my heart when I saw it,-at the five talents which Clean disgorged. How I was transported at this, and for this deed I love the Knights, for it was worthy of Greece ! But then again I suffered another woe, a tragic one ; just when1 I was gaping with expectation for Æschylus, the herald proclaimed, " Theognis,2 introduce your Chorus." You can't think how this agitated my heart! But then again I was pleased, when at length Dexitheus en tered, after Moschus,3 to sing a Boeotian strain. And this year I almost died, and stared my eyes asquint at the sight, when Chæris strutted forward to chaunt the Orthian strain. But never at any time since I began to wash, have I been so tor mented in my eyebrows by dust as now, when, the regular morning assembly being come, the Pnyx here is empty, while the members in the market-place gossip, and shift up and down to avoid the vermilion'd rope.4 Neither have the Prytanes arrived; and when they arrive too late, you can't think5 how they will jostle each other for the first seat6 rushing down in a body. But how peace is to be made, they take no heed. 0 city, city! While I, always coming first to the assembly, take my seat; and there being alone, groan, gape, stretch and yawn,1 break wind, puzzle, scribble, pluck my hairs, calculate, looking towards the country, anxious for peace, disgusted with the city, and longing for my own farm, which never at any time said, "Buy coals," or "vinegar, or "oil;" or knew the word "buy,"—but of itself produced all things, and the " buy" was absent. Now therefore I have come thoroughly prepared to bawl, interrupt, rail at the ora tors, if any one talk of any thing but peace. But see here come our Prytanes at noon ! Did I not say so ? Exactly as I said, every man of them is jostling for the first seat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.37"/>
          <p n="9">HER. Advance to the front; advance, that ye may be within the purified 2 ground.</p>
          <p n="10">AMP. Has any one spoken yet ?</p>
          <p n="11">HER. Who wishes to speak ?</p>
          <p n="12">AlP. No ; but an immortal. For Amphitheüs was son of Ceres and Triptolemus; and of him was born Celeüs; and Celeiis married my grandmother Phænarete, of whom was born Lucinus; and from him I, an immortal, am descended; and to me alone the gods intrusted to make peace with the Lacedæmonians. Yet, immortal as I am, sirs, I have no travelling allowance, for the Prytanes grant3 none.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.45"/>
          <p n="13">HER. Ho, Tipstaffs !</p>
          <p n="14">AMP. Triptolemus and Celeüs, will you allow me to be treated thus ?</p>
          <p n="15">Die. Mr. Prytanes, you wrong the assembly in ordering the mail to be led away,1 who was wishing to make peace for us, and hang up our bucklers. [Amphitheüs is ejected by force. ]</p>
          <p n="16">HER. Sit down, and hold your tongue.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.53"/>
          <p n="17">DIC. By Apollo, will I not, unless you bring forward a motion for peace.</p>
          <p n="18">HER. The ambassadors from the king.</p>
          <p n="19">DIC. What king?2 I am aweary of ambassadors, and their peacocks,3 and their quackeries. [Enter ambassadors gorgeously dressed out.]</p>
          <p n="20">Die. Bah ! Ecbatana, what a dress!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="21">AMB. You sent us to the great king, with a salary of two drachmae a day, in the archonship of Euthymenes.4</p>
          <p n="22">Die. Ah me ! the drachmae !</p>
          <p n="23">AMB. And in truth we were worn out with wandering about in tents along the plain of the Cayster, being half killed with reclining luxuriously on our close carriages.</p>
          <p n="24">Die. Why, did I get off well, who lay upon litter5 beside the battlements ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="25">AMB. And being entertained with hospitality, we drank against our wills, from cups of glass and golden chalices, sweet unmixed wine.</p>
          <p n="26">Die. 0 city of Cranaus ! perceivest thou the mockery of the ambassadors ?</p>
          <p n="27">AMB. For the Barbarians esteem those only men, who have the greatest power to eat and drink.</p>
          <p n="28">Die. While we consider wenchers and debauchees as such.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="29">AMB. Howbeit, on the fourth year we arrived at the palace ; but he had gone to ease himself, having taken an army; and for eight months he eased himself upon the golden mountains.</p>
          <p n="30">Die. When did the effects of the medicine wear off?</p>
          <p n="31">AMB. At the full of the moon : and then he returned home. Then he entertained us, and served up to us whole oxen from the baking pot.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="32">Die. And who ever beheld baked oxen ? What impostures !</p>
          <p n="33">AMB. And, by Jupiter, he served up to us a bird thrice the size of Cleonymus:1 its name was Cheat.</p>
          <p n="34">Die. For this reason then you 'cheated' us in taking two drachmæ.</p>
          <p n="35">AMB. And now we have brought with as Pseudartabas, the King's Eye.</p>
          <p n="36">Die. Would that a crow would strike and knock thine out, ambassador.</p>
          <p n="37">HER. The King's Eye!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.96"/>
          <p n="38">Die. King Hercules ! By the gods, main, do you look like a man of war, or, while doubling a promontory, are you look ing out for a dry-dock ? A rowlock-leather you have, I ween, about your eye below.</p>
          <p n="39">AMB. Come now, Pseudartabas, declare what the king sent you to say to the Athenians.</p>
          <p n="40">KING's EYE. Iartaman exarx' anapissonai satra.2</p>
          <p n="41">AMB. Do you understand what he says ?</p>
          <p n="42">Die. By Apollo, not I.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.104"/>
          <p n="43">AMB. He says the king will send you gold. Now say 'gold' louder, and distinctly.</p>
          <p n="44">KING'S EYE. Ou lepsi cruso chaunoproct' iaonau.3</p>
          <p n="45">Die. 0 wretched me! how distinctly!</p>
          <p n="46">AMB. What, then, says he ?</p>
          <p n="47">Die. Ask what he says?—he says the Ionians are gaping fools, if they expect gold from the Barbarians.</p>
          <p n="48">AMB. Not so; he speaks of chaldrons1 of gold.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.113"/>
          <p n="49">Die. What2 chaldrons? Truly you are a great impostor. But go to ; I will examine this man myself. Come now, tell me clearly, in the presence of this ambassador, lest I dip you in a Sardian 3 dye ; will the great king send us any gold ? [Pseudar tabas gives a nod of dissent.] Are we then heedlessly gulled by our ambassadors ? [Pseudartabas gives a nod of assent.] These fellows nodded assent at least in Greek, and they are certainly from this very country: Jand of the two eunuchs, this here one I know, who he is—Clisthenes, the son of Sibyrtius. 0 thou who hast a hot-tempered rump shaven,1 with such a beard as this, hast thou come to us dressed as a eunnch? But whoever is this? ifSurely it is not Straton ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <p n="50">HER. Silence: be seated. The senate invites the King's Eye to the Prytaneum. [Exeunt Pseudartabas and attend ants.]</p>
          <p n="51">Die. Is not this, pray, as bad as hanging ? And then do I, forsooth, tarry here ? while the door never5 restrains them from entertaining guests. I will do a dread and mighty deed. Where is Amphitheus ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.130"/>
          <p n="52">AMP. See, here he is. [Enter Amphitheüs.]</p>
          <p n="53">Die. For me alone, and for my children, and my wife, take these eight drachmas, and make peace with the Lacedæmonians. But do you1 send your embassies, and gape away. [Exit Ampltitheüs.] .</p>
          <p n="54">HER. Let Theorus come forth, who has returned from Sitalces.</p>
          <p n="55">Die. This is another impostor, who is summoned.</p>
          <p n="56">THEOR. We would not have been a long time in Thrace-</p>
          <p n="57">Die. By Jove, you wouldn't, if you did not receive a long salary.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.138"/>
          <p n="58">THEOR. Had not Zeus covered the whole of Thrace with snow and congealed the rivers, about the very time when Theognis2 here was contending for the prize. During this time I was drinking with Sitalces. And, in truth, he was marvellously fond of the Athenians, and of you he was a sin cere lover, so that he was even in the habit of writing on the walls3 " Pretty Athenians." And his son,4 whom we had made an Athenian citizen, was desirous of eating Apaturian5 sausages, and entreated his father to aid his country. And he swore with a libation, that he would lend his assistance, with so great a host, that the Athenians should exclaim, " What a swarm of locusts 6 approaches !"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.148"/>
          <p n="59">Die. May I die the worst of deaths, if I believe one jot of this, which you have said here, except the locusts.</p>
          <p n="60">THEOR. And now he has sent you the most warlike tribe of the Thracians.</p>
          <p n="61">Die. This is now evident.</p>
          <p n="62">THEOR. Come hither, you Thracians, whom Theorus brought.</p>
          <p n="63">Die. What plague have we here ?</p>
          <p n="64">THEOR. A band of the Odomanti.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.156"/>
          <p n="65">Die. What Odomanti ?2 Tell me, what means this? How came the Odomanti to resemble lewd Athenians ?</p>
          <p n="66">THE OR. If one give them two drachmae as their pay, they will overrun with light-armed troops the whole of Bceotia.</p>
          <p n="67">Die. Two drachmæ to these lewd fellows! With reason might our topmost rowers groan, the safeguards of the state. [ Thracians attack Dicæopolis and rob him.] Ah me, un happy man, I am undone! being robbed of my garlic by the Odomanti. Will you not lay down my garlic ?</p>
          <p n="68">THE OR. Wretched man ! Don't approach a these fellows when primed with garlic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.165"/>
          <p n="69">Die. Do the Prytanes suffer me to be treated thus in my own country, and that too at the hands of Barbarians ? I forbid you to hold an assembly4 for the Thracians on the subject of pay, and acquaint you that there is an omen from the sky,5 and that a drop of rain has struck me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.173"/>
          <p n="70">HER. The Thracians will retire, and present themselves the day after6 to-morrow ; for the Prytanes7 dismiss the as sembly. [Exeunt Theorus, Herald, &amp;c.]</p>
          <p n="71">Die. Ah me, unhappy man ! what an olio have I lost! But here's Amphitheüs from Lacedæmon. Hail, Amphitheüs! [Enter Amphitheüs.]</p>
          <p n="72">AMP. Not yet, until I cease running ; for I am obliged to escape from the Acharnians by flight.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="73">Die. What's the matter ?</p>
          <p n="74">AMP. I was hastening hitherward, bringing you a peace, but certain seniors of Acharnæ got scent of me, sturdy old fellows, tough as oak, inflexible, Marathon men, stout as maple. Then all of them lifted up their voices—" Abandoned villain ! do you bring a peace, when our vines are cut?" And they set a gathering some stones into their cloaks. But I fled, while they pursued and bellowed.</p>
          <p n="75">Die. Then let them bellow.1 But bringest thou the afore said peace ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <p n="76">AMP. Aye marry, here are three samples. These are for five years. Take and taste.</p>
          <p n="77">AMP. What 's the matter ?</p>
          <p n="78">Die. They please me not, because they smell of pitch and naval preparations.2</p>
          <p n="79">AMP. At least take and taste this, which is for ten years.</p>
          <p n="80">Die. This too smells very sharply of embassies to our towns, as it were of delay amongst the allies.</p>
          <p n="81">AMB. Well, this is for thirty3 years, both by land and sea.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.199"/>
          <p n="82">Die. 0 Dionysia ! These truly smell of ambrosia and nectar, and not to have in readiness provision for three4 days; and they say openly, " Go where thou wilt." These I receive, I make libation with, and will drink up, bidding a long fare well to the Acharnians. And I, freed from war and toils, will go within and celebrate the rural Dionysia.5 [Exit Dicæopolis.]</p>
          <p n="83">AMP. While1 I will escape from the Acharnians. [Exit Amphitheüs.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.204"/>
          <p n="84">CHO. Follow, each of you, this way, pursue, and inquire after the man from all the travellers; for 'tis worthy of our city to seize this fellow. But declare to me, if.any one knows where in the world he that bears the peace has turned. He is fled away ; he is vanished and gone. Alas my years, wretched man that I am ! In the days of my youth, when, bearing a load of coals, I followed Phayllus in the race, this truce-bearer would not have so easily escaped, when pursued by me; neither would he have so nimbly slipped off. But now, since at length my shin is stiffened, and the legs of the aged Lacratides are wearied, he is gone. He must be pursued ; for never let him laugh at us, nor one who, by having escaped the Acharnians, old men as we are, made peace, 0 Jove and ye gods, with our foes, against whom, on account of my estates, hostile war is increased by me; and I will Dot give over until, like a rush, I stick right into them sharp, painful, up to the hilt, so that they may never again trample on my vines. We must seek for the fellow, and look towards Ballene,3 and pur sue him from land to land,4 until at length he be found: for I could Dot be surfeited with pelting him with stones.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.219"/>
          <p n="85">Die. Use no ill-omened words: use no ill-omened words.</p>
          <p n="86">CiO. Silence, each of you. Did you hear, friends, the proclamation of silence ? This is the very person whom we are seeking for. Hither, each of you ; get out of his way; for the man, as it seems, is coming out to sacrifice.</p>
          <p n="87">Die. Use no ill-omened words: use no ill-omened words. Let the basket-bearer advance a little forward. Let Xanthias set up the Phallus erect.</p>
          <p n="88">WIFE. Do you, my daughter, put down the basket, that we may commence the rites.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.234"/>
          <p n="89">DAUGH. Mother, reach here the soup-ladle, that I may pour some soup upon this pan-cake.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.241"/>
          <p n="90">Die. Well, now 'tis right, 0 sovereign Bacchus, that I, hav ing led this procession agreeably to thee, and having sacrificed with my household, should celebrate the rural Dionysia hap pily, having been freed from military service; and that my peace for thirty years turn out well.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.253"/>
          <p n="91">WIFE. Come, daughter, take care that, pretty as you are, you bear the basket prettily, with a verjuice face. How blest the man who shall wed you, and beget upon you pussies to stink no less than you, as soon as it is dawn. Proceed, and in the crowd take especial care, that no one secretly nibbles off your golden ornaments.</p>
          <p n="92">Die. 0 Xanthias,l you two must hold the Phallus erect be hind the basket-bearer, and I following will sing the Phallic hymn ; and do you, wife, look at me from the house-top. [Ex eunt wife and daughter.] Proceed, 0 Phales, companion of Bacchus, fellow-reveller, roaming by night, friend of love and lechery: in the sixth year I address you, having come with delight to my township, having made for myself a peace, and being freed from troubles and battles and Lamachi.2 For it is far sweeter, 0 Phales, Phales ! having found a pretty wood gatherer, Strymodorus' Thracian maid, purloining wood from Phelleus,3 to catch her by the waist and lift her up, and throw her down and roll her in the grass. 0 Phales, Phales! if with us you quaff your cups, in the morning, after your sick head-ache, you shall gulp down a bowl-of peace; and my shield shall be hung up amidst the sparks.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.261"/>
          <p n="93">CEO. This is the very fellow, this: pelt, pelt, pelt, pelt; strike, strike the wretch, each of you ; will you not pelt ? will you not pelt ? [ Chorus pelts him.]</p>
          <p n="94">Die. 0 Hercules ! what's this? You'll smash my pitcher.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.271"/>
          <p n="95">CHe. Nay, rather, we will stone you to death, rascally fellow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.280"/>
          <p n="96">Die. For what cause, Acharnian seniors ?</p>
          <p n="97">CHO. Do you ask this ? You are shameless and abomin able, 0 betrayer of your country, who, having made a peace without us,' canst look me in the face.</p>
          <p n="98">Die. But ye do not know wherefore I made the peace: hear me.</p>
          <p n="99">CHO. Shall we hear you ? You shall perish; we will overwhelm you with stones.</p>
          <p n="100">Die. By no means, before you hear me; come, have patience, good sirs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.293"/>
          <p n="101">CiO. I will not be patient ; nor do thou utter a word to me, for I hate thee still more than Cleon, whom I will cut up into shoe-soles for the Knights. I'll not hearken to you uttering long speeches, who have made a peace with the Lacedaemonians ; but will punish you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.305"/>
          <p n="102">Die. Good sirs, leave the Lacedæmonians out of the ques tion ; and hear my peace, if I have rightly made it.</p>
          <p n="103">CHio. How can you any more talk of "rightly," if once you have made peace with those, with whom neither altar, nor pledge, nor oath 3 holds good ?</p>
          <p n="104">Die. I know that the Lacedaemonians, against whom we are excessively vehement, are not the causes of all our troubles.</p>
          <p n="105">CHO. Not of all, you villain ? Hast thou the audacity, pray, openly to say this to us ? Then shall I spare you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.313"/>
          <p n="106">DIC. Not of all, not of all; but I here, who address you, could prove abundantly that they have even been injured in some cases.</p>
          <p n="107">CHO. This expression is dreadful and heart-troubling, if you shall dare to speak to us in defence of our foes.</p>
          <p n="108">Die. And if I speak not what is just, and am not approved of by the people, I shall he ready to speak with this neck of mine over a chopping-block.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.321"/>
          <p n="109">CHO. Tell me, fellow-tribesmen, why spare we our stones, so as not to card this fellow into a scarlet rag ?</p>
          <p n="110">Die. How again a black burning coal has blazed up within you ! Will you not hear, will you not hear, pray,' 0 sons of the Acharnians ?</p>
          <p n="111">CHO. Assuredly we will not hear you.</p>
          <p n="112">Die. Then I shall suffer dreadful things.</p>
          <p n="113">CHO. May I utterly perish if I hear you.</p>
          <p n="114">Die. By no means, 0 Acharnians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.331"/>
          <p n="115">CHO. Be assured now that you shall die.</p>
          <p n="116">Die. Then I will sting you; for I will kill in turn the dearest of your friends, since I have hostages of you, whom I will take and butcher.2 [Seizes a hamper of charcoal, and dresses it up like a baby.]</p>
          <p n="117">CHO. Tell me,3 fellow-tribesmen, what word is this, with which he threatens us Acharnians ? Has he shut up within a child of any of those present ? or at what is he embold ened ?</p>
          <p n="118">Die. Pelt, if ye will, for I will kill this one. I shall quickly know who of you cares at all for coals.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.340"/>
          <p n="119">CiO. How we are undone! this coal-basket is my fellow tribesman. But do not do what you purpose; by no means, 0 by no means !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.347"/>
          <p n="120">Die. Be assured that I will kill him: 4 cry on, for I will not hear you.</p>
          <p n="121">CHO. Will you then kill this my companion in age, the friend of colliers ?</p>
          <p n="122">Die. But you did not just now give ear to me when I spoke.</p>
          <p n="123">CiO. Well now, if it seems good to you, say that the Lace dæmonians themselves are dear to your mind; for never will I betray this little coal-basket.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.357"/>
          <p n="124">Die. First, then,5 empty your stones upon the ground.</p>
          <p n="125">CiO. See ! they're on the ground ; and do you in turn lay down your sword.</p>
          <p n="126">Die. But see that some stones are not lying in ambush somewhere in your cloaks.1</p>
          <p n="127">CiO. They have been shook out on the ground. Don't you see it shaking ? No excuses ; lay down your weapon; since this is shaken with the whirl in the dance.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.368"/>
          <p n="128">Die. So then you were all of you going 2 to raise a war cry, and the coals of Parnes all but met with their death, and that too on account of the unnatural conduct of their fel low-tribesmen ; and under the influence of fear the coal-basket, like a cuttle-fish, squirted upon me abundant coal-dust. For it is a sad thing that the mind of men should be naturally harsh,3 so as to pelt and shout and be willing to hear nothing which offers half and half, while I am willing to say over a chopping-block all that I say in behalf of the Lacedaemonians ; and yet I love my life.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.377"/>
          <p n="129">CHO. Why then don't you bring out the chopping-block and state, you wretch, whatever is this weighty matter which you have in hand ? for an earnest desire strongly possesses me to know what you have in your mind. But place here the chopping-block and begin to speak, as you yourself deter mined the punishment. [Exit Dicœopolis, and re-enter with a chopping-block.]</p>
          <p n="130">Die. Lo, behold! here is the chopping-block, and the man who is to speak, see here! as small as this ! Of4 a surety I'll not fit myself with a shield, by Jupiter, but will speak in behalf of the Lacedæmonians what seems good to me. And yet I greatly fear, for I know the humour of the rustics to be wondrous tickled, if any quack praise them and their city, right or wrong : and there unknowingly they are bought and sold.5 Of the elders again I know the mind, that they look to nothing else except vexing with their vote; and I know what I suffered myself at the hands of Cleon, on account of my last1 year's comedy. For he dragged me into the senate-house, and calumniated me, and spoke lies against me, and roared like the torrent Cycloboros, and drenched me so that I almost perished altogether, getting into dirty quarrels. Now, therefore, in the first place permit me, ere I speak, to clothe myself like a most wretched man.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.385"/>
          <p n="131">CHO. Why shuffle in this way, and deal subtilly, and con trive delays ? Borrow, for all I care, from Hicronymus 2 some helmet of Pluto dark with rough thick hair, and then exhibit Sisyphus's wiles, since this trial will not admit of any excuse.3</p>
          <p n="132">Die. Then 'tis time for me to take a bold heart, and I must repair to Euripides.—Slave, slave ! [Knocks at the door.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="133">SERVo OF EUR. Who's that ?</p>
          <p n="134">DIC. Is Euripides within ?</p>
          <p n="135">SERV. OF EUR. Not within, he is within, if you have any sense.</p>
          <p n="136">Die. How within, and then not within ?</p>
          <p n="137">SERVo OF EUR. Rightly, old man. His mind, collecting scraps of poetry abroad, is not within, while he himself with in is making tragedy with his legs lying up.4</p>
          <p n="138">Die. Thrice happy Euripides! when your servant inter prets5 so wisely. Call him out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.404"/>
          <p n="139">SERVo OF EUR. It is impossible.</p>
          <p n="140">Die. Still you must; for I won't go away, but will knock at the door. Euripides, dear little Euripides,1 hearken, if ever you did to any man. Dicæopolis of Collidæ calls you</p>
          <p n="141">EUR. I have no leisure.</p>
          <p n="142">Die. Yet be wheeled out.</p>
          <p n="143">EUR. It is impossible.</p>
          <p n="144">Die. Yet, however, do.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.412"/>
          <p n="145">EUR. Well then, I will be wheeled out; but I have no leisure to descend. [Euripides is wheeled in.]</p>
          <p n="146">EUR. What sayest thou ?</p>
          <p n="147">Die. You make verses with your legs lying up, when you might with them down. No wonder you make your charac ters lame. But why wear you the rags from tragedy, a piteous attire ? No wonder you make your characters beg gars. Come, I beseech you by your knees, Euripides, give me some little rag from your old drama,3 for I must speak a lengthy speech to the chorus ; and if I speak it badly it brings me death.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.420"/>
          <p n="148">EUR. What rags ? those in which Æneus here, the wretched old man, contended ? [Points to a suit of rags.]</p>
          <p n="149">Die. They were not Æneus's, but a still more wretched man's.</p>
          <p n="150">EUR. The rags of the blind Phoenix ?</p>
          <p n="151">Die. Not Phœnix's, no; there was another more miserable than Phoenix.</p>
          <p n="152">EUR. What ragged garments does the man require ? What! do you mean the rags of the beggar Philoctetes ?</p>
          <p n="153">Die. No ; but of one far, far more beggarly than he.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.428"/>
          <p n="154">EUR. What! do you wish for the squalid garments which Bellerophon, this lame fellow, wore ?</p>
          <p n="155">Die. Not Bellerophon; yet he too, whom I mean, was lame, an importunate beggar, and the deuce at talking.</p>
          <p n="156">EUR. I know the man—Telephus of Mysia.</p>
          <p n="157">Die. Aye, Telephus: give me, I entreat you, his swad dling-clothes.</p>
          <p n="158">EUR. Slave, give him the rags of Telephus: they lie above the Thyestean rags, between1 those of Ino and his.</p>
          <p n="159">SERV. Well! take them.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.437"/>
          <p n="160">Die. 0 Jupiter, that seest through2 and beholdest all things on every side, grant me to dress myself like a most wretched man.3 [Puts on the old coat.] Euripides, since you have freely given me these, give me also those things which go with the rags-the little Mysian cap about my head. " For to-day 'tis needful that I seem to be a beggar; to be indeed what I am, but not to appear so." The spectators must know who I am; but the chorus, on the other hand, must stand by like fools, that I may fillip them with quibbles.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.445"/>
          <p n="161">EUR. I will give it; for you devise subtleties with a sa gacious intellect.</p>
          <p n="162">Die. Mayest thou be happy ! but to Telephus,6 what I wish him. Bravo! How I am filled now with quibbles! But still I want the beggar's stick.</p>
          <p n="163">EUR. Take this, and begone from my stone dwelling.</p>
          <p n="164">Die. My soul,-for thou seest how I am driven away from his house, though in want of many articles of dress,-now be thou importunate, teasing, and earnest in prayer. Euripides, give me a little basket burnt through with a lamp.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.454"/>
          <p n="165">EUR. What need, unhappy man, possesses you for this wicker-work ?</p>
          <p n="166">Die. No need, but still I wish to take it.</p>
          <p n="167">EUR. Know that thou art troublesome, and begone from my house.</p>
          <p n="168">Die. Alas ! Mayest thou be happy, as once thy mother !</p>
          <p n="169">DIC. Nay, grant me only one little cup whose rim is knocked off!</p>
          <p n="170">EuR. Take it, and be damned !1 know that you are trouble some to the house.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.462"/>
          <p n="171">Die. By Jove, (aside,) you know not yet what ills you work yourself. — But, sweetest Euripides, give me only this, a little pipkin stopped up as to its chinks with sponge.</p>
          <p n="172">EUR. Fellow, you will rob me of my tragedy.2 Take this and depart.</p>
          <p n="173">Die. I am going: and yet what shall I do? for I need one thing, which, if I obtain not, I am undone. Hear, sweetest Euripides ! If I obtain this, I will depart, and will not come any more. Give me some withered green-stuff for my little basket.</p>
          <p n="174">EUR. You will ruin me. Here they are. My dramas are vanished!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.470"/>
          <p n="175">DIC. Well, I'll beg no more, but will be gone ; for I am exceeding troublesome,3 " not considering that the chiefs ab- hor me." Ah me, unhappy ! how I am undone ! I have for gotten that on which all my affairs depend. Sweetest and dearest little Euripides ! may I perish most miserably, if I ask for any thing any more, but one thing only, this only one, this only one. Give me the chervil you got from your mother.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.479"/>
          <p n="176">EUR. The fellow becomes insolent: shut the door.2 [Ex eunt Euripides and his slave.]</p>
          <p n="177">Die. Heart of mine ! we must proceed sans chervil. Do you know how great is the contest you will soon have to en counter, about to speak in behalf of the Lacedæmonians? Proceed then, my heart! there is the starting-place! Do you stand ? Will you not go, after having imbibed Euripides ? —I commend you. Come now, unhappy heart! go there, and then, there offer your head, and say what seems you good. Dare :-go: advance.3 Well done, heart! [Lays his head on the chopping-block. J</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.490"/>
          <p n="178">CHO. What will you do ? What will you say ? Know now that you are a shameless and an iron-hearted man, who, having offered your neck to the state, alone are going to con tradict them all. The man does not tremble at the cause. Come now, since you yourself make the choice, say on.</p>
          <p n="179">Die. Take it not ill of me, spectators, if, being a beggary I am yet about to speak amongst the Athenians on the subject of their state, in comic verse, for even comedy knows what is right: and my words will be severe, but just. For Cleon shall not now1 calumniate me, that I slander the state in the pre sence of strangers; for we are by ourselves, and the contest is in the Lenæum;2 and as yet strangers are not present; for neither is the tribute come in, nor the allies from the states. But now we are winnowed clean ; for the sojourners I call the chaff of the citizens. I hate the Lacedæmoni ans exceedingly, and may Neptune, the god of Tænarus, with an earthquake,3 shake and throw down on all of them their houses; for my vines have been cut down as well as yours. But,-for those who are present at my speech are friends, why do we thus accuse the Lacedmonians ? For men of us,—I do not mean the state, bear this in mind, that I do not mean the state, but certain rascally fellows, base coin, unfranchised, and counterfeit, and alien-citizens, were in the habit of informing against the small cloaks of the Megarians :4 and if any where they were to see a cucumber, or a leveret, or a sucking-pig, or garlic, or salt in lumps,5 these were Me garian, and were confiscated the same day. And these, in deed, are trifles, and customary.6 But certain young men, drunk with playing at the cottabus, went to Megara and stole away the courtesan Simætha; and then the Megarians, ex cited by their griefs, stole away in return two harlots from Aspasia;7 and hence the beginning of the war broke out for all the Greeks from three strumpets. Then Pericles, the Olympian, in his ire, lightened, thundered, utterly confounded Greece, enacted laws, written like catches, " That the Megari ans should neither remain in our territory, nor in our markets, nor on the sea, nor on the mainland."1 Then the Megarians, when now they were gradually famishing, entreated the Lace dæmonians that the decree which had been made on account of the strumpets might be changed through their intervention; and we were not willing, though they often entreated us. And after this now there was a clatter of bucklers. Some one will observe, we ought not: but tell us what we ought to have done. Come, if some Lacedæmonian sailed out with his ship and informed against and sold a little Seripbian dog, would you have sat still at home ? Far from it, certainly. Most assuredly you would have launched immediately three. hundred vessels, and the city would have been full of the din of soldiery, of shouting about the election of a Trierarch, pay being issued, figure-heads getting gilded, piazzas groan ing, provisions getting measured out, of wine-skins, of oar leathers, of people buying jars, of garlic, olives, onions in nets, chaplets, sprats, flute-girls, and black eyes. And the dock yard again had been filled with spars getting cut into oars, wooden pins sounding, bottom-oars getting furnished with thongs, boatswain's flutes, fifes, whistlings. I know that you would have done this, " and do we not imagine that Telephus2 will do the like? Then there is no sense in us."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.500"/>
          <p n="180">1 SEM. CHOR.3 What, really, you rogue and blackguard? Have you the audacity to say this of us, you beggar? And if any of us has been an informer, do you upbraid us with it?</p>
          <p n="181">2 SEM. CHOR. Yea, by Neptune, and he says too, what he does say, all justly ; and about none of them does he tell lies.</p>
          <p n="182">1 SEM. CHOR. Then, if it was just, ought this fellow to mention it? But neither shall you dare to say this with impunity.4</p>
          <p n="183">2 SEM. CHOR. Hollo you! whither are you running ? will you not stop ? Since if you strike this man, you yourself shall quickly be raised aloft!1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.508"/>
          <p n="184">1 SEM. CHOR. Ho, Lamachus ! thou who lookest lightning, help us, thou with the Gorgon crest, having appeared !—Ho, Lamachus ! friend ! fellow-tribesman ! let every one as sist with speed, if any there be a Taxiarch or engineer, for I am seized by the middle.</p>
          <p n="185">LAM. Whence heard I the warrior cry ? Whither must I , render assistance ? whither send in tumult ? Who roused the Gorgon from my shield's cover?</p>
          <p n="186">Die. (affecting to be terrified,) 0 hero Lamachus! what crests and cohorts !</p>
          <p n="187">CHOR. 0 Lamachus! has not this fellow for a long time been speaking evil of our whole city ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.520"/>
          <p n="188">LAM. You there! do you, you beggar, dare say this ?</p>
          <p n="189">DIC. 0 hero Lamachus ! yet pardon me, if, a beggar, I have spoken, and babbled any thing.</p>
          <p n="190">LAM. What have you said of us ? Will you not tell ?</p>
          <p n="191">Die. I don't know as yet, for I am dizzy in my head through fear of your arms. But, I entreat you, remove from me the bugbear.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.528"/>
          <p n="192">LAM. Very well! [Turns away the shield from him. ]</p>
          <p n="193">Dic. Now place it for me upside down.3</p>
          <p n="194">LAM. There it lies. [Puts the shield upside down before him.]</p>
          <p n="195">DIC. Come now, give me the him.]feather 4 out of your helmet.</p>
          <p n="196">LAM. Here's a feather for you.</p>
          <p n="197">Die. Now take hold of my head, that I may vomit, for my stomach's turned at the crests.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.538"/>
          <p n="198">LAM. Hollo you! what are you going to do ? Are you about to cause a vomit with the feather ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.552"/>
          <p n="199">Die. Why, is it a feather ? Tell me, what bird's ? Is it a braggadocio's ?1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.560"/>
          <p n="200">LAM. Woe for you, assuredly you shall2 die. [A scuffle, in which Lamachus is foiled.]</p>
          <p n="201">Die. By no means, Lamachus; for it is not a matter for such strength as yours. But if you are strong, why don't you give a proof of it ? for you are well armed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.569"/>
          <p n="202">LAM. You say this of your general, you beggar ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.577"/>
          <p n="203">Die. Why, am I a beggar ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.585"/>
          <p n="204">LAM. Then what are you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.593"/>
          <p n="205">Die. Ask me who ?-a good citizen, no stickler for office, but, since what time the war commenced, a son of Mars; while you, since what time the war commenced, a Mr. Place man.</p>
          <p n="206">LAM. For they elected me.</p>
          <p n="207">Die. Aye,3 three cuckoos. Therefore, being disgusted at this, I made peace, when I saw hoary-headed men in the ranks, but striplings, such as you,4 shirking the ser vice ;5 some in Thrace, with an allowance of three drachmæ, Tisameno-Phænippi;6 Panourg-Hipparchidæ ; others with Chares ; others among the Chaonians, Gereto-Theodori; Diomei-Alazones; others at Camarina,l and at Gela, and at Catagela!2</p>
          <p n="208">LAM. For they were elected.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.607"/>
          <p n="209">Die. But what's the reason that you somehow or other always receive pay, while none of these present gets any? Prithee, Marilades, you with the grey head, have you ever been on an embassy ? [touches his pocket.] See! he shakes his head; and yet he is temperate and hard-working. What, pray, says Draeyllus, or Euphorides, or Prinides ? Has any among you knowledge of Ecbatana, or the Chaonians ? They say no. But the son of Cæsyra3 and Lamaehus know them; whom lately, on account of their shot and debts, like those who pour out their dirty wash-water of an evening, all their friends exhorted,4 " Get out of the way."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.618"/>
          <p n="210">LAM. 0 democracy ! Is this then to be endured ?</p>
          <p n="211">Die. Certainly not, unless Lamachus gets paid for it.</p>
          <p n="212">LAM. Well then, I will ever wage war with the Pelopon nesians, and will harass them in every way, both with ships and land forces, to the best of my power.</p>
          <p n="213">Die. I, on the other hand, give notice to all the Pelopon nesians, and Megarians, and Bœotians, to sell, to traffic with me, but not with Lamaehus.5 [Exeunt omnes</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.626"/>
          <p n="214">CHOR. The man prevails with his arguments, and makes converts of the people on the subject of the peace. But let us strip and follow with our Anapaests.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.636"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.655"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.665"/>
          <p n="215">From the time that our instructor has presided over the comic choruses, he never yet came forward to the spectators to tell how clever he is. But being calumniated1 among the hasty-deciding Athenians by his enemies, that he ridicules our state and insults the democratic party, he wants now to make his defence before the changeful Athenians. Now your poet says he is worthy of much good treatment at your hands, in that he put an end to your being neatly cajoled by strangers' words,2 and to your delighting in flattery, and to your being gaping-mouthed cockneys.3 And formerly the ambassadors from the cities, trying to cajole you, used first to call you " violet crowned;" 4 and as often as any one said this, immediately, by reason of the " crowns," you sat on the tips of your-bums.5 And as often as any one soft-sawdered you and called you " sleek Athens," he used to obtain all his wish through the "sleekness," for having attached to you the glory of an anchovy.6 By having done this, he has been the cause to you of many advantages, and from having made known to you how the people in the cities live under a democracy.7 Accordingly, now from the cities they have come, bringing in to you tribute, desiring to see the best of poets, who had the hardihood to say amongst the Athenians what is just. And so far already has the fame of his daring reached, wlren even the King, questioning the embassy of the Lacedæmonians, first asked them whether of the two had the superiority at sea ; and then about this poet,1 which of the two lie plentifully abused. For he said that those people must have become far better, and would be far superior in war, who had him as an adviser. For this reason the Lacedæmonians make you pro posals of peace, and demand back Ægina. And for that island2 they do not care, but only that they may dispossess this poet. But do you therefore never give him up, inas much as he will represent in his comedies what is right. And he says he will teach you mauy good points, so that you be fortunate, not by wheedling you, nor yet by offering bribes, nor yet by cheating a little, nor yet by playing the villain, nor yet by besprinkling you with praise, but by teaching what is best. Wherefore let Cleon cunningly devise, and con trive every thing against me : for that which is good, and that which is just with me, shall be my ally; and never will I be found, like him, a cowardly and effeminate minister of the state. Come hither, ardent, eager, Acharnian Muse, having the strength of fire, like as the sparks, roused by the favouring fan, bounce from the oaken ashes, when our small fry are lying in readiness, while others mix up the sparkling3 Thasian pickle, and others knead the bread. Come thus to me, your fellow-tribesman, with a pompous, vehement, rustic melody.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.683"/>
          <p n="216">We aged veterans blame the city; for we are not cherished in our old age in a manner worthy of those our naval victo ries, but we suffer hardships at your hands, who having east aged heroes into suits, suffer us to be laughed at by stripling orators, being nothing but dumb and crack-voiced, whose preserving Neptune is the staff we bear. And babbling through age, we take our stand at the bar,1 not seeing any thing but the mist of Justice. While he, eager to have a stripling2 act as junior counsel to himself, strikes quickly,3 engaging him with periods well-rounded; and then he drags into court the aged Tithonus, and interrogates him, setting word-traps, rending and troubling and confounding him. But he mumbles through old age, and then, cast in his suit, departs. Then he whines, and weeps, and says to his friends, " I depart, having incurred as a fine that wherewith I was to have bought a coffin."4 How is this fitting, to ruin an old man, a hoary warrior, at the clepsydra, who has la boured much with you, and wiped off the heated sweat, manly, indeed, and copious, who acted the warrior's part at Marathon, for the city's sake ? Then, when we were at Ma rathon, we were the pursuers,5 but now we are pursued by very knavish men; and are taken besides. What will Marpsias reply to this ? 6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.692"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.706"/>
          <p n="217">For how is it fitting that a man bent double, such as Thu- cydides,1 should perish, entangled in the Scythian wilderness, this Cephisodemus, the prattling advocate? Wherefore I pitied him, and wiped my eyes, when I saw an aged man confounded by an archer-fellow; who, by Ceres, when he was Thucydides, would not readily have put up with even Ceres herself; but first he would have floored in wrest ling ten Evathli, and with bawling would have silenced three thousand Archers, and would have out-constahled2 the relations of the father himself of Cephisodemus. But, since you do not suffer the aged to get any sleep, decree that the indictments be separate, so that the advocate of the old man may be old and toothless; but the young men's, lewd and prating, and the son of Clinias.3 And henceforth it is the old man's 4 business to banish, and, if one be brought to trial, to fine the old, and the young man's business to banish and fine the young.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.719"/>
          <p n="218">Die. These are the boundaries of my market-place. Here it is allowable for all the Peloponnesians, and Megarians, and Bœotians to traffic, on condition that they sell to me, and not to Lamachus. But as clerks of the market6 I appoint these three, who have obtained the office by lot,—thongs from Mange town. Here let neither any sycophant enter, nor any other that is a man of Phasis.7 But I will go to fetch the pillar," upon which I have inscribed the peace, that I may set it up in the market-place open to view. [Exit Dicæopolis.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.727"/>
          <p n="219">MEG. Market of Athens, hail! beloved of the Megarians! By the god of friendship, I longed for you, as for a mother. But, 0 unhappy daughters of a miserable father, get2 up to the barley-cake, if any where you find it. Hear, pray; let your bellies3 give attention. Whether do you wish to be sold, or miserably starve ?</p>
          <p n="220">DAUGH. To be sold ! to be sold!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.735"/>
          <p n="221">MEG. I also myself say yes. But who so simple as to buy you, an evident loss ? However, I have a certain Megarian device; for I will dress you up as hogs and say I am bring ing them for sale. Put on these hog's hoofs, and take care that you appear to be the offspring of a noble sow; since, by Mercury, if you shall come home, you shall miserably ex perience4 excess of hunger. Put on also these little snouts, and then enter thus into the sack. But take care that you grunt and cry coï, and utter the voice of the pigs of the Mys teries.5 While I will call Dicæopolis, to see where he is.6 Dicæopolis ! do you wish to buy some little pigs ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.744"/>
          <p n="222">Die. What! a Megarian ?</p>
          <p n="223">MEG. We have come to traffic.</p>
          <p n="224">DIC. How fares it with you ?7</p>
          <p n="225">MEG. We are always hungering one against the other by the fire-side.</p>
          <p n="226">Die. By Jove, but that's jolly, if a piper be present. But what else are you Megarians about now ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.752"/>
          <p n="227">MEG. Just what we are doing.1 When I set out from thence, the committee were contriving this for the state, how we might most quickly and most miserably perish !</p>
          <p n="228">Die. Then you will soon get rid of your troubles.</p>
          <p n="229">Die. But what else is going on at Megara? What is the price2 of grain ?</p>
          <p n="230">MEG. With us, of a high price, like the gods.</p>
          <p n="231">DIC. Do you then bring 3 salt ?</p>
          <p n="232">MEG. Have you not the command of it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="233">Die. Nor yet garlic ?</p>
          <p n="234">MEG. What garlic ?-the heads of which you always grub up with a stake, like field-mice, whenever you make your inroads.</p>
          <p n="235">Die. What then do you bring ?</p>
          <p n="236">MEG. Why, pigs for the mysteries.</p>
          <p n="237">Die. You say well: show them.</p>
          <p n="238">MEG. But indeed they are fine ones. Take one up, if you will. How fat and sleek !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.768"/>
          <p n="239">MEG. A pig, by Jove !</p>
          <p n="240">Die. What say you ? What country pig is this ?</p>
          <p n="241">MEG. Of Megara. Or is not this a pig ?</p>
          <p n="242">Die. It does not seem so to me.</p>
          <p n="243">MEG. Is it not shameful ? See the incredulity of the man ! He says this is not a pig. But sooth, if you will, make a wager with me now for salt flavoured with thyme, if this is not a pig after the usage of the Greeks.4</p>
          <p n="244">Die. Yet at least it is a woman's.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.776"/>
          <p n="245">MEG. 'Tis mine, by Diodes! Whose do you suppose they are ? Do you wish to hear them speak ?</p>
          <p n="246">Die. By the gods I do.</p>
          <p n="247">MEG. Speak quickly now, piggy. Devil take you,1 you must not be silent. By Mercury, I will carry you home again!</p>
          <p n="248">MEG. Is this a pig ?</p>
          <p n="249">Die. Aye, now it seems a pig, but w.hen grown up it will be a sow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.784"/>
          <p n="250">MEG. Within five years, be well assured, it will be like to its mother.</p>
          <p n="251">Die. But this one here is not fit for sacrifice.</p>
          <p n="252">MEG. Why not ? How is it not fit for sacrifice ?</p>
          <p n="253">Die. It has not a tail.</p>
          <p n="254">MEG. For it is young: but when grown up to pig's estate, it will have a great thick red one. But if you like to bring it up, here's a fine pig for you !</p>
          <p n="255">DIC. How similar this one is to the other.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.793"/>
          <p n="256">MEG. For it is of the same mother,2 and of the same father. But when it is grown fat and hairy, it will be a very fine pig to sacrifice to Venus.</p>
          <p n="257">Die. But pig is not sacrificed to Venus.</p>
          <p n="258">MEG. Not a pig to Venus ? Yea, to her only of the gods. And the flesh too of these pigs is sweetest when it is pierced with a spit.3</p>
          <p n="259">Die. Can they feed now without their mother ?</p>
          <p n="260">MEG. Aye, by Neptune, and without their father too.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.801"/>
          <p n="261">Die. But what do they like best to eat ?</p>
          <p n="262">MEG. Whatever you give them. Ask them yourself.</p>
          <p n="263">DIC. Can you eat chick-pease ?</p>
          <p n="264">DAUGH. Coï, coï, coï.</p>
          <p n="265">DIC. What then ? Early4 figs ?</p>
          <p n="266">DIC.1 How sharply you squeak at the figs ! Let some one bring in some figs from within for the little pigs.2 Will they eat them ? Bless me! How they do munch them, much esteemed Hercules ! Of what country are the pigs ? How 3 Tragasean they look. But they have not perhaps4 eaten up all the figs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.809"/>
          <p n="267">MEG. No-for I took up this one of them.</p>
          <p n="268">Die. By Jove, the beasts are fine ones ! For how much shall I buy5 your little grunters of you ? Say.</p>
          <p n="269">MEG. The one for a bunch of garlic; the other, if you will, for a single chcenix of salt.</p>
          <p n="270">Die. I'll buy them of you. Wait you here.</p>
          <p n="271">MEG. Aye, aye,6 sir. [Exit Dicœopolis.] Mercury, thou god of traffic, grant me to sell my wife in this way, and my mother too !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.818"/>
          <p n="272">INF. Fellow ! of what country are you ?</p>
          <p n="273">MEG. A pig-merchant of Megara.</p>
          <p n="274">INF. Then I will inform against these little pigs and you, as enemies.</p>
          <p n="275">MEG. The very7 thing! Again it comes, whence the be ginning of our woes took its rise.</p>
          <p n="276">INF. You shall Megarize to your cost. Will you not let go the sack ?</p>
          <p n="277">MEG. Dicæopolis ! Dicaeopolis ! I am informed against by some one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.826"/>
          <p n="278">Die. Who is he that informs against you ? Clerks of the market, will you not exclude the informers ? What has come into your head, pray,' that you lay2 informations without a wick ?</p>
          <p n="279">INF. What! shall I not inform against our foes ?</p>
          <p n="280">DIC. Aye, to your cost, if you will not run elsewhere and play the informer. [Exit Informer.]</p>
          <p n="281">MEG. What an evil is this in Athens !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.836"/>
          <p n="282">Die. Be of good heart, Megarian. Come, take this gar lic here, and the salt, at which price you sold your pigs, and fare thee well!</p>
          <p n="283">MEG. But to fare well is not in fashion with ns.3</p>
          <p n="284">Die. On my own head then be the impertinence.</p>
          <p n="285">MEG. My little grunters, make the attempt, even without your father, to eat the cake to your salt,4 if any one offer it. [Exeunt omnes.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="286">CHO. The man is prosperous ! Have you not heard how the measure5 succeeds ? For the man will reap the benefit, sitting in the market-place. And if any Ctesias enter, or other informer, he shall sit down in tears. Neither shall any other man injure you by cheating you in the purchase of provisions. Neither shall Prepis wipe upon you his lewd ness.6 Nor shall you jostle with Cleonymus ; but shall pass through with a clean cloak. And Hyperbolus, when he meets - with you, shall not involve you in lawsuits. Nor yet, again, shall Cratinus, when lie falls in with you in the market-place, walk up to you with his head close shaven,' the very rascally Artemo, the man so very rapid in his music, stinking beastly of his Tragasean father in his arm-pits.2 Neither, again, shall the most villanous Pauson jeer you ; nor Lysistratus in the forum, the disgrace of Cholargeus, he who is double dyed in villany, shivering and starving continually more than thirty days3 each month.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.854"/>
          <p n="287">BŒOT. Let Hercules be witness, I am wretchedly tired in my neck. Ismenias, do you lay down the penny-royal gently. But you, as many flute-players 4 as are present from Thebes, with your bone pipes play " the dog's backside."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.860"/>
          <p n="288">Die. (coming out of his house). Go to the devil ! Won't you get away from my doors, you wasps ? Whence have the bumble-bees of Chæris (the devil take them!) flown to my doors ?5 [Ereunt pipers.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.868"/>
          <p n="289">BŒOT. With pleasure, stranger, by Iolaus. For playing behind me from Thebes, they have shaken off the blossoms of the penny-royal on the ground. But, if you like, purchase some of the fowls or locusts,6 which I bring.</p>
          <p n="290">Die. Hail, my roll-eating little Boeotian ! What are you bringing ?</p>
          <p n="291">BŒOT. Absolutely whatever is good amongst the Bœo tians : origanum, penny-royal, rush-mats, wicks, ducks, jack daws, woodcocks, coots, sand-pipers, divers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.877"/>
          <p n="292">Die. Then you have come to the market, as if a tempest of birds.</p>
          <p n="293">BŒOT. Moreover I bring geese, hares, foxes, moles, hedge hogs, cats, beavers, ferrets, otters, Copaic eels.</p>
          <p n="294">Die. 0 tbou that bringest a fish most delightful to men! if you are bearing the eels, permit me to address them.</p>
          <p n="295">BŒOT. " Eldest1 of fifty Copaïc daughters," come forth, and be civil to this2 stranger.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="296">Die. 0 dearest thou, and long desired ! Thou hast come longed for indeed by the comic chorusses, and dear to Mory chus.3 Attendants, bring out for me the brazier and the fan hither. [Servants crowd round the eel.] Look, my boys, at the splendid eel, which has come at length in the sixth year, longed for. Address it, my children, and I will furnish you with coals for this stranger's sake. But carry it in : for not even when dead may I ever be bereft of you stewed in beet.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.893"/>
          <p n="297">BŒOT. But how shall I have a recompense for this ?</p>
          <p n="298">Die. This one, perhaps, you will give me as my market toll. But if you are for selling any of these others, say on.</p>
          <p n="299">BŒOT. All these will I.</p>
          <p n="300">Die. Come, for how much, say you? Or will you take home other wares from hence ?</p>
          <p n="301">BŒOT. Aye, whatever there is at Athens, and not among the Bœotians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.901"/>
          <p n="302">Die. Will you buy and take with you Phaleric anchovies, or crockery?</p>
          <p n="303">BŒOT. Anchovies or crockery? We have them at home. Let me have whatever is not amongst us, but is, on the contrary, abundant here.</p>
          <p n="304">Die. Then I know your wants: bring out an informer, having packed him up like crockery.</p>
          <p n="305">BCEOT. By the two gods,1 I should certainly get even a large profit, if I took him with me, like an ape full of much mischief.</p>
          <p n="306">Die. And see ! here comes Nicarchus to lay informations.</p>
          <p n="307">BCEOT. He is small in stature.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.909"/>
          <p n="308">Die. But all there is of him is bad.</p>
          <p n="309">Nic. Whose are these wares?</p>
          <p n="310">BCEOT. Mine here,2 from Thebes, be Jove my witness.</p>
          <p n="311">Nic. I then here inform against them as an enemy's.</p>
          <p n="312">BCEOT. What ails you 3 then that you have commenced war and battle with the little birds ?</p>
          <p n="313">Nic. I will inform against you too, as well as these.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.917"/>
          <p n="314">BŒOT. In what way having been injured ?</p>
          <p n="315">Nic. I will tell you, for the good of the bystanders. You are importing wicks 4 from the enemy.</p>
          <p n="316">Die. And so, forsooth, you are for informing against a wick?</p>
          <p n="317">Nic. Yes; for this wick might set fire to the dock-yard.</p>
          <p n="318">Die. A wick a dockyard ? Oh ! oh !-As how ?</p>
          <p n="319">Nic. A Bœotian might stick it in a tom-tailor,5 and kin dle it and send it into the dockyard through a sewer, having watched for a mighty wind. And if the fire were once to catch the ships, they would be immediately in a blaze.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.925"/>
          <p n="320">Die. Abandoned miscreant! would they be in a blaze from a torn-tailor and a wick ? [Beats him.]</p>
          <p n="321">Nic. I call you all to witness!</p>
          <p n="322">Die. Stop his mouth ! Give me some straw, that I may take and pack him up like crockery, lest he get broken in the carriage.1 [Throws him down and packs him up.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.929"/>
          <p n="323">CHO. Pack up well, good sir, the stranger's2 merchandise in such a manner, that he may not break it in carrying it.</p>
          <p n="324">Die. This shall be my care; for of a truth it rings3 loud, and cracked, and hateful to the gods besides.</p>
          <p n="325">CHO. Whatever will he make of it ?</p>
          <p n="326">Die. It will be a vessel good for all work ; a mixer for mis chiefs ; a pestle for law-suits ; a lamp to inform against4 those liable to give in an account; and a cup to mix up troubles in.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.943"/>
          <p n="327">CiO. But how could any one confidently use such a vessel in his house, always making such a jar ?</p>
          <p n="328">DIC. It is strong, good sir, so that it would never break, if it were suspended by the feet, head downwards. [Lifts him up by the legs.]</p>
          <p n="329">CHO. It's all right now.</p>
          <p n="330">BŒOT. Marry, I am going to make a harvest.5</p>
          <p n="331">CHO. But, best of strangers, with this man on your side, take and make an attack, where'er you please, upon every informer.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="332">DIC. At last I've packed him up, and be damned to him! Boeotian, take and bear off your crockery.</p>
          <p n="333">BŒOT. Stoop your neck as you go, Ismenias.</p>
          <p n="334">Die. And take care that you carry him with caution., At all events you '11 carry a shaky piece of goods.-Yet still up with it. And if you make any gain by carrying this mer chandise, you '11 be a happy man, as far2 as informers are con cerned. [Exit BoeotiaM carrying the informer on his back. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="335">Die. What is the matter! Why do you call me ?</p>
          <p n="336">SERVo Why ? Lamachus requested you to let him have for this here drachma some of your thrushes for the feast of Pitchers. But requested you to let him have a Copaic eel for three drachmae.</p>
          <p n="337">Die. Who may this Lamachus be that requests the eel ? SERVo The dreaded one, he with the shield of tough bull's- hide, who brandishes the Gorgon, waving three over-shadow ing crests.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="338">Die. I would not, by Jove, if even he were to give me his buckler. Let him wave3 his crests at salt-fish. But should he make a great din, I will call the Market-clerks. And I will take this merchandise for myself, and enter to the accompani ment of thrushes' wings4 and blackbirds. [Exeunt omnes.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.971"/>
          <p n="339">CHO. You have seen, oh ! you have seen, city at large, the prudent man, the very wise, what articles of merchandise he is able to deal in, by having made peace; of which some are useful in the house, others again are suitable to eat up warm. All good things are spontaneously provided for him. Never will I welcome War to my house, nor yet shall he ever at my house chaunt " The Harmodius," seated as a guest; be cause he is a fellow quarrelsome over his cups, who, having made a furious assault upon us, possessed of every blessing, perpetrated all evils, and overturned, and squandered, and fought; and, moreover, when I frequently invited him: "Drink, sit down, take this cup of friendship,"-so much the more burnt our vine-props in the fire, and in our despite poured out the wine from our vines. * * * to a feast; at the same time also he is highly elated, and, as a proof of his good fare, threw out these feathers 2 before his doors.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.986"/>
          <p n="340">0 Reconciliation,3 companion of the beautiful Venus and the dear Graces, I never knew you had so fair a face ! Would4 that some Cupid, with a chaplet of flowers, like the5 one in the picture, would take and join together me and thee ! or, do you consider me peradventure a very old man ? Yet, if I gained you, I fancy I could add three things beside: first, I would plant a long row of vines; then, near to this, some young suckers of young fig-trees; and thirdly, I, this old man here, would plant a branch of the cultivated vine; and about your whole estate olives round about, so that you and I may anoint ourselves from them at the New-moons.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.995"/>
          <p n="341">HER. "0 yez, 0 yez! according to our national6 customs you must drink the Pitchers at the sound of trumpet; and wbosoever shall have first emptied his Pitcher, shall receive the wine-skin of Ctesiphou."1[Exit Herald.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1000"/>
          <p n="342">Die. Slaves, women, did you not hear ? What are you about? Do you not hear the Herald? Boil, roast, turn, draw off the hare's flesh quickly, wreathe the chaplets. Bring the spits, that I may spit the thrushes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1008"/>
          <p n="343">CHO. I deem you happy for your good counsel, but more, sir, for your present good cheer.</p>
          <p n="344">Die. What then will ye say, when ye see the thrushes roasting ?</p>
          <p n="345">CHO. I believe you say this also rightly.2</p>
          <p n="346">Die. Stir up the fire.</p>
          <p n="347">CHO. Did you hear how cook-like and daintily and dinner like he serves up to himself ?</p>
          <p n="348">HUSB. Ah me, unhappy man !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1018"/>
          <p n="349">Die. 0 Hercules ! who is this ?</p>
          <p n="350">HUSB. A miserable man.</p>
          <p n="351">Die. Then go your own way.3</p>
          <p n="352">HUSB. My dearest sir, measure me out a particle of peace, if it be but for five years, for you only are possessed of peace.</p>
          <p n="353">Die. What have you suffered ?</p>
          <p n="354">HUSB. I am undone, having lost my two oxen.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1027"/>
          <p n="355">HUSB. The Bœotians took them off from Phyle.</p>
          <p n="356">Die. Thrice miserable wretch ! then are you dressed in white ? 5</p>
          <p n="357">HUSB. And that too, certainly, by Jove, which used to keep me in all kinds of-cow-dung.1</p>
          <p n="358">Die. Then what want you now ?</p>
          <p n="359">HUSB. I am ruined in my eyes 2 with weeping for my oxen. But, if you have any regard for Dercetes of Phyle, anoint my eyes quickly with peace.</p>
          <p n="360">Die. Nay, you rascal, I am not the public physician.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1035"/>
          <p n="361">HUSB. Come, I entreat you, if by any means I may re cover my oxen.</p>
          <p n="362">Die. It cannot be : weep to Pittalus' apprentices.</p>
          <p n="363">HUSB. At least3 drop for me one drop of peace into this little reed.</p>
          <p n="364">Die. Not a fraction : go and lament some where.</p>
          <p n="365">HUSB. Woe's me, wretched man ! for the oxen which tilled my ground ! [Exit Husbandman,]</p>
          <p n="366">CHO. The man has found out something sweet in the peace, and does not seem about to give a share to any one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1047"/>
          <p n="367">Die. Pour the honey on the sausage. Fry the cuttle-fish.</p>
          <p n="368">CiO. Did you hear his loud shoutings ?</p>
          <p n="369">CHO. You will kill me with hunger, and your neighbours with savoury smells and bawling, if you shout in this way.</p>
          <p n="370">DIC. Roast these and brown them well.</p>
          <p n="371">PAR. Dicæopolis ! Dicaeopolis !</p>
          <p n="372">PAR. A bridegroom sent you these meats from the marriage- feast.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1056"/>
          <p n="373">Die. Well done he,4 whoever he was.</p>
          <p n="374">PAR. And he requested you to ponr, on account of the meats, into his ointment-box one cyathus of peace, that he might not go on service, but might kiss his wife at home.</p>
          <p n="375">Die. Take away, take away your meats, and give them not to me, for I would not pour in any for a thousand drachmæ. But who is this here ?</p>
          <p n="376">PAR. The bridesmaid wants to say something to you in private from the bride.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1064"/>
          <p n="377">DIC. Come now, what are you for saying ? [Bridesmaid whispers in his ear.] How ridiculous, ye gods, is the request of the bride, which she earnestly asks of me, that the bride groom may stay at home !1 Bring hither the peace, that I may give some to her alone, because she is a woman and not fit for war.—Woman, hold under here your ointment-box in this way. Do you know what ye are to make of this? Tell the bride, whenever they levy soldiers, let her by night anoint the bridegroom's breeches with this. [ Exeunt Para nymph and Bridesmaid.] Take away the peace. Bring the funnel, that I may take and pour some wine into the Pitchers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="378">CHO. And see ! here's some one hastening hither with his brows drawn up, as if about to announce something dreadful !</p>
          <p n="379">HER. O! toils, and fights, and Lamachuses !</p>
          <p n="380">LAM. Who sounds around the mansion adorned with brass ?</p>
          <p n="381">HER. The generals 2 ordered you to march to-day in haste with your companies and crests; and then, though snowed upon, to guard the passes. For some one has brought them word that Bœotian robbers would make3 an incursion on the approach of the feast of Pitchers and Pots. [Exit Herald. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1078"/>
          <p n="382">LAM. 0 generals more numerous than brave ! Is it not hard that I should not be permitted even to celebrate the feast ?</p>
          <p n="383">Die. 0 warlike Lamachean Achaian host!</p>
          <p n="384">LAM. Ah me, miserable ! you are mocking me now.1</p>
          <p n="385">Die. Will2 you fight with a four-winged Geryon?</p>
          <p n="386">LAM. Alas ! alas ! what tidings has the crier announced to me!</p>
          <p n="387">Die. Alas! alas ! what tidings, in turn, is some one run ning up to announce to me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <p n="388">Die. What is the matter ?</p>
          <p n="389">MESS. Come to dinner quick, with your box and pitcher; for the priest of Bacchus sends for you. But make haSte; you have delayed the dinner this long time. All the rest of the things are in readiness; couches, tables, cushions for the head, bedding, chaplets, ointment, sweetmeats, the courtesans arc there, cakes of fine flour, cheese-cakes, sesame-cakes, honey-cakes, lovely dancing girls, Harmodius's delight.3 But hasten as quick as possible. [Exit Messenger.]</p>
          <p n="390">Die. For you have chosen the Gorgon as your great patron. Shut the door, and let some one get ready the dinner.</p>
          <p n="391">LAM. Slave ! slave ! bring out my knapsack hither.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1094"/>
          <p n="392">Die. Slave ! slave ! bring out ray box hither.</p>
          <p n="393">LAM. Bring salt flavoured with thyme, slave, and onions.</p>
          <p n="394">Die. But slices of salt-fish for me, for I abominate onions.</p>
          <p n="395">LAM. Bring hither, slave, an5 olio of rancid salt-fish.</p>
          <p n="396">DIC. Bring me too an olio of fat; and I will roast it there.</p>
          <p n="397">LAM, Bring hither the two plumes from my helmet.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1102"/>
          <p n="398">Die. But for me bring the ring-doves, and the thrushes.</p>
          <p n="399">LAM Beautiful, and white is the ostrich's plume.</p>
          <p n="400">Die. Beautiful, and yellow is the ring-dove's flesh.</p>
          <p n="401">LAM. Fellow, cease scoffing at my equipment.</p>
          <p n="402">Die. Fellow, will you not gaze at my thrushes ?1</p>
          <p n="403">LAM. Bring out the crest-case for the three plumes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1110"/>
          <p n="404">Die. And give me a little dish of hare's flesh.</p>
          <p n="405">LAM. Verily the moths have eaten up my crests.</p>
          <p n="406">Die. Verily I shall eat up the hare-soup before dinner.</p>
          <p n="407">LAM.Fellow, will you not address me ?2</p>
          <p n="408">Die. I am not addressing you; but I and the slave have been disputing this long time. Will you lay a wager, and give the decision to Lamachus, whether locusts or thrushes are the sweeter ?</p>
          <p n="409">LAM. Ah me, how you insult me !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1118"/>
          <p n="410">Die. (turning to the slave). He decides the locusts to be far sweeter.</p>
          <p n="411">LAM. Slave ! slave ! take down my spear and bring it out hither. [ Slave brings him his spear.]</p>
          <p n="412">Die. Slave ! slave ! do you draw off and bring the sausage hither. [Slave brings him the spit.]</p>
          <p n="413">LAM. Come, let me draw off the cover of my spear. Take hold, pull at it, slave.</p>
          <p n="414">DIC. And do you, slave, pull at this.3 [Offers the spit to pull at.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1126"/>
          <p n="415">LAM. Slave, bring the trestles for my shield.</p>
          <p n="416">Die. And bring forth the baked bread for mine.4</p>
          <p n="417">LAM. Bring hither the orb of my shield with the Gorgon on its back.</p>
          <p n="418">Die. And to me give the orb of my cheese-cake, with cheese on its back.</p>
          <p n="419">LAM. Is not this flat mockery for a man?</p>
          <p n="420">Die. Is not this, pray, sweet cheese-cake for a man ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1134"/>
          <p n="421">LAM. Slave, pour the oil over it. I see in the shield an old man about to be brought to trial on a charge of cowardice.</p>
          <p n="422">Die. Pour over the honey. There too an old man is clearly seen bidding Lamachus, the son of Gorgasus,1 go weep.</p>
          <p n="423">LAM. Slave, bring hither my warrior breastplate.</p>
          <p n="424">Die. For me too, slave, bring out my pitcher as a breast plate.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1142"/>
          <p n="425">LAM. In this I will arm myself against my foes.</p>
          <p n="426">Die. In this I will arm myself against my boon-com panions.</p>
          <p n="427">LAM. Slave, fasten my bedding to my shield.</p>
          <p n="428">Die. Slave, fasten my dinner to my box.</p>
          <p n="429">LAM. But I'll take and carry my knapsack for myself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1150"/>
          <p n="430">Die. But I'll take my coat and go out.</p>
          <p n="431">LAM. Take up the buckler, slave, and go with it. It snows. Bless me ! 'Tis a stormy affair.</p>
          <p n="432">Die. Take up the dinner. 'Tis a jolly affair. [Exeunt omnes. ]</p>
          <p n="433">Che. Go ye now to the warfare and joy be with ye ! How different a journey you two are going ! For the one, to drink crowned with chaplets ; but for you, to shiver and keep watch: and for the other, to sleep with a most lovely girl, and enjoy himself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1162"/>
          <p n="434">May Jove, to speak plainly, miserably destroy Antimachus, the son of Sputter, the miserable composer of miserable songs, who, when Choregus at the Lenæa, dismissed me dinnerless, unhappy man ! whom may I yet see longing for a cuttle-fish; and may it, when broiled, frizzling, ready salted, lying upon the table, run aground. And then, when he is about to seize it, may a bitch snatch it and run away. May this be one misfortune for him. And then may he have another by night. For as he is returning home, feverish after his horse- exercise, then let some drunken mad Orestes break his head; and may he, when wishing to seize a stone, in the dark seize with his hand a newly-born Sir-reverence; and may he rush out with the shining lump, and then miss his aim and hit Cratinus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1174"/>
          <p n="435">MESS. Servants,1 who are in the house of Lamachus, heat water, water in a little pot, get ready linen, cerate, greasy wool, a bandage to go round his ancle. The hero has been wounded with a vine-prop in leaping over a trench, and has dislocated his ancle, so as to be twisted; and has broken his head by having fallen upon a stone, and roused the Gorgon from his shield. And as the mighty plume of the big-boaster fell2 upon the rocks, he uttered a doleful strain : " 0 thou bright luminary, now having seen you for the last time I leave the light : I am no more." When he had said thus much,3 having fallen into a sewer, he gets up again, and meets with some runaways, driving and urging on the plunderers with his spear. But see! here's the man himself! Come, open the door. [Exit Messenger. J</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1182"/>
          <p n="436">LAM. Attatai ! attatai ! These hateful and chilling suffer ings ! Wretched man, I am undone, struck by the spear of the enemy! But that would be lamentable for me-Dicæopolis4 may see me wounded; and then he will laugh at my misfor tunes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1190"/>
          <p n="437">DIC.5 Attatai! attatai! What breasts ! How firm and plump ! Kiss me softly, my little treasures, with a wanton and lascivious kiss; for I am the first man who drank up his pitcher.</p>
          <p n="438">LAM. 0 the unhappy calamity of my woes ! alas ! alas ! my painful wounds !</p>
          <p n="439">Die. Hurra! Hurra ! Hail, Knight Lamachus !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1200"/>
          <p n="440">LAM. Ah me, distressed !</p>
          <p n="441">Die. Ah me, oppressed !</p>
          <p n="442">LAM. Why do you kiss me ?</p>
          <p n="443">Die. Why do you bite me ?</p>
          <p n="444">LAM. Ah me, unhappy man ! for the grievous shot!</p>
          <p n="445">Die. Why, did ever any one exact a shot1 at the feast of Pitchers ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1210"/>
          <p n="446">LAM. Oh! oh ! Paean ! Pæan ! 2</p>
          <p n="447">Die. But the Pæonia arc not celebrating now3 to-day.</p>
          <p n="448">LAM. Take hold of me, take hold of my leg. 0 dear, take hold, my friends.</p>
          <p n="449">Die. And do you, both of you, take hold of me by the middle, my sweets.</p>
          <p n="450">LAM. I am dizzy from the blow of a stone on my head, and inclined to vertigo.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1218"/>
          <p n="451">Die. I too wish to sleep, and am stiff, and inclined to a dirty go.</p>
          <p n="452">LAM. Carry me out of doors to the house of Pittalus for his healing hands.4</p>
          <p n="453">Die. Carry me forth to the judges. Where is the king ?1 Pay me the wine-skin.</p>
          <p n="454">LAM. An afflicting spear is fixed through my bones.</p>
          <p n="455">Die. Behold this empty ! Huzza ! victorious !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1227"/>
          <p n="456">CHO. Huzza ! then, victorious ! if, old man, you call so.</p>
          <p n="457">Die. And moreover, too, I poured in pure wine, and quaffed it at one draught.</p>
          <p n="458">CHO. Huzza ! then, noble fellow ; go with your wine-skin.</p>
          <p n="459">Die. Follow then, and sing “ Huzza ! victorious !”</p>
          <p n="460">CiO. Well, for your sake, we will follow, and sing of you and of your wine-skin, " Huzza! victorious ! " [Exeunl omnes.]</p>
          <p n="461">END OF THE ACHARNIANS.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
