<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Theocritus, Epigrams</title>
        <author>Theocritus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0005.tlg002.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">THESE 1dewy roses and yon thick 2 creeping-thyme are dedicated to the Heliconian Muses. And the dark-leaved bays to thee, 0 Pythian Paean : for the 3 Delphic rock hath given thee this for an ornament. And this 4white he-goat with the horns, browsing the extremity of a branch of the turpentine tree, shall stain thy altar.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">5 DAPHNIS the fair-complexioned, that did modulate pastoral hymns with beautiful pipe, dedicated to Pan these gifts; his reed-pipe with stops, his shepherd's crook, his sharp dart, his fawn's skin, and 6 the wallet, in which he once used to carry apples.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.1"/>
          <p n="1">DAPHNIS, you sleep on leaf-strown ground, I resting your wearied body; and the 2 poles are fresh fastened along the mountains. But Pan is in chase of you, and 3Priapus, who has saffron-berried ivy bound about his lovely head, advancing to the interior of the cave with one bound. But do you take flight, fly, having 4 shaken off the lethargy of sleep, that is stealing over you.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.1"/>
          <p n="1">5 WHEN you have turned down yon lane, goatherd, where the oaks are, you will find 6 a fresh-carved image of fig-wood, 7 with three legs, with the bark on, and without handles, but with creative phallus able to accomplish works of Venus: and an enclosure duly sacred surrounds it, and an ever-run ing stream from the hollow rocks luxuriates on all sides in laurels and myrtles, and fragrant cypress : where the grape begetting vine sheds itself around with its tendrils, and ver- nal blackbirds, with sweet-voiced songs, chaunt various-noted melodies : yellow nightingales respond with their plaints, warbling with their throats the sounds of music. Prythee, take your seat there, and supplicate the graceful Priapus, that I may discourage the loves of Daphnis : and say that I will straightway sacrifice a fine he-goat: but if he shall have re fused, I am willing, after having succeeded in this, to pay three victims. 1For I will offer a heifer, a shaggy he-goat, and a lamb which I am keeping in the stall: and may the god hear propitiously.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="5">
          <milestone unit="section" n="5.1"/>
          <p n="1">ARE you willing, I ask you by the Nymphs, to sing me some sweet trifle on the 2 double flutes ? And I will take up 3a harp, and begin to strike it somewhat: and the cowherd Daphnis shall charm us at the same time, singing to the breathing 4 of a wax-bound pipe. Then standing near a leafy oak, behind the cave, would we rob of sleep 5the goat-footed Pan.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="6">
          <milestone unit="section" n="6.1"/>
          <p n="1">All ! thou wretched Thyrsis, what boots it thee, if thou waste with tears thy two eyes in lamentation ! The young she-goat 6 is gone, the pretty kid is gone to the shades ; for a ruthless wolf crushed her with his talons. And 7 the dogs then give tongue. What boots it, when, gone as she is, nor a bone nor ash is left of her ?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="7">
          <milestone unit="section" n="7.1"/>
          <p n="1">THE son of Paean came even to Miletus, 2to dwell along with a man that heals diseases, Nicias by name: 3who ever day by day approaches him with sacrifices, and has had this statue carved out of 4 fragrant cedar, having promised the highest price to Eetion, because of his skilful hand ; and he has thrown all his art into the work.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="8">
          <milestone unit="section" n="8.1"/>
          <p n="1">STRANGER, Orthon, a man of Syracuse, gives thee this charge: Walk no where, in your cups, of a wintry night. For such is the fate, which I have met: and 5 instead of my ample father land, I lie having wrapped myself in foreign soil.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="9">
          <milestone unit="section" n="9.1"/>
          <p n="1">GOOD man, 6 be careful of your life, nor be a voyager out of season: since life is not long to a man. Wretched Cleoni cus, you, on the other hand, were in haste to go as a merchant from 1Coelesyria to fruitful 2Thasos. Ay, a merchant, 0 Cleonicus ; but crossing ocean just about the 3 very setting of the Pleiad, you went down along with the Pleiad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="10">
          <milestone unit="section" n="10.1"/>
          <p n="1">To you, goddesses, Xenocles dedicated this marble statue, in gratitude 4 to Nine altogether: a musician, no one will say otherwise, and enjoying repute on the score of this talent, he is not forgetful of the Muses.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="11">
          <milestone unit="section" n="11.1"/>
          <p n="1">THIS monument is of Eusthenes : he was the philosopher 5 who judged men by their features; being clever at learning even the mind from the eye. Worthily have his friends buried him, though a foreigner, in a foreign land: 6 and to lyric poets he was wondrously dear. The philosopher in death bath all it was fitting he should have; even though he was powerless, I wot he found friends-to-care-for-him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="12">
          <milestone unit="section" n="12.1"/>
          <p n="1">DEMOTELES, 2the leader of the choir, who set up the tripod, 0 Dionysus, and 3 thee the sweetest of gods, was pretty- 4 well-in-merit among boys ; but in the choir of men he gained victory, seeing both the beautiful and the becoming.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="13">
          <milestone unit="section" n="13.1"/>
          <p n="1">5 OUR Venus is not the vulgar : propitiate the goddess by having called her ‘heavenly,' the offering of chaste Chryso gona in the house of Amphicles, with whom she had both children and life in common ; and ever it was better to them 6 from year to year, 7 as they began with thee, 0 divine lady; for if they care for the immortals, mortals find advantage in it themselves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="14">
          <milestone unit="section" n="14.1"/>
          <p n="1">You left an infant son ; and yourself too in life's prime, Eurymedon, found a tomb here, in death. For you indeed there is 1a seat amid godlike men ; but him citizens will honour, remembering his sire as worthy.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="15">
          <milestone unit="section" n="15.1"/>
          <p n="1">TRAVELLER, I shall know, whether you pay any more honour to the good, than the bad, or if even the coward gets likewise an equal share from you. You will say 2 Hail to this tomb, for it lies light upon the sacred head of Eurymedon.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="16">
          <milestone unit="section" n="16.1"/>
          <p n="1">STRANGER, regard this statue 3 carefully, and say, when you have returned home, 4‘In Teos, I saw a likeness of Anacreon, 5 pre-eminent, if ever man was, among bards of old.' And by having added also, that he delighted in the young, you will truthfully describe the whole man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="17">
          <milestone unit="section" n="17.1"/>
          <p n="1">BOTH the inscription is Doric, and the lOOn, he who in- vented comedy, 1Epicharmus. 0 Bacchus, to thee 2the Pelo rians, who are settled in the city of Syracuse, set him up here in brass instead of in his true nature, inasmuch as they are mindful to pay the price of his labours to a fellow citizen, a for he had abundance of wealth ; for many saws useful for life and conduct taught he to their children. Great gratitude is due to him.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="18">
          <milestone unit="section" n="18.1"/>
          <p n="1">THE little Medeius raised this monument by the way-side to his of Thracian nurse, and inscribed it ‘Of Cleita.' The woman will enjoy his thanks in requital for her having reared the boy. Why not ? 5She has yet another name, Useful.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="19">
          <milestone unit="section" n="19.1"/>
          <p n="1">STAND and behold the ancient poet, ! Archilochus, him of the Iambics, whose 2 infinite renown has reached both to the west and to the east. Of a truth, I ween, the Muses and Delian Apollo were wont to love him: so melodious was he, and skilful both in making Iambics and singing to his lyre.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="20">
          <milestone unit="section" n="20.1"/>
          <p n="1">FOR you this man, 3 Pisander from Camirus, first of the former poets, wrote the exploits of Jove's son, the lion-subduer, the quick-of-hand; and declared how many labours he had ac complished. And this very man, that you may duly know it, the people setup here, having made him of brass, .. many months and years afterwards.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="21">
          <milestone unit="section" n="21.1"/>
          <p n="1">HERE lies 5Hipponax the poet. If thou art worthless, come not nigh his tomb ; but if thou art both 1good, and come of good stock, sit down boldly, and sleep, if thou wilt.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="22">
          <milestone unit="section" n="22.1"/>
          <p n="1">2THE Chian Theocritus is another ; but I, Theocritus who wrote these Idylls, am a Syracusan, one of the commonalty, 3son to Praxagoras and well-known Philina, and I have never 4 claimed to myself another's muse.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="23">
          <milestone unit="section" n="23.1"/>
          <p n="1">THIS bank allows the same to strangers as to citizens. Deposit your money, and take it up again, 5a calculation being duly made. Let some one else make excuses; but 6Caicus tells back the monies of others, even by night if they wish it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="24">
          <milestone unit="section" n="24.1.1"/>
          <p n="1">7 THE inscription will declare what is the tomb, and who under it: I am the grave of her that was called Glaucè.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
