<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Thesmophoriazusae</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">William James Hickie</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>William James Hickie (1853). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg008.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.19"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.27"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.35"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.43"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.52"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.63"/>
          <p n="1">MNESILOCHUS, father-in-law of Euripides.</p>
          <p n="2">" THE Thesmophoriazusæ was acted 01. 92, 1, in the archonship of Callias. Scholiast on vs. 841, yap . Lamachus died in the beginning of 01. 91, 2. See Thuc. vi. 101. Scholiast on vs. 190, . Eu rioides died about the close of 01. 93, 2, or the beginning of 93, 3. Scholiast on Ran. 53, , i. e. 01. 91, 4. Now Aristophanes himself (Thesm. vs. 1060) testifies that the Andromeda was acted the year before the Thesmophoriazusæ." Enger. Dindorf and Wachsmuth also refer it to this year ; on the contrary, Dobree and Fritzsche refer it to 01. 92, 2.</p>
          <p n="3">The Thesmophoriazusæ has a proper intrigue, a knot which is not loosed till the conclusion, and in this therefore possesses a great advantage. Euripides, on account of the well-known hatred of women displayed in his tragedies, is accused and condemned at the Thesmophoria, at which festival women only wereadmitted. After a fruitless attempt to induce the effeminate poet Agathon to under take the hazardous experiment, Euripidesprevails on his father-in- law, Mnesilochus, who was somewhat advanced inyears, to disguise himself as a woman, that under this assumed appearance he may plead his cause. The manner in which he does this gives rise to suspicions, and -he is discovered to be a man ; be flies to the altar for refuge, and to secure himself still more from the impending danger, he snatches a child from the arms of one of the women, and threatens to kill it if they do not let him alone. Upon examin ation, however, it turns out to be a wine-skin, wrapped up like a child. Euripides now appears in a number of different shapes to save his friend': at one time he is Menelaus,who finds Helen again in Egypt; at another time he is Echo, helping the chained Andro meda to pour out her lamentations, and immediately after he ap pears as Perseus, about to release her from the rock. At length he succeeds in rescuing Mnesilochus, who is fastened to a sort of pit lory, by assuming the character of a procuress, and enticing away the officer of justice who has charge of him, a simple barbarian, by the charms of a dancing-girl. These parodied scenes, composed almost entirely in the very words of Euripides' tragedics, are in imitable. Whenever Euripides is introduced, we may always, ge nerally speaking, lay our account with having the most ingenious and apposite ridicule : it seems as if the mind of Aristophanes pos sessed a peculiar and specific power of giving a comic turn to the poetry of this tragedian. Whatever be the faults of the present play, it will be very generally admitted to be the drollest and most facetious of all the writings of Aristophanes.</p>
          <p n="4">MNES. 0 JUPITER! will the swallow ever1 appear? The man will kill me with dragging me about2 from early dawn ! Is it possible, Euripides, before I lose my spleen entirely, to learn from you whither you are leading me ?</p>
          <p n="5">EUR. (with great seriousness). Nay, you must3 not hear all that you will soon see, being present.</p>
          <p n="6">MNES. How say you ? Tell it me again! Must I not hear?</p>
          <p n="7">EUR. Not what you are to see.</p>
          <p n="8">MNES. Then must I not even see ?</p>
          <p n="9">EUR. Not what you must hear.</p>
          <p n="10">MNES. How do you advise me? Upon my word, you speak cleverly! You say I must neither hear nor see.</p>
          <p n="11">EUR. Not so; for, be well assured, the nature of each of them is distinct, of not hearing, and of not seeing.</p>
          <p n="12">EUR. Thus have these been distinguished formerly.1 For Ether, when first it was separated,2 and in itself bore moving animals, first contrived an eye for that which ought to see, modelled after the sun's disk, and bored ears like a funnel.</p>
          <p n="13">MNES. On account of the funnel, then, must 13 neither hear nor see? By Jove, I am delighted at having learned this in addition! What a thing, I ween, are learned con versazioni !</p>
          <p n="14">EUR. Many such matters mayest thou learn from me.</p>
          <p n="15">MNES. Would,4 then, that, in addition to these good things, I could find out how I might still learn in addition to be lame5 in my legs.</p>
          <p n="16">EUR. Come hither, and give me your attention!</p>
          <p n="17">EUR. Do you see this little door ?6</p>
          <p n="18">MNES. Yes, by Hercules, I think so !</p>
          <p n="19">EUR. Be silent then !1</p>
          <p n="20">MNES. Must I be silent about the little door ?</p>
          <p n="21">MNES. Must I hear and be silent about the little door ?</p>
          <p n="22">EUR. Here dwells 2 the illustrious Agathon the tragic poet.</p>
          <p n="23">MNES. Of what sort3 is this Agathon ?</p>
          <p n="24">EuR. There is a certain Agathon-</p>
          <p n="25">MNES. Is it the black, the strong one ?</p>
          <p n="26">EUR. No; another one. Have you never seen him?4</p>
          <p n="27">MNES. Is it the shaggy-bearded one?5</p>
          <p n="28">EUR. Have you never seen him ?</p>
          <p n="29">MNES. Certainly not, by Jove, as far as I know !6</p>
          <p n="30">EUR. And yet you have coquetted with him, but you don't know it perhaps. Come, let us crouch out of the way ! for a domestic of his is coming out with fire and myrtle- wreaths. He seems about to make a previous8 sacrifice on behalf of his poetic composition. [They retire to one side.]</p>
          <p n="31">SERVANT OF AGATHON (coming out of the house). Let all the people abstain from ill-omened words, having closed their mouths; for the company of the Muses is sojourning within my master's house, composing lyric poems. And let the breathless1 Ether check its blasts, and the azure wave of the sea not roar-</p>
          <p n="32">EUR. Be silent! What are you saying ?2</p>
          <p n="33">SERV.—and let the race of birds be put to sleep, and the feet of savage wild beasts that roam the woods not be put in motion.</p>
          <p n="34">MNES. Oh my gracious !</p>
          <p n="35">SERVo For the beautifully-speaking Agathon our chief3 is about-</p>
          <p n="36">MNES. To be debauched ?</p>
          <p n="37">SERVo Who's he that spoke ?</p>
          <p n="38">MNES. Breathless Ether.</p>
          <p n="39">SERVo -to lay the stocks,4 the beginning of a drama. And he is bending new felloes for verses: others he is turning5 on the lathe, other verses he is patching together ; and he is coining maxims, and speaking in tropes,6 and is moulding as in wax, and is rounding, and is casting- MNES. And is wenching.</p>
          <p n="40">SERVo What rustic7 approaches our eaves?</p>
          <p n="41">MNES. One who is ready to turn and whirl round and cast this toe of mine in the eaves of8 you and your beauti fully-speaking poet.</p>
          <p n="42">SERV. Doubtless you were a rake, old man, when you were young.1</p>
          <p n="43">EUR. My good sir, let this man go; but do you by all means call out Agathon hither to me !</p>
          <p n="44">SERVo Make no entreaty; for he himself will come out soon; for he is beginning to make lyric poems. In truth, when it is winter, it is not easy to bend3 the strophes, unless one come forth to the door to the sun. [Exit.]</p>
          <p n="45">MNES. What then shall I do ?</p>
          <p n="46">EUR. Wait; for he is coming forth. 0 Jove, what do you purpose4 to do to me to-day ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.71"/>
          <p n="47">MNES. By the gods, I wish to learn what this business is. Why do you groan ? Why are you vexed? You ought5 not to conceal it, being my son-in-law.</p>
          <p n="48">EUR. A great evil is ready kneaded for me.</p>
          <p n="49">MNES. Of what kind ? 6</p>
          <p n="50">EuR. On this day will be decided whether Euripides still lives 7 or is undone.</p>
          <p n="51">MNES. Why, how? For now neither the courts are about to judge causes, nor is there a sitting of the Senate; for it is the third 1 day, the middle of the Thesmophoria.</p>
          <p n="52">EUR. In truth, I expect this very thing2 even will de stroy me. For the women have plotted against me, and are going to hold an assembly to-day about me in the temple of3 Demeter and Persephone for my destruction.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.81"/>
          <p n="53">MNES. Wherefore ? why, pray ?4</p>
          <p n="54">EUR. Because I represent them in tragedy and speak ill of them.</p>
          <p n="55">MNES. And justly too would you suffer,5 by Neptune! But, as this is the case,6 what contrivance have you ?</p>
          <p n="56">EUR. To persuade Agathon the tragic poet to go to the temple of Demeter and Persephone.</p>
          <p n="57">MNES. What to do ? Tell me !</p>
          <p n="58">EUR. To sit in assembly among the women, and to speak whatever7 is necessary in my defence.</p>
          <p n="59">MNES. Openly,8 or secretly ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.90"/>
          <p n="60">EUR. Secretly, clothed in a woman's stole.1</p>
          <p n="61">MNES. The device is a clever2 one, and exceedingly in conformity with your disposition; for ours is the prize3 for trickery. [ The creaking of machinery is heard.]</p>
          <p n="62">MNES. What's the matter ?</p>
          <p n="63">EUR. Agathon is coming out.</p>
          <p n="64">MNES. Why, of what sort is he ?</p>
          <p n="65">EUR. He who is being wheeled4 out. [ The doors of the back scene are thrown open, and Agathon is wheeled in, fan tastically dressed in women's clothes. ]</p>
          <p n="66">MNES. Assuredly5 I am blind; for I don't see any man here : I see Cyrene.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.99"/>
          <p n="67">EuR. Hush ! He is preparing again to sing.7</p>
          <p n="68">MNES. " The ant's8 paths?" or what is he plaintively singing ?</p>
          <p n="69">AGATH.9 Damsels, take the torch sacred to the infernal goddesses,1 and, with a free country, raise2 a shout in the dance!</p>
          <p n="70">CHO.3 In honour of which of the gods4 is the ode? Tell us then ! I am readily induced to honour the gods.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.107"/>
          <p n="71">AGATH. Come, then, Muse, glorify Phœbus, the drawer of the golden bow, who founded the walls6 of the city in the land of Simois!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.117"/>
          <p n="72">CHO. Deign to accept our most noble strains, 0 Phœbus, who in musical honours bearest off the sacred prize !</p>
          <p n="73">AGATH. And chant the maiden dwelling in oak-grown mountains, the huntress Diana</p>
          <p n="74">CHO. I follow, celebrating and glorifying the revered off spring of Latona, the unwedded Diana.</p>
          <p n="75">AGATH. And Latona, and the notes of the lyre7 accom panying the dances of the Phrygian graces in harmony with the foot.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.129"/>
          <p n="76">CHO. I honour queen Latona, and the lyre, the mother of songs, with an approved masculine8 voice; by which9 light is kindled in divinely-inspired eyes, and by our sudden voice. On which account glorify king Phœbus with honours ! Hail, happy child of Latona !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.137"/>
          <p n="77">MNES. How sweet the song, 0 venerable Genetyllides,1 and womanish, and wanton, and lascivious !2 So that, whilst I listened, a tickling passed under my very bottom. I wish, O youth, to ask you who you are,3 in the words of Æschylus in his Lycurgeia:4 of what land,5 you weakling? What's your country ? What means the dress ? what the confusion of fashions? What does the harp prattle6 to the saffron- coloured robe? what the lyre to the head-dress? What mean the oil-flask and the girdle ? How unsuitable ! What connexion then between a mirror and a sword ? And you yourself, 0 youth, are you reared7 as a man ? Why, where are the tokens of a man ? Where is your cloak ? Where are your boots ? 8 Or9 as a woman then ? Where then 10 are your breasts? What do you say? Why are you silent? Nay, then, I'll judge of you1 from your song, since you are not willing to tell me yourself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.146"/>
          <p n="78">AGATH. Old man,2 old man, I heard, indeed, the censure of your envy, but the pain I did not feel! I wear my attire in accordance with 3 my thoughts. For it behoveth a poet, conformably to the dramas which he must compose, to have his turn of mind in accordance with these. For example,4 if one be composing female dramas, the body of the poet ought to have a participation in their manners.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.154"/>
          <p n="79">MNES. Therefore do you mount on horseback when you compose a Phædra ? 5</p>
          <p n="80">AGATH. But if one be composing male dramas, this is sub sisting in the body.6 But what we do not possess, this now is found to be all imitation.7</p>
          <p n="81">MNES. When therefore you compose satyric dramas, call me,8 in order that I may actively compose poetry along with you in your rear.</p>
          <p n="82">AGATH. Besides, it is unpolished 1 to see a poet boorish and rough with hair. Consider that that well-known2 Ibycus, and Anacreon of Teos, and Alcæus, who softened down our music, wore a head-band, and practised soft Ionian airs ;3 and that Pkrynichus,—for you have certainly 4 heard him,—was both handsome himself and dressed handsomely. On this account then his dramas also were handsome : for it is5 un avoidable that one compose similarly to one's nature.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <p n="83">MNES. On this account then Philocles,6 as he is ugly, com poses uglily ; and Xenocles,7 as he is vile, composes vilely ; and Theognis,8 again, as he is frigid, composes frigidly.</p>
          <p n="84">AGATE. Most unavoidably ! For, assuredly, being aware of this, I paid attention to my person.</p>
          <p n="85">MNES. How, by the gods ?</p>
          <p n="86">EUR. Cease to abuse ! for I also was such a one, when I was his age, when I began to compose.</p>
          <p n="87">MNES. By Jove, I do not envy you your training.</p>
          <p n="88">EUR. Yet suffer me to tell on what account I came.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.175"/>
          <p n="89">EUR. Agathon, "it9 suits a wise man, who is able briefly to abridge many words in a proper manner." But having been smitten 1 by a new calamity, I have come to you as a suppliant.</p>
          <p n="90">AGATH. In need of what ?</p>
          <p n="91">EUR. The women purpose to destroy me to-day at the Thesmophoria, because I speak ill of them.</p>
          <p n="92">AGATH. What aid then can you have from me ? 2</p>
          <p n="93">EUR. All ; for if you secretly take your seat amongst the women, so as to seem to be a woman, and defend me, you will assuredly save 3 me : for you alone can speak in a manner worthy of me.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.183"/>
          <p n="94">AGATH. How then do you not defend yourself in person ?</p>
          <p n="95">EUR. I will tell you. In the first place, I am known; next, I am gray-headed and have a beard; while you are of a good countenance, fair,5 shaven, with a woman's voice,6 de licate, and comely to look at.</p>
          <p n="96">EUR. What's the matter ?</p>
          <p n="97">AGATH. Did you ever compose this verse? "You take7 pleasure in beholding the light; and do you not think your father takes pleasure in beholding it?"</p>
          <p n="98">AGATH. Don't expect then that I will undergo your mis fortune for you: for I should be mad. But bear yourself what is yours, as a private matter. For it is not right to bear 8 one's calamities with artifices, but with endurance.</p>
          <p n="99">MNES. And yet you, you lewd fellow, are loose-breeched, not through words, but through endurance.</p>
          <p n="100">EUR. But what is it, for which you fear to go thither ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.193"/>
          <p n="101">AGATH. I should perish more miserably than you.</p>
          <p n="102">AGATH. How? — seeming to steal the nightly labours of the women, and to filch away the women's love.</p>
          <p n="103">MNES. " Steal," quoth'a ! Nay, rather, by Jove, to be rav ished ! But, by Jove, the pretext is plausible.</p>
          <p n="104">EUR. What then ? Will you do this ?</p>
          <p n="105">AGATH. Don't imagine it'</p>
          <p n="106">EUR. Oh thrice-unlucky ! how I am undone !</p>
          <p n="107">MNES. Euripides, my dearest, my son-in-law,2 do not abandon yourself!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.202"/>
          <p n="108">EUR. How then, pray, shall I act ?</p>
          <p n="109">MNES. Bid a long farewell to this fellow, and take and use me as you please.</p>
          <p n="110">EUR. Come then, since you give yourself up to me, strip off this garment!</p>
          <p n="111">MNES. Well now, it is on the ground. But what are you going to do to me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.210"/>
          <p n="112">EUR. To shave 3 these clean, but singe clear the parts below.</p>
          <p n="113">MNES. Well, do whatever you think fit! or I ought4 never to have given myself up to you.</p>
          <p n="114">EUR. Agathon, you, of course, always carry a razor,-now lend us a razor!</p>
          <p n="115">AGATH. Take it from thence yourself out of the razor-case.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.218"/>
          <p n="116">EUR. (to Agathon). You are very good! [ To Mnesilo chus.] Sit yourself down! Puff out your right cheek! [Mnesilochus sits down and Euripides commences shaving.]</p>
          <p n="117">EUR. Why do you cry out ? I'll put a gag in your mouth, 1 if you don't be silent.</p>
          <p n="118">MNES. Alas ! woe is me ! [Mesilochus starts up and at tempts to run away.]</p>
          <p n="119">EUR. Hollo you ! whither are you running ?2</p>
          <p n="120">MNES. To the temple of the august goddesses; for, by Ceres, I will not stay here any longer,4 being gashed!</p>
          <p n="121">EUR. Will you not then be ridiculous, pray, with the one half5 of your face shaved ?</p>
          <p n="122">MNES. I little care.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.227"/>
          <p n="123">EUR. By the gods, by no means abandon me! Come hither ! [ Takes him by the arm and makes him sit down again.]</p>
          <p n="124">MNES. Ah me, miserable !</p>
          <p n="125">EUR. Keep quiet,6 and lift up your head ! Whither are you turning ?</p>
          <p n="126">EUR. Why do you mutter ?8 Every thing has been accom plished well.</p>
          <p n="127">MNES. Ah me, miserable ! Then I shall serve as a light- armed 9 soldier!</p>
          <p n="128">EUR. Don't be concerned about it; for you shall appear very comely. Do you wish to see yourself?</p>
          <p n="129">MNES. If you think fit, give me the looking-glass!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.235"/>
          <p n="130">EUR. Do you see yourself ?</p>
          <p n="131">MNES. No, by Jove, but Clisthenes!1</p>
          <p n="132">EUR. Stand up, that I may singe 2 you; and stoop for wards ! 3</p>
          <p n="133">MNES. Ah me, miserable! I shall become a sucking pig.4</p>
          <p n="134">EUR. Let some one bring a torch or a lamp from within! [To Mnesilochus.] Bend yourself forwards! Take care now of your extremities ! [Euripides begins to singe him.]</p>
          <p n="135">MNES. It shall be my care, by Jove ! only that I am burn ing. Ah me, miserable ! Water, watery neighbours, before the flame take hold of my rump !</p>
          <p n="136">EUR. Be of good courage !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.244"/>
          <p n="137">MNES. How be of good 7 courage, when I'm quite burnt up ?</p>
          <p n="138">EUR. But you've no further trouble now; for you have fin ished the greatest part.</p>
          <p n="139">MNES. Foh! oh, what 8 soot! I have become burnt all about my rump.</p>
          <p n="140">EUR. Don't be concerned ! for another shall wipe it with a sponge.9</p>
          <p n="141">MNES. He shall weep then, whoever shall wash my breech.</p>
          <p n="142">EUR. Agathon, since you grudge to give yourself up to me, at any rate at least lend us a dress for this man,10 and a girdle; for you will not say that you haven't them.</p>
          <p n="143">AGATH. Take and use them! I donat grudge them.11</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.252"/>
          <p n="144">MNES. What then shall I take ?</p>
          <p n="145">AGATH. What ? First take and put on the saffron-coloured robe.</p>
          <p n="146">MNES. (sniffing at it). By Venus, it smells sweetly of— lechery ! Gird me up quickly! Now bring 12 me a girdle ! [Euripides brings a girdle.]</p>
          <p n="147">MNES. Come then, fit me out about the legs.</p>
          <p n="148">EUR. We want a head-dress and headband.1</p>
          <p n="149">AGATH. Nay, rather, see here's a woman's cap2 to put round him, which I wear by night!</p>
          <p n="150">EUR. By Jove, but it's even very suitable! 3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.260"/>
          <p n="151">MNES. Will it fit me ? [Puts it on.]</p>
          <p n="152">AGATH. By Jove, but it's capital!</p>
          <p n="153">EUR. Bring an upper garment! 4</p>
          <p n="154">AGATH. Take it from the little couch.</p>
          <p n="155">AGATH. Here, take mine !</p>
          <p n="156">MNES. Will they fit me? At all events you like to wear them loose.</p>
          <p n="157">AGATH. Do you see5 to this ! But indeed6 you have what you want. Let some one wheel me in as quickly as possible. [Exit Agathon.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.269"/>
          <p n="158">EUR. (surveying Mnesilochus' attire). He, though a man,7 is now a woman in appearance. If you speak, see that you talk like a woman in your voice, well and naturally.8</p>
          <p n="159">MNES. No, by Apollo ! unless you swear to me—</p>
          <p n="160">MNES. -that you will help to deliver me with all your arts,1 if any misfortune befall me.</p>
          <p n="161">EUR. " I swear then by Ether, the dwelling of Jove." 2</p>
          <p n="162">MNES. Why rather than by the lodging of Hippocrates?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.277"/>
          <p n="163">EUR. I swear then by all your gods in a lump.4</p>
          <p n="164">MNES. Remember this then, that " your mind 5 swore, but your tongue has not sworn neither will I bind it by an oath.</p>
          <p n="165">EUR. Hasten quickly; for the signal 6 for the assembly in the temple of Ceres is exhibited ; but I will be off. [Exit</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.286"/>
          <p n="166">MNES. Come on then, Thratta, follow me! See, Thratta, what a quantity of smoke 1 ascends as the torches burn! Come, 0 very-beautiful Thesmophorse,2 receive me with good luck,3 both on my entrance here, and on my return home again! Thratta, take down the box, and then take out a cake, that I may take and offer it to the two goddesses. 0 highly-honoured mistress, dear Demeter, and thou, Persephone, let me, possessing much, often4 sacrifice to thee ! but if not, now at least be undiscovered ! and let my daughter, my pig,5 meet with a husband who is rich, and besides, silly6 and stu pid! and let my little boy7 have sense and understanding! Where, where shall I sit down in a good place, that I may hear the orators ? Do you, Thratta, be off out of the way! for it is not permitted slaves to hear the words.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.295"/>
          <p n="167">HER. Let there be8 solemn silence ! Let there be solemn silence! Pray to the1 Thesmophoræ, Demeter, and Cora,2 and to Plutus, and to Calligenia, and to Tellus, nurse of youths,3 and to Mercury,4 and to the Graces, to convene this assembly and the present meeting in the most becoming and most profitable5 manner:-very beneficially for the state of the Athenians, and fortunately for ourselves ; and that she may get her opinion passed, who acts and speaks the best for the people 6 of the Athenians and that of the women.7 Pray for these things, and for yourselves what is good. lo Paean ! io Paean ! Let us rejoice !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.311"/>
          <p n="168">CiO. We accept the omen, and supplicate the race of the gods to appear and take pleasure in these prayers. 0 Jove of great renown ! and thou with golden lyre, who inhabitest sacred Delos! and thou, all powerful damsel, gray-eyed, with spear of gold, who inhabitest a desirable city, come hither ! and thou of many names, damsel slaying wild beasts, offspring of golden-eyed Latona ! and thou marine, august Neptune, lord of the sea, having left thy fishy, storm-vexed9 recess! and ye daughters of marine Nereus! and ye moun tain-roaming nymphs ! And let the golden lyre accompany our prayers; and may we well-born Athenian women bring our debates to an accomplishment.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.320"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.335"/>
          <p n="169">HER. Pray to the Olympic gods and to the Olympic god desses,2 and to the Pythian gods and to the Pythian goddesses, and to the Delian gods and to the Delian goddesses, and to the other deities ; if any oneplots any evil3 against the people of the women, or makes proposals of peace to Euripides 4 and the Persians for the purpose of any injury to the women, or purposes to be a tyrant,5 or to join in bringing back the tyrant, or has denounced a woman as substituting a child, or if anywoman's female slave, being a go-between, has his pered the matter, in her master's ear, -or if any, when Sent, brings lying messages, or if any paramour deceivesby telling falsehoods, and does not give what he shall have formerly promised, or if any old woman6 gives presents to aparamour, or even if a mistress receives presents, betraying her friend, and if any male or female publican7 falsifies the legal measure of the gallon or the half-pint, pray that he may perish miserably, himself and family, but pray that the gods may give many blessings9 to all the rest of you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.350"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.366"/>
          <p n="170">CHO. We offer our united prayers that these wishes may come to be accomplished for the state, and accomplished for the people ; and that those women who give1 the best advice (as many as this befalls) may get their opinions passed. But as many as for the sake of gain deceive, and violate the established oaths for the purpose of injury, or seek to revolutionize de crees and law, and tell our secrets to our enemies, or bring in the Persians for the purpose of injury to the country, act wickedly and injure the state. But, 0 all-powerful Jove, mayest thou accomplish this, so that the gods stand by us, although2 we are women.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.373"/>
          <p n="171">HER. Hear, every one ! [ Unfolds a paper and begins to read the preliminary decree.] " These things have been de termined on by the Senate of the women: Timoclea was Epistates,3 Lysilla was secretary, Sostrata moved the decree ; to convene an assembly in the morning4 in the middle of the Thesmophoria, when we are most at leisure; and to debate first about Euripides, what he ought to suffer; for he has been adjudged5 guilty by us all." Who6 wishes to speak ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.381"/>
          <p n="172">HER. Then first put on this crown1 before you speak. [ To the meeting.] Be silent 1 Be quiet! Give2 attention ! for she is now expectorating, as the orators do. She seems to be going to make a long speech.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.398"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.407"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.418"/>
          <p n="173">1ST WOMAN. Through no3 ostentatiousness, by the two goddesses, have I stood up to speak, 0 women; but indeed I have been vexed, unhappy woman, now for a long time, see ing you treated with contumely by Euripides the son of the herb-woman,4 and abused with much abuse5 of every kind.For what abuse does henot6 smear upon us? And-where has he not calumniated us, where, in short,7 are spectators, and tragic actors, and choruses? calling us adulteresses in disposition, lovers of the men, wine-bibbers,8 traitresses, gossips, masses of wickedness, great pests to men. So that, as soon as9 they come in from the wooden-benches, they look askance at us, and straightway search, lest10 any paramour be concealed in the house. And we are no longer able to do any of those things which we formerly did: such badness has he taught our husbands. So that, if even any woman weave a crown,11 she is thought to be in love; and if she let fall any vessel while roaming about the house, her husband asks her, " In whose honour is the pot broken ? It must be for the Corinthian12 stranger." Is any girl1 sick ; straightway her brother says, “ This colour in the girl does not please me." Well; does any woman, lacking children, wish to substitute a child; it is not possible even for this to go undiscovered; for now the husbands sit down beside2 them. And he has calumniated us to the old men, who heretofore used to marry girls; so that no old man is willing to marry a woman, on account of this verse, " For a woman is ruler over an old bridegroom." In the next place, through him they now put seals and bolts4 upon the women's apartments, guarding us; and moreover they keep Molossian5 dogs, a terror to paramours. And this, indeed, is pardonable ; but as for what was permitted us heretofore, to be ourselves the housekeepers, and to draw forth and take barley-meal, oil, and wine; not even this is any longer per mitted us. For the husbands now themselves carry secret little keys, most ill-natured, certain Spartan 7 ones with three teeth. Previously, indeed, it was possible at least1 to secretly open the door, if we got a three-obol2 seal-ring made. But now this home-born slave3 Euripides has taught them to have rings of worm-eaten wood, having them suspended about them. Now therefore I move 4 that we mix up some destruc tion in some 5 way or other for him, either by poison, or by some one artifice, so that he shall perish. These I speak openly ; but the rest I will draw up in the form of a motion in conjunction with the secretary.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.434"/>
          <p n="174">CiO. Never yet did I hear a woman more intriguing than this, nor one that spoke more ably. For she speaks all justly, and has well examined all appearances, and weighed7 all things in her mind, and shrewdly discovered artful, well invented words ; so that, if Xenocles the son of Carcinus were to speak immediately after8 her, he would appear to us all, as I think, to say absolutely nothing to the purpose.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.444"/>
          <p n="175">2ND WOM. For the purpose of a few words I also have eome forward. For the other matters she has laid to his charge rightly: but what I have suffered personally, these I wish to state. My husband died in Cyprus,' having left behind him five little children, whom I used to maintain with diffi culty by plaiting wreaths in the myrtle-wreath-market.2 Be fore this3 I supported myself, indeed, but miserably.4 But now this fellow by representing in his tragedies,5 has persuaded the people that there are no gods; so that we do not now earn even to the amount of6 one half. Now therefore I exhort and charge all to punish this man for many reasons ; for, 0 women, he does savage deeds to us, as having been reared himself among the potherbs8 in their wild state. But I will be off to the market-place ; for I have twenty bespoken9 wreaths to plait for people.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.452"/>
          <p n="176">CHO. This other disposition, again, appears still cleverer than the former one. How' she talked! not what was ill timed, nor yet what was void of understanding, but all per suasive, being possessed of sense and a subtle mind. The man must manifestly2 give us satisfaction for this insolence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.465"/>
          <p n="177">MNES. It is not wonderful, 0 women, that you who are so abused3 should be exceedingly exasperated at Euripides, nor yet that your bile should boil over ; for I myself hate that man, if I be not mad,—so4 may I be blessed in my chil dren ! But nevertheless we must grant the privilege of speak ing amongst each other; for we are by ourselves, and there is no blabbing5 of our conversation. Why thus do we ac cuse6 him, and are vexed, if, being cognizant of two or three misdeeds of ours, he has said them of us7 who perpetrate in numerable ? For I myself, in the first place,-not to speak of any one else,—am conscious with myself of many shameful8 acts: at all events of that9 most shameful one, when I was a bride of three days, and my husband was sleeping beside me. Now I had a friend,10 who had debauched me when I was seven years of age. He, through love of me, came and began scratching at the door; and then I immediately understood it; and then I was for going down11 secretly, but my husband asked me, " Whither are you going down ? " " Whither ?-A colic1 and pain, husband, possesses me in my stomach; there fore I am going to the necessary." "Go then!" said he. And then he began pounding juniper berries, anise, and sage. But after I had poured some water on the hinge,2 I went out to my paramour; and then I conversed with him beside the statue3 of Apollo, holding by the bay-tree. These, you see,4 Euripides never yet at any time spoke of. Nor does he men tion how we give ourselves up to our slaves and to muleteers, if we have not any other.5 Nor how, when we junket ever so much during the night, we chew up garlic6 in the morning, in order that the husband having smelt it when he comes in from the wall,7 may not suspect us of doing any thing bad. These things, you see, he has never at any time spoken of. And if he does abuse a Phædra, what is this to us ?8 Neither has he ever mentioned that, how that well-known woman,9 while showing her husband at day-break10 how beautiful her upper garment is, sent out her paramour hidden in it—that he has never yet mentioned.11 And I know another woman, who12 for ten days said she was in labour, till she purchased a little child; while her husband went about purchasing drugs to procure a quick delivery.' But the child2 an old woman brought in a pot with its mouth stopped with honey comb,3 that it might not squall. Then, when she that carried it nodded, the wife immediately cried out, " Go away,4 hus band, go away, for methinks I shall be immediately delivered." For the child kicked against the bottom of the pot.5 And he ran off delighted, while she drew out the stoppage from the mouth of the child, and it cried out. And then the abomin able6 old woman who brought the child, runs smiling to the husband, and says, " A lion has been born to you, a lion! your very image, both in all other respects whatever, and its nose is like yours, being crooked like an acorn-cup."7 Do we not practise these wicked acts ? Yea, by Diana, do we ! And then are we angry at Euripides, " who2 have suffered nothing greater than we have committed?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.473"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <p n="178">CHO. This3 certainly is wonderful, where the creature was found, and what land reared this so audacious woman. For I did not think the villanous woman would4 even ever have dared thus shamelessly to say this publicly amongst us. But now every thing may take place. I commend the old proverb, "For5 we must look about under every stone, lest an orator bite us." But indeed there existeth not any thing more wicked for all purposes1 than women shameless by na ture,—unless perhaps it be women.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.490"/>
          <p n="179">3RD WOM. You are certainly not in your right senses, women, by Aglaurus !3 But you have either been bewitched, or have suffered some other great evil, who permit this pesti lent creature to wantonly insult us all in such a manner. If indeed there be any one who will do it, it is well; but if not,4 we ourselves and our slaves, having got ashes from some quarter, will depillate her rump, so that she may be taught, woman as she is, henceforth5 not to speak ill of women.</p>
          <p n="180">MNES. Nay not my rump, pray, 0 women. For if, when there was freedom of speech and it was permitted us all to speak, as many citizens as are present, I then spoke what pleas I knew in defence of Euripides, ought I on this account to suffer punishment by being depillated by you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.502"/>
          <p n="181">3RD WOM. Why, ought you not to suffer punishment ? who1 alone hast dared to reply in defence of a man, who has done us many injuries, purposely devising tragedies where a wo man has been vile, writing plays on Melanippes and Phasdras.2 But he never at any time wrote a play on3 Penelope, because she has been adjudged to be a chaste woman.</p>
          <p n="182">MNES. I know the reason. For you could not mention a single Penelope among the women of the present day, but Phædras every one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.510"/>
          <p n="183">3RD WOM. You hear, women, what things the villanous woman has again said of us all.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.520"/>
          <p n="184">MNES. And, by Jove, too, I have not yet mentioned as many as I am cognizant of! For would you that I mention more ?</p>
          <p n="185">3RD NOM. Nay, you cannot any further ; for you have poured forth all that you knew.</p>
          <p n="186">ANES. No, by Jove, not yet the ten-thousandth4 part of what we do ! For, you see, I have not mentioned this, how we take strigils5 and then draw off the wine with a siphon.</p>
          <p n="187">3RD WOM. You be hanged!1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.528"/>
          <p n="188">MNES. And how, again, while we give the meats from the Apaturia2 to our go-betweens, we then say that the cat3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.540"/>
          <p n="189">3RD WOM. Me miserable ! you talk nonsense.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.549"/>
          <p n="190">MNES. Nor have I mentioned how another struck down her husband with the axe ;4 nor how another drove5 her hus band mad with philtres; nor how the Acharnian woman6 once buried</p>
          <p n="191">3RD WOM. May you utterly perish !</p>
          <p n="192">MNES. -her father under the kitchen boiler.</p>
          <p n="193">3RD WOM. Are these, pray, endurable to hear?7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.558"/>
          <p n="194">MNES. Nor how you, when your woman-slave had borne a male child, then substituted this for yourself, and gave up your little daughter to her.</p>
          <p n="195">3RD WOM. By the two goddesses, you certainly shall not get off with impunity for saying this ! but I will twitch out your hairs.8</p>
          <p n="196">MNES. You shall not touch me, by Jove !</p>
          <p n="197">3RD WOM. Well now, see !</p>
          <p n="198">MNES. Well now, see !</p>
          <p n="199">3RD WOM. Take my cloak, Philista! [ Strips off her cloak.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.566"/>
          <p n="200">MNES. Only put your hand upon me, and, by Diana, I will</p>
          <p n="201">3RD WOM. What will you do?</p>
          <p n="202">MNES. I'll make you evacuate this sesame-cake9 which you have devoured!</p>
          <p n="203">CHO. Cease railing at one another; for some woman10 is running towards us in haste. Therefore, before she is near,1 be ye silent, in order that we may hear decorously what2 she is going to say. [Enter Clisthenes.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.574"/>
          <p n="204">CLISTH. 0 women dear, ye kindred3 of my disposition, I show4 by my cheeks that I am a friend to you; for I am woman-mad, and am always your patron.5 And now 6 having heard an important matter about you, which was canvassed a little before7 in the market-place, I have come to tell it and announce it to you, in order that you may see and take care, lest a terrible and important affair come suddenly upon you off your guard.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.582"/>
          <p n="205">CHO. What is it, boy ? for 'tis natural to call you boy,8 as long as you have your cheeks thus smooth.</p>
          <p n="206">CLISTH. They say that Euripides has sent a man up hither to-day his own father-in-law, an old man.</p>
          <p n="207">CHO. For what deed ? for the purpose of what design ?</p>
          <p n="208">CLISTH. In order that he might be a spy upon your words, whatever you deliberated and purposed to do.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.590"/>
          <p n="209">CHO. Why, how was a man among women without being detected ?</p>
          <p n="210">CLISTH. Euripides singed and depillated him, and dressed him up like a woman in all other respects.</p>
          <p n="211">MNES. Do you believe him in this ? What man is so foolish, as to bear1 to have his hairs plucked out ? I don't believe it, O ye highly-honoured goddesses!</p>
          <p n="212">CLlSTH. You talk foolishly; for I would not have come to report it, if I had not heard this from those who clearly knew.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.598"/>
          <p n="213">CiO. This affair is a dreadful one which is announced.2 Come, women, we ought not to be idle, but to look out for the man, and search where he has secretly taken his seat un known to us. And do you, [turning to Clisthenes, our patron, help to find him out! so that you may have thanks for this as well as for that.3</p>
          <p n="214">CLISTH. Come, let me see! [ Turning to one of the women.] First, who are you ?</p>
          <p n="215">MNES. (aside). Whither can one turn ?</p>
          <p n="216">CLISTH. For you must be examined.</p>
          <p n="217">MNES. (aside). Me miserable !</p>
          <p n="218">4TH WOMAN. Did you ask me,5 who I am ? The wife of Cleonymus.</p>
          <p n="219">CLISTH. Do you know who this woman is ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.606"/>
          <p n="220">CHO. Oh yes, we know her ! But examine the others.</p>
          <p n="221">CLISTH. But who, pray, is this who has the child ?</p>
          <p n="222">4TH WOM. My nurse, by Jupiter!</p>
          <p n="223">MNES. (aside). I am6 undone ! [Attempts to slip away.]</p>
          <p n="224">CLISTH. (turning to Mnesilochus). Hollo you ! whither are you turning ? Stay here ! What's your ailment ?7</p>
          <p n="225">MNES. Permit me to make water.</p>
          <p n="226">CLISTH. You're a shameless1 creature. Do you then2 do so! for I will wait here.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.614"/>
          <p n="227">CHO. Pray do wait, and watch her carefully too! for her alone, sir, we don't know.</p>
          <p n="228">CLISTH. You're a long time making water.</p>
          <p n="229">MNES. Yes, by Jove, my good friend; for I suffer from strangury: I ate some nasturtium yesterday.</p>
          <p n="230">CLISTH. Why do you chatter5 about nasturtium ? Will you not come hither to me ? [Drags him away from the corner. ]</p>
          <p n="231">MNES. Why, pray, do you drag me when I am ill ?</p>
          <p n="232">CLISTH. Tell me, who's your husband ?</p>
          <p n="233">MNES. Do you inquire about6 my husband ? Do you know What's his name, of the burgh of Cothocidæ ?7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.622"/>
          <p n="234">CLISTH. What's his name ! What sort of a person ?</p>
          <p n="235">MNES. There is a What's his name, who once What d'ye call 'em, the son of What's his name</p>
          <p n="236">CLISTH. You appear to me to be talking nonsense. Hare you ever a come up hither before ?</p>
          <p n="237">MNES. Yes, by Jove, every9 year!</p>
          <p n="238">CLISTH. And who is your messmate ?10</p>
          <p n="239">MNES. Mine is What's her name. Ah me, miserable !</p>
          <p n="240">CLISTH. You say nothing to the purpose.11</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.630"/>
          <p n="241">5TH WOM. (to Clisthenes). Go away! for I will12 examine her properly by the rites of last year. And do you stand away, that you may not hear, as you are a man. [Clisthenes retires to one side.] Do you tell me, what one of the rites1 used to be first exhibited to us.</p>
          <p n="242">MNES. Come, let me see! Nay,2 what was the first ?—We drank.</p>
          <p n="243">5TH WOM. What was the next after this ?</p>
          <p n="244">MNES. We drank each other's health.</p>
          <p n="245">5TH WOM. This you heard from some one. What, then, was the third ?</p>
          <p n="246">MNES. Xenylla asked for a night-stool; for there was no chamber-pot.3</p>
          <p n="247">5TH WOM. You say nothing to the purpose. Come hither, hither, Clisthenes ! This is the man whom you speak of.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.638"/>
          <p n="248">CLISTH. What then shall I do ?</p>
          <p n="249">5TH WOM. Strip him; for he says nothing that is right.</p>
          <p n="250">MNES. And will you then4 strip the mother of nine children ?</p>
          <p n="251">CLISTH. Unloose your girdle quickly, you shameless crea ture !</p>
          <p n="252">5TH WOM. How very stout and strong she appears ! and, by Jove, too, she has no breasts, as we have.</p>
          <p n="253">MNES. For I am barren, and have never been pregnant.</p>
          <p n="254">5TH WOM. Now; but you were the mother of nine chil dren a while ago.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="255">CLISTH. Stand upright! Whither are you thrusting down your hand ?</p>
          <p n="256">5TH WOM. See there, it peeped out! and very fresh-coloured it is, you rogue.</p>
          <p n="257">CLISTH. Why, where is it ?</p>
          <p n="258">5TH WOM. It's gone again to the front. [ Clisthenes goes in front of Mnesilochus.]</p>
          <p n="259">CLISTH. It is not here.6</p>
          <p n="260">5TH WOM. Nay, but1 it has come hither again.</p>
          <p n="261">CLlSTH. You've a kind of an isthmus,2 fellow ; you're worse than the Corinthians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.655"/>
          <p n="262">5TH WOM. Oh the abominable fellow !3 On this account4 then be reviled us in defence of Euripides.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.663"/>
          <p n="263">MNES. Me miserable! in what troubles have I involved myself!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.672"/>
          <p n="264">5TH WOM. Come now, what shall we do ?</p>
          <p n="265">CLISTH. Guard him properly, so that he shall not escape ; and I'll report these to the Prytanes. [Exit Clisthenes. ]</p>
          <p n="266">CiO. Then we ought now after this:; to kindle our torches and gird ourselves up well and manfully, and strip off6 our garments and search, if perchance some other man too has entered, and to run round the whole Thesmophorium7 and the tents, and to examine closely the passages. Come then,8 first of all we ought to rouse a nimble foot and look about in every direction in silence. Only we must not9 loiter, since the time admits no further delay,10 but we ought now first11 to run as quickly as possible round about. Come then, search, and quickly investigate all parts, if any other, again, is se cretly sitting in these places.1 Cast your eye round in every direction, and properly examine all parts, in this direction, and in that. For if he be detected 2 after having done unholy deeds, he shall suffer punishment, and in addition to this shall be an example3 to all the others of insolence and unjust deeds and ungodly manners; and he shall say that there are evi dently gods; and he shall be forthwith a witness to all4 men to honour the gods, and that they justly pursuing what is pious, and devising what is lawful, should do what is right. And if they do not do so, the following shall happen to them: when any of them is detected acting profanely, burning with madness, mad with frenzy, if he do any thing,5 he shall be a conspicuous warning to all women and mortals6 to behold, that the god punishes what is unlawful and unholy, and it is done immediately. But it seems that pretty nigh all parts have been properly examined by us: at any rate we don't now see any other man sitting among us. [ Mnesilochus snatches a child from the arms of one of the women.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.689"/>
          <p n="267">6TH IVM. Ah ! Whither are you flying ? Ho you ! Ho you ! will you not stay ? Me miserable ! miserable ! And he is gone, having snatched away my child from my breast.</p>
          <p n="268">MNES. Bawl1 away; but this you shall never feed with morsels, unless you let me go ; but here at the altars2 being struck with this sword upon its bloody veins, it shall stain the altar with blood.</p>
          <p n="269">6TH WOM. Oh me miserable! Will you not succour me, women ? Will you not raise a mighty and rout-causing3 shout, but suffer me to be deprived of my only child?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.699"/>
          <p n="270">CHO. Ha! ha ! 0 venerable Fates, what new portent, again, is this which I behold ? How all then, arc deeds of audacity and shamelessness! What a deed is this, again, which he has done ! what a deed, again, my friends !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.707"/>
          <p n="271">MNES. How I'll knock your excessive arrogance out of you !</p>
          <p n="272">CHO. Are not these, pray, shameful deeds and more6 than that?</p>
          <p n="273">6TH WOM. Shameful certainly, if one7 has snatched away my child.</p>
          <p n="274">CtO. What then can one say to this, when this man is shameless enough to do8 such things ?</p>
          <p n="275">MNES. May this, however, by no means take place, I pray God!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.715"/>
          <p n="276">CHO. Who then, who of the immortal gods, would come as your helper,4 with your unjust5 deeds ?</p>
          <p n="277">MNES. You talk in vain: herI will not let go.</p>
          <p n="278">CHO. But, by the two goddesses, perhaps you will not in sult us with impunity, and speak unholy words. For we will requite you for these with ungodly deeds,8 as is reasonable: and perhaps some fortune, having cast9 you into an evil of a different kind, will restrain you. But [turning to Mica] you ought to take these 10 women-slaves, and bring out some wood, and burn the villain to ashes, and destroy him with fire as soon as possible.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.728"/>
          <p n="279">6TH WOM. Let us go to fetch the brushwood, Mania.' And I'll make you [addressing Mnesilochus] to-day a hot coal.</p>
          <p n="280">MNES. Set on fire and burn ! But do you [addressing the child] quickly strip off your Cretan 2 garment; and blame your mother alone of women for your death, child. [ Strips the child, whereupon it turns out to be a wine-skin dressed up like an infant.] What's this ? The girl has become a wine- skin 3 full of wine, and that too with Persian slippers. 0 ye most thirsty. women, 0 most bibacious,5 and contriving by every device to tipple, 0 great6 blessing to publicans, but to us, on the contrary, a pest; and a pest also to the furniture 7 and to the woof ! 8</p>
          <p n="281">6TH. WOM. (returning with a bundle of brushwood). Heap up beside him abundant brushwood, Mania.</p>
          <p n="282">MNES. Yes, heap it up ! But do you answer me this ques tion : do you say you bore this ehild ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.739"/>
          <p n="283">6TH WOM. Yes, and carried it ten9 months.</p>
          <p n="284">MNES. Did you carry it ?</p>
          <p n="285">6TH WOM. Yea, by Diana !</p>
          <p n="286">MNES. Holding three Cotylæ, or how ? tell me ! [Exposes the wine-skin to view.]</p>
          <p n="287">6TH WOM. What have you done to me ? You have stripped my child, you shameless fellow, being so little.</p>
          <p n="288">6TH WOM. Yes, by Jove, little</p>
          <p n="289">MNES. How many years old is it? three Choæ,1 or four?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.747"/>
          <p n="290">6TH WOM. About so much,2 and as long as since the Dio nysia. But restore it.</p>
          <p n="291">MNES. No, by this 3 Apollo !</p>
          <p n="292">6TH WOM. Then we'll set fire to you.</p>
          <p n="293">MNES. Set fire by all means ; but this shall be slaughtered forthwith.</p>
          <p n="294">6TH WOM. Nay, do not, I beseech you; but do to me what you please instead4 of it.</p>
          <p n="295">MNES. You are very fond of your children by nature:5 but this shall be slaughtered none the less.6</p>
          <p n="296">9TH WOM. Alas, my child ! Give me a bowl,7 Mania; so that certainly I may at least catch the blood of my child.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.756"/>
          <p n="297">MNES. Hold it under, for I will gratify you in this one thing. [Drinks up the wine-skin himself]</p>
          <p n="298">6TH WOM. May you perish miserably! How grudging and malevolent you are!</p>
          <p n="299">MNES. (holding up the empty wine-skin). This hide 1 be longs to the priestess.</p>
          <p n="300">6TH WOM. What belongs to the priestess ?</p>
          <p n="301">MNES. (tossing her the empty wine-skin). Take it!</p>
          <p n="302">7TH WOM. Most wretched Mica, who has robbed you of 2 your daughter ? who has taken away your beloved child ? 3</p>
          <p n="303">6TH WOM. This villain ! But since you are present, guard him, in order that I may take Clisthenes and tell to the Pry tanes 4 what this man has done. [Exit 6th woman. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.765"/>
          <p n="304">'NES. Come now, what shall be my contrivance for safety? what my attempt ? what my device ? For he who is the author of this, and who has involved5 me in such troubles, does not yet appear. Come, what messenger can I send to him ? Now I know a contrivance out of his Palamedes :6 I'll write upon the oars and throw them out, as that well- known 7 character did. But the oars are not at hand. Whence therefore can it be possible for me to get oars ? whence? 1 But what if2 I were to write on these here images instead of the oars, and throw them about ? Much better! Certainly indeed 3 both these are wood and those were wood. 0 hands of mine, you must take in hand a practicable4 deed ! Come now, you plates of polished tablets, receive the traces of the graver, messengers of my miseries. Ah me, this Rho is a miserable5 one ! through what a furrow it goes, it goes ! Go ye, hasten through all roads, that way, this way ! You ought speedily. [Exit Mnesilochus.]6 6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.773"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.785"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.795"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.804"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.814"/>
          <p n="305">CHO. Let us then praise ourselves in our parabasis.7 And yet every one says many ill things of the race of women, that we are an utter evil8 to men, and that all evils spring from us, strifes, quarrels, sedition, painful grief, and war. Come now, if9 we are an evil, why do you marry us, if indeed we are really an evil, and forbid any of us either to go out, or to be caught peeping out,1 but wish to guard the evil with so great dili gence ? And if the wife should go out any whither, and you then should discover her to be out of doors, you rage with madness, who ought to offer libations and rejoice, if indeed you really find the evil to be gone away from the house, and do not find it at home. And if we sleep in other people's houses, when we play2 and are tired, every one searches for this evil, going round about the beds. And if we peep out3 of a window, he seeks to get a sight of the evil. And if she retire again, being ashamed, so much the more does every one desire to see4 the evil peep out again. So manifestly are we much better than you. And a test is at hand to see.5 Let us make trial, which of the two are worse. For we say that you are; but you say that we are. Let us consider now, and compare each with each, placing each name6 side by side, both the woman's and the man's. Charminus7 is inferior to Nausi mache : his deeds are manifest. And in truth also Cleophon8 is, I ween, by all means inferior to Salabaccho. And none of you even attempts to contend with Aristomache for a long time,9 that notable one at Marathon, and with Stratonice. But what senator of those of last year, who delivered up his senatorial office1 to another, is superior to Eubule ? Not even he himself2 will say this. So much 3 better do we profess to be than the men. Neither would a woman who has stolen at the rate4 of fifty talents of the public money come into the city in a chariot; but when she may have committed her greatest 5 peculations, when she has stolen a bushel of wheat from her husband, she restores them6 the same day. But we could point out many of these present who do this, and who are, in addition to this, more gluttonous than we, and footpads, and parasites,7 and kidnappers. And in truth also they are, I ween, inferior to us in preserving8 their patri mony. For still even now our loom 9 is safe, our weaving beam, our baskets, and our parasol; while the beam 10 of many of these our husbands has perished from the house together with the head, and the parasol of many others has been cast from their shoulders in their expeditions. We women 11 could justly and deservedly 12 bring many charges against the men: but one most monstrous. For it were proper, if any of us bore a man serviceable to the state, a taxiarch or general, that she should receive some honour, and that precedence be given her at the Stenia and Scirophoria, and at the other festivals which1 we have been accustomed to keep. But if any wo man bore a cowardly and worthless man, either a worthless trierarch or a bad pilot, that she should sit behind her who has borne the brave man, with her hair cut bowl-fashion.2 For how3 is it equitable, 0 city, that the mother of Hyper bolus 4 should sit near the mother of Lamachus,5 clothed in white, and with loose flowing hair, and lend out money on usury ? To whom, if she were to lend out to any one, and exact usury, no man ought to give any interest, but they ought to take away her money by force, saying this, " In sooth you're deserving of interest, having borne such 7 pro duce." [Re-enter Mnesilochus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.824"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.832"/>
          <p n="306">MNES. I've got a squint with looking for8 him; but he does not yet 9 appear. What then can be the hinderance? It must be that he is ashamed of his Palamedes' because it is frigid. With what drama then can I draw1 him up ? I know it! I’ll imitate his new2 Helen. At all events I have a woman's dress.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.846"/>
          <p n="307">7TH WOM. What are you again plotting ? or why do you look gaping about?3 You shall soon see4 a bitter Helen, if you will not be orderly, until some of the Prytanes come.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.855"/>
          <p n="308">MNES. (as Helen). “These5 are the streams of the Nile with beautiful nymphs, which, in place of rain from heaven, moistens the plain of white7 Egypt, a people using black draughts.” 8</p>
          <p n="309">7TH WOM. You're a knave, by the torch-bearing9 Hecate! .nes. “Not10 inglorious is my native land, Sparta, and Tyndareus is my sire."</p>
          <p n="310">7TH WOM. Is he your father, you pest? Nay, rather, Phrynondas.11</p>
          <p n="311">MNES. " And1 I am called Helen."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.863"/>
          <p n="312">7TH WOM. Are you again becoming a woman, before you've suffered punishment for your former acting the woman ?2</p>
          <p n="313">ANES. "And3 many men died on my account at the streams of the Scamander."</p>
          <p n="314">7TH WOM. And would 4 that you had died too.</p>
          <p n="315">MNES. " And I am here ; but my unhappy husband, my Menelaus, does not yet come. Why then 6 do I still live ? "</p>
          <p n="316">7TH WOMAN. Through the laziness7 of the crows.</p>
          <p n="317">MNES. “ But8 something as it were chccrs my heart. Do not cheat 9 me of my coming hope, 0 Jove! ” [Enter Euri pides attired as Menelaus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.871"/>
          <p n="318">EUR. “ Who has10 the rule over these fortified mansions, who11 would receive strangers distressed with storm 12 and shipwreck on the open sea ? "</p>
          <p n="319">MNES. “ This13 is the house of Proteus."</p>
          <p n="320">EUR. “ What Proteus ? "</p>
          <p n="321">7TH WOMAN. Oh thrice-unlucky! [Turning to Euripides.] He is telling lies, by the two goddesses ! for Protcas 1 has been dead these ten years.</p>
          <p n="322">EUR. “ At what country have we landed with our ship ?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.879"/>
          <p n="323">EUR. “ 0 wretched ! whither have we sailed !"</p>
          <p n="324">7TH WOMAN. Do you believe this fellow at all-the devil take 2 him — talking nonsense ? This is the Thesmopho rium.</p>
          <p n="325">EUR. "Is Proteus himself3 within, or out of sight ?”</p>
          <p n="326">7TH WOMAN. It must be that you are4 still sea-sick, stranger, who having heard that Proteus is dead, then5 ask if he is within, or out of sight.</p>
          <p n="327">EUR. “ Alas, he is dead! Where has he been buried in the tomb?"</p>
          <p n="328">MNES. “ This is his tomb,6 upon which I am sitting."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.887"/>
          <p n="329">7TH WOMAN. Then may you perish miserably! and cer tainly indeed you will perish, who have the impudence to call the altar a tomb.</p>
          <p n="330">EUR. "Why,8 pray, do you sit in these sepulchral seats covered9 with a veil, 0 female stranger ?"</p>
          <p n="331">MNES. "I am 1 forced to mingle in wedlock with the son of Proteus."</p>
          <p n="332">7TH WOMAN. Wherefore, you wretch, are you again de ceiving the stranger ? [ To Euripides.] This fellow, 0 stranger, acting the knave, came up hither to the women for the stealing of the gold.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.895"/>
          <p n="333">MNES. "Bark away, assailing2 me with censure."</p>
          <p n="334">EUR. Female stranger, who is the old woman who re viles 3 you ? "</p>
          <p n="335">MNES. " This is Theonoe, daughter of Proteus."</p>
          <p n="336">7TH WOMAN. No, by the two goddesses! unless4 Critylla daughter of Antitheus of Gargettus be so. But you're a knave.</p>
          <p n="337">MNES. " Say whatever you please. For I will never marry5 your brother, having abandoned6 Menelaus, my hus band, in Troy."</p>
          <p n="338">EUR. " What say you, woman ? Turn your sparkling eyes7 towards mine."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.903"/>
          <p n="339">.,,NES. "I am ashamed before you, having been mauled8 in my cheeks."</p>
          <p n="340">EUR. "What's this? Speechlessness9 possesses me. Ye gods, what sight 10 do I behold ? Who art thou, woman ?"</p>
          <p n="341">MNES. " And who are you? for the same1 word holds you and me."</p>
          <p n="342">EUR. Are you a Grecian woman, or a woman of this country?"</p>
          <p n="343">MNES. "A Grecian woman. But I also wish to learn2 yours."</p>
          <p n="344">EUR. " I see you very like to Helen, woman."</p>
          <p n="345">MNES. " And I you to Menelaus,3 as far as may be judged from the pot-herbs."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.911"/>
          <p n="346">EUR. " Then4 you rightly recognise a most unfortunate man."</p>
          <p n="347">MNES. " 0 thou who hast come late to the arms of thy wife ! Take me, take me, husband ! Throw thy arms5 around me! Come, let me kiss you ! Take and lead me away, lead me away, lead me away, lead me away6 very quickly."</p>
          <p n="348">7TH WOM. Then, by the two goddesses, he shall weep,7 whoever shall lead you away, being beaten with the torch.</p>
          <p n="349">EUR. " Do you hinder me from leading my wife, the daughter of Tyndareus, to Sparta?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.920"/>
          <p n="350">7TH WOM, Ah me, what 8 a knave you also appear to me to be, and this man's counsellor! No wonder you were acting the Egyptian9 this long while. But he shall suffer punish ment; for the Prytanis is approaching, and the Policeman. [Goes towards them. ]</p>
          <p n="351">EUR. This is unlucky. Well, I must sneak away.10 5 A parody upon Eur. Helen. 627, 628.</p>
          <p n="352">MNES. But what shall I do, unhappy man ?</p>
          <p n="353">EUR. Remain quiet; for I will never abandon you, if I live; 1 unless my innumerable artifices fail me. [Exit Eu ripides. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.928"/>
          <p n="354">MNES. This line2 has drawn up nothing. [Enter Prytanis and Policeman.]</p>
          <p n="355">PRYT. Is this the knave of whom Clistheqes spoke to us ? Ho you, why do you hang down3 your head? Lead him4 within, Policeman, and bind him to the plank, and then place him here and guard him, and suffer no one to approach him; but beat them with your whip, if any approach.</p>
          <p n="356">7TH WO M. Yes, by Jove! for now assuredly5 a tricky fellow6 almost took him away from me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.936"/>
          <p n="357">MNES. 0 Prytanis, by your right hand, which you are ac customed to hold7 out bent, if any one offer you money, grant me a small favour, although about to die.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.947"/>
          <p n="358">PRYT. In what shall I oblige 8 you ?</p>
          <p n="359">AiNiS. Order the Policeman to strip me naked and fasten me to the plank ; in order that, being an old man, I may not in saffron-coloured robes, and a woman's night-cap, afford laughter to the crows, while I feast them.9</p>
          <p n="360">PRYT. It has been determined by the Senate to bind you with them on, in order that you may be clearly seen by the passers-by1 to be a knave. [Exit Prytanis.]</p>
          <p n="361">MNES. Oh my ! oh my ! 0 saffron robe, what things you have done ! No longer is there any hope of safety. [Police man leads Mnesilochus within.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.957"/>
          <p n="362">CHO.2 Come now, let us sport, as is here the custom with the women, whenever on holy seasons we celebrate the solemn orgies of the two goddesses, which Pauson3 also honours, and fasts, oftentimes protesting to them from season to season that such are frequently a care to himself.4 Put yourself in motion, each of you, advance, come on lightly with your feet in a circle,5 join hand to hand, move to the time6 of the dance ; go with swift feet. It beboveth the choral order7 to look about, turning round the eye in every direction. And at the same time also celebrate, each of you, and honour with your voice, the race of the Olympic gods, with a mind mad for dancing. But if any one expects that I, woman as I am, will speak ill of men during the sacred rites,1 he docs not think rightly. But it behoveth us immediately, as our duty is, first to dispose the graceful step of the circling danced Advance with your feet, celebrating Apollo with beautiful lyre. and the bow-bearing Diana, chaste queen. Hail, thou far-darter, and grant us the victory! And let us celebrate, as is fitting, Juno who presides over marriage, who sports in all the dances, and keeps the keys of marriage.3 And I entreat the pastoral Mercury, and Pan, and the dear Nymphs, benevo lently to smile upon and take pleasure in our danccs.4 Begin now zealously the Diple,5 the joy of the dance. Let us sport, O women, as is the custom ! Assuredly we keep 6 the fast. But come ! turn to another measure with foot keeping good time ; round off the whole ode. And do thou thyself,8 0 ivy wreathed king Bacchus, lead us; and I will celebrate thee with chorus-loving odes,9 0 Evius, 0 Bromius, child of Jove and Semele, delighting in dances, in the mountains among the pleasing hymns of the Nymphs, 0 Evius, Evius, beginning a choral dance, evoe ! And the echo of Cithæron ' resounds around thee, and the thick-shaded mountains dark with leaves and the rocky dells re-echo; while around thee the beautiful-leaved ivy flourishes with its tendrils round about. [Mnesilochus is brought upon the stage again by the Policeman fast bound to the plank. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.966"/>
          <p n="363">POLICEMAN. There now1 you shall wail to the open sky.</p>
          <p n="364">MNES. 0 Policeman, I bescech you !</p>
          <p n="365">POL. Don't beseech me!</p>
          <p n="366">MNES. Loosen the nail.</p>
          <p n="367">POL. Well, I am2 doing so. [Hammers it in tighter.]</p>
          <p n="368">MNES. Ah me, miserable! you are hammering it in the more.3</p>
          <p n="369">POL. Do you wish 4 it to be hammered still more?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.974"/>
          <p n="370">MNES. Alas, alas ! May you perish miserably.</p>
          <p n="371">Per,. Be silent, miserable old man ! Come, let me bring a mat,5 in order that I may guard you. [ Goes out and returns again with a mat.]</p>
          <p n="372">MNES. These are the blessed fruits which6 I have enjoyed from Euripides. Ha, ye gods, preserver Jove, there are hopes ! The man docs not seem likely to abandon7 me; but he ran forth as8 Perseus, and secretly gave me a sign that I must become Andromeda. At all events I'm furnished with the fetters.1 Therefore it is still2 evident that he will come to save me ; for otherwise he would not have flown near me. [Enter Euripides as Perseus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.982"/>
          <p n="373">EUR. Dear,3 dear virgins, would I could approach and escape the observation of the Policeman ! [Addressing the Policeman.] Dost thou4 hear ? 0, I beseech thee, who dwellest in caves, by reverence, assent, permit me to come to the woman !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.990"/>
          <p n="374">MNES. Pitiless5 was he, who bound me, the most distressed of mortals. When I had with difficulty escaped the anti quated6 old woman, I perished notwithstanding. For this Policeman has been standing by me this long while as my keeper: has hung me up, undone and friendless, as a dinner for the crows. Do you see? not among dances, nor yet accompanied by the girls1 of my own age, do I stand with the ballot-box of pebbles, but, entangled in strong fetters, I am exposed as food for the whale Glaucetes.2 Lament me, 0 women, not with a bridal song, but with a prison-song,3 since I have suffered wretched things, wretched man, oh me unhap py, unhappy! and among my other impious sufferings from my relations, supplicating the man,4 kindling the all-tearful lamentation of death,5 alas ! alas! who first shaved me clean, who clothed me in a saffron-coloured robe ; and, in addition to this, sent me up to this temple, where the women were assembled. Ah me, thou unrelenting god of my fate ! Oh me, accursed ! Who at the presence of my woes will not look6 upon my unenviable suffering ? Would that the fire-bearing star7 of Æther would utterly destroy me, ill-fated man. For no longer is it pleasing to me to behold the immortal flame ; since I am hung up, the cut-throat woes of the gods,! for a quick journey to the dead.2</p>
          <p n="375">EUR. (as Echo). " Hail, 0 dear child! but may the gods destroy thy father Cepheus, who exposed thee."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1001"/>
          <p n="376">MNES. (as Andromeda). " But who are you, who have pitied my suffering?"</p>
          <p n="377">EUR. " Echo, responsive mocker of words,3 who, last year in this very place, myself even shared in the contest4 with Euripides. But, child, you must act your own part, to weep5 piteously."</p>
          <p n="378">MNES. " And you must weep in answer after me.''</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1009"/>
          <p n="379">EuR. " This shall be my care : but commence your words." [Goes behind the scene.]</p>
          <p n="380">MNES. "0 sacred6 night, how long a course you pursue, driving over the starry back of sacred Æther through the most august Olympus."</p>
          <p n="381">EUR. (from behind1 the scene as Echo). “ Through Olym pus."</p>
          <p n="382">MNES. “ Why ever have I, Andromeda, obtained a share of woes above2 the rest?"</p>
          <p n="383">EUR. “ Obtained a share."</p>
          <p n="384">MNES. “ Wretched3 for my death."</p>
          <p n="385">EUR. " Wretched for my death."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1019"/>
          <p n="386">MNES. " You will destroy me, old woman,4 with chatter ing."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1035"/>
          <p n="387">EUR. “ With chattering."</p>
          <p n="388">MNES. “ By Jove, you have got in very troublesome.”5</p>
          <p n="389">MNES. “ Good sir,6 permit me to sing a monody, and yon will oblige me. Cease."</p>
          <p n="390">MNES. Go to the devil.</p>
          <p n="391">EUR. “ Go to the devil."</p>
          <p n="392">MNES. What's the pest ?</p>
          <p n="393">EUR. " What's the pest ?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1045"/>
          <p n="394">MNES. You talk foolishly.</p>
          <p n="395">EUR. “ You talk foolishly."</p>
          <p n="396">MNES. Plague take you.</p>
          <p n="397">EUR. “ Plague take you."</p>
          <p n="398">EUR. “ Confound you."</p>
          <p n="399">POL. (awaking1 and starting up from his mat). Hollo you, what are you talking ?</p>
          <p n="400">EUR. “ Hollo you, what are you talking ?”</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1056"/>
          <p n="401">POL. I'll summon the Prytanes.</p>
          <p n="402">EUR. “ I'll summon the Prytanes."</p>
          <p n="403">POL. What's the pest?</p>
          <p n="404">EUR. “ What's the pest ?"</p>
          <p n="405">POL. Whence was the voice ?2</p>
          <p n="406">EUR. “ Whence was the voice ?"</p>
          <p n="407">POL. (turning to Mnesilochus). Are you talking?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1064"/>
          <p n="408">EUR. “ Are you talking?"</p>
          <p n="409">POL. You shall weep.</p>
          <p n="410">EUR. " You shall weep."</p>
          <p n="411">POL. Are you laughing at me ? 4</p>
          <p n="412">EUR. “ Are you laughing at me ? "</p>
          <p n="413">MNES. (to the Policeman). No, by Jove! but this woman near you.5</p>
          <p n="414">EuR. " This near you."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="415">POL.'Where is the abominable woman? Now she's flying. Whither, whither are you flying ?</p>
          <p n="416">EUR. “ Whither, whither are you flying ? ”</p>
          <p n="417">POL. You shall not get off6 with impunity.</p>
          <p n="418">EUR. " You shall not get off with impunity."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1082"/>
          <p n="419">POL. Why, are you still muttering ?</p>
          <p n="420">EUR. "Why, are you still muttering?"</p>
          <p n="421">POL. Catch7 the abominable woman!</p>
          <p n="422">EUR. “ Catch the abominable woman."</p>
          <p n="423">Per. The chattering and accursed woman.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1092"/>
          <p n="424">EUR. (entering as Perseus. “Ye8 gods! to what land of barbarians have we come with swift sandals ? for I, Perseus, place my winged foot, cutting my way through mid air,1 travelling to Argos, carrying the head of the Gorgon."2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1103"/>
          <p n="425">POL. What are you saying ahout3 the head of Gorgus the secretary ?</p>
          <p n="426">EUR. " I say the head of the Gorgon."</p>
          <p n="427">POL. I also mean Gorgus.4</p>
          <p n="428">EUR. “Ha!5 what cliff is this which6 I see, and virgin like to the goddesses, moored like7 a ship ?"</p>
          <p n="429">MNES. " 0 stranger, pity me all wretched: loose me from my fetters."</p>
          <p n="430">POL. Don't you talk ! Accursed8 for your audacity: do you chatter when about to die ?</p>
          <p n="431">EUR. " 0 virgin, I pity you, seeing you hung up."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1111"/>
          <p n="432">POL. It is not a virgin, but a sinful old man, and a thief, and a knave.</p>
          <p n="433">EUR. " You talk foolishly, Policeman; for this is Andro meda, daughter of Cepheus."</p>
          <p n="434">POL. Look at his breasts ! Do they look like a woman's ?</p>
          <p n="435">EUR. "Give me here your1 hand, in order that I may touch the damsel; give me it, Policeman: for all men have their weaknesses, and love of this damsel has seized myself."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1119"/>
          <p n="436">POL. I'm not at all jealous of you; but if his face had been turned this way, I would not have refused your going and kissing2 him.</p>
          <p n="437">EUR. “ But why, Policeman, do you not permit me to re lease her and recline upon3 the couch and marriage-bed?"</p>
          <p n="438">POL. If you strongly desire to kiss the old fellow, bore through the plank and go to him.</p>
          <p n="439">EUR. " No, by Jove, but I will loosen the fetters."</p>
          <p n="440">POL. Then I'll whip you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1127"/>
          <p n="441">EUR. " And yet I'll do so."</p>
          <p n="442">POL. Then I'll4 cut off your head with this scimetar.</p>
          <p n="443">EUR. " Alas! what shall I do? To what words shall I turn ? But his barbarous nature will not give car to them.5 For in truth, if you were to offer new inventions of wisdom to stupid6 people, you would spend your labour to no purpose.</p>
          <p n="444">But I must apply some other device1 which is adapted to him." [Exit Euripides.]</p>
          <p n="445">POL. Abominable fox ! how he was for deceiving2 me.</p>
          <p n="446">MNES. Remember, Perseus, that you are leaving me miserable.</p>
          <p n="447">POL. What, you're still wishing to get the whip! [Lies down again and falls asleep.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1136"/>
          <p n="448">Cno. It is3 my custom to invite hither to4 the chorus Pallas, friend of the chorus, virgin, unwedded damsel, who guards our city, and alone possesses visible sovereignty, and is called guardian. Appear,5 0 thou that hatest tyrants, as is fitting ! Of a truth the people of the women6 invokes thee; and mayest thou come to me with Peace the friend of festi vals.7 Come, ye8 mistresses, benevolent arid propitious, to your hallowed place ; 9 where in truth it is not lawful for men to behold the solemn orgies of the two goddesses, where, by torch-light,10 ye show your immortal countenances. Come, approach, we supplicate you, 0 much-revered Themophoræ ! If ever before ye came11 in answer to our call, come now, we beseech you, here to us. [Enter Euripides as an old pro curess, accompanied by a dancing-girl and a boy with a flute. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1145"/>
          <p n="449">EUR. Women, if you are willing to make1 peace with me for the future, it is now in your power; I make you these proposals of peace on the understanding2 that you are to be in no wise abused by me at all henceforth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1153"/>
          <p n="450">CiO. On account3 of what matter do you bring forward this proposal ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1160"/>
          <p n="451">EUR. This man in the plank is my father-in-law. If there fore I recover him, you shall never4 be abused at all. But if you do not comply, I will accuse you to your husbands when they come home from the army of those things which you do secretly.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1170"/>
          <p n="452">CHO. For our6 parts, be assured that we are prevailed upon. But this barbarian you must7 prevail upon yourself.</p>
          <p n="453">EUR. That is my business; and yours, [turning to the dancing-girl,] Elapnium, is to remember to do what I told you on the road. In the first place therefore walk past him,8 and gird yourself up. And do you, [turning to the boy,] Teredon,9 play an accompaniment to the Persian10 dance.</p>
          <p n="454">POL. (waking up). What's this bumming ?1 What band of revellers awakens me ?</p>
          <p n="455">EUR. The girl was about to practise beforehand, Police man ; for she is going to certain people to dance.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1178"/>
          <p n="456">POL. Let her dance and practise,2 I will not hinder her. [ She begins to dance.] How nimble ! like a flea in a sheep- skin.</p>
          <p n="457">EUR. Pull up this dress, child, and sit upon the Police man's knee and hold out your feet, that I may take off your shoes.3</p>
          <p n="458">POL. Yes, yes, sit down, sit down, yes, yes, my little daughter. [Dancing-girl sits down upon the Policeman's knee. ] Ah, how firm4 her breast is, like a turnip.</p>
          <p n="459">EUR. (to the boy). Play you quicker! Are you still afraid of the Policeman ?</p>
          <p n="460">POL. Beauteous she is behind! You shall repent, if you do not remain within. Well! beauteous she is before !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1186"/>
          <p n="461">EUR. It is well. Take your dress: it is time for us now to go.</p>
          <p n="462">POL. Will she not kiss me first ?</p>
          <p n="463">EUR. Certainly. [To the dancing-girl. ] Kiss him! [ She kisses him.]</p>
          <p n="464">POL. Oh, oh, oh ! Oh my ! How sweet her lips ! like Attic honey. Why does she not remain with me ?</p>
          <p n="465">EUR. Farewell, Policeman ! for this cannot be.</p>
          <p n="466">POL. Yes, yes, old woman, gratify me in this.</p>
          <p n="467">EUR. Then will you give me a drachma ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1194"/>
          <p n="468">POL. Yes, yes, I’ll give it you.</p>
          <p n="469">EUR. Then bring the money.</p>
          <p n="470">POL. But I have not any.5 Come, take my quiver.</p>
          <p n="471">EUR. Then you'll bring her again.</p>
          <p n="472">Per. (to the dancing-girl). Follow me, my child! And do you, old woman, guard the old man.—But what's your name ?</p>
          <p n="473">EUR. Artemisia. Therefore remember my name.</p>
          <p n="474">POL. Artamuxia. [Exit Policeman with the dancing-girl. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1202"/>
          <p n="475">EUR. 0 crafty Mercury, this you manage well as yet. Do you then [addressing the boy] run off with this flute, my boy ; and I will set him at liberty. Mind that you fly man fully, as soon as ever1 you are at liberty, and hasten 2 home to your wife and children.</p>
          <p n="476">MNES. This shall be my3 care, if once I be at liberty.</p>
          <p n="477">EUR. Be thou free! Your business! fly! before the Policeman comes and catches you.</p>
          <p n="478">MNES. I will do so now. [Exeunt Euripides and Mnesi lochus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1210"/>
          <p n="479">POL. (returning with the dancing girl). How agreeable your daughter is, old woman, and not ill-natured, but gentle. Where's the old woman ? [Dancing-girl slips off. Ah me, how I am undone ! Where is the old man gone from hence ? O old woman, old woman. I don't commend you, old woman. Artamuxia. The old woman has deceived me. [Picks up his quiver and throws it across the stage.] Away with you as soon as possible ! It is rightly called quiver, for it imposes upon me. Ah me, what shall I do ? Whither is the old woman gone? Artamuxia.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1218"/>
          <p n="480">CiO. Are you inquiring for5 the old woman, who was carrying the harp ?</p>
          <p n="481">POL. Yes, yes. Did you see her ?</p>
          <p n="482">CHO. Both she herself has gone this way, and an old man was following her.</p>
          <p n="483">POL. The old man with the saffron-coloured robe ?</p>
          <p n="484">CiO. Yes; you might still catch her, if you were to pur sue her this way.</p>
          <p n="485">POL. Oh the abominable old woman ! Which way 6 shall I run ? Artamuxia.</p>
          <p n="486">CHO. Run straight upwards. Whither are you running ? Will you not run back this way? you are running the con trary way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1226"/>
          <p n="487">POL. Me miserable ! But Artamuxia is running off. [Exit Policeman. ]</p>
          <p n="488">CHO. Run then, run then, with a fair wind to the Devil ! But we have sported sufficiently; so that in truth it is time for each to go home. May the Thesmophoræ return us a gracious kindness for this. [Exeunt omnes. ]</p>
          <p n="489">END OF THE THESMOPHORIAZUS-E.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
