<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Frogs (Ranae)</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">Benjamin Bickley Rogers</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Benjamin Bickley Rogers (1919). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg009.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.19"/>
          <p n="1">THE comedy of the Frogs was produced during the Lenaean festival, at the commencement of the year B.C. 405, when Callias was Archon, that Callias who, to distinguish him from other archons bearing the same name, was commonly designated “the Callias who succeeded Antigenes1.” It at once took its position, which has never since been challenged, amongst the masterpieces of the Athenian drama. It carried off the prize at the Lenaean 2 contest, from the " Muses " of Phrynichus, which was placed second, and the “Cleophon" of Plato, which was placed last; and the victorious poet was crowned in the full theatre with the usual wreath of Bacchic ivy. But it achieved a far higher success than this. It enjoyed the, apparently, unique distinction of being acted a second time, as we should say, by request; and at this second representation the poet was again crowned, not now with mere leaves of ivy, but with a wreath made from Athene's sacred olive 3, an honour reserved for citizens who were deemed to have rendered important services to Athene's city.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.51"/>
          <p n="2">It was not for its wit and humour that these exceptional honours were accorded to the play; nor yet for what to modern readers constitutes its pre-eminent attraction, the literary contest between Aeschylus and Euripides. It was for the lofty strain of patriotism which breathed through all its political allusions, and was especially felt in the advice tendered, obviously with some misgiving as to the spirit in which the audience would receive it, in the epirrhema of the parabasis. There the poet appeals to the Athenian people to forego all party animosities, to forget and forgive all political offences, to place the state on a broader basis, to leave no Athenian disfranchised. More particularly, he pleads for those who having been implicated in the establishment of the Council of Four Hundred had1 ever since been deprived of all civic rights. They could vote for no candidate, hold no office, and take no part in the popular assemblies. Other citizens, however illiterate, enfranchised slaves, half-breeds, and the like, would be hurrying on to support the most ill-judged proposals of Cleophon; but they—men of the purest Athenian blood, and the highest and most liberal Athenian culture- must needs stand aside, as though they had neither part nor lot in the Republic of Athens. Aristophanes calls upon the people to put an end to this anomalous state of things, and to re-enfranchise all dis- franchised Athenians; . His doubt as to the reception of his appeal is manifested in every part of the epirrhema. It is the Mystic Chorus, he insists, the Company of the Blessed Dead who are taking upon themselves to advise the Athenian people; the errors of the excluded citizens are described as slips and slidings, not deliberate, but occasioned by the wily machinations of Phrynichus ; the people whom he is addressing are mollified by the appellation , although in the antepirrhema, where he feels himself on safer ground, he resorts to his more customary address ; while, both before and afterwards, he indulges in a wild vein of harmless jocularity, calculated to mitigate any ire which his boldness may have aroused.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.92"/>
          <p n="3">It tells much for the generosity of the Athenian people, that instead of resenting the poet's appeal, they rewarded it with the highest and most exceptional honours. For we are told on the authority of Dicaearchus, a writer of. the very greatest weight on such matters, that it was this very appeal which won the admiration of the public, and obtained for the play the honour of a second representation 1. And this is fully borne out by the well-known fact that on the next political crisis, imme- diately after the disaster of Aegospotami, the Athenians followed to the letter the advice of Aristophanes, and their very first step was Tous , to enfranchise the disfranchised citizens. " When your fleet was destroyed, and the siege commenced,” says Ando- cides 2, “ye took counsel together to create harmony in the state, and ye determined to enfranchise the disfranchised, and Patrocleides it was who introduced the decree." He then sets out the decree, TO To , and adds, " So then in pursuance of this decree, ye enfranchised the disfranchised3.” So Xenophon speaking of the commencement of the siege says 4, “The Athenians, having enfranchised the disfranchised, held out." So Lysias, though with his usual vague- ness and inaccuracy, says 5, " Your disposition was such that ye recalled the exiles, and enfranchised the disfranchised." I say " with his usual inaccuracy," because it is certain that the exiles did not return until after the city had been surrendered to Lysander, and could not help itself. It was one of the conditions of peace imposed by the Spartans. Indeed, the passage already cited from Andocides goes on, "In pur- suance of this decree ye enfranchised the disfranchised. But Patrocleides did not propose, nor did ye decree, the return of the exiles. But when the treaty with the Lacedaemonians was concluded, and ye dismantled your walls and received back the exiles,” &amp;c.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="4">It seems certain that the comedy has come to our hands in the revised form which it assumed on its second representation. The strange duplication of certain passages towards the end of the play must force itself upon the attention of the most unobservant reader: a duplication which in my opinion arises in almost every case from the fact that the reading of the original play has crept from the margin into the text of the revised edition 1. There is a very similar duplication, arising from the same circumstance, in some of Biron's speeches in Activ. scene 3, and Act v. scene 2, of Shakespeare's Love's Labour's Lost.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.116"/>
          <p n="5">But to my mind the most convincing passage is that contained in lines 1109-1114. The Chorus have been exhorting the rival poets not to rest content with a mere general criticism of their respective aims and merits, but to come to close quarters, and to attack each other's dramas in every possible way, with a minute dissection of individual lines, phrases, and metres. This would obviously require an audience not only thoroughly intelligent, as an Athenian audience would naturally be, but also thoroughly primed in the details about to be discussed ; and it is impossible to doubt that on the first representation of the Frogs many of the most delicate hits would pass altogether unnoticed. But this would not be so on the second representation. The play would then have become public property; it would be in the hands of the spectators, and they would not fail to appreciate and applaud every point as it arose. And it is on this very ground that the Chorus encourage the rivals to proceed. But if this ye fear, lest there be in the spectators any lack of knowledge, so that they will not recognize your subtleties when ye speak them, be not afraid of this, since the matter is no longer so. For they are old campaigners now; and each of them holding a book of the words is conning your clever hits. The words 'EO' ’ seem to imply that on the first representation of the play the audience were not always able .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.125"/>
          <p n="6">The play was acted about six months after the great naval victory of Arginusae; about four months after the death of Euripides; and about two months after the death of Sophocles.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.125"/>
          <p n="7">The victory of Arginusae was the result of an almost unexampled effort on the part of the Athenian people. Conon, their most brilliant officer, had been defeated at Mitylene, and was closely blockaded there. One trireme managed to run the blockade, and bring news of his peril to Athens. The Athenians received the intelligence in a spirit worthy of their best traditions. All classes at once responded to the call with hearty and contagious enthusiasm. In thirty days a fleet of 110 triremes, fully equipped and manned, was able to put to sea. The knights had emulated the devotion of their forefathers (as recorded in the parabasis of the comedy which bears their name), and volunteered for service on the unaccustomed element. The very slaves had been induced to join by the promise of freedom and, what was even more than freedom, the privileges of Athenian citizenship. Further triremes, as the fleet went on, were obtained from the islands, till it finally reached a total of more than 150 vessels. These exertions were rewarded by a victory which, if it was the last, was also the most considerable of all that were gained by the Athenians during the Peloponnesian War. And the slaves who fought in the great battle were admitted to be free Athenian citizens1 on the same liberal terms as had been granted to the Plataeans who had escaped from their beleaguered city some one and twenty years before. They were enrolled in Athenian tribes and domes and enjoyed all the privileges of Athenian citizens, they and their sons after them for ever; save only that the individuals first enfranchised were not eligible for certain hereditary priesthoods (such as those of the Eumolpidae, the Eteobutadae, and the Ceryces), nor yet for the office of Archon. This exception was right and proper. It would have been very unpalatable for an Athenian to see a man who had been brought up altogether outside the Athenian traditions, and still more so for a master to see his former slave, occupying the supreme position of Archon. Yet even these excepted offices were not withheld from the children of the Plataean, or of the slave, even though they were born before their father acquired the Athenian citizenship.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.169"/>
          <p n="8">The wholesale conversion of loyal slaves into free Athenian citizens, which met with the warmest approval of Aristophanes, readily lent itself to comic humour; and throughout the play, whenever he alludes to the battle of Arginusae, this incident is sure to crop up. In the epirrbema, which we have already discussed, “Shalt we give the fran- chise,” ask the Chorus, " to slaves who have fought but one battle, and yet withhold it from freeborn Athenians, who, and whose fathers before them, have fought so many battles for Athens ?” " 0 why was I not at the sea-fight ? " cries Xanthias to his master1, " I would have bidden you go and be hanged; I would hare snapped my fingers at your commands.” “I take no slave on my ferry,” says Charon 2, “unless he fought in the sea-fight,” in which case, be it observed, he would not be a slave at all. And this consideration will, I think, lead us to the true signification of a much misunderstood phrase in the last-mentioned passage, where the battle of Arginusae is described as the sea-fight .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.177"/>
          <p n="9">" I take no slave," says Charon, A . The word , as Aristarchus 3 is quoted by the Scholiast as saying, is frequently used for ; and such is doubtless its meaning here. Now a slave's body belonged not to himself but to his master. For a slave's body, such is fate, belongs Not to himself, but to the man who bought him. But a free man's body is his own; and he therefore who, in the courts of law or elsewhere, was contending for his freedom (as opposed to slavery), was said TOV to be contending for his body, that is to say, for the ownership of his body. A remarkably apposite illustration of this usage is supplied by the brief, but inter- esting, oration of Lysias, Against Pancleon. The plaintiff had taken proceedings before the Polemarch against Pancleon, believing him to be a resident alien. To these proceedings Pancleon pleaded that he was a " Plataean " enrolled in the tribe Hippothoontis, and the deme of the Deceleians, and was therefore a full Athenian citizen, over whom the Polemarch had no jurisdiction. And the action was accordingly set down to be heard, not on its merits, but on this preliminary plea to the jurisdiction. The oration of Lysias was intended for the plaintiff's speech on the trial of this preliminary issue. It attempts to show that Pancleon, so far from being a “Plataean,” was not even a free man (’ ’ ), but the runaway slave of a " Plataean” master; and that on a previous occasion he feared to bring his claim to the proof; , metuisse, as Reiske translates it, periculum judicii de ingenuitate adire. Here we have the expression applied to a slave contending for the rights of a “Plataean,” the identical position of the slaves who fought at the battle of Arginusae. So far, therefore, as these slaves are con- cerned—and it is only to them that the observation of Charon is addressed—the battle of Arginusae was in truth a , or in a comedians language, a . And this, I am persuaded, is the sense in which the words are here employed. The opinions which have hitherto prevailed are given in the note below1.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.185"/>
          <p n="10">To the subsequent tragedy, which made the victory of Arginusae a word of shame, instead of a word of glory, in the annals of Athens- I mean the condemnation of the victorious generals, and the execution of the six who ventured within the reach of the democracy—Aristophanes makes but one, and that a very faint and obscure, allusion. Aeschylus is considering whether it is right to predicate of Oedipus that he was ever deserving of the epithet ; and running through the various calamities of his life, he comes at last to the statement, he blinded himself, whereupon Dionysus at once cuts in with the remark- meaning, I suppose, that had Oedipus been a colleague of Erasinides in the , his blindness would have been a piece of good fortune. For then he would not have gone to the great battle, and so would not have fallen a victim to the machinations of Theramenes and the madness of the people. This is the only direct allusion to the fate of the generals. But doubtless it was to the attack of "the blear-eyed Archedemus " upon Erasinides, the precursor of the graver charge, that the scorn and contempt with which he is twice2 mentioned in this play are mainly due; and Theramenes owes the ironical censure twice3 passed upon his career rather to the fatal ingenuity with which he shifted the blame from his own shoulders to those of. the generals, than to his former double- dealing in the affair of the Four Hundred.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.221"/>
          <p n="11">At the commencement of the play we find Dionysus journeying to the world below, for the express and only purpose of bringing back Euripides to the Athenian stage. And one reason which he gives for the selection of Euripides is that he is a , a man up to anything, a master of shifts and evasions, who would readily assist in carrying out any plan that might be devised for his rescue. We should therefore naturally suppose that we were intended presently to witness a series of scenes analogous to those in the Thesmophoriazusae ; we should expect to see Euripides utilizing for the purpose of effectuating his own escape some of the ingenious schemes and devices contained in his own plays, just as he had utilized them in the earlier comedy for the purpose of effectuating the escape of Mnesilochus. But nothing of the kind occurs ; there is no idea of an escape; no artful contrivance is required; the plot takes an entirely different trend; nor is Euripides brought back. We shall return to this subject shortly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.251"/>
          <p n="12">The Chorus of the play are the Blessed Mystics, those who had on earth been initiated into the Eleusinian mysteries, and had led a holy and virtuous life in accordance with the doctrines therein inculcated. But before they make their entrance in that character their voices have been heard from behind the scenes chanting the melodious songs of the dead frogs, from whom the comedy derives its name. They do not enter until some scenes later, and then they come in singing a series of hymns and songs, which are not, as commonly supposed, mere unconnected lyrics, but are a continuous presentation of the earlier stages of their annual procession to Eleusis, from the moment when they call Iacchus forth from his sumptuous temple at Athens down to the time when, having passed over the bridge of Cephisus, they are streaming away to weave their mystic sports and dances on the Thriasian plain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.277"/>
          <p n="13">Brimful as the comedy is of genial humour and exuberant vivacity, it nevertheless, to my mind at least, is everywhere invested with a certain solemnity. This is doubtless due, in part, to the fact just mentioned, that the Chorus consists not, as in other comedies, of Athenian citizens, or of comic creations, but of dead mystae, performing in the world below the religious ceremonies which they had, in life, performed in the world above ; and partly again to the circumstance that the action lies chiefly among the dead, and that the great poetical contest which it describes is a contest between two dead poets; but most of all, perhaps, to our knowledge of the terrible time at which the play was produced, when the long anguish of the Deceleian War was visibly drawing to a close, and when the Athenian Empire certainly, and possibly the very existence of Athens, seemed in risk of immediate extinction.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.285"/>
          <p n="14">After passing through various adventures Dionysus arrives safely at the halls of Pluto, and we are at once confronted with an entirely unexpected situation. For it so happens that, at the moment of his arrival, a dramatic contest is about to commence between Aeschylus and Euripides; and Dionysus, clean forgetting the errand on which he came, readily undertakes to act as judge. The actual contest, without reckoning either the preliminary discussions or the political catechism by which it is succeeded, occupies 551 lines (from 875 to 1413, according to Brunck's numbering, which is adopted by all editors, whatever the number of their own lines may be), more than a third of the entire play. Its object is to determine which is the better tragedian of the two; and the rivals discuss not only their general merits and demerits, but also various subordinate questions, their prologues, their choral metres, and the weight of their iambic verses. And all their dramatic stores, both old and new, TO. , are ransacked for passages to support their respective contentions.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.285"/>
          <p n="15">It is difficult to believe that all this detailed and elaborate criticism, together with the remainder of the play in which it is found, can have been entirely worked out during the very brief period which had elapsed since the death of Euripides; especially since from that period itself we must deduct, at its commencement, the time that would pass before the news of the poet's death, which occurred in Macedonia, would have been received at Athens; and at its'close, the time required for the submission of the play to, and its acceptance by, the Archon; the granting of a Chorus; the training of the Chorus; the rehearsals; and all the arduous preparation required for placing the comedy on the stage. It seems far more probable that the contrast between Aeschylus and Euripides, which had been present 1 to the mind of Aristophanes from the very commencement of his career, had taken this form before the younger tragedian's death; and that Aristophanes, finding the time too short for the completion of the play on the lines originally intended, fell back upon this great scene which was ready to his hand, and inserted it in a comedy with the plot of which it was quite unconnected. And, indeed, it can hardly be said to be woven into the texture of the play at all; it is but loosely tacked on, and the stitches by. which it is attached to the main fabric are quite visible to a careful observer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.293"/>
          <p n="16">Nothing can be more abrupt than the manner in which the first mention of the contest is dragged in, some 120 lines before the contest itself begins. It does not spring out of anything which has gone before. Two slaves are talking, and in the very midst of a speech one of them breaks off, and asks the other, 1 Why, what is the meaning of all that hubbub ? And the other explains that a contest is impending between the two great tragedians. And when we come to the contest itself there is not, throughout its whole progress (from line 875 to line 1413), a single syllable tending to show that it is taking place in the world below; nor is Euripides ever spoken of as if he were dead. On the contrary, there is one passage from which, if this scene were detached from the rest of the play, we should certainly assume that he was still alive. To the question what Euripides deserves if the charges brought against him by Aeschylus are sustained, Dionysus promptly replies, " He deserves to DIE 2." In itself the language seems to imply that he was still alive: although, as the play stands, it is of course a mere joke, the joke of dooming to death a person who is already dead. And in truth the poetical contest is so foreign to the general purpose of the play, that we cannot be surprised to find that it ends in a complete fiasco. Dionysus, the chosen judge, having heard the entire competition, declares himself unable or unwilling to give any judgement at all.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.332"/>
          <p n="17">And now a singular thing occurs. Pluto, who has been present during the last 600 lines, or thereabouts, without once opening his mouth, suddenly breaks silence, and announces that the successful poet-whose promised reward has hitherto been the right to occupy the Chair of Tragedy in the Prytaneum of Hades-shaH return with Dionysus to the world above. We therefore, at the close of the poetical contest, return to the old purpose of the play as abruptly as we left it when that contest commenced. And Dionysus marks the change more distinctly by declaring that he will choose, not necessarily the better tragedian (which was the sole object of the poetical competition), but the man who can give to the State the wiser political counsel. The counsel of Aeschylus—that Alcibiades shall be recalled, and the entire resources of the State devoted to the aggrandizement of the fleet-commends itself to Dionysus, who on that ground, and that only, awards the victory to Aeschylus. And Aeschylus therefore it is who .reascends to earth, to do what he can for the city in her hour of need. Yet the decision, though made without the slightest reference to the dramatic merits of the two contending tragedians, carries with it, strangely enough 1, the right to occupy the Tragic Chair. All this curious jumble is occasioned by the clashing of the two motives, the motive of the poetical contest, and the motive of the general plot of the comedy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.354"/>
          <p n="18">Whatever may be the secret history of this poetical contest, it has always formed a most important, and to modern readers probably the most interesting, section of the Comedy of the Frogs. It consists of four distinct trials of strength, divided from each other by choral songs; the rivals discussing (1) their general merits and demerits, (2) their prologues, (3) their choral metres, and (4) the weight of their iambic verses. It may, perhaps, be permissible to make a few observations on this great contest here, at somewhat greater length than would be con- venient in a footnote.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.354"/>
          <p n="19">This, though by far the most important, one might almost say the only important and serious, part of the criticism, need not delay us long. To enter at large into the perennial controversy as to the relative merits of Aeschylus and Euripides is no part of the duty of an editor of Aris- tophanes. But a few brief remarks may not be considered out of place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.396"/>
          <p n="20">It must be remembered that this is not the case of two poets striving after the same ideal, and one approaching it more closely than the other. Their ideals, their aims, their views of the tragic art are in almost every respect diametrically opposed; so that what to the one might seem the chief merit of a play, to the other might appear its greatest defect. The object of Aeschylus was to elevate the drama : to give to his audience an impressive and worthy representation of the demigods and heroes of their noble traditions. To this end he intro- duced the stately robe, the lofty buskin : and, far more important than robe or buskin, the lofty sentiment and the stately language. To Euripides all this appeared mere idle pomposity: his aim was to bring down the drama to the level of ordinary humanity and every-day life. And this contrast is the main topic in the first encounter of the poetical contest. In it each poet is made to give his own view of the aims and objects which tragic poets should set before them: Aeschylus considering it their duty to describe heroic deeds, and clothe noble thoughts in noble language; whilst Euripides insists that they ought to portray the world as they find it, describing the deeds, unveiling the motives, and employ- ing the language, of daily life. The idea of Aeschylus is to elevate and exalt the minds of the audience: the idea of Euripides is to paint the world, its passions and infirmities, as they really are 1. Each may be considered to have summed up his own theory in a single half-verse. l (1056), It is our bounden duty to speak what is noble and good, is the language, and might be taken as the motto, of Aeschylus; (1058), We ought to speak all other men speak, is the language and motto of Euripides. Each theory will always have its advocates ; it is my good fortune, as a translator of Aristophanes, to be in entire accord with the views of my author.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.426"/>
          <p n="21">From the foregoing considerations it naturally follows that neither poet altogether denies the charges advanced by the other. He merely denies that the characteristic attacked is a blemish, and claims it as a merit. If Euripides reproaches Aeschylus with his gigantic com- pounds and grandiloquent language, Aeschylus does not deny the grandiloquence, but maintains that his is the only diction befitting the divine and heroic personages which both poets brought upon the stage. If Aeschylus censures his opponent for infusing a talkative and argumentative spirit into the Athenian people, Euripides is so far from denying the charge, that he glories in it as one of his brightest achieve- ments. They agree as to the facts : they differ only in their estimate of the facts.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.460"/>
          <p n="22">Perhaps one other point should be mentioned. It is frequently said that the antagonism of Aristophanes to the dramatic influence of Euripides was based on considerations of morality. And this is per- fectly true; only it must not be understood as suggesting that Euripides was, in any sense whatever, the holder or propagator of immoral prin- ciples. But1 the great civic and social virtues, honour and justice and valour, patriotism and self-devotion, respect to parents and reverence to the gods, and the like-virtues which to Aeschylus, and generally to the Athenians of the old heroic days, were matters of conscience, about which no discussion could be tolerated-were by Euripides brought to the test of " that universal solvent, the wild living intellect of man." There were few, if any, virtues, and few, if any, vices, for and against which a store of arguments might not be found somewhere in the plays of Euripides. And though he himself might conclude in favour of the right, yet he left it open for a more powerful or more plausible reasoner to turn the scale in favour of the wrong. Euripides might hold, as Hippolytus in the tragedy named after him did certainly hold, that an oath must be kept inviolate, even though taken in ignorance of what it involved; but the theory that in some circumstances an oath might not be binding on the conscience, had been disseminated amongst a quick and ingenious audience, and might bring forth fruit which the poet little meant.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.479"/>
          <p n="23">I do not propose to enter more largely into this part of the con- troversy between the two poets; but some very admirable and instructive remarks on the subject, which I have been permitted by the kindness of Sir R. C. Jebb to extract from his lectures on " The Growth and Influence of Classical Greek Poetry," will be found in a separate note at the end of this Introduction.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.479"/>
          <p n="24">In the second encounter the combatants no longer deal with the general theory of tragic poetry, but commence their criticism of special portions of a tragic play. "We will first begin with the prologue," Euripides is made to observe, since the prologue is the first beginning of a play." But in truth there is no method in these attacks. Aristo- phanes merely selects one point here and another there, just as they seem to afford the readiest handle to his wit and satire.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.516"/>
          <p n="25">Euripides was accustomed to make his prologue an exposition of the facts upon which his play was founded ; a vehicle for conveying to the audience the information which was necessary to bring them to the point at which the action of the drama commenced. His prologues, as a rule, consisted of a lucid and neatly-worded historical narrative; and the charge which he first brings against his rivals prologues is founded on the obscurity and ambiguity () of their language. It must be admitted that he could not have selected a prologue more suitable for his purpose than the stately and impressive lines with which the Choephoroe opens; lines, it is to be observed, which do not exist in the imperfect MS. of the Choephoroe, and which would have been altogether lost if they had not been cited in the Frogs. The lines are spoken by Orestes over the grave of his murdered father :— The first line consists of five words only ; but each of its '.last three words is susceptible of two very different interpretations, neither 'of which can be called in any way repugnant to the context. may signify either " belonging to my father, Agamemnon," or " belonging to thy father Zeus"; may refer either to an earthly rule, or to a divine attribute; whilst may be employed either in the ordinary sense of " surveying, overlooking" or in the special1 Eleu- sinian sense of "participating in." Euripides takes the first (or human) interpretation of each word : Aeschylus explains that he meant them all to bear the second. Euripides understands them to mean " overlooking my father's realm" and inquires whether the god of craft was supposed to be looking on when Agamemnon met his death by a woman's craft. Aeschylus replies that the expression refers to the benignant power of the supreme divinity, Z, the saviour Zeus• and that Orestes is beseeching Hermes to take up that great power, and so become a saviour to him, 2 Widely different as these inter- pretations are from each other, they are both legitimate explanations of the Greek, nor can either be said to be unsuitable to the circumstances under which the words were uttered. Herein lies the of which Euripides complains. And he charges the lines cited with yet another defect, namely, the defect of tautology. Of this he gives two instances. The first is in the third line and mean exactly the same thing, he says. Aeschylus has no difficulty in showing that this is not the case. , he points out, may be predicated of anybody arriving anywhere; it connotes nothing beyond the mere fact of arrival; whilst involves the further idea of the exile returning to his home. This is true, and yet perhaps the answer is not quite satisfactory. It shows that introduces a new idea, beyond what , by itself, would convey; but it does not show that the meaning of is in any way extended by the addition of . And so with the next objection, , which is only met by a joke of Dionysus. It is possible that may signify more than ( OVK Prom. 456), but , apparently, does not imply anything not comprehended in . In neither case is the meaning of the two words identical, but in each the second appears to comprehend the first.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.532"/>
          <p n="26">The true answer to objections of this character is that this is the prayer of Orestes over the grave, now beheld for the first time, of his mighty and cruelly murdered father, whose death he has returned to avenge; and that in moments of strong emotion and exaltation of feeling the soul can only satisfy itself by repeated iteration of the selfsame thought. Take the appeal of a lover to his mistress; take, as in the passage before us, the uplifting of the soul in prayer; take the litanies of the Church in all ages. Our own Liturgy1 teems with such instances. I may perhaps, without offence, quote some passages from the General Exhortation ; " to acknowledge and confess our manifold sins and wicked- ness" "with an humble, lowly, penitent, and obedient heart," " by His infinite goodness and mercy," " when we assemble and meet together," " wherefore I pray and beseech you." Doubtless in all these passages (as in the lines of Aeschylus) an acute grammarian might detect some distinction between the synonyms, but such a distinction would not be perceptible to ordinary worshippers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.563"/>
          <p n="27">It is now the turn of Aeschylus to dissect his opponents prologues, and, after a short criticism of the first two lines of the Antigone of Euripides (which is perhaps sufficiently discussed in the Commentary), he propounds his famous test. Euripides was fond of commencing his plays, as we have already observed, with an historical narrative, which was occasionally prefaced by some philosophical apophthegms; and Aeschylus proposes to show that as a rule, within the first three lines, the words , or , or can be so tacked on as to complete the metre and complete the sense. Euripides recites six prologues, and in each of them, before three lines are over, the words fit in exactly as Aeschylus had predicted. We may well believe that the tacking of this formula to the well-known prologues of Euripides produced an irresistibly comic effect; an effect so lasting that the 1 trochaic dimeter catalectic—the section of the line displaced by the words —was thenceforth named by metrical writers the 2 or .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.580"/>
          <p n="28">Commentators have disquieted themselves in vain to determine the real defect at which Aristophanes is aiming; for there is no real defect; the criticism is merely comic. Some indeed have supposed him to be ridiculing the constant break in the line after the first 2½ feet: but this is out of the question. No break is more common or more harmonious than this, and it would be difficult to cite any set of iambic trimeters in which it does not occur. In the first twenty lines of the humenides it is found no less than eighteen times. And indeed the prologue of that tragedy affords a very happy example for the application of this tag. It begins-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.580"/>
          <p n="29">With this the prologue competition concludes, and we now proceed to the third question.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.589"/>
          <p n="30">Euripides, as usual, is on the alert, and eager to commence the fray. He puts in two ways the case he is going to make. He will display the sameness of his rival's metres (at ). And again, he will cut down all his metres to one ().</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.605"/>
          <p n="31">What then is this particular metre which is so continually cropping up in the Choral Odes of Aeschylus ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.605"/>
          <p n="32">Now we know that Aeschylus was, to adopt Mr. Keble's 1 felicitous phrase, " Tragoedorum Atticorum '." And he himself described his tragedies as " slices cut from Homer's mighty feast." And we cannot wonder therefore if the roll of the Homeric hexameter was always sounding in his mind, and constantly reproducing itself in his choral measures. And this is, in truth, the charge which Euripides is bringing against him. In whatever metre the lyrics of Aeschylus may commence, says his rival, yon are sure to find them, sooner or later, assuming the form of the Homeric hexameter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.623"/>
          <p n="33">The one standard to which the lyrics of Aeschylus are to be cut down is -, or, to use the line which Aristophanes either invented himself, or, more probably, was fortunate enough to find ready-made to his hand in the Myrmidons of Aeschylus,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.623"/>
          <p n="34">Euripides therefore selects five lines from the choral odes of Aeschylus— one from each of the following tragedies, the Myrmidons, the Psychagogi, the Telephus, the Priestesses, and the Agamemnon-and shows that the last twelve syllables of each are in the exact metre of the standard, . To make this perfectly clear, he repeats the standard after each selected line.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.640"/>
          <p n="35">The standard is really an Homeric hexameter which has dropped its first foot, and all but the last syllable of the second. It so happens that its own first syllable is short, , so that it represents an hexameter in which the second foot is a dactyl. And consequently, in each of the five selected lines the corresponding syllable is short.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.640"/>
          <p n="36">This first batch of lines, , therefore bear out, so far as they go, the allegation of Euripides. However they commence, they all conclude with the exact twelve syllables of the standard. But he will not rest content with this; he will give another batch, .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.648"/>
          <p n="37">The plan of repeating the standard after every selected line might easily grow rots . Euripides therefore discards it; he calls his second series of lines , not because, in the tragedies of Aeschylus, they differed in this respect from the former series; but because, whilst lie had recited the former to the music of the , he is about to recite these to the music of the lyre, which is represented by the refrain . And as he does not now introduce the standard ov , so lie no longer keeps to the rule of having the first syllable short. It may now represent an hexameter which has a spondee, as well as one which has a dactyl, in the second place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.656"/>
          <p n="38">This batch contains four lines (for line 1294 may be disregarded), viz. two from the Agamemnon, one from the Sphinx, and one from an unnamed tragedy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.675"/>
          <p n="39">Here then are nine instances in which the metrical system occurs in the choruses of Aeschylus. Euripides might easily have increased the number. Three of the nine instances are taken from the first chorus of the Agamemnon; and, at the risk of being tedious, I will here set down a list of the instances which I have noticed in that immortal song.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.675"/>
          <p n="40">We find therefore in this one chorus, of course a very exceptional case, and indeed within 120 lines of the chorus, the standard measure occurring twenty-six times, if not oftener. And I have omitted every instance (unless indeed the first example be an offender in this respect) in which the close of the measure does not coincide with the close of a word.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.686"/>
          <p n="41">Euripides having finished his criticism, Dionysus demands of Aeschylus whence he derived the incriminated metre, for of course, on the lips of Dionysus, the expression signifies not the music of the lyre, but the verses to which that music had formed the accompaniment. And Aeschylus replies that he had transplanted it from one fair soil to another, in TOV , meaning, from the Homeric epos to the Athenian drama. There was doubtless nothing Homeric in the lays of Phrynichus. In drawing his inspiration, therefore, from the wells of Homer, Aeschylus was striking out a new and independent line, not following in the steps of his predecessor; not , to use his own language, .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.686"/>
          <p n="42">In truth the recurrence of these Homeric echoes imparts an unequalled grandeur and dignity to the Choral Odes of Aeschylus; but if it were otherwise, if it is to be treated as a defect, it is certainly shown to exist; and possibly no other peculiarity of these odes is more prominent, or more easily assailable by Aristophanic humour.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.738"/>
          <p n="43">It is therefore really wonderful that every commentator, without a single exception, should have contrived to ignore the real point of the criticism which Aristophanes takes such pains to elucidate, and have supposed that Euripides was concocting an ode, or rather two odes, in the manner of Aeschylus; each ode being a cento of lines taken at random, without any special metrical purpose, from the latter's Choral Odes. Of the first supposed cento (that is, the first batch of selected lines) they can make nothing; it is admittedly nonsensical; ridiculus ille cento, it is called by Brunck and Dindorf. But in the second supposed cento they fancy themselves able dimly to descry a sort of ponderous and unmeaning sentence, which they imagine to be a carica- ture of the complex stanzas with which we occasionally meet in the choruses of Aeschylus. Several have essayed to translate it. Quomodo Achivorum geminum imperium, Hellenicae pubis, Sphingem tristificam, rectorem canem, mittit cum hasta et manu vindice impetuosus ales, incidere faciens in audaces canes aera pervagantes (I omit the phlattothrats).—Brunck. Quo- modo Achivorum duplex imperium, Graecae juventutis Sphingem, monstrum infortunio praefectum, mittat (Trojam) cum hasta et manu ultrice bellicosus ales (aquila), qui ad pruendam praebuit audacibus avibus in aere volantibus phalangem Ajacis.—Fritzsche. How the ominous bird of war sends forth with spear and vengeful hand the twin sovereignty of the Achaeans, Sphinx of the chivalry of Hellas, foul fiend dispenser of disasters, granting to-the eager soaring vultures to find their prey.—Merry. "We are presented," says Mr. Mitchell, " with a long sentence, in which the nominative case is thrown to a most awkward distance, the accusative presenting itself in the front of the sentence, and the interval offering all the peculiarities of Aeschylean style-bold and dithyrambic diction, harsh appositions and metonyms, and even appositions doubly apposited." Fritzsche indeed does not agree with Aristophanes that Euripides is endeavouring " to show that all Aeschylean metres are identical,” and “ to cut them down to one," His opinion is quite different. “ Ostensurus est Euripides Aeschylo obscuritatem rectissime objici solere." Without citing other commentators it is sufficient to say that every one of them, from the scholiast downwards, takes the same view of Euripides' objection.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.754"/>
          <p n="44">All this criticism is based upon an entire delusion. There is no “ long sentence" here ; there is no " cento." The lines are brought forward as individual specimens, each complete in itself, to be tried by the test of the standard measure ; and have no more connexion with each other than had the various prologues of Euripides brought forward in the preceding encounter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.771"/>
          <p n="45">Exactly the same hallucination has prevailed with regard to the counter-criticism which Aeschylus proceeds to apply to the metres of Euripides. Here too, several isolated passages, seven in number, are selected for the purpose of showing, in each of them, some metrical irregularity or variation. Here too, the commentators, with one accord, persist in huddling all these seven isolated passages into a “ cento " (in supposed imitation of an ode of Euripides) which they vainly endeavour to construe. Here too, there is no " center and no construction. Each of the seven selected passages is intended to be judged, by itself, on its own merits.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.787"/>
          <p n="46">But this misconception is far more excusable than the former. Aristophanes does not point out here, as he did there, the particular irregularities intended to be assailed. Nor are we sufficiently familiar with the metres themselves to determine with certainty in what these irregularities consist, especially as the later writers on metre form their canons on the practice of all the great poets, and consequently look upon the variations introduced by Euripides as regular metrical forms. And certainly I have no confidence whatever in my own ability to point out, in each or any case, the defect, or supposed defect, at which Aeschylus is aiming his criticism. Doubtless, on the stage, the impeached metre was made perfectly plain by the voice and manner of the actor. However, I will set down my ideas on the subject in the hope that they may be corrected by competent scholars.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.795"/>
          <p n="47">It seems to me, then, that the criticism is directed against the variations introduced into three metres, the Choriambic, the Glyconic, and the Paeonic ; variations, it should be remembered, which would be considered defects by those only who would restrict the tragic choruses to austere and simple metrical forms. Variations of this kind are freely admitted in the lyric metres of comedy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.803"/>
          <p n="48">The seven passages which Aristophanes selects are as follows. The letters C, G, and P placed against some of the lines are intended to assist the reader in ascertaining the character and locality of the supposed defect.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.803"/>
          <p n="49">Let us consider the variations which Euripides has in these passages introduced into</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="50">The pure cboriambic dimeter of course consists of two choriambs, As a specimen of this metre, Gaisford, in his notes to Hephaestion, cites the following passage from the Bacchae :— But the metre is rarely found in this pure form I. As a rule, an iambic dipody is substituted for one of the two choriambs; thus This is the ordinary and regular metre. Let us see how Euripides varies it. Four instances are given, in each of which the choriamb concludes the line, as in form (a) supra.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="51">In passage (1), line 4, and also in passage (6), line 2, each iamb is changed into a tribrach, - and ,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.830"/>
          <p n="52">In passage (3) the first iamb is changed into a dactyl, .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.840"/>
          <p n="53">In passage (5) the last syllable of the iambic dipody is omitted, .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.840"/>
          <p n="54">A glyconic line may be best described as consisting of a 2 choriamb, preceded by a dissyllabic base (of any quantity), and followed by a single iamb</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.848"/>
          <p n="55">Hephaestion (chap. x) gives the following example :—</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.856"/>
          <p n="56">when that terribly-raging boar slew with mastiff-destroying tusk Aphrodite's delight and joy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.865"/>
          <p n="57">The metre is very common in both Greek and 1 Roman poetry; and in the passages we are now considering there are three unimpeachable glyconic lines, viz. But there are two other lines in which the incriminated irregularities may be discovered.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.865"/>
          <p n="58">In passage (4), line 1, the base is changed into a tribach, v' -.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.874"/>
          <p n="59">In passage (7) it becomes an anapaest</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.874"/>
          <p n="60">This metre, I may observe in passing, is the favourite metre of Aris- tophanes in his earlier comedies.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.923"/>
          <p n="61">A paeonic line, as a rule, ends with a cretic foot, — –v v v | — ^—|</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.931"/>
          <p n="62">In passage (1), line 1, Euripides makes it end with an iambic dipodý, -- |.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.939"/>
          <p n="63">For take away, he says, the base and the iamb, which he considers mere excrescences, and then Solum Pierides manet, Quod dicunt Choriambicum.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.948"/>
          <p n="64">Here there are two paeons. Passage (2), line 3, is exactly the same, except that it has only one paeon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.979"/>
          <p n="65">We thus see that in every one of the seven selected passages there is at least one deviation from the regular metre.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.996"/>
          <p n="66">This then is the sum of the metrical contest. The charge which Euripides brings against Aeschylus is that he habitually introduced into his odes the greater part of an Homeric hexameter. The charge which Aeschylus brings against Euripides is that he habitually introduced variations into the solemn and carefully regulated metres of ancient tragedy. In each case the charge is fully proven; but in each case, whether the peculiarity charged was really a defect or a merit, is a ques- tion on which opinions might naturally be expected to differ.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1037"/>
          <p n="67">But though the metrical contest is now concluded, Aeschylus will not part with the general question of tragic odes, without giving a caricature of the Monody, or Lyrical Monologue, which was a special feature of the plays of Euripides. Here we find all the splendour of mythical imagery thrown around, not some great and heroic event, but a simple and homely incident of everyday life. A poor spinning-girl has lost her domestic cock, and wishes to search the cottage of her neighbour Glyce, whom she suspects of stealing it. That is all. But it is sung in strains which might befit a falling dynasty or some tremendous catastrophe of nations. The girl has seen an awful vision of the night, a terrible portent, which " shakes her breast with vague alarms."" She describes it in really blood-curdling terms. What can it mean, this vision from the unseen world ? What soul-thrilling calamity can it portend ? It is like the vision of Clytaemnestra in the Choephoroe, or the vision of Atossa in the Persae. And, like a tragedy queen, the girl bids her maidens draw from the running water, to wash away the evil omens of her dream. Suddenly the true interpretation of the dream flashes upon her. GLYCE HAS STOLEN HER COCK. This, nothing less than this, is the catastrophe which the terrible dream portends. Alas for the overwhelming calamity which has fallen upon her unawares ! But soon her sorrow changes into wrath. She will go forth and search the cottage of Glyce. And she calls upon Artemis the huntress to come with her supernatural hounds to trace the missing cockerel, and upon Hecate of the moon to pour her brightest rays into the darksome recesses of her neighbours house.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1053"/>
          <p n="68">And in good truth, however broad the caricature, the Monody does really touch the one striking and inevitable blot of the Euripidean drama. The poet's aim was to paint men and women as they really were, as he saw them around him in everyday life; whilst the inflexible rules of the Attic stage compelled him to select his characters from amongst the 1 mighty personages of legendary and heroic times. This was no hardship to Aeschylus, whose mind was cast in the Homeric mould, and whose Agamemnon, for instance, was not an Athenian of the Peloponnesian War, but the very king of men, whom Homer sang. But the more completely Euripides succeeded in portraying the smart- ness and loquacity of contemporary life, the less were his characters fit to wear the armour, and speak the language, of demigods and heroes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1069"/>
          <p n="69">So strangely arc the commentators fascinated -with the idea of a "cento," that there are some who even in this Monody would fain descry a "cento" of Euripidean passages. No suggestion can be further from the truth. It is as original as anything in Aristophanes : though in composing a parody of a Euripidean monologue he would of course imitate as closely as he could that poet's language, and style, and repro- duce, if not exaggerate, his peculiar mannerisms, such as his musical shakes (), and his reduplication of words,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1078"/>
          <p n="70">Which of the competitors wrote the weightiest verses? This is the last subject for discussion : and to determine it by weighing their verses in a pair of scales is of course to present in a merely laughable form a topic rather minute in itself, but perhaps not altogether unworthy of more serious consideration.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1089"/>
          <p n="71">With this the literary competition concludes: and all at once, by a transformation scene as sudden and complete as that which brought the literary competition on the stage, we find ourselves retransferred to the earlier aspect of the play. The question now becomes, not which of the two is the better tragedian and shall occupy the Chair of Tragedy in the world below, but which -of them can give the wiser political counsel to the state, and shall reascend with Dionysus to the world above. We have already, in the earlier part of this Introduction, touched upon the counsel which Aristophanes, through the lips of Aeschylus and the favourable verdict of Dionysus, now tenders to the assembled Athenians, viz. that Alcibiades shall be recalled, and the whole wealth of the state expended upon the fleet. And although we know, on the great authority of Dicaearchus, that it was to the advice given in the Parabasis that the play owed its exceptional favour, yet it is impossible to doubt that such advice was regarded not as a mere isolated event, but as the crown and culmination of that noble and exalted1 patriotism which breathed through the entire comedy, and indeed had sustained the poet throughout the whole of his career. This was probably the last counsel which he ever had an opportunity of offering to Imperial Athens.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1136"/>
          <p n="72">The plays which contended with the Frogs for the prize were the " Muses " of Phrynichus, which was placed second, and the " Cleophon " of Plato, which was placed last.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="73">The poets of the Old Comedy mostly dealt with subjects which were, at the moment, attracting the attention of the public : and it is therefore natural that occasionally the same topics should be introduced, and the same persons assailed, in more than one of the comedies exhibited at the same Dionysia. We know that when the Peace was exhibited the tragedian Melanthius was held up to ridicule in each of the three com- peting comedies. The Birds, and the of Phrynichus, were produced at the same festival, and in each of them allusions were made to Execestides, Syracosius, and the military contrivances of Nicias. And it seems that each comedy which competed with the Frogs concurred in some part of its criticism. It is probable that the "Muses" of Pbrynichus was concerned with the poet Euripides; it is certain that the " Cleophon " of Plato was a satire on that pernicious demagogue who is more than once attacked in the comedy before us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1205"/>
          <p n="74">I have already 1 intimated my dissent from Meineke's theory that the " Muses " contained a poetical contest between Euripides and Sophocles, similar to that contained in the Frogs between Euripides and Aeschylus; and my belief that if the play dealt with Euripides at. all, it treated him as a culprit on his trial, for his offences against the art of tragedy. Apart from the shortness of the time which had elapsed since the death of Sophocles, and the intrinsic improbability that the two poets should have framed their plays on such precisely similar lines, it seems to me that the very fragment which Meineke adduces in support of his theory is really decisive against it. Photius, S. V. . Lo, here the vote, and there the verdict-urns, This the condemning, that the absolving one. Is it not clear that this is the case of a prisoner on his trial, and not of two rival poets contending for victory ? The Muses were probably the Chorus of the play, and were accusing Euripides before Dionysus, or some other judge, of having lowered the standard of tragedy. In the “ Muses," as in the Frogs, there is an allusion to the very recent death of Sophocles ;- The speaker would seem to be contrasting the peaceful passing away of Sophocles from old age with the cruel death of Euripides who, we are told, was torn to pieces in Macedonia by a pack of savage dogs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1248"/>
          <p n="75">Cleophon doubtless owes to his outrageous folly, a few months before, the distinction of being immortalized at this festival by both Aris- tophanes and Plato. After the battle of Arginusae, Athens had her last chance of emerging in safety from the Peloponnesian War. The Lace- daemonians offered to evacuate Deceleia and conclude a general peace, on the terms that each side should retain what it then held. The wiser citizens were naturally anxious to embrace the offer, but the 1 populace, inflamed by the frenzy of Cleophon, rejected it altogether. On that occasion, according to. Aristotle, he appeared in the assembly tipsy and wearing a military breastplate. And Aeschines adds that he threatened to chop off the head of any one who dared even to speak of peace. To such a depth of degradation had the " leadership of the Demus," held by Pericles at the commencement of the war, descended before its con- clusion. It is in reference to this disastrous policy that Aristophanes bids Cleophon, if he wants fighting, go back to his 1 native country and fight there. By his native country" he means Thrace, from which barbarian land he was said, on his mothers side, to derive his origin. And Plato 2 also, in his comedy, described him as a Thracian, and intro- duced his mother, speaking a barbarian dialect. It is said by the Scholiast on Euripides that the poet intended the following lines of the Orestes to be a description of Cleophon :— The Orestes was exhibited three years before the Frogs, but we know that this ignoble demagogue had retained for many years 4 the control of all the affairs of the state.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1266"/>
          <p n="76">Several excellent translations of the Frogs in English verse have been published; but hardly any of them give the play in its entirety. The most notable are those by Charles Dunster, A.D. 1785 ; the Right Honourable John Hookham Frere, A.D. 1839; Sir Charles Cavendish Clifford, A.D. 1848; Leonard Hampson Rudd, A.D. 1867; the Rev. Alfred Davies Cope, A.D. 1895 ; and the Rev. Edward Wynn Hunting- ford, A.D. 1900.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1276"/>
          <p n="77">I think that I have made only two alterations of any importance in the text, and they are in the admittedly corrupt lines 1028 and 1301. EASTWOOD, STRAWBERRY HILL, October, 1901.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1296"/>
          <p n="78">The following passages are extracted from " The Growth and In- fluence of Classical Greek Poetry. Lectures delivered in 1892 on -the Percy Turnbull Memorial Foundation in the Johns Hopkins University by It. C. Jebb, Litt.D. M.P. Regius Professor of Greek and Fellow of Trinity College in the University of Cambridge. London: Macmillan and Co. and New York, 1893." I cordially thank their distinguished author for allowing me to insert them here:-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1341"/>
          <p n="79">" In reading the Frogs of Aristophanes, written fifty years after the death of Aeschylus, we see his place in Athenian memory. That comedy is an inestimable document, of which the historical value is not impaired by the free play of humour and of fancy ; it is nearer, both in time and in spirit, to the age of Aeschylus, and is far more instructive, than any other document that we possess. There we catch an echo of the sweet lyrics of Phrynichus—of those ' native wood-notes wild ' which he had warbled as if the birds had taught him—a music dying away in the distance of that century's earliest years-the lyrics of which elderly men had heard their fathers speak with delight. And there, too, rises before us a living image of the majestic poet who had come after Phrynichus, the poet who. first of the Hellenes, had built up a stately diction for Tragedy, and also invested it with external grandeur; the poet who had described the battle of Salamis as he had seen it; whose lofty verse had been inspired by the wish to nourish the minds of his fellow-citizens with ennobling ideals, to make them good men and true, worthy of their fathers and their city; the poet to whom many an Athenian, sick at heart with the decay of patriotism and with the presage of worse to come, looked back, amidst regret for the recent loss of Sophocles and Euripides, as to one who had been not only the creator of the Attic drama, but also in his own person an embodiment of that manly and victorious Athens which was for ever passing away." Pp. 184, 185.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1365"/>
          <p n="80">" The wit of Aristophanes often packs a great deal of sound criticism into a few words. His Euripides says that, when he received Tragedy from Aeschylus, it was* plethoric, swollen, and heavy. He treated it for this malady, giving it decoctions which reduced it to a leaner but more healthy state. Then he proceeded to feed it up again, with such a stimulating diet as monodies. There is a biting truth in this mockery.. Euripides had to apply the principle of compensation. The heroic had to be replaced by the sensational.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1382"/>
          <p n="81">In attempting to estimate the work of Euripides, we must indeed guard against allowing too much weight to the verdict of Attic Comedy; but neither can we ignore it. It is necessary to apprehend the point of view from which this contemporary satire assailed him, and the grounds on which it based its unfavourable judgement. If we then proceed to modify that judgement in the light of a larger survey, we shall do so with less fear of erring through modern misconception.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1390"/>
          <p n="82">Thp hostility of Aristophanes to Euripides was certainly bitter; nor can it surprise us, if he believed Euripides to have done all the mischief with which he charges him. But Aristophanes was not the only comic poet who attacked Euripides. There was a deeper reason for this than any individual or personal sentiment. Attic Comedy had a natural quarrel with the innovator in Tragedy, and the ground of this lay in its own history.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1433"/>
          <p n="83">Sicily is one of two regions in which the origin of Comedy is to be sought; the other is Athens. The Dorians, both in Sicily and in Greece Proper, early showed a bent towards farcical humour; an the case of the Siceliots, there may have been some Italic influences at work, since it has always been an Italic gift to seize those traits of life and character which suit farce and burlesque. At the courts of the Sicilian princes such entertainments were welcome. The Dorian Epicharmus, from the Sicilian Megara, was the first who developed the ruder farce into a species of dramatic poetry. This was done at Syracuse, where the tragic poets Phrynichus and Aeschylus had been the guests of Hieron ; and Attic Tragedy may have suggested the general idea of the form which Epi- charmus adopted, though he does not seem to have used a Chorus. Athens, during the same period-the first half of the fifth century B.C.— developed a comic drama from a different source. At the Dionysia, when the people were assembled to worship the god and to see tragedy, the merry procession called a comus had become a recognized feature of the festival. It was at first a voluntary and unofficial affair. One or more troops of men dressed themselves up in mummers' costume, and marched into the sacred precinct to the music of the flute. They then sang a song in honour of Dionysus ; and one of their number addressed the audience in a humorous speech, turning on civic interests and on the topics of the day. The festal procession then withdrew again. The name Comedy, , originally denoted this Song of the Comus,' and was doubtless coined at Athens, on the analogy of tragoedia. About B. c. 465 the comus was adopted into the official programme of the festival: instead of being the voluntary work of private persons, it was now organized with aid from the State. The steps by which a dramatic performance was built up around the comus-song and speech can no longer be traced. But some five-and-thirty years later, at the beginning of the Peloponnesian War, Attic Comedy, as we know it, was mature. Tragedy naturally furnished the general model on which the new kind of drama was constructed. This is apparent in the limit placed on the number of actors; no extant play of Aristophanes requires more than three regular actors, allowance being made for small parts being taken by supernumeraries who were not required to be absolutely mute. But Comedy was connected with Tragedy by much more than this kinship of form. Comedy expressed the frolic- some side of that Dionysiac worship from which Tragedy took its birth. Religion, the religion of Dionysus, was the breath of life to Comedy, not less-perhaps even more-than to her grave sister. It was religion that authorized the riot of fancy which turns the world topsy-turvy, the jest upon all things Olympian or human, the unsparing personal satire. Let that popular religion once lose its hold, and then, though Tragedy might survive, Comedy, such as Aristophanes wrote, must lose its sacred privileges, and, with them, its reason for existing. By the first law of its being, the Old Comedy was the sworn foe of all things which could undermine the sway of Dionysus, the god who not only inspires the poet, but protects his liberties. And the nearer Tragedy stood to the original form which the Dionysiac cult had given to it, the closer was the kinship which Comedy felt with it. For this reason Aeschylus represents, even better than Sophocles, the form of Tragedy with which the muse of Aristophanes was in spiritual accord ; and Euripides represents everything which that muse abhors. Euripides, who dwarfs the heroic stature, and profanes heroic lips with the rhetoric of the ecclesia or the law-court; Euripides, with his rationalism, his sophistry, his proclivity to new-fangled notions of every kind-here Comedy, with sure instinct, saw a dramatist who was using the Dionysia against the very faith to which that festival was devoted, and whose poetry was the subtle solvent by which Comedy and Tragedy alike were destined to perish.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1460"/>
          <p n="84">It was a happy fortune that, before its short life came to an end, the essence of Attic Comedy was so perfectly expressed by the great satirist who was also a great poet. The genius of Aristophanes indeed transcends the form in which he worked ; but it exhibits all the varied capabilities of that form. He can denounce a corrupt demagogue or an unworthy policy with a stinging scorn and a force of righteous indignation which make the poet almost forgotten in the patriot. He can use mockery with the lightest touch. But it is not in denunciation or in banter that his most exquisite faculty is revealed. It is rather in those lyric passages where he soars above everything that can move laughter or tears, and pours forth a strain of such free, sweet music and such ethereal fancy as it would be hard to match save in Shakespeare. A poet who united such gifts brought keen insight and fine taste to the task of the critic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1482"/>
          <p n="85">In reading the Frogs, we do not forget that it is a comedy, not a critical essay. And we allow for the bias against Euripides. But no careful student of the play can fail to admire how Aristophanes seizes the essential points in the controversy between the two schools of Tragedy. When Aeschylus has said that a poet ought to edify, Euripides rejoins (in effect), ' Are you edifying when you indulge in dark grandiloquence, instead of explaining yourself in the language of ordinary humanity ?' Now observe the rejoinder of Aeschylus. He replies, ' Great sentiments and great thoughts are suitably clothed in stately words. Besides, it is natural that the demigods () should have grandeur of words ; for their clothes are much grander than ours. I exhibited all this properly-and you have utterly spoiled it.' Here Aristophanes has put the true issue in a simple form. Aeschylus is right in vindicating his own style, and condemning his rival's, by an appeal to the nature of his subject-matter. Heroes and demigods ought not to speak like ordinary men. He is right, too, when he enforces his point by referring to the stately costume which he had devised for Tragedy. This was a visible symbol of the limit set to realism.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1500"/>
          <p n="86">When Aristophanes passes from the ground of art to that of ethics, the justice of his criticism may be less evident to moderns, but here also he is substantially right from the Athenian point of view. His Aeschylus complains that Euripides had sapped the springs of civic manliness, of patriotism, and even of morality. It is true that Euripides, . as a dramatic poet, had contributed to tendencies setting in that direction. Homer had been regarded by the Greeks as their greatest teacher, because the heroes were the noblest ideals of human life which they possessed. Aeschylus and Sophocles, in their different ways, had preserved the Homeric spirit. If the heroes once ceased to be ideals of human life, the ordinary Greek of the fifth century had no others. To depose the heroes from their elevation above commonplace humanity was also to destroy an indispensable link between god and man in the popular religion. But that religion was at the root of the Greek citizen's loyalty to the city.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1528"/>
          <p n="87">In the smaller details of his polemic against Euripides, the comic poet is sometimes acute and just, sometimes excessively unfair. We are not here concerned with such details. The broad facts which claim our attention are simply these. Attic Comedy, as such, was the natural foe of a tragic poet like Euripides. Aristophanes clearly understood the artistic limits proper to Attic Tragedy. He clearly saw where and how Euripides had transgressed them ; he also saw that this error of Euripides in art was, for the Athens of his day, inseparable from a bad moral influence. And Aristophanes can sum up his judgement by saying that Euripides, in pursuing new refinements, had abandoned the greatest things (ra ) of the Tragic Art-as Athens had known it." Pp. 225-233.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
