<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Lysistrata</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">William James Hickie</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>William James Hickie (1853). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg007.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">CHORUS OF OLD WOMEN.</p>
          <p n="2">HERALD OF THE LACEDÆMONIANS.</p>
          <p n="3">AMBASSADORS OF THE LACEDÆMONIANS.</p>
          <p n="4">. Four years were the actual interval, from the sailing of the expedition, a. c. 415, , to the Dionysia of the Archon Callias, B. c. 411. Musgrave has neglected these testimonies, and has followed Petitus in the chronology of this Play, which he places in 01. 92, 4, or three years below the true time." Clinton, Fasti Hellenici, p. 73. Droysen, (Introduction to the Lysistrata, p. 127,) " It has not been recorded whether this play was brought on the stage at the Lenaean festival, or at the Dionysia, i. e. in January or March of the year 411. According to the internal evidence of the time, the latter would appear the more probable." The plot is this:—Lysistrata, the wife of an Athenian magistrate, takes it into her head to attempt a pacification between the belli gerents. She summons a council of women, who come to a deter mination to expel their husbands from their beds, until they con clude a peace. In the mean time the elder women are commissioned to seize the Acropolis, and make themselves masters of the money which had been stowed therein for the purposes of war. Their design succeeds ; and the husbands are reduced to a terrible plight by the novel resolution of their wives. Ambassadors at length come from the belligerent parties, and peace is concluded with the greatest despatch, under the direction of the clever Lysis trata.</p>
          <p n="5">Lys. WELL! if one had summoned them to the temple of Bacchus,1 or Pain, or Collar or Genetyllis, it would not even have been possible to pass through by reason of the kettle drums : but now not a single woman is present here ; saving that my neighbour here is coming forth. [Enter Calonice.] Welcome, Calonice!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="6">CALON. And you too, Lysistrata ! Why are you troubled ? Be not of a sad countenance, child! for it does not beseem you to arch3 your eyebrows.</p>
          <p n="7">Lys. I am inflamed in my heart, Calonice, and am greatly vexed on account of us women, because we are considered among men to be bad;</p>
          <p n="8">CALON. For,4 by Jove, we are so!</p>
          <p n="9">LTS. andwhen it was told5 them to meet together here, to deliberate about no small matter, they sleep, and have not come.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <p n="10">CALON. But, my dearest, they will come. Of a truth wo men find it difficult to get out. For one of us goes poking1 about her husband, another wakens the servant, another puts the child to bed, another washes hers, another feeds hers with morsels.</p>
          <p n="11">Lys. But indeed there were other matters more important for them than these.</p>
          <p n="12">CALON. What is the matter, dear Lysistrata, for which you summon us women? What is the affair? Of what size is it ?</p>
          <p n="13">CALON. Is it also thick ?2</p>
          <p n="14">Lys. And thick, by Jove.</p>
          <p n="15">CALON. Why, how then have we not come?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.25"/>
          <p n="16">LYS. This is not the fashion of it; for, if it had been so, we should have quickly assembled. But there is a certain affair which has been investigated by me, and revolved with much sleeplessness.</p>
          <p n="17">CALON. Doubtless the matter revolved is somewhat subtle.</p>
          <p n="18">Lys. Aye, so subtle, that the safety of all Greece depends upon 4 the women.</p>
          <p n="19">CALON. Uppn the women ? Why, it depended5 on a slight thing then.</p>
          <p n="20">Lys. Since6 the affairs of the state depend upon us, either that there should be no longer any7 Peloponnesians——</p>
          <p n="21">CALQN. Then, by Jove, 'tis best they should no longer exist.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.35"/>
          <p n="22">Lys. andthat all the Bœotians perish utterly.'</p>
          <p n="23">CALON. Not all, pray ; exempt the eels.2</p>
          <p n="24">Lys. But about Athens I will utter no such ill language. 3 Do you conjecture something4 else ! If the women assemble here, both those from Bœotia, and those from the Peloponnese, and we from Attica, we shall save Greece in common.</p>
          <p n="25">CALON. What prudent or brilliant action could women accomplish ? we, who sit decked 5 out, wearing saffron-eoloured robes, and beautified, and wearing loose Cimmerian vests, and sandals ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="26">Lys. For6 in truth these are even the very things, which I expect will save us ; the little saffron-coloured robes, and the unguents, and the sandals, and the alkanet root, and the trans parent vests.</p>
          <p n="27">CALON. In what manner, pray ?</p>
          <p n="28">Lys. So that none of the men of the present day lift a spear against each other</p>
          <p n="29">CALON. Then, by the two goddesses, I'll get me a saffron robe dyed.</p>
          <p n="30">Lys. nortake a shield</p>
          <p n="31">CALON. I'll put on a Cimmerian vest.</p>
          <p n="32">Lys. norlittle sword.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.54"/>
          <p n="33">CALON. I'll get sandals.</p>
          <p n="34">LYS. Ought not, then, the women to have been present?</p>
          <p n="35">CALON. No, by Jove, but to have come flying long ago.1</p>
          <p n="36">Lys. Nay, my dear,2 you'll see them thorough Attic-doing every thing later than they ought. Yet not even from the people of the sea-coast3 is any woman present, nor from Salariis.</p>
          <p n="37">CALON. But those, I well know, have crossed over at day- break in the swift boats.</p>
          <p n="38">Lys. Nor have the Acharnian women4 come, whom I ex pected and counted on to come hither the first.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <p n="39">CALON. At any rate the wife of Theogenes5 consulted the statue of Hecate, with the intention of coming hither. But see! here now are some coming ! and, again, some others are coming! Hah ! hah ! Whence are they ?</p>
          <p n="40">CALON. Aye, by Jove! In sooth methinks Anagyrus6 has been set in motion. [ Enter Myrrhina.]</p>
          <p n="41">MYRRH. Surely we have not come too late, Lysistrata? What do you say ? Why are you silent ?</p>
          <p n="42">Lys. I do not commend you, Myrrhina, who have only now come about so important a matter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <p n="43">MYRRH. I had great difficulty in finding my girdle in the dark. But if it be very pressing,1 tell it to us now we are present.</p>
          <p n="44">Lys. No, by Jove ; but let us wait for a little while for the women from Bœotia and from the Peloponnese to come.</p>
          <p n="45">MYRRH. You say far better. But see ! here now's Lampito approaching! [Enter Lampito.]</p>
          <p n="46">Lys. 0 dearest Laconian ! welcome, Lampito ! How your beauty, dearest, shines forth! What2 a fresh colour you have ! how vigorous your body is ! You could even throttle a bull.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="47">LAMP. I fully believe so, by the two goddesses ! I exercise myself and spring against my buttocks.</p>
          <p n="48">LYS. What beautiful breasts3 you have !</p>
          <p n="49">LAMP. Upon my word you handle me like a victim.</p>
          <p n="50">Lys. But from what country is this other young woman ?</p>
          <p n="51">LAMP. By the two goddesses, a Bœotian of rank is coming to you. [Enter Bœotian.]</p>
          <p n="52">LYS. Aye, by Jove, 0 Boeotian, with a beautiful bosom.4</p>
          <p n="53">CALON. And, by Jove, with the hair very neatly plucked out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="54">LYS. Who is the other girl ? [Enter Corinthian.]</p>
          <p n="55">LAMP. A good one, by the two goddesses; but a Corinthian.</p>
          <p n="56">Lys. Aye, by Jove, she is evidently good,5—see here! in these parts !</p>
          <p n="57">LAMP. But who brought together this company of women ?</p>
          <p n="58">LAMP. Then say6 to us what you wish.</p>
          <p n="59">Lys. Yea, by Jove, my dear woman.</p>
          <p n="60">MYRRH. Mention, then, the important business, whatever this is.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.96"/>
          <p n="61">LYS. I will now mention it. But before I mention it, I will ask you this small question.</p>
          <p n="62">MYRRH. Whatever you please.</p>
          <p n="63">Lys. Do you not long for the fathers of your children, who are absent on military service? for I well know that the husband of each one of you is abroad.1</p>
          <p n="64">CALON. In truth my husband has been absent, 0 unhappy man, five months in Thrace, guarding Eucrates.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.104"/>
          <p n="65">Lys. And mine has been absent seven whole months in Pylos.</p>
          <p n="66">LAMP. And mine, even if he ever does depart from the ranks,3 having taken up his shield, flies off and disappears.</p>
          <p n="67">Lys. But- not even a spark of a paramour is left; for since the Milesians4 betrayed us, I have not seen a thing of the kind, which might have consoled us in the absence of our husbands. Would you be willing, therefore, with me to put an end to the war, if I were to find a contrivance ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.113"/>
          <p n="68">MYRRH. Yea, by the two goddesses, I would be willing, if I were obliged even to pawn this upper garment, and drink the proceeds this very day.5</p>
          <p n="69">CALON. Methinks I would even cut myself in half like a turbot and give 6 it away.</p>
          <p n="70">LAMP. And I would even go up to Taygetus, if there1 I were about to get a sight of peace.</p>
          <p n="71">Lys. I will mention it; for the matter must not remain concealed. We, 0 women, if we are to compel the men to be at peace, must abstain</p>
          <p n="72">MYRRH. From what ? tell us !</p>
          <p n="73">Lys. Will you do it then ?</p>
          <p n="74">MYRRH. We will do it, even if we must die.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.124"/>
          <p n="75">Lys. Then we must abstain3 from the marriage-bed. Why do you turn away from me ? Whither are you going ? Ho you ! why do you compress your lips and shake your heads at me ? Why is your colour changed ? Why is the tear let fall ? Will you do it, or will you not do it ? or what do you pur pose 4 to do ?</p>
          <p n="76">MYRRH. I cannot do it; let the war go on !</p>
          <p n="77">CALON. Neither can I, by Jove ! let the war go on.5</p>
          <p n="78">Lys. You say this, you turbot ? And yet,6 just now, you said you would even cut yourself in half.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.133"/>
          <p n="79">CALON. Any thing else, any thing else, whatever you wish. I am willing to walk even through fire, if I must: this7 rather than the loss of conjugal rights; for there's nothing like them, dear Lysistrata.</p>
          <p n="80">Lys. (to Myrrkina). What, then, do you say?</p>
          <p n="81">MYRRH. I also am willing to walk through fire.</p>
          <p n="82">Lys. Oh, our entire race, devoted to lewdness ! No won der tragedies8 are made from us; for we are nothing but "Neptune and a boat."9 But, my dear Laconian, vote with me! for if only you side with me, we may yet restore the affair.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.143"/>
          <p n="83">LAMP. By the two goddesses, women find it hard to sleep alone without a husband. Yet still we must do it, for there is great need of peace.</p>
          <p n="84">Lys. 0 thou dearest, and the only woman out of these !</p>
          <p n="85">CALON. But if we were to abstain as much as possible from what2 you now mention, (which may heaven forefend !) would peace be made aught the more for this ?</p>
          <p n="86">LYS. Aye, much, by the two goddesses ! For if we were to sit3 at home painted, and approach them lightly clad in our vests of fine linen, having the hairs plucked off our bosoms, the men would become enamoured, and desire to lie with us; and if we were not to come nigh them, but abstain, they would quickly make peace, I well know.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.155"/>
          <p n="87">LAMP. Of a truth Menelaus, when he had taken a side glauce at the breasts 5 of Helen when naked, threw away his sword, I believe.</p>
          <p n="88">MYRRH. But what, my friend, if our husbands leave us ?</p>
          <p n="89">Lys. The saying of Phcrecrates,6 " to flay a skinned dog."</p>
          <p n="90">CALON. These similes are idle talk. If they should lay hold of us and drag us to the chamber by force ?</p>
          <p n="91">LYS. Do you hold on by the doors.</p>
          <p n="92">CALON. But what if they beat us ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.163"/>
          <p n="93">Lys. You must be niggardly of conjugal rights ; for there is no pleasure in these acts which are accomplished by force. Besides, you must pain them; and be assured they will very soon give up. For a man1 will never be delighted, unless it suits the woman.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.172"/>
          <p n="94">CALON. If in truth you two are decided about this, we also agreed</p>
          <p n="95">LAMP. And so we will persuade our husbands every where justly to keep peace without deceit. In what way, however, could4 any one, on the other hand, persuade the unstable crowd of the Athenians not to talk nonsense ?</p>
          <p n="96">Lys. We of course will persuade our party.</p>
          <p n="97">LAMP, Not as long as the triremes are in readiness5 and the inexhaustible sum of money is in the temple of the god dess.</p>
          <p n="98">Lys. But this also has been well provided for; for to-day we shall seize upon the Acropolis. For orders have been given to the oldest to do this,1 while we arrange these mat ters, to seize upon the Acropolis while pretending to sacrifice.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.180"/>
          <p n="99">LAMP. It may be altogether well,2 for so you represent it.</p>
          <p n="100">Lys. Why then, Lampito, do we not swear to these things as soon as possible, that they may be inviolable ?</p>
          <p n="101">LAMP. Produce the oath, that we may swear.</p>
          <p n="102">Lys. You say well. Where is the policewoman ? 3 Whither are you staring ? Set the shield before us upside down; and let some one give me the sacrificial parts.</p>
          <p n="103">CALON. Lysistrata, what oath in the world will you make us swear?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.188"/>
          <p n="104">Lys. What? Over a shield, slaying sheep, as they say Æschylus 4 once did.</p>
          <p n="105">CAMON. Nay, do not swear anything about peace, 0 Lysis trata, over a shield.</p>
          <p n="106">Lys. What, then, should the oath be ?</p>
          <p n="107">CALON. If we were to get a white horse 5 from some quarter and sacrifice it as a victim.</p>
          <p n="108">LYS. For what purpose a white horse ?</p>
          <p n="109">CALON. How then6 shall we swear ?</p>
          <p n="110">Lys. I will tell you, by Jove, if you wish. Let us place a large black cup upside down,7 and slaughter a Thasian jar of wine, and swear over the cup-to pour no water in.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.198"/>
          <p n="111">LAMP. 0 earth ! I commend the oath prodigiously.1</p>
          <p n="112">Lys. Let some one bring a cup from within and a jar.</p>
          <p n="113">CALON. 0 dearest women, what a vast jar!2 Any one would be immediately exhilarated if he got this.</p>
          <p n="114">LYS. Set this down and take hold of the boar.3 Mistress Persuasion,4 and Cup sacred to friendship, receive the victims, being friendly to the women.5 [Calonice here pours the wine into the cup.]</p>
          <p n="115">CALON. The blood is of a good colour and bubbles out well.</p>
          <p n="116">LAMP. (stooping and smelling at the wine). Moreover it smells sweet too, by Castor !</p>
          <p n="117">LYS. Permit me, women, to swear the first. [Tries to drink out of the jar. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.206"/>
          <p n="118">CALON. No, by Venus, unless you obtain it by lot.</p>
          <p n="119">LYS. Lampito, do all of you lay hold6 on the cup, and let one say in behalf of the rest of you whatever I say; and you shall swear to these things, and abide by them. “There is no one, either paramour or husband "—</p>
          <p n="120">CALON. “There is no one, either paramour or husband</p>
          <p n="121">LYS. "Who shall approach me in an amorous mood." Say it!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.215"/>
          <p n="122">CALON. "Who shall approach me in an amorous mood," Bless me ! Lysistrata, my knees sink under me.</p>
          <p n="123">Lys. "But I will spend my life at home in1 chastity</p>
          <p n="124">CALON. " But I will spend my life at home in chastity"-</p>
          <p n="125">LYS. " Wearing a saffron-coloured robe, and decked out”—</p>
          <p n="126">CALON. "Wearing a saffron-coloured robe, and decked out”—</p>
          <p n="127">LYS. "So that my husband may be as much as possible enamoured "—</p>
          <p n="128">CALON. “So that my husband may be as much as possible enamoured ”—</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.223"/>
          <p n="129">Lys. "And I will never willingly comply with my hus band ”—</p>
          <p n="130">CALON. “And I will never willingly comply with my husband”—</p>
          <p n="131">Lys. “But if he force me by violence against my will”—</p>
          <p n="132">CALON. " But if he force me by violence against my will”—</p>
          <p n="133">Lys. “I will be niggardly of conjugal rights and will not indulge him”—</p>
          <p n="134">CALON. "I will be niggardly of conjugal rights and will not indulge him”—</p>
          <p n="135">LYS. "I will not raise my slippers towards the roof —</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.231"/>
          <p n="136">CALON. “I will not raise my slippers towards the roof”—</p>
          <p n="137">LYS. “Iwill not stand like a lioness upon a cheese-scraper</p>
          <p n="138">CALON. "I will not stand like a lioness upon a cheese- scraper "—</p>
          <p n="139">LYS. " If2 I abide by these, may I drink from hence ”—</p>
          <p n="140">CALON. "If I abide by these, may I drink from hence”—</p>
          <p n="141">LYS. "But if I violate them, may the cup be3 filled with water ”—</p>
          <p n="142">CALON. " But if I violate them, may the cup be filled with water”—</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.239"/>
          <p n="143">LYS. Do you all swear to these ?</p>
          <p n="144">MYRRH. Yea, by Jove!</p>
          <p n="145">LYS. Come, let me dedicate this. [ Takes a drink.J</p>
          <p n="146">CALON. Your share only, my dear, that from the first we may be friends1 of each other. [ The goblet is passed round. A cry of women is heard behind the scene.</p>
          <p n="147">LAMP. What shout is that ?</p>
          <p n="148">LYS. The very thing2 I spoke of! for the women have already seized upon the Acropolis of the goddess. Come, Lampito, do you go and arrange well your affairs, and leave these here with us as3 hostages; and let us, along with the other women who are in the citadel,4 go in and help to put in the bolts.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.247"/>
          <p n="149">CALON. Do you not think, then, that the men will immedi ately render joint aid against us ?</p>
          <p n="150">LYS. I care little for them. For they will not come with either so great threats or so much fire as to open these gates, except upon the terms which we mentioned.</p>
          <p n="151">CALON. Never, by Venus ! For we women should be called unconquerable and abominable to no purpose. [Enter chorus of old men carrying billets of wood and pans of charcoal.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.254"/>
          <p n="152">CHO. Advance, Draces, lead on slowly, although5 you are pained in your shoulder with carrying so great a weight of a trunk of fresh olive. Of a truth there are many unex pected things in long life, alas! for who would ever have expected, 0 Strymodorus,6 to hear that women whom we supported at home, a manifest pest, would get possession1 of the sacred image, and seize upon my Acropolis, and also make fast the Propylæa2 with bolts and bars ? But let us hasten to the citadel as soon as possible, 0 Philurgus, so that we may place these trunks round about them, as many as began and prose cuted this business, and heap up one pyre, and with our own hands set fire to them all with one vote ; and the wife3 of Lycon the first. For, by Ceres, she shall not laugh at us, while I am alive! Since not even Cleomenes,4 who was the first that seized upon it, departed scot-free ;5 but never theless, though breathing Laconian fury, he went off, having delivered up his arms 6 to me, with a very small little cloak, dirty, squalid, unkempt, unwashed for seven years. So savagely did I besiege that noted7 man, sleeping at the doors seventeen8 deep. And shall I not then being present restrain from so great daring these enemies to Euripides and to all the gods ? No longer then may my trophy9 be in Tetrapolis! But indeed the steep part itself of my road towards the citadel whither1 I am hastening, remains for me to traverse. And we must manage to draw this at length, without a pack ass. How the yoke2 has heavily pressed my shoulder ! But nevertheless we must go, and must blow up the fire, lest at the end of our journey it be extinguished without our per ceiving it. [Blows at the coals. ] Faugh ! faugh ! Oh ! oh, what a smoke ! 0 king Hercules, how dreadfully it bites my eyes, like a mad dog, having assailed me from the pan ! and this fire is by all means Lemnian 3 too. For otherwise it would never thus have bitten my sore eyes with its teeth. Hasten for wards to the citadel, and assist the goddess; or when shall we aid her better than now, Laches ? [Blows at the coals.] Faugh! faugh! Oh! oh, what4 a smoke! By the favour of the gods, this fire is awake and alive. Should we not there fore, if we were first to deposit the yoke here, and stick the torch of vine-wood into the pan and kindle it, then burst in the door like a ram?5 And if the women do not undo the bolts when we call, we must set fire to the doors and oppress them with the smoke. Now let us deposit our load. [Blows at the coals.] Oh, what a smoke! Bless my soul! Who of the generals at Samos6 will help with the yoke? This has now ceased to gall my back. It is your business, 0 pan,7 to kindle your cinders, so that you may first bring me the torch alight. Mistress Victory, assist us, and let us set up1 a trophy over the now present audacity of the women in the citadel. [Enter chorus of women coming out of the citadel.]</p>
          <p n="153">CHO. OF WOM. Women, methinks I perceive flame and smoke as of a fire burning. We must hasten more quickly. Fly, fly, Nicodice, before that Calyce and Critylla, being blown upon from all sides,2 be set on fire by grievous laws and mis chievous old men ! But I am afraid of this. Surely I am not coming3 to the rescue too late? For now, having filled ray bucket at the fountain early in the morning, with difficulty, by reason of the crowd and tumult and clatter of pitchers, jostling with women-servants and runaway slaves, having brought it eagerly, I come with water to the rescue of my fellow tribes-women being on fire. For I heard that old dotards were coming, carrying logs, about three talents in weight, as if about to wait upon persons at the bath,4 threatening most dreadful words, that it behoved them to burn the abominable women to a cinder with fire ; whom, 0 goddess, may I never see set on fire, but to have delivered Greece and the citizens from war and madness ! for which purpose, 0 guardian of the city with golden crest, they occupied thy seat. And I invoke thee as our ally, 0 Tritogenia, if any5 man burn them from below, to bring water along with us ! Let be! What's I this ? 0 men laboriously wicked ! for never would good or pious men have been for doing this.</p>
          <p n="154">CHO. OF MEN. This affair has come unexpected for us to see.2 See! here again's a swarm of women coming out of doors to the rescue ! [They make a retrograde movement. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="155">CHO. OF WOM. Why do you insult3 us ? We don't 4 seem to be many, I suppose ? And yet you don't see as yet the ten-thousandth part of us.</p>
          <p n="156">CHO. OF MEN. 0 Phædrias, shall we suffer these to prate so much ? Ought one not to have broken one's cudgel about them with beating them ?</p>
          <p n="157">CiO. OF WOM. Let us also now deposit our pitchers on the ground; so that, if any one lay his hand upon us, this may not be a hinderance. [ They lay down their pitchers. ]</p>
          <p n="158">CHO. OF MEN. If, by Jove, one had already struck their jaws twice or thrice, like those5 of Bupalus, they would not have a voice.</p>
          <p n="159">CHO. OF WOM. Well now, there! let any one strike me! I'll stand and offer6 myself; and no other bitch shall ever lay hold of your nose.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.281"/>
          <p n="160">CHO. OF MEN. If you will not be silent, I'll beat and drive away your8 old age.</p>
          <p n="161">CiO. OF WOM. Come forward and only touch Stratyllis with your finger!</p>
          <p n="162">CHO. OF MEN. But what, if I thump her with my fists ? what mischief 1 will you do to me ?</p>
          <p n="163">CHO. OF WOM. I'll bite and tear out your lungs and en trails.2</p>
          <p n="164">CHO. OF MEN. There's no poet wiser3 than Euripides; for there's no creature so shameless4 as women.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.289"/>
          <p n="165">CHO. OF WOM. Let us take up the pitcher of water, 0 Rhodippe.</p>
          <p n="166">CHO. OF MEN. Why, 0 thou hateful to the gods, hast thou come hither with water ?</p>
          <p n="167">CHO. OF WOM. Why then have you come with fire, you old man nigh to the grave ?5 With the intention of setting your self on fire ?</p>
          <p n="168">CHO. OF MEN. I have come in order that I may heap up a pyre and set fire to your friends underneath.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.299"/>
          <p n="169">CiO. OF WOM. And I, that I might extinguish6 your pyre with this.</p>
          <p n="170">CHO. OF MEN. Will you extinguish my fire ?</p>
          <p n="171">CHO. OF WOM. The deed itself 7 will soon show.</p>
          <p n="172">CHO. OF MEN. I don't know but I'll scorch you with 8 this torch just as I am.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.307"/>
          <p n="173">CHO. OF WOM. If you happen to have any soap,1 I'll pro vide a bath.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.315"/>
          <p n="174">CHO. OF MEN. You a bath for me, you filthy wretch ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.326"/>
          <p n="175">CEO. OF WOM. And that, too,2 a nuptial one.</p>
          <p n="176">CHO. OF MEN. Did you hear her audacity ?</p>
          <p n="177">CHO. OF WOM. For I am free.</p>
          <p n="178">CHO. OF MEN. I'll stop you from your present clamour.</p>
          <p n="179">CHO. OF WOM. But you shall no longer sit in the Heliæa.3</p>
          <p n="180">CHO. OF MEN. Set fire to her hair!</p>
          <p n="181">CHO. OF Wom. Thy task,4 0 Achelöus! [ The women empty their buckets on the men's heads.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.335"/>
          <p n="182">CHO. OF MEN. Ah me, miserable !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.346"/>
          <p n="183">CHO. OF WOM. Was it hot ? [Another volley of buckets. J</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.354"/>
          <p n="184">CHO. OF MEN. Why, hot ? Will you not stop ? What are you doing?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.362"/>
          <p n="185">CHO. OF WOM. I am watering you, that you may grow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.370"/>
          <p n="186">CHO. OF MEN. But I am parched:; up and shaking already.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.378"/>
          <p n="187">CHO. OF WOM. Therefore, since you have fire, you shall warm yourself. [Enter committee-man.6]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.387"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.395"/>
          <p n="188">COM. Has the wantonness of the women burst forth, and their drumming, and their frequent orgies,7 and this mourning on the roofs for Adonis, which I once9 heard when I was in the Assembly. Demostratus (a plague take1 him!) was advising to sail to Sicily; but his wife, dancing, cries, " Ah ! ah, for Adonis !" And Demostratus was advising2 to enlist Zacynthian hoplites; but his wife upon the roof, being rather tipsy, tells them to mourn for Adonis. But he, Cholozyges, hateful to the gods and abominable, overpowered her. Such are their acts of wantonness. 3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.403"/>
          <p n="189">CHe. OF MEN. What then would you, say, if you were also to hear of the insolence of these ? who have both insulted us in other respects, and drenched us with their pitchers, so that we may wring our garments, as if we had made water in them.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.411"/>
          <p n="190">COM. Justly, by the briny Neptune! For when we our selves join with the women in villany, and teach them to be licentious, such5 counsels spring from them; we, who speak in this wise in the workmen's6 shops, “Goldsmith, as my wife was dancing in the evening, the clasp of the necklace you7 made dropped out of the hole. For my part, I must sail to Salamis; but do you, if you have leisure, come by all means towards evening and fit in the clasp1 for her." And some other one speaks after this manner to the shoemaker, a youth, but able to do a man's work, " Shoemaker, the cross straps pinch the little toe2 of my wife's foot, since it is tender. Come you, therefore, at noon and loosen this, so that it may be wider. Such things concur in such 3 affairs, when I, who am a Committee-man, who have provided spars for oars,4 am shut out5 from the gates by the women, now when there's need of the money. But it's no6 use to stand. Bring the levers, that I may restrain them from their insolence. Why do you gape, you wretch ? Whither, again, are you staring, who do nothing but look after a tavern ? Will you not place your levers under the gates and force your way on that side ? and I will join in forcing this way. [Enter Lysistrata. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.420"/>
          <p n="191">LYS. Do not force 7 with your levers! for I am coming forth of my own accord. What need is there of levers ? For there is not more need of levers, than of sense and judgment.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.428"/>
          <p n="192">COM. What, really, you abominable creature? Where is the policeman ? Seize her, and tie her hands behind her!</p>
          <p n="193">LYS. By Diana, if in truth he shall lay the tip of his hand upon me, he shall weep for it, policeman8 as he is! [Police men draw back.]</p>
          <p n="194">COM. Are you afraid, you Callow ? Will you not seize her by the waist, and you with him, and bind her quickly ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.437"/>
          <p n="195">1ST WOM. By Pandrosus,1 if in truth you shall only lay your hand upon her, you shall be trampled on and ease your self again!</p>
          <p n="196">COM. " Shall ease yourself again," quoth'a! Where is there another policeman? Bind this one the first, because she also chatters!</p>
          <p n="197">' 2ND WOM. By Diana,3 if in truth you shall lay the tip of your hand upon her, you shall soon ask for a 4 cupping-glass!</p>
          <p n="198">COM. What's this? Where is there a policeman ?5 Lay hold on her ! I will stop some of you from this going out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.445"/>
          <p n="199">3RD WOM. By Diana, if in truth you shall approach her, I'll pluck out the hairs that will make you scream !6 [Police men run away.]</p>
          <p n="200">COM. Ah me, unfortunate! The policeman has deserted7 me. But we must never be conquered by8 women. [Police come back.] Let us march against them, 0 policemen, in order of battle!</p>
          <p n="201">LYS. By the two goddesses, then you shall know that with us also there are four companies of warlike women within, fully armed!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.453"/>
          <p n="202">COM. Twist back their hands, policemen ! [Policemen lay hands on the women. ]</p>
          <p n="203">LYS. 0 allied women, run out from within, ye green grocery-market-women, ye garlic-bread-selling-hostesses ! Will ye not drag ?1 Will ye not beat ? Will ye not smite ? Will ye not revile ? Will ye not behave impudently ? [ Women rush in and drive off the policemen.] Stop ! Retire ! Do not despoil them!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.461"/>
          <p n="204">COM. Ah me, how miserably have my policemen2 fared !</p>
          <p n="205">LYS. Nay, what did you expect ? Did you think you had come against some women-slaves, or do you suppose anger is not in women ?</p>
          <p n="206">CoM. Aye, by Apollo, and very much too, if a tavern3 be near!</p>
          <p n="207">CHO. OF MEN. 0 commissioner of this land, who have wasted many words, why do you hold a parley with these wild beasts ? Do you not know with what a bath these just now drenched us in our garments, and that too4 without lye ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.467"/>
          <p n="208">CiO. OF WOM. But, my good sir, you ought not rashly to lay your hand upon your neighbours. But if you do this, you must have swelled eyes. For I am willing to sit modestly, like a virgin, offending no one here, nor even stirring a chip, unless one take my comb, like a wasp's nest, and irritate me.</p>
          <p n="209">CHO. OF MEN. 0 Jupiter! what ever shall we make of these5 monsters? For these things are no longer bearable. But you must inquire into this casualty along with me, with whatever intent they seized upon the citadel, and for what purpose they seized upon the Acropolis on the mighty rock, not to be trodden; the sacred enclosure. But ask repeatedly, and do not be persuaded,6 and apply all tests. For it is dis graceful to leave such7 an affair as this untested, having given it up.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.476"/>
          <p n="210">COM. Well now, by Jove, I wish to learn this first from them; with what intent you shut up our citadel with your bolts.</p>
          <p n="211">LYS. That we might make the money safe, and that you might not fight on account of it.</p>
          <p n="212">COM. Why, are we fighting on account of the money ?</p>
          <p n="213">LYS. Aye, and all the other matters, too, have been thrown into confusion. For in order that Pisander2 might be able to steal, and those who aim at offices, they were always stir ring up some commotion. a Therefore let them do whatever they please, for that matter! for they shall no longer take out this money.</p>
          <p n="214">COM. What will you do then ?4</p>
          <p n="215">LYS. Ask me this ? We will manage it.</p>
          <p n="216">COM. Will you manage the money ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.486"/>
          <p n="217">LYS. Why 5 do you think this strange ? Do we not wholly manage your domestic property also for you ?</p>
          <p n="218">COM. But the case is not the same.</p>
          <p n="219">LYS. HOW not the same ?</p>
          <p n="220">COM. We must carry on the war out7 of this money.</p>
          <p n="221">LYS. But in the first place there is no occasion for war.</p>
          <p n="222">COM. Why, how otherwise shall we be saved ?</p>
          <p n="223">LYS. We will save you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.494"/>
          <p n="224">LYS. Aye, we to be sure.</p>
          <p n="225">COM. A sad case indeed !</p>
          <p n="226">LYS. Be assured1 that you shall be saved, even if you do not wish.</p>
          <p n="227">COM. You mention a shameful case.</p>
          <p n="228">LYS. You are indignant: but this must be done notwith standing.</p>
          <p n="229">COM. By Ceres, 'tis unjust!</p>
          <p n="230">LYS. We must save you, my friends.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.502"/>
          <p n="231">COM. Even if I don't want ?</p>
          <p n="232">LYS. Aye, so much the more, for that matter.</p>
          <p n="233">COM. But how came you to care about war and peace ?</p>
          <p n="234">LYS. We will tell you.</p>
          <p n="235">COM. (with a significant motion of his fist). Tell me now quickly, that you may not get a beating !</p>
          <p n="236">LYS. Hear now, and try to restrain your hands !</p>
          <p n="237">COM. But I am not able: for through my passion3 it is dif ficult to restrain them.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.510"/>
          <p n="238">LYS. Then you shall suffer for it so much the more.</p>
          <p n="239">COM. Croak this4 at yourself, old woman; but tell me your story.</p>
          <p n="240">LYS. I will do so. During the former war and former time, through our modesty, we bore with you5 men, whatever you did; for you did not allow us to mutter: and then you did not please us. But we perceived6 you very well; and oftentimes when we were at home we used7 to hear that you had determined some important matter badly ; and then being pained internally,8 we used to ask you with a smile, "What has been determined by you to-day amongst the people1 to post up upon the pillar2 about peace?" "What's that to you?" the man used to say; "will you not be silent?” And I used to be silent.</p>
          <p n="241">WOMAN. But I would never have been silent.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.518"/>
          <p n="242">COM. Aye, and you'd have howled too, if you were not silent.</p>
          <p n="243">LYS. Sp then I kept silence at home. We used to hear3 perhaps of some other more pernicious decree of yours ; and then we used to ask, " How is it, husband, that you manage these matters so foolishly ? " But he having looked askance at me used immediately to tell me that, "if I will not weave4 my warp, I should wail loudly in my head; but war shall be a care to men."5</p>
          <p n="244">COM. Rightly said of him, by Jove!</p>
          <p n="245">LYS. How6 rightly, you wretch ? if not even when you were determining badly, it was permitted us to advise you. But7 when now we plainly heard you now saying in the streets, “Is there not a man in the country ?" and some other said, “Certainly not, by Jove!" after this it was immediately determined by us women, being assembled, to save Greece in common. For why1 ought we to wait ? If therefore you be willing to hear us in turn giving good advice, and to be silent in turn, as we were then, we would restore you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.527"/>
          <p n="246">COM. You restore us ? You mention a shameful case, and not to be endured by me.</p>
          <p n="247">LYS. Hold your tongue!</p>
          <p n="248">COM. Must I hold my tongue for2 you, you abominable creature, and that too wearing a hood about your head ? Then may I not live !</p>
          <p n="249">LYS. Well, if this be an obstacle to you, there! take this hood from me, and take and put it about your head, and then hold your tongue !-and this little basket! and then gird yourself up3 and card wool, munching beans! 4 " but war shall be a care to women."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.536"/>
          <p n="250">Cno. OF WOM. Retiree 0 women, from your pitchers, in order that we also in turn may assist our friends. For I would never be tired with dancing, nor would exhausting6 weariness seize my knees. I am willing to venture7 every- thing with'these in the cause of virtue, in whom is intellect, is beauty, is boldness, is wisdom, is prudent patriotism. Come, most courageous offspring of graudmothers, and of fruitful nettles, advance with vehemence,8 and do not yield! for you are now still running before the wind.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.549"/>
          <p n="251">LYS. But if delightful Eros and the Cyprus-born Venus breathe desire upon our bosoms and our breasts, and then create in the men a pleasing passion and voluptuousness, I think that we shall some time be called amongst the Greeks Lysimachæ.9</p>
          <p n="252">Coin. By having done what ?</p>
          <p n="253">LYS. If in the first place we put a stop to people lounging1 in the market-place with arms and acting madly.</p>
          <p n="254">WOMAN. Aye, by the Paphian Venus !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.557"/>
          <p n="255">LYS. For now in truth in the pottery-market,2 and in the vegetable-market alike, they walk about throughout the mar ket-place with arms, like Corybantes.</p>
          <p n="256">COM. Yes, by Jove ! for it becomes the brave.</p>
          <p n="257">LYS. And yet the affair is ridiculous, when a fellow with a shield and a Gorgon then purchases mackarel.</p>
          <p n="258">WOMAN. At all events, by Jove, I saw a man with long hair, a commander of cavalry, upon a horse putting pease soup into his brazen helmet, which he had bought from an old woman. And another, again, a Thracian, shaking a shield and javelin like Tereus, frightened the woman that dealt in figs and swallowed the ripe ones.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.565"/>
          <p n="259">COM. How then will you be able to allay many disturbed affairs in the country, and to put an end to them ?</p>
          <p n="260">COM. How ? Show us !</p>
          <p n="261">LYS. Like as, when our thread is tangled, we take it in this way and draw it out with our spindles hither and thither, thus also will we put an end to this war, if you let us, having brought it to an end by means of embassies hither and thither.</p>
          <p n="262">COM. Do6 you think, pray, to allay a dreadful state of affairs with your wool, and threads, and spindles, you silly women?</p>
          <p n="263">LYS. Aye, and if there was any sense in you, you would administer all your affairs after the fashion of our wool.</p>
          <p n="264">COM. How, pray ? Come, let me see !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.573"/>
          <p n="265">LYS. In the first place it behoved you, as if washing away the dirt of a fleece in a bath, to flog the knaves headlong out of the city, and to pick out the briers; and to tear in pieces these who combine together and those who press themselves close together2 for the magistracies, and to pluck their heads ;3 and then all to card public good-feeling into a basket, having mixed up4 both the resident-aliens and whatever stranger or friend there is with you, and whoever is indebted to the pub lic, and to mix these up 5 in one body ; and, by Jove, to mark6 the states, as many as are colonies of this city, that these lie uncared for, like the pieces of wool, each apart by itself; and then, having taken the wool from all these, to bring it to gether, and collect it into one mass ; and then to make a large ball; and then, out of this to weave a cloak for the people.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.582"/>
          <p n="266">COM. Is it not, therefore, shameful that these should cudgel7 these things and wind them off into a ball, who had not even any concern in the war at all ?</p>
          <p n="267">LYS. And yet, 0 you utterly accursed, we bear more than twice as8 much of it as you do ; who in the first instance bore sons and sent them forth as hoplites.9</p>
          <p n="268">COM. Be silent, and do not remind1 us of our woes!</p>
          <p n="269">LYS. And then, when we ought to be cheered and enjoy our youth, we sleep alone on account of the expeditions.2 And our case I omit: but I am grieved for the maidens who grow old in their chambers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.591"/>
          <p n="270">COM. Do not men, therefore, grow old as well ?</p>
          <p n="271">LYS. But, by Jove, you do not mention a like case. For he, when he has come back, even though he be gray-headed, soon marries a young girl; but the woman's time is short, and if she do not take advantage of it, no one is willing to marry her; but she sits looking for omens.3</p>
          <p n="272">COM. But whoever is still able to act a manly part-</p>
          <p n="273">LYS. Why then do you not die? You shall have a little pig :5 you shall purchase a coffin: I will now knead you a honey-cake.6 Take this and crown yourself! [Drenches him with water.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.600"/>
          <p n="274">1ST WOM. And receive these7from me! [Drenches him.]</p>
          <p n="275">2ND WOM. And take this crown ! [Drenches him.]</p>
          <p n="276">LYS. What is wanting ? What do you desire ? Go to the ship ! Charon calls you,8 and you hinder him from setting sail.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.608"/>
          <p n="277">COM. Then is it not shameful that I should suffer these things? But, by Jove, I will show myself to the Committee forthwith, going as9 I am.</p>
          <p n="278">LYS. Will you lay a complaint10 against us, that we did not lay you out ? But on the third day at any rate the sacrifices to the dead will come from us very arly1 in the morning ready prepared. [Exeunt Committee-man and attendants.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.614"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.626"/>
          <p n="279">CHO. OF MEN. It is his business to sleep no longer, who is free. But, sirs, let us strip2 and set to work at this affair ! For already these matters appear to me to savour of more and greater deeds ; and especially I scent the tyranny of Hip pias;3 and I fear greatly lest some men of the Spartans, having assembled here in the house of Clisthenes,4 should by craft stir up the women hateful to the gods to seize upon our money, and our pay, whereby I lived. For surely it is shame ful that these, women as they are, should now advise the citizens, and prate about a brazen shield, and besides5 recon cile us to the Lacedæmonians, to whom there's no trusting,6 unless one can a gaping wolf. But these things, sirs, they have contrived for a tyranny. But over me they shall not tyrannize ; for I will be on my guard, and will henceforth wear my sword in a myrtle-bought and will lounge in the market- place in arms nigh the statue of Aristogiton, and will stand beside him thus ;2 for that very destiny is mine,3 to smite the jaw of this old woman hateful to the gods.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.636"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="280">CHO. OF WOM. Then your mother shall not recognise4 you when you enter the house. But, 0 dear matrons, let us first place these on the ground. For we, 0 all ye citizens, begin words serviceable to the state; naturally, since it reared me splendidly in luxury. As soon as5 I was seven years of age I carried the peplus; and then,6 when I was ten years of age, I was meal-grinder to Diana ;7 and then I was Arctos8 at the Brauronia, wearing the saffron-coloured robe; and at length, when I was a beautiful girl, I carried the basket, wearing a chain of figs. Do I not then owe9 it to the state to give it some good advice ? But if I am a woman, do not grudge me this,10 if I introduce something better than the present part of affairs. For I have a part in the contribu tion ; for I contribute men. But you miserable old men have no part; for after you have expended11 your ancestral fund, as it is called, which you got from the Persians,12 you do not " Da auch mir das Schicksal hiess." Droysen. pay in turn your contributions. But moreover we are in danger of being ruined by you. Then ought you to grumble ? But if you shall annoy me at all, I will strike your jaw with this untanned buskin.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.656"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.672"/>
          <p n="281">CiO. OF MEN. Then are not these matters great insolence ? and methinks the matter will increase still more. But who ever is a perfect man must repel the matter. Come, let us strip off our sleeveless coat, since it behoveth a man forthwith to savour of manhood ; but it does not become him to be muffled up. But come, ye white-footed,1 now it behoveth us, who went to Lipsydrium,2 when as yet3 we were men, now it behoveth us to grow young again, and to make our whole body active,4 and to shake off this old age. For if any of us shall afford these if it were but a small handle,5 they will in no wise fail of assiduous handicraft; but they will both build ships, and furthermore attempt to fight by sea, and to sail against us, like Artemisia.6 But if they turn themselves to horse manship, I strike the Knights off the list. For a woman is a creature most skilful in horsemanship and having a good seat.7 And she would not slip off when it runs. See the Amazons whom Micon painted8 on horseback fighting with the men! But we ought to take and fit this neck9 into the perforated stocks of all these.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.680"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.691"/>
          <p n="282">CHO. OF WOM. By the two goddesses, if you shall provoke me, I will now let loose my passion,1 and will make you to- day call your fellow-tribesmen to your aid, being pommeled. But let us also,2 0 women, speedily strip, so that we may savour of women angered even to biting.3 Now let any one come near me ! in order that he may never eat garlic or black beans.4 Since, if you shall even merely speak ill of me, -for I am exceedingly angry,—I the beetle will deliver you like5 an eagle that is laying eggs. For I will not care for you, if my Lampito live, and the dear Theban girl, well-born6 Ismenia. For you will have no power, not even if you make decrees seven times, who, 0 wretch, wast hateful even7 to all your neighbours. Therefore also yesterday, when I was making a feastS to Hecate, I invited from my neighbours a good and amiable girl as the companion of my children-an eel9 from Bœotia ; but they said they would not send it, on account of your decrees. And you will not cease10 from these decrees, till some one, having taken you by the leg, take and break your neck. 0 thou11 authoress of this deed and design, why hast thou come to me from the house with a sad coun tenance ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.706"/>
          <p n="283">"Rightly Voss, 'diesen langgestreckten Hals:' provided that be rightly understood. Neither Droysen nor Bothe have understood it. Cf. Eccles. 624. Equit. 1045." Enger. See note on Thesm. 74.</p>
          <p n="284">LYS. Wicked women's proceedings and the female mind make me down-hearted, and to walk up1 and down.</p>
          <p n="285">CHO. OF WOM. What do you say ? what do you say ?</p>
          <p n="286">LYS. The truth ! the truth !</p>
          <p n="287">CHO. OF WOM. What is there alarming ? Tell it to your own friends!</p>
          <p n="288">LYS. But it is disgraceful2 to mention, and difficult to keep silent.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.714"/>
          <p n="289">CHO. OF WOM. Do not then conceal from me what ill we have suffered.</p>
          <p n="290">LYS. To speak in fewest words,3 we long for the men.</p>
          <p n="291">CHO. OF WOM. 0 Jupiter !</p>
          <p n="292">LYS. Why call on4 Jupiter? In truth this is so. Con sequently I am no longer able to keep them from their husbands; for they are escaping by stealth. The first I caught widening the hole where the cave of Pane is; the other, again, creeping down by the pulley;6 the other desert ing ; the other one upon a sparrow, purposing now to fly down to the house of Orsilochus,7 I dragged down yester day by the hair. And they keep making all sorts of ex cuses 8 so as to depart home. In sooth, one of them is now coming. Hollo you ! whither are you running ? [A woman attempts to run past.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.726"/>
          <p n="293">IST WOM. I wish to go home ; for my Milesian fleeces are being destroyed by the moths at home.</p>
          <p n="294">LYS. What9 moths ? Will you not go back again ?</p>
          <p n="295">1ST WOM. But, by the two goddesses, I will return speedily, when I have only spread them out on the couch-</p>
          <p n="296">LYS. Don't spread them out, or depart any whither !</p>
          <p n="297">IST WOM. Must I then suffer the fleeces to be destroyed?</p>
          <p n="298">LYS. Yes, if there be need of this.1 [1st woman goes back again.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.734"/>
          <p n="299">2ND WOM. Ah me, miserable! miserable for my flax which I have left at home unhackled !</p>
          <p n="300">LYS. See! here's another coming out for her unhackled flax! 2 Come back again hither!</p>
          <p n="301">2ND WOM. But, by Diana,3 I will return instantly when I have barked it ? 4</p>
          <p n="302">LYS. Don't5 bark it! for if you begin this, another woman will wish to do the same. [2nd woman goes back again.]</p>
          <p n="303">3RD WOM. 0 mistress6 Ilithyia, delay my parturition until I shall have gone to a place not hallowed!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.742"/>
          <p n="304">LYS. Why do you talk this nonsense?</p>
          <p n="305">3RD WOM. I shall bring forth immediately.</p>
          <p n="306">LYS. But you were not pregnant yesterday.</p>
          <p n="307">3RD WOM. But to-day I am. Come, Lysistrata, send me home as soon as possible to the midwife !</p>
          <p n="308">Lys. What tale are you telling ? What is this hard thing7 that you have ?</p>
          <p n="309">3RD WOM. A male child.</p>
          <p n="310">LYS. Not you, by Venus ! except that8 you appear to have some hollow brazen vessel. I will know. [Feels her dress.] 0 you ridiculous ! said you you were pregnant, when you had the sacred9 helmet?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.751"/>
          <p n="311">3RD WOM. And I am pregnant too, by Jove!</p>
          <p n="312">LYS. Why then had you this ?</p>
          <p n="313">3RD WOM. In order that, if my delivery should come upon me while still in the Acropolis, I might go into this helmet and bring forth, as the pigeons do.</p>
          <p n="314">Lys. What do you say ? You are making excuses. The matter is evident. Will you not wait here for the helmet's2 naming-day ?</p>
          <p n="315">3RD WOM. But I am not even able to sleep in the Acro polis, since once I saw the serpent, the guardian3 of the house.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="316">4TH WOM. And I, unhappy, am destroyed with want of sleep through the owls, which are constantly crying, "to- who."4</p>
          <p n="317">LYS. My good women, cease from your juggling tricks! You long for your husbands perhaps: but do you not think that we long for them ? They spend uneasy nights, I well know. But hold out, my good friends, and persevere still further for a short time! for we have an oracle that we shall prevail, unless we be distracted by seditions. Now this is the oracle.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.769"/>
          <p n="318">CHO. OF WOM. Tell us what it says.6</p>
          <p n="319">LYS. Be silent now ! " But when the Swallows,7 avoiding the Hoopoes, cower into one place, and abstain from the phallus, there shall be a rest from evils, and high-thundering Jove shall make8 the higher to be lower "</p>
          <p n="320">CiO. OF WOM. Shall we lie above them ?</p>
          <p n="321">LYS. "but if the Swallows be at variance,1 and By away with their wings from the sacred temple, no longer shall any bird whatever appear to be more lewd."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.777"/>
          <p n="322">CiO. OF WOM. By Jove, the oracle is clear! Let us not then, 0 all ye gods, give up through suffering; but let us go in. For this will be disgraceful, my dearest women, if we shall betray the oracle.2 [Exit Lysistrata.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.781"/>
          <p n="323">CHO. OF MEN. I wish to tell you a story, which I once heard myself when I was yet a boy ; in this wise:3—There was once a youth, Melanion, who, avoiding marriage, went to a desert place and dwelt in the mountains. And then he hunted hares,4 having made nets: and he had a dog. And he returned home again no more by reason of his hatred. So much5 did he abominate the women: and we, who are chaste, abominate them no less than Melanion.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.793"/>
          <p n="324">OLD MAN. I wish, old woman, to kiss you</p>
          <p n="325">WOMAN. Then you shall not eat an onion.7</p>
          <p n="326">OLD MAN. ——— and to lift up your leg and tread on you.</p>
          <p n="327">WOMAN. You wear a large beard.</p>
          <p n="328">OLD MAN. For Myronides8 also was rough in those parts, and black-bottomed to all his foes ; and thus also was Phormio.9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.805"/>
          <p n="329">CHO. OF WOM. I also wish to tell you a story in reply to your Melanion. There was a certain Timon,1 unsettled, en compassed round as to his face with unapproachable thorns,2 a scion of the Furies. This Timon, then, by reason of his hatred, went off having imprecated many curses against wicked men. So much did he always hate in return your3 wicked men ; but he was very dear to the women.</p>
          <p n="330">WOMAN. Would you that I strike your jaw ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.816"/>
          <p n="331">OLD MAN. By no means ! I am afraid of it.</p>
          <p n="332">WOMAN. But I will strike you with my leg.</p>
          <p n="333">OLD MAN. You will show your ancles.</p>
          <p n="334">WOMAN. Yet, however, you would not see them with long hair, though I am an old woman, but depillated with the lamp.4 [Enter Lysistrata attended by several women.]</p>
          <p n="335">LYS. Ho ! ho, women ! come hither to me quickly !</p>
          <p n="336">1ST WOM. What's the matter ? tell me, what means the cry ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.829"/>
          <p n="337">LYS. I see a man, a man approaching frantic, seized5 with the transports of love. 0 mistress,6 who rulest over Cyprus and Cytheræa and Paphos, proceed straight on the course you are going !</p>
          <p n="338">IST WOM. Where is he, whoever he is ?</p>
          <p n="339">LYS. Near the temple of Ceres.7</p>
          <p n="340">IST WOM. Oh, by Jove, in truth there is! Who8 in the world is he ?</p>
          <p n="341">LYS. Look ! Does any one of you know him ?</p>
          <p n="342">MYRRH. Yes, by Jove, I do; and he is my husband Cinesias.9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.837"/>
          <p n="343">LYS. 'Tis your business1 now to roast him, and torture him, and cheat him utterly, and to love him and not love him, and to afford him all things, except those of which2 the cup is conscious.</p>
          <p n="344">MYRRH. Don't trouble yourself: I'll do so.</p>
          <p n="345">LYS. Moreover I will remain3 here and cheat him utterly and roast him thoroughly. But do you depart! [Exit Myr rhina, and enter Cinesias, attended by a servant leading his child by the hand.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <p n="346">CIN. Ah me, miserable ! What a spasm and what a ten sion possesses me,4 as if I were racked upon a wheel!</p>
          <p n="347">LYS. Who is this who stands within the outposts ?5</p>
          <p n="348">LYS. Then will you not begone out of the way ?</p>
          <p n="349">CIN. Who are you who driver me out ?</p>
          <p n="350">ClN. By the gods, then, call me out Myrrhina!</p>
          <p n="351">LYS. Must I call6 your Myrrhina, quoth'a? Who are you?</p>
          <p n="352">CIN. Her husband, Cinesias the Pæonian.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.853"/>
          <p n="353">LYS. Welcome, thou dearest! for thy name8 is not without fame among us, nor yet inglorious. For your wife constantly has you in her mouth ; 1 and if she get an egg or an apple, she says, “ May Cinesias have this !”</p>
          <p n="354">CIN. Oh, by the gods !</p>
          <p n="355">LYS. Yes, by Venus; and if any conversation about hus bands arise, straightway your wife says, that every thing else is nonsense in comparison with Cinesias.</p>
          <p n="356">CIN. Go then, call her !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.861"/>
          <p n="357">LYS. What then ? will you give me any thing ?</p>
          <p n="358">CIN. Aye, by Jove, will I, if you wish it! I have this. What, then, I have, I give you.</p>
          <p n="359">LYS. Come then, let me descend and call her.</p>
          <p n="360">CIN. Very quickly then ! [Exit Lysistrata. ] For I have no pleasure in my life since she went away from the house; but I am grieved when I go in ; and every thing appears to me to be desolate ; and I find no pleasure in my victuals when I eat, for I am tortured.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.870"/>
          <p n="361">MYRRH. (talking with Lysistrata in the Acropolis above). I love him, I love him ; but he is not willing to be loved by me. Do not call me to him !</p>
          <p n="362">CIN. My dearest little Myrrhina, why do you act thus ? Come down 3 hither !</p>
          <p n="363">MYRRH. By Jove, I will not go down thither !</p>
          <p n="364">CIN. Will you not come down when I call you, Myrrhina ?</p>
          <p n="365">MYRRH. No; for you call me when you don't want me at all.</p>
          <p n="366">CIN. I not in want of you ? Nay, rather, undone.</p>
          <p n="367">MYRRH. I will go away.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.878"/>
          <p n="368">CIN. Nay don't, pray! but at least hearken to your little child ! [ Turning to the child. ] Ho you ! will you not call4 your mother ?</p>
          <p n="369">CHILD. Mamma ! mamma ! mamma! 5</p>
          <p n="370">CIN. Ho you ! what are 1 you about ? Do you not even pity the little child, being unwashed and unsuckled six days past ?</p>
          <p n="371">MYRRH. Of course I pity it; but its father2 is negligent.</p>
          <p n="372">CIN. Come down, my good girl, to your little child !</p>
          <p n="373">MYRRH. What 3 a thing it is to be a mother ! I must de scend. For what shall I do ? 4 [ Enter Myrrhina. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.887"/>
          <p n="374">CIN. Why she seems to me to have become much younger, and more loving5 to look at; and in that she is cross to me, and bears herself haughtily,6 these are the very things now which kill me with desire.</p>
          <p n="375">MYRRH. 0 thou dearest little child 7 of a bad father! come, let me kiss you, most dear to your mother !</p>
          <p n="376">CIN. Why, 0 wretch, do you do this, and comply with other women, and cause me to be grieved, and8 art grieved yourself ?</p>
          <p n="377">MYRRH. Don't put your hand on me !</p>
          <p n="378">CIN. While you are ruining 9 my and your property, which is in the house.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.896"/>
          <p n="379">MYRRH. I care little about them.</p>
          <p n="380">CIN. Care you little about your thread, which is tossed10 about by the cocks and hens ?</p>
          <p n="381">MYRRH. Even so, by Jove 11</p>
          <p n="382">CIN. The rites of Venus have been so long a time uncele brated by you. Will you not go back ?</p>
          <p n="383">MYRRH. Not I, by Jove ! unless you make peace and cease from the war.</p>
          <p n="384">CIN. Therefore, if it seem good to you, we will e'en do so.</p>
          <p n="385">MYRRH. Therefore, if it seem good to you, I will e'en go thither ; but now I have sworn not to do it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.904"/>
          <p n="386">CIN. At least lie down with me for 2 a while !</p>
          <p n="387">MYRRH. Certainly not! and yet I cannot say3 that I do not love you.'</p>
          <p n="388">CIN. Do you love me ? Why then do you4 not lie down, my little Myrrhina ?</p>
          <p n="389">MYRRH. 0 you ridiculous man ! in presence of the child ?</p>
          <p n="390">CIN. No, by Jove ! but, Manes, do you take it home! [Servant leads the child off.] There! the child is now out of the way : will you not lie down ?</p>
          <p n="391">MYRRH. Why, where could one do this, you rogue ?</p>
          <p n="392">CIN. Very well,5 where the temple of Pan is.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.912"/>
          <p n="393">MYRRH. Why, how, pray, any longer could I go to the Acropolis pure ?</p>
          <p n="394">CIN. Very well, I ween, after you have washed in the Clepsydra.6</p>
          <p n="395">MYRRH. Shall I then, pray, break my oath, you rogue, after having sworn ?</p>
          <p n="396">CIN. On my head be it!7 Don't be concerned at all for your oath!</p>
          <p n="397">MYRRH. Come then, let me bring a little bed for us.</p>
          <p n="398">CIN. By no means! It suffices us upon the ground.</p>
          <p n="399">MYRRH. By Apollo, I will not' make you lie down upon the ground, although being such ! [Runs</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.920"/>
          <p n="400">CIN. Of a truth it is right well evident that my wife loves me.2</p>
          <p n="401">MYRRH. (returning with a bedstead). There! lie down quickly ; and I will undress myself. [ Cinesias lies down upon the bed.] And yet, bless3 my soul, I must bring out a mat tress.</p>
          <p n="402">CIN. What mattress ? Don't talk to me4 of that!</p>
          <p n="403">MYRRH. Yea, by Diana! for it were shameful to lie upon the bed-cords.</p>
          <p n="404">CIN. Let me give you a kiss then !</p>
          <p n="405">MYRRH. There! [Kisses him and runs off.</p>
          <p n="406">CIN. Ah ! Return then very quickly !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.928"/>
          <p n="407">MYRRH. (returning with a mattress). There's a mattress ! Lie down ! I'll now undress myself. And yet, bless my soul! you have not a pillow.</p>
          <p n="408">CIN. Neither do I want one.</p>
          <p n="409">MYRRH. But, by Jove, I do ! [Runs off:]</p>
          <p n="410">CIN. Truly my carcase is entertained like Hercules.5</p>
          <p n="411">MYRRH. (returning with a pillow). Rise ! jump up !6</p>
          <p n="412">CIN. I have every thing now.7</p>
          <p n="413">CIN. Come then, my little treasure ! 9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.936"/>
          <p n="414">MYRRH. Now I'll undo my girdle !1 Remember then ; do not deceive me about the peace.</p>
          <p n="415">CIN. Then 2 may I perish, by Jove !</p>
          <p n="416">MYRRH. You have not a counterpane.3</p>
          <p n="417">CIN. Neither do I want one, by Jove; but I want some thing else.</p>
          <p n="418">MYRRH. Don't trouble yourself! You shall do so; for I will come speedily. [Runs off.]</p>
          <p n="419">CIN. The woman 4 will kill me with her bed-clothes.</p>
          <p n="420">MYRRH. (returning with a counterpane). Raise yourself up !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.944"/>
          <p n="421">CIN. But I am raised up already.</p>
          <p n="422">MYRRH. Would you that I anoint you ?</p>
          <p n="423">CIN. Nay, do not, by Apollo !</p>
          <p n="424">MYRRH. Yea, by Venus, whether you will or no! [Runs Off.]</p>
          <p n="425">CIN. 0 Lord Jove, would the unguent were 5 poured out!</p>
          <p n="426">MYRRH. (returning with a flask of ointment). Reach forth your hand now, and take it and anoint yourself!</p>
          <p n="427">CIN. By Apollo, this ointment is not sweet! unless to be dilatory and not savouring of marriage be so.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="428">MYRRH. Ah me, miserable ! I have brought the Rhodian 7 unguent.</p>
          <p n="429">CIN. 'Tis excellent! Never mind it,1 ray good girl I</p>
          <p n="430">MYRRH. Nonsense! [Runs off.</p>
          <p n="431">CIN. May he perish most miserably, who first boiled un guents !</p>
          <p n="432">MYRRH. (returning with a fresh flask). Take this casket!</p>
          <p n="433">CIN. But I have another. Come, you tiresome2 thing, lie down and don't bring me any thing at all!</p>
          <p n="434">MYRRH. I will do so, by Diana ! In sooth I am taking off my shoes. But, my dearest, see that you vote to make peace.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.961"/>
          <p n="435">CIN. I will determine about it. [Exit Myrrhina.] My wife has undone me and killed me, both in all other respects, and because she has flayed me and gone. Ah me ! what shall I do ?3 Whom shall I solicit, being disappointed of the prettiest of all? How shall I educate this? Where's the Dog-fox?4 Let out5 a nurse to me.</p>
          <p n="436">CHO. OF MEN. 0 thou unhappy, thou art afflicted in thy soul with dreadful suffering, having been deceived ! And I pity you, alas ! alas ! For what kidneys could hold out, what soul,6 and what bowels, and what loins ? What rump could, being strained, and not having to do with any one in the morning ? 7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.970"/>
          <p n="437">CIN. 0 Jove, what dreadful convulsions! 8</p>
          <p n="438">CHO. OF MEN. This, however, has your all-abominable and all-execrable wife now done to you.</p>
          <p n="439">CIN. No, by Jove, but dear and sweetest of all!</p>
          <p n="440">CHO. OF MEN. Don't talk to me9 of sweet! Abominable, abominable certainly. [Exit Cinesias.] 0 Jove, Jove, would that you would whirl her away and turn her round,1 and carry her off with a great whirlwind and hurricane, as you do the heaps of corn, and then let her go, and she might be borne back again to the earth, and then suddenly bestride the trident! [ Enter LacedæmoniaM Herald and Committee-man.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.980"/>
          <p n="441">HER. Where is the Senate of the Athenians, or the2 Pry tanes ? I wish to make an announcement.</p>
          <p n="442">COM. Whether are you a man or Conisalus ?3</p>
          <p n="443">HER. By the two gods, I have come from Sparta as a he rald, young4 man, about the peace !</p>
          <p n="444">COM. And then, pray, have you come with a spear under your arm ?</p>
          <p n="445">HER. No, by Jove, not I!</p>
          <p n="446">COM. Whither are you turning yourself? Why, pray, do you put forward your cloak ? or have you a swelling in the groin from your journey ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.989"/>
          <p n="447">HER. The fellow's a fool,5 by Castor!</p>
          <p n="448">COM. But you are excited, 0 you most abominable!</p>
          <p n="449">HER. No, by Jove, not I! Don't talk nonsense 6 again!</p>
          <p n="450">COM. But what's this here ?</p>
          <p n="451">HER. A Spartan scytale.7</p>
          <p n="452">COM. Aye, if this too is a Spartan scytale.8 But tell me the truth, as to one9 that knows! How are your affairs at Sparta?</p>
          <p n="453">HER. All Sparta is excited, and all the allies are excited. There is need of Pellene.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="454">COM. From whom did this misfortune fall upon you ? From Pan ?2</p>
          <p n="455">HER. No; Lampito, I think, began it; then the other women throughout Sparta at once, as if starting. from one starting-post, drove away their husbands from their beds.</p>
          <p n="456">COM. How are you then ?</p>
          <p n="457">HER. We are distressed;3 for we go bending through the city, as if carrying4 lamps. For the women will not even suffer us to touch them, till we all with one accord make peace with Greece.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1007"/>
          <p n="458">COM. This thing has been sworn to by the women from all parts: I have just now5 ascertained it. But bid them as soon as possible send here ambassadors with full powers to treat about peace ! and I will bid the senate choose other ambas sadors from hence, having exhibited this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1014"/>
          <p n="459">HER. I will fly; for you speak altogether most excellently. [ Exeunt Herald and Committee-man.]</p>
          <p n="460">CHO. OF MEN. There is no wild beast more unconquerable than a woman, nor fire, nor any panther so shameless.</p>
          <p n="461">CHO. OF WOM. Why, are you aware of this, and then make war upon me, when it is in your power, you wretch, to have me a firm friend ?</p>
          <p n="462">CHO. OF MEN. " For I will never cease to hate woman."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1022"/>
          <p n="463">CHO. OF WOM. Well, when7 you please: but now I will not suffer you to be thus naked. For see how ridiculous you are! Come, let me come to you and put on8 your sleeveless coat!</p>
          <p n="464">CHe. OF MEN. This,9 by Jove, which you have done is not amiss! But, indeed, through evil anger I formerly strip ped it off.1</p>
          <p n="465">CHO. OF WOM. In the first place, you appear2 a man; in the next place, you are not ridiculous: and if you had not vexed me, I would have seized and taken out this little insect in your eye, which now is in it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1030"/>
          <p n="466">CHO. OF MEN. This, it seems, is the thing which was dis tressing me. See ! there's 3 my ring ! Pull it out! and then show it me, when you've taken it out! for, by Jove, it has been stinging my eye this long while.</p>
          <p n="467">CHO. OF WOM. Well, I'll do so ; although you are a cross man. 0 Jove ! in truth a monstrous gnat to look at is in your eye. Don't you see it ? Is not this gnat a Tricorysian one ?4</p>
          <p n="468">CHO. OF MEN. By Jove, you have eased5 me; for it has been digging wells in me this long while ; so that, after it has been taken out, my tears flow copiously.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1043"/>
          <p n="469">CHO. OF WOM. But I will wipe you clean, although you are very bad, and will kiss you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1054"/>
          <p n="470">CHO. OF MEN. Do not kiss6 me !</p>
          <p n="471">CHO. OF WOM. Whether7 you will or no.</p>
          <p n="472">CHO. OF MEN. A plague8 take you ! since you are wheed ling by nature ; and that saying is rightly said, and not badly, “ Neither with 9 utterly-abandoned women, nor without utterly abandoned women." But now I make peace with you, and henceforth I will neither do any thing bad any more,1 nor suffer it from you. Come, let us be united and begin 2 our song together!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1063"/>
          <p n="473">CHO. OF WOM. We are not prepared,3 sirs, to speak any ill at all4 of any of the citizens; but, quite the contrary, both to say and do every thing good ; for our present5 sufferings even are sufficient. But let every man and woman make it known,6 if any wishes to receive money, two or three minæ : we have plenty within, and have purses. And if ever peace appear, whoever shall have now borrowed from us, shall never repay what he shall have received. We are going to en tertain some Carystian8 strangers, honourable and good men ; and I have still some broth; and I had a sucking-pig; and this I have slaughtered, so that you shall eat tender and fine meat. Come therefore to my house to-day ! But you ought to do this early,9 having bathed, both you and your children; and then to go in, and ask no one any questions, but boldly to proceed straight forward, as if into your own houses, for the door shall beshut.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1072"/>
          <p n="474">CHO. OF MEN. Well now, see! here are the ambassadors from Sparta coming, trailing beards ! as if with a bandage10 about their thighs. [Enter Spartan Ambassadors.] Spar tans, in the first place, welcome ! next, tell us in what state you are come!</p>
          <p n="475">SPART. What need to say many words to you ? for you may see in what state we have come.</p>
          <p n="476">CHO. OF MEN. Bless me! This calamity is dreadfully excited! It seems to he worse inflamed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1080"/>
          <p n="477">SPART. Unspeakably ! What can one say ?1 But let some one come hy all means and make peace with us, as he pleases.</p>
          <p n="478">CiO. OF MEN. Well now, I see these here aborigines put ting back their dress from their bellies, like wrestleis, so that the disease2 appears to be one belonging to an athlete. [En ter Athenians. ]</p>
          <p n="479">ATHEN. Who can tell us where Lysistrata is ? for see ! we men here 3 have come, of such rank !</p>
          <p n="480">CHO. OF MEN. Both this disease and the other agree in this way.4 Does a tension seize you towards morning ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1088"/>
          <p n="481">ATHEN. No, hy Jove, but we are killed when we undergo5 this: so that, if some one will not quickly make peace be tween us, we shall certainly commit a rape upon Clisthenes.6</p>
          <p n="482">Cno. OF MEN. If you are wise, you will take your clothes, so that none of the mutilaters of the Hermæ 7 shall see you.</p>
          <p n="483">ATHEN. By Jove, you certainly say well!</p>
          <p n="484">SPART. Yea, hy the two gods, hy all means ! Come, let us put on our dress ! 8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1096"/>
          <p n="485">ATHEN. Welcome, Spartans ! We have suffered shameful things.</p>
          <p n="486">SPART. 0 my dearest! of a truth we should have suffered dreadful things, if the men could have seen9 us excited.</p>
          <p n="487">ATHEN. Come now, Spartans, you must mention each severally. For what are you come hither ?</p>
          <p n="488">SPART. As ambassadors about peace.</p>
          <p n="489">ATHEN. In truth you say well: we also are come on ac count of this. Why then do we not summon Lysistrata, who alone can make peace between us !</p>
          <p n="490">SPART. Aye, by the two gods, and Lysistratus,1 if you like.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1105"/>
          <p n="491">CHO. OF MEN. But there's no occasion, as it seems, for us to call her; for see! here she2 is herself coming out, when she heard it! [Enter Lysistrata.] Hail! 0 thou bravest of all women ; now it behoveth thee to be clever,3 good, easy, grave, mild, and shrewd ; for the chiefs of the Grecians, caught by thy charm, have yielded to thee, and referred all their grievances to thee in common.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1114"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1122"/>
          <p n="492">LYS. Well, the business is not difficult, if one were to find people eager for peace,4 and not making trial of each other. But I'll soon know. Where is Peace?5 First take and lead, forward the Spartans, and not with a hand violent or self wired, nor as our husbands6 used unskilfully to do it, but very affectionately,7 as is proper women should. If any do not give his hand, lead him by the nose. [Enter Peace represented by a beautiful girl. ] Come! do you also lead these Athenians, and lead them forward, having caught hold of them by whatever part they present. You Spartans, stand close beside me, and you on this side, and hear my words! I am a woman, it is true; but sense is in me :8 “ and of myself I am not ill off in respect of 1 intellect." By having often heard the remarks of my father and my elders, I have been not ill educated. I wish to take and justly chide you2 in common, who, although you besprinkle your altars with the same lustral-water,3 as kindred people, at Olympia, Pylæ, and Delphihow many others could I mention, if there were occasion for me to be prolix? are destroying Grecian men and Grecian cities with your armies, when barbarians4 are before you as enemies. One part of my speech 5 is thus far finished.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1133"/>
          <p n="493">ATHEN. I am killed with desire.</p>
          <p n="494">LTS. In the next place, ye Spartans,for I will turn to you,———do you not know, when formerly Peri clides6 the Spartan came hither as a suppliant of the Athenians, and sat upon the altars, pale, in a red cloak, begging an army ? At that time Messena7 was pressing upon you, and at the same time the god was shaking the earth. But Cimon went with four thousand hoplites and saved the whole of Sparta. After you have been benefited in this way by the Athenians, do you devastate a land, from which you have received benefits?</p>
          <p n="495">ATHEN. By Jove, Lysistrata, these are in the wrong!</p>
          <p n="496">SPART. We are in the wrong: but sin is unspeakably beautiful. 2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1143"/>
          <p n="497">LYS. Do you suppose I shall let you 3 Athenians off? Know you not when the Spartans in turn came in arms and slew many Thessalians,4 and many confederates and allies of Hip pias, alone on that day5 marching out with you to battle, and freed you, who were wearing servile6 dresses, and in place of the servile dress, clothed your people again with a mantle?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1157"/>
          <p n="498">SPART. I have never seen a better7 woman !</p>
          <p n="499">A THEN. And I, never yet a fairer bosom !</p>
          <p n="500">LYS. Why, then, when many benefactions8 exist on both sides, do you fight, and not cease from your wickedness ? Why do you not make peace ? Come, what's the hinderance ?</p>
          <p n="501">SPART. We are willing, if one be willing to restore to as this spencer.</p>
          <p n="502">A THEN. Of what kind, good sir ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1165"/>
          <p n="503">SPART. Pylos,9 which we have been wishing for and de siring this long while.</p>
          <p n="504">ATHEN. By Neptune, this you shall10 not do !</p>
          <p n="505">LYS. Give it up to them, good sir!</p>
          <p n="506">ATHEN. And whom then shall we solicit ?</p>
          <p n="507">LYS. Do you demand another place instead of this! ATHEN. Then do you deliver up to us the what dye call ’em—in the first place this Echinus, and the Melian Gulf behind it, and the legs1 of Megara!</p>
          <p n="508">SPART. No, by the two gods, not all, my good sir !2</p>
          <p n="509">LYS. Give them up ! do not dispute about legs !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1173"/>
          <p n="510">ATHEN. I am willing now to strip and cultivate the land naked.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1181"/>
          <p n="511">SPART. And I, by the two gods, to dung them4 in the morning.</p>
          <p n="512">LYS. When5 you shall have made peace, you shall do so. But if you think fit to do this, deliberate, and go and consult your allies!</p>
          <p n="513">ATHEN. What6 allies, my friend? We are excited. Will not our allies be of the same opinion-all to enjoy themselves ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1189"/>
          <p n="514">SPART. Ours 7 will, at any rate, by the two gods !</p>
          <p n="515">ATHEN. Aye, by Jove ! for the Carystians also will.8 LYS. You say well. Now therefore see that you be pure, so that we women may entertain you in the Acropolis with what we have in our chests. And there give oaths and as surances to each other; and then each of you shall take his own wife and depart.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1200"/>
          <p n="516">ATHEN. Well, let us go as soon as possible.</p>
          <p n="517">SPART. Lead whither you please.</p>
          <p n="518">ATHEN. Yes, by Jove, as quickly as possible ! [Exeunt Lysistrata, Athenians, and Spartans.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1208"/>
          <p n="519">CHO. OF WOM. I do not grudge to offer my variegated bed- clothes, and little cloaks, and state-robes,1 and golden orna ments, as many as I have, to all to carry to their children, and whenever any one's daughter is Canephorus. I tell you all now to take of my property out of the house; and that nothing is so well sealed up, that2 you may not break the sealing-wax, and bear away whatever is in the house. But he shall see nothing when he looks, unless some of yon see sharper than I do. But if any of you has no food, and maintains domestics and many small children, he may receive from me husked wheat; but the chœnix-loaf is very fresh to look at. Whatever poor person therefore wishes, let him come to my house with sacks and wallets; for he shall receive wheat; and Manes my servant shall put it into them. I fore warn you, however, not to come to my door, but to beware of the dog.3 [Enter Market-loungers, and knock clamorously at the door of the Citadel.]</p>
          <p n="520">MARK. Open the door!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1216"/>
          <p n="521">SERVANT (coming out with a torch in his hand). Will you get away ? Why do you sit ? Shall I burn you with the torch?4 The post is a troublesome one.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1225"/>
          <p n="522">MARK. I'll not do so !</p>
          <p n="523">SERV. If we must by all means do so, we will endure, to gratify you.</p>
          <p n="524">CHO. OF MEN. And we too will endure with you.</p>
          <p n="525">SERVo Will you not begone? You shall howl aloud in your hairs.6 Will you not begone, so that the Spartans may depart from the house in quietness, after their entertainment ? [Enter an Athenian returning from the entertainment.]</p>
          <p n="526">ATHEN. I have never seen such an entertainment! Upon my word, the Spartans were even entertaining ; but we were the cleverest boon-companions over the wine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1233"/>
          <p n="527">CHO. OF MEN. Aye, rightly said; because we Athenians are not in our right senses when we are sober. If I prevail upon the Athenians by my words,2 we shall always go on embassies3 to all places drunk. For at present, whenever we go to Sparta sober, we immediately look to see what we can disturb: 4 so that, what they say, we hear not; but what they don't say, this we wrongly suspect.5 And we do not make the same report about the same things.6 But now every thing pleases; so that, if any one were to sing the scolion of Telamon,7 when he ought to sing that of Clitagora, we would praise8 him, and swear a false oath beside that it was quite the thing. [Market-loungers again crowd about the door.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1241"/>
          <p n="528">SERVo But see! here are these people coming together again ! Will you not begone, you scoundrels ?</p>
          <p n="529">MARK. Yes, by Jove ! for now they are coming out of the housed [Enter Spartans returning from the entertainment. ]</p>
          <p n="530">SPART. Take your wind-instruments, my dearest, so that I may dance the Dipodia, and sing2 a pleasing strain upon the Athenians and upon us at the same time.</p>
          <p n="531">ATHEN. Take, then, your pipes,3 by the gods! for I am pleased to see you dancing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1256"/>
          <p n="532">CHORUS OF SPARTANS. Rouse, 0 Mnemosyne, the youths,4 and my Muse, who is cognizant of us and of the Athenians, when they at Artemisium dashed against the ships,5 like to the gods, and conquered the Persians. But us, on the con trary, did Leonidas lead, like boars, I ween, sharpening their tusks; and abundant foam6 sprang up about our jaws, and abundant foam at the same time flowed down our legs:7 for the men, the Persians, were8 not less numerous than the sands. Huntress Diana, slayer of wild beasts, virgin goddess, come hither to our truce, so that you may keep us united for a long time ! Now again may fruitful friendship ever subsist through our covenants, and may we cease from the flattering foxes!9 0 come hither, hither, 0 virgin huntress!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1266"/>
          <p n="533">LYS. Come now, since the other matters have been trans acted well, do you, Spartans, lead away these,' and you, Athenians, the others! and let husband stand beside wife, and wife beside husband: and then, after having danced in honour2 of the gods for our prosperous fortune, let us be cau tious henceforth never to sin again !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1279"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1287"/>
          <p n="534">CHORUS OF ATHENIANS. Lead forward the chorus! offer thanks! and invoke Artemis ! and invoke her twin brother, leader of the chorus, the gracious Apollo ! and invoke Nysius ! Bacchus,3 who sparkles with his eyes amongst the Mænads ! and Jove blazing with fire! and invoke his venerable, blessed spouse ! and then the deities, whom we shall use as no forget ful witnesses respecting the noble Peace, which the goddess Venus made ! Alalai! io paean !4 Raise yourselves5 aloft ! io ! io ! io ! for the victory !6 Evoe, evoe ! evæ, evæ ! 7 Spartan,8 do you now produce a new song after our new song.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1295"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1311"/>
          <p n="535">CHORUS OF SPARTANS. Come again, Spartan Muse, hav ing left the lovely Taygetus, celebrating Apollo, the god of Amyclæ, revered by us ; and Minerva dwelling in a brazen house;10 and the brave Tyndaridæ, who sport beside the Eurotas. Come, advance rapidly! Oh, come, bounding lightly! so that we may celebrate Sparta, to whom the choruses of the gods are a care and the sound of feet ; and the damsels, like fillies, bound up frequently with their feet beside the Eurotas, making haste; and their locks are agi tated, like those of the Bacchanals brandishing the thyrsus 3 Enger has adopted the conjecture proposed by Bergk, (Rhen. Mus. 1841, p. 95,) . and sporting.1 And the chaste daughter of Leda, the comely. leader of the chorus, leads them. But come, bind your hair with a fillet, and dance with hand and foot, like a stag ! and at the same time make a noise cheering the chorus; and again celebrate the most mighty, the all-conquering goddess dwell ing in a brazen house ! [Exeunt omnes.]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
