<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Wasps (Vespae)</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">Benjamin Bickley Rogers</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Benjamin Bickley Rogers (1919). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg004.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">SOSIAS. You ill starred Xanthias, what's the matter now?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="2">XANTHIAS. The nightly watch I'm studying to relieve.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.20"/>
          <p n="3">Sos. Why then, your ribs will have a score against you. Do you forget what sort of beast we're guarding ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.20"/>
          <p n="4">XANTH. No, but I'd fain just drowse dull care away.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.28"/>
          <p n="5">XANTH. Sure you're a maniac or a Corybant.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.28"/>
          <p n="6">Sos. (Producing a wineflask.) Nay 'tis a sleep from great Sabazius holds me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.28"/>
          <p n="7">XANTH. (Producing another.) Aha ! and I'm your fellow-votary there. My lids too felt just now the fierce assault Of a strong Median nod-compelling sleep. And then I dreamed a dream; such a strange dream !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.37"/>
          <p n="8">Sos. And so did I: the strangest e'er I heard of. But tell yours first. XANTH. Methought a monstrous eagle Came flying towards the market-place, and there Seized in its claws a wriggling brassy shield, And bore it up in triumph to the sky, And then—Cleonymus fled off and dropped it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="9">Sos. Why then, Cleonymus is quite a riddle.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="10">Trapa (x. 74), and the like. Compare the case of Samson in the Book of Judges : . (Judges xiv. 10—12. LXX).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="11">XANTH. How SO ? Sos. A man will ask his boon companions, What is that brute which throws away its shield Alike in air, in ocean, in the field ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.54"/>
          <p n="12">XANTH. 0 what mishap awaits me, that have seen So strange a vision ! Sos. Take it not to heart, 'Twill be no harm, I swear it by the Gods.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.62"/>
          <p n="13">XANTH. No harm to see a man throw off his shield ! But now tell yours. Sos. Ah, mine's a big one, mine is ; About the whole great vessel of the state.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.71"/>
          <p n="14">XANTH. Tell us at once the keel of the affair.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.71"/>
          <p n="15">Sos. 'Twas in my earliest sleep methought I saw A flock of sheep assembled in the Pnyx, Sitting close-packed, with little clokes and staves;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.71"/>
          <p n="16">XANTH. Pheugh! Sos. Eh? XANTH. Stop, stop, don't tell us any more. Your dream smells horribly of putrid hides.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="17">Sos. Then the vile grampus, scales in hand, weighed out Bits of fat beef, cut up. XANTH. Woe worth the day ! He means to cut our city up in bits.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <p n="18">Sos. Methought beside him, on the grouud, I saw Theorus seated, with a raven's head. Then Alcibiades lisped out to me, Gwemark ! Theocwus has a cwaven's head.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="19">XANTH. Well lisped ! and rightly, Alcibiades !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="20">Sos. But is not this ill-omened, that a man Turn to a crow? XANTH. Nay, excellent. Sos. How? XANTH. How ! Being a man he straight becomes a crow: Is it not obvious to conjecture that He's going to leave us, going to the crows ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <p n="21">Sos. Shall I not pay two obols then, and hire One who so cleverly interprets dreams ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.97"/>
          <p n="22">XANTH. Come, let me tell the story to the audience</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="23">Sos. Ah,he conjectures from his own disease.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="24">XANTH. Nay, but the word does really end with -lover. Then Sosias here observes to Dercylus, That 'tis a DRINK-lover. Sos. Confound it, no :</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.106"/>
          <p n="25">Sos. What, like Philoxenus ? No, by the do, Not quite so lewd, Nicostratus, as that.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.125"/>
          <p n="26">XANTH. Come, you waste words : you'll never find it out, So all keep silence if you want to know. I'll tell you the disease old master has. He is a LAWCOURT-lover, no man like him. Judging is what he dotes on, and he weeps Unless he sit on the front bench of all. At night he gets no sleep, no, not one grain, Or if he doze the tiniest speck, his soul Flutters in dreams around the water-clock. So used he is to holding votes, he wakes With thumb and first two fingers closed, as one That offers incense on a new moon's day. If on a gate is written Lovely Demus,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.133"/>
          <p n="27">BDELYCLEON. Xanthias and Sosias ! are ye fast asleep ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.133"/>
          <p n="28">XANTH. 0 dear ! Sos. What now ? XANTH. Bdelycleon is up.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.142"/>
          <p n="29">BDEL. One of you two run hither instantly, For now my father's got into the kitchen,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.142"/>
          <p n="30">BDEL. 0 heavens ! what's that ? what makes the chimney rumble ? Hallo, sir! who are you ? PHILOCLEON. I'm smoke escaping.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.142"/>
          <p n="31">BDEL. Smoke ? of what wood ? PHIL. I'm of the fig-tree panel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.150"/>
          <p n="32">BDEL. Ay, and there's no more stinging smoke than that. Come, trundle back : what, won't you ? where's the board ? In with you ! nay, I'll clap this log on too. There now, invent some other stratagem. But I'm the wretchedest man that ever was; They'll call me now the son of Chimney-smoked.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.150"/>
          <p n="33">Sos. He's at the door now, pushing. BDEL. Press it back then With all your force : I'm coming there directly. And 0 be careful of the bolt and bar, And mind he does not nibble off the door-pin.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.150"/>
          <p n="34">PHIL. (Within.) Let me out, villains ! let me out to judge.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.150"/>
          <p n="35">BDEL. What if he should ? PHIL. Why once, when I consulted The Delphian oracle, the God replied, That I should wither if a man escaped me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.158"/>
          <p n="36">BDEL. Apollo shield us, what a prophecy !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.158"/>
          <p n="37">PHIL. 0 let me out, or I shall burst, I shall.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.158"/>
          <p n="38">BDEL. No, by Poseidon ! no, Philocleon, never !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.158"/>
          <p n="39">PHIL. 0 then by Zeus I'll nibble through the net.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <p n="40">BDEL. You've got no teeth, my beauty. PHIL. Fire and fury ! How shall I slay thee, how ? Give me a sword, Quick, quick, or else a damage-cessing tablet.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <p n="41">BDEL. Hang it, he meditates some dreadful deed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <p n="42">PHIL. 0 no, I don't: I only want to take And sell the donkey and his panniers too. 'Tis the new moon to-day. BDEL. And if it is, Cannot I sell them ? PHIL. Not so well as 1.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <p n="43">BDEL. No, but much better: drive the donkey out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.174"/>
          <p n="44">XANTH. How well and craftily he dropped the bait To make you let him through. BDEL. But lie caught nothing That haul at least, for I perceived the trick. But I will in, and fetch the donkey out. No, no; he shan't come slipping through again.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.174"/>
          <p n="45">BDEL. Who ? where ? XANTH. Why here. BDEL. Why what in the world is this ? Who are you, sirrah ? PHIL. Noman I, by Zeus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="46">BDEL. Where from ? PHIL. From Ithaca, son of Runaway.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="47">BDEL. Noman I promise to no good you'll be. Drag him out there from under. 0 the villain, The place he had crept to ! Now he seems to me The very image of a sompnour's foal.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="48">PHIL. Come now, hands off : or you and I shall fight.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <p n="49">BDEL. Fight! what about ? PHIL. About a donkey's shadow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <p n="50">BDEL. You're a born bad one, with your tricks and fetches.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <p n="51">PHIL. Bad ! 0 my gracious ! then you don't know yet How good I am : but wait until you taste The seasoned paunch let of a prime old judge.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <p n="52">BDEL. Get along in, yon and your donkey too.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <p n="53">PHIL. 0 help me fellow-dicasts : help me, Cleon !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.198"/>
          <p n="54">BDEL. Bellow within there when the door is shut. Now pile a heap of stones against the door, And shoot the door-pin home into the bar, And heave the beam athwart it, and roll up, Quick, the great mortar-block. Sos. (Starting.) Save us ! what's that ? Whence fell that clod of dirt upon my head ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.198"/>
          <p n="55">XAXTH. Belike some mouse dislodged it from above.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.198"/>
          <p n="56">Sos. A mouse ? 0, no, a rafter-haunting dicast, Wriggling about behind the tiling there.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.207"/>
          <p n="57">BDEL. Good lack ! the man is changing to a sparrow. Sure he'll fly off: where, where's the casting-net ? Shoo ! shoo there ! shoo! 'Fore Zeus, 'twere casier work To guard Scione than a sire like this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.207"/>
          <p n="58">Sos. Well but at last we have fairly scared him in, He can't slip out, he can't elude us now, So why not slumber just a-just a —drop ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.207"/>
          <p n="59">BDEL. Slumber, you rogue ! when in a little while His fellow-justices will come this way Calling him up. Sos. Why sir, 'tis twilight yet.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.217"/>
          <p n="60">BDEL. Why then, by Zeus, they are very late to-day. Soon after midnight is their usual time To come here, carrying lights, and warbling tunes Sidono-Phrynich-beautiful-antique</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.225"/>
          <p n="61">BDEL. Pelt them, you rogue ! you might as well provoke A nest of wasps as anger these old men. Each wears beside his loins a deadly sting, Wherewith they smite, and on with yells and cries They leap, and strike at you, like sparks of fire.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.225"/>
          <p n="62">Sos. Tut, never trouble, give me but some stones,. I'll chase the biggest wasps-nest of them all.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.230"/>
          <p n="63">CHORUS. Step out, step out, my comrades stout: no loitering, Comias, pound along, You're shirking now, you used, I vow, to pull as tough as leathern thong, Yet now, with ease, Charinades can walk a brisker pace than you. Ho! Strymodore of Conthylè, the best of all our dicast crew, Has old Euergides appeared, and Chabes too from Phlya, pray ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.240"/>
          <p n="64">BOY. 0 father, father, here's some mud ! look sharp or in you'll go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.240"/>
          <p n="65">CHOR. Pick up a stick, and trim the wick, a better light to show.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.240"/>
          <p n="66">BOY. Nay, father, with my finger, thus, I choose to trim the lamp.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.248"/>
          <p n="67">CHOR. How dare you rout the wick about, you little wasteful scamp, And that with oil so scarce ? but no, it don't disturb your quiet, However dear the oil may be, when I have got to buy it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.248"/>
          <p n="68">BOY. If with your knuckles once again you 'monish us, I swear We'll douse the light, and take to flight, and leave you floundering there. Then wading on without the lamp in darkness, I'll be bound You'll stir and splash the mud about, like snipes in marshy ground.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.248"/>
          <p n="69">Dr. Barham, in his edition of Hephæstion, p. 227, translates the latter couplet in the same metre: Apollo surely's in tho choir: hark, the lyre resounding. And there too I the Loves discern; there too Aphrodite.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.256"/>
          <p n="70">CHOR. All, greater men than you, my boy, 'tis often mine to beat. But, bless me, this is filth indeed I feel beneath my feet: Ay, and within four days from this, or sooner, it is plain, God will send down upon our town a fresh supply of rain : So dense and thick around the wick these thieves collect and gather, And that's, as everybody knows, a sign of heavy weather. Well, well, 'tis useful for the fruits, and all the backward trees, To have a timely fall of rain, and eke a good North breeze.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.264"/>
          <p n="71">Ach. 782; Fritzsche at Thesm. 806. The Chorus are not, as Richter imagines, inferring from the mud that rain has fallen within the last four days; they would have known that without the evidence supplied by the mud. They are inferring from the cloggy wicks that rain will fall within the next four days. The use of in line 262 is conclusive in favour of this construction, which is in fact required by the whole tenor of the passage.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.264"/>
          <p n="72">CHOR. Certainly I will, my son. Tell me what you'd have me buy. Dibs, my son ? Hey, my son ? Dibs it is, undoubtedly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.264"/>
          <p n="73">Boy. Dibs, my father ! No, my father! FIGS ! for they are sweeter far.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.273"/>
          <p n="74">CHOR. You be banged first: yet you shall not Have them, monkey, when you are.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.281"/>
          <p n="75">Boy. Then, my father, woe betide you ! Not another step I'll guide yon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.281"/>
          <p n="76">CHOR. Is it not enough that I With this paltry pay must buy Fuel, bread, and sauce for three ? Must I needs buy figs for thee!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.289"/>
          <p n="77">BOY. Father, if the Archon say That the Court won't sit to-day, Tell me truly, father mine, Have we wherewithal to dine ? O my father, should not we Then in " Straits of Helle " be ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.297"/>
          <p n="78">CHOR. Out upon it! out upon it! Then, indeed, T should not know For a little bit of supper Whither in this world to go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.309"/>
          <p n="79">Boy. Why, my mother, didst thou breed me, giving nothing else to feed me, But a store of legal woe ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.309"/>
          <p n="80">CHOR. Empty scrip ! 0 empty show,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.309"/>
          <p n="81">BOY. 0! 0! woe! woe! Ours to sorrow and lament.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.323"/>
          <p n="82">PHIL. (Appearing above.) Long my reins have been stirred, Long through chinks have I heard, Heard your voices below. Vain my efforts to sing, These forbid me to go. Vainly my sad heart yearns, Yearns to be marching with you, On to the judgment urns, There some mischief to do. 0 change to smoke by a lightning stroke, Dread-thundering Zeus ! this body of mine, Till I'm like Proxenides, like the son Of Sellus, that false tree-vine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.334"/>
          <p n="83">CHOR. Who is he that thus detains you ? Who with bolted door restrains you ? Tell us, you will speak to friends.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.334"/>
          <p n="84">PHIL. 'Tis my son, but don't be bawling: for he's slumbering now at ease There, upon the roof before you : drop your tone a little, please.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.342"/>
          <p n="85">CHOR. What's his object, idle trifler, that he does such things as these? What's the motive he pretends ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.342"/>
          <p n="86">PHIL. He will let me do no mischief, and no more a lawsuit try. True it is he'll feast and pet me, but with that I won't comply. CHOR. This the Demagogcleon blared Out against you, since you dared Truth about the fleet to show. He must be involved, I see, In some dark CONSPIRACY, Else he durst not use you so. It is time some means of escape to find, some novel, ingenious plan, that so, Unseen of your son, you may get you down, alighting in safety here below.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.342"/>
          <p n="87">PH. 0 what shall it be ? consider it ye ! I'm ready to do whatever is planned : So sorely I'm longing a circuit to go, through the lists of the Court, with a vote in my:</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.350"/>
          <p n="88">CH. Can you find no cranny or secret run, through which, from within, your path to urge, And then like wily Odysseus, here, disguised in tatters and rags, emerge ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.350"/>
          <p n="89">PH. Each cranny is baITed: there's never a run, thro'which though itwerebuta midge could squ</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.350"/>
          <p n="90">CHOR. 0 don't you remember the old campaign, when you stole the spit, and let yourself down, And away by the side of the wall you hied ? 'Twas when we had captured Naxos town.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.350"/>
          <p n="91">PHIL. Ah, well I remember ! but what of that ? it is quite another affair to-day. For then I was young, and then I could steal, and over myself I possessed full sway, And then none guarded my steps, but I Was free, wherever I chose, to fly; Whilst now, in every alley and street, Armed men with arms are stationed about, Watching with care that I steal not out. And there at the gate you may see those two Waiting with spits to spit me through, Like a cat that is running away with the meat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.365"/>
          <p n="92">CHOR. Well but now be quickly shaping Some contrivance for escaping; Morning breaks, my honey-bee.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.365"/>
          <p n="93">PHIL. Then the best that I can think of, is to gnaw these meshes through. May Dictynna, queen of hunters, pardon me the deed I do.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.365"/>
          <p n="94">PHIL. There, I've gnawn them through completely—Ah ! but do not raise a shout, We must use the greatest caution, lest Bdelycleon find us out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.373"/>
          <p n="95">CHOR. Fear not: fear not: if he speak, He shall gnaw his heart, and seek For his life to run amain. We will quickly make him learn Nevermore again to spurn Th’ holy statutes of the Twain. So now to the window lash the cord, and twine it securely your limbs around. With all Diopeithes fill your soul, then let yourself cleverly down to the ground.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.381"/>
          <p n="96">PHIL. But suppose they catch me suspended here, and hoist me up by the line agaiu, And angle me into the house once more, say what ye will do to deliver me then.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.381"/>
          <p n="97">CHOR. Our hearts of oak we'll summon to aid, and all give battle at once for you. 'Twere vain to attempt to detain you more: such wonderful feats we are going to do.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="98">PHIL. This then will I do, confiding in you : and if anything happens to me, I implore</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.389"/>
          <p n="99">Kuights (729), was an or harvest-wreath. Bdelycleon orders the servant to clamber up on one side of the door, and as the old man descends by the other, to seize the , and beat him back with it. It would seem, how ever, that on hearing the threat, Philo clean anticipates its execution by drop ping at once to the ground, though only to find himself in the clutches of his persecutors, whose attention does not appear to have been drawn as yet to the menacing attitude of the Chorus. The was an olive-bough, wreathed and matted with wool, in which were stuck divers symbols of the harvest and vintage, figs, breadcakes, honey, oil, and wine. The boughs so bedecked were carried about in the festivals of the Thargelia and Pyanepsia by boys who sang After the festival the boughs were hung up before the doors, and probably re mained there until the next anniversary. See Plutarch, Theseus, cap. 22 ; Suidas s. v. ; and the Scholiast on Knights, 729, and Plutus, 1054.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.397"/>
          <p n="100">PHIL. Help ! help ! all those whoever propose this year to busy themselves with suits. Smicythion, help ! Tisiades, help ! Pheredeipnus, Chremon, the fray begin : 0 now or never, assist your friend, before I'm carried away within.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.403"/>
          <p n="101">CHOR. Wherefore slumbers, wherefore slumbers, that resentment in onr breast, Such as when a rash assailant dares provoke our hornets-nest ? Now protruding, now protruding, Comes the fierce and dreadful sting, Which we wield for punishing. Children, hold these garments for us : then away with all your speed, Shout and run and bawl to Cleon, tell him of this direful deed ; Bid him quickly hither By As against a city-hater, And a traitor doomed to die, One who actually proposes That we should no lawsnits try.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.403"/>
          <p n="102">BDEL. Listen, worthy sirs, to reason : goodness ! don't keep screaming so.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.403"/>
          <p n="103">CHOR. Scream ! we'll scream as high as heaven. BDEL. I don't intend to let him go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="104">CHOR. These be frightful things to see ! This is open TYRANNY ! Rouse the State ! Rouse the great God-abhorred Sneak Theorus ! And whoever Else is there, Fawning lord Ruling o'er us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="105">XAN. Heracles ! they've stings beside them! Master, master, don't you see ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="106">BDEL. Ay, which slew the son of Gorgias, Philip, with their sharp decree.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="107">CHOR. You we'll also slay directly ! Wheel about him, every one, Draw your stings, and, all together, in upon the fellow run. Close your ranks, collect your forces, brimming full of rage and hate,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.426"/>
          <p n="108">XANTH. Now with such as these to combat is, by Zeus, a serious thing: Verily I quake and tremble, but to look upon their sting.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.426"/>
          <p n="109">CHOR. Let him go ! Loose your hold ! If you don't I declare You shall bless Tortoise-backs For the shells Which they wear.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.426"/>
          <p n="110">PHIL. On then, on, my fellow-dicasts, brother wasps of heart severe, Some By in with angry buzzings, and attack them in the rear, Some surround them in a ring, and both their eyes and fingers sting.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.426"/>
          <p n="111">BDEL. Ho there ! Midas! Phryx ! Masyntias ! hither ! hither! haste to mo ! Take my father, guard him safely: suffer none to set him free ; Else you both shall lunch off nothing, clapped in fetters strong and stout. There's a sound of many fig-leaves (well I know it) buzzed about.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.435"/>
          <p n="112">CHOR. This shall stand infixed within you if you will not let him go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.435"/>
          <p n="113">PHIL. Mighty Cecrops ! King and hero ! Dragon-born and -shaped below, Wilt thou let these rude barbarians vex and maul me at their pleasure, Me who heretofore have made them weep in full imperial measure ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.435"/>
          <p n="114">CHOR. Truly, of abundant evils, age is evermore the source :</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.448"/>
          <p n="115">PHIL. Won't you even now unhand me, shameless villain, worst of rogues ? When the grapes I caught you stealing, 0 remember, if you can, How I tied you to the olive, and I flogged you like a man, So that all beheld with envy: but a grateful soul you lack ! 0, unhand me, you, and you, at once, before my son come back.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.448"/>
          <p n="116">CHOR. But a famous retribution ye for this shall undergo, One that will not lag nor linger; so that ye betimes shall know, Know the mood of angry-tempered, righteous, mustard-glancing men.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.456"/>
          <p n="117">BDEL. Beat them, Xanthias, from the door-way; beat the wasps away again.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.456"/>
          <p n="118">XANTH. That I will, sir. BDEL. Fume them, Sosias, drive the smoke in dense and thick. Shoo there, shoo! be off, confound you. At them, Xanthias, with the stick! Smoke them, Sosias, smoke, infusing Æschincs, Selartius' son.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.456"/>
          <p n="119">Sos. So then we at last were going, as it seems, to make you run.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.456"/>
          <p n="120">BDEL. But you never would have managed thus to beat them off with ease, Had it chanced that they had eaten of the songs of Philocles.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.471"/>
          <p n="121">CHOR. Creeping o'er us, creeping o'er us, Here at least the poor can see Stealthy-creeping TYRANNY ! If you from the laws debar us, which the city has ordained, You, a curly-haired Amynias, you, a rascal double-grained, Not by words of wit persuading, Not for weighty reasons shown, But because, forsooth, you WILL it, Like an autocrat, alone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.471"/>
          <p n="122">BDEL. Can't we now, without this outcry, and this fierce denunciation, Come to peaceful terms together, terms of reconciliation ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.471"/>
          <p n="123">CHOR. Terms with THEE, thou people-hater, and with Brasidas, thou traitor, Hand and glove! You who dare Woolly-fringed Clothes to wear, Yes, and show Beard and hair Left to grow Everywhere.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <p n="124">BDEL. 0, by Zeus, I'd really liefer drop my father altogether Than endure these daily conflicts, buffeting with waves and weather.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <p n="125">CHOR. Why, as yet you've hardly entered on the parsley and the rue:</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <p n="126">BDEL. 0 by all the gods I ask you, will ye never go away? Are ye quite resolved to linger, thwacked and thwacking all the day ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <p n="127">CHOR. Never more Will I while There's a grain Left of me Leave your door Traitor vile Bent to gain TYRANNY.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.491"/>
          <p n="128">BDEL. Ay " Conspiracy " and " Tyrant," these with you are all in all, Whatsoever is brought before you, be the matter great or small. Everywhere the name of Tyrant, now for fifty years unknown, Is than cheap salt-fish at Athens commoner and cheaper grown. Everywhere about the market it is bandied to and fro: If you wish a basse to purchase, and without a pilchard go,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.500"/>
          <p n="129">XANTH. Even so a naughty damsel yesternoon observed to me, Just because I said her manners were a little bit too free, She supposed that I was wishing Hippias's Tyranny.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.500"/>
          <p n="130">BDEL. Ay, by charges such as these our litigious friends they please. Now because I'd have my father (quitting all this toil and strife, This up-early-false-informing-troublesome-litigious life) Live a life of ease and splendour, live like Morychus, you see Straight I'm charged with Tyrant leanings, charged with foul conspiracy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.508"/>
          <p n="131">Scholiast. is the bait which in the , 1673, Peisthctærus appro priately holds out to the greedy and gullible Heracles. Cf. Id. 733. Lucian (De Mercede Conductis, 13) says to one who after long toil has achieved the position of companion to some great . I do not know whether our corresponding phrase, pigeon's milk, was in use before Hunter (on the Animal Economy, p. 194) discovered that pigeons do in truth nourish their young by means of a milky or curdy secretion, or whether it was introduced by the sceptics of the day in ridicule of that discovery.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.508"/>
          <p n="132">BDEL. Yes, for that's the sort of dainty you, by Zeus, have loved so long. Yet I think I'll soon convince you that your mode of life is wrong, If you can but once be silent, and to what I say give heed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.508"/>
          <p n="133">PHIL. I am wrong to be a dicast! BDEL. Laughed to utter scorn indeed, Mocked by men you all but worship, for you can't their treachery see, You're a slave, and yet don't know it. PHIL. Name not slavery to me ! I am lord of all, I tell you. BDEL. You're the veriest drudge, I vow, Thinking that you're lord of all. For come, my father, teach us now, If you reap the fruits of Hellas, what's the benefit to you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.516"/>
          <p n="134">PHIL. Willingly. Let these be umpires. BDEL. I'll accept their judgment too. Now then all at once release him. PHIL. And besides a sword supply,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.516"/>
          <p n="135">PHIL. May I never drink thereafter, pure and neat, good fortune's—pay. CHOR. Now must the champion, going Out of our school, be showing Keen wit and genius new,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.526"/>
          <p n="136">BDEL. Bring forth my memorandum-book : bring forth my desk to write in. I'll quickly show you what you're like, if that's your style of fighting. CHOR. In quite another fashion To aught this youth can do. Stern is the strife and anxious</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.537"/>
          <p n="137">BDEL. Now I'll observe his arguments, and take a note of each.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.548"/>
          <p n="138">PHIL. What would you say, if he to-day should make the conquering speech ? CHOR. Ah ! should that mischance befall us, Our old troop were nothing worth : In the streets with ribald mirth Idle boys would dotards call us, Fit for nought but olive-bearing, Shrivelled husks of counter swearing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.556"/>
          <p n="139">BD. (Writing.) I'll take a note of the point you make, that suppliant fellows your grace implore.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.564"/>
          <p n="140">PH. So when they have begged and implored me enough, and my angry temper is wiped away, I enter in and I take my seat, and then I do none of the things I say.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.572"/>
          <p n="141">BD. (Writing.) A second point for my note-book that, a derision of wealth with its show and its pride. Go on to mention the good you get by your empire of Hellas so vast and wide.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.572"/>
          <p n="142">PH. 'Tis ours to inspect the Athenian youths, when we enter their names on the rolls of men. And if ever Œagrus gets into a suit, be sure that he'll never get out again Till he give us a speech from his Niobe part, selecting the best and the liveliest one. And then if a piper gain his cause, he pays us our price for the kindness done, By piping a tune with his mouth-band on, quick march as out of the Court we go.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.581"/>
          <p n="143">TO . Bergler refers to Birds, 861, where a crow comes on as a piper , with a mouth-band on; and Florent Chretien to Cicero (Epist. ad Att. ii. 16), who says, " Cnæus quidem noster jam plane quid cogitet nescio, Sophoclis Inc. fab. fragmenta, 100, Wagner. The was the accom paniment which the pipers played as the Chorus were finally leaving the stage at the end of the Play : it was the exit-, as the Parodos was the entrance- piece. , says the Scholiast, .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.581"/>
          <p n="144">BD. Ay that, and that only, of all you have said, I own is a privilege lucky and rare, But uncapping the seal of the heiress's will seems rather a shabby and doubtful affair.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.589"/>
          <p n="145">PH. And if ever the Council or People have got a knotty and difficult case to decide,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.598"/>
          <p n="146">BD. Ay, chatter your fill, you will cease before long : and then I will show that your boasted success Is just the success of a tail that is washed, going back to its filth and its slovenliness.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.622"/>
          <p n="147">PH. But the nicest and pleasantest part of it all is this, which I'd wholly forgotten to say, 'Tis when with my fee in my wallet I come, returning home at the close of the day, 0 then what a welcome I get for its sake; my daughter, the darling, is foremost of all, And she washes my feet and anoints them with care, and above them she stoops, and a kiss lets fall, Till at last by the pretty Papas of her tongue she angles withal my three-obol away. Then my dear little wife, she sets on the board nice manchets of bread in a tempting array, And cosily taking a seat by my side, with loving entreaty constrains me to feed; I beseech you taste this, I implore you try that. This, this I delight in, and ne'er may I need To look to yourself and your pantler, a scrub who, whenever I ask him my breakfast to set, Keeps grumbling and murmuring under his breath. No ! no ! if he haste not a manchet to get Lo here my defence from the evils of life, my armour of proof, my impregnable shield.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.631"/>
          <p n="148">CHOR. I never, no, I never Have heard so clear and clever And eloquent a speech-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.642"/>
          <p n="149">PHIL. Ay, ay, he thought he'd steal my grapes, and pluck them undefended,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.642"/>
          <p n="150">Scholiast. means in my interest. The usage is a common one, and it will be sufficient to refer with Bergler to Œd. Tyr. 1434, where Œdipus making a request to Creon says, . 0 2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.650"/>
          <p n="151">BD. Hard were the task, and shrewd the intent, for a Comedy-poet all too great To attempt to heal an inveterate, old disease engrained in the heart of the state. Yet, 0 dread Cronides, Father and Lord, PHIL. Stop, stop, don't talk in that father-me way, Convince me at once that I'm only a slave, or else I protest you shall die this day, Albeit I then must ever abstain from the holy flesh of the victims slain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.650"/>
          <p n="152">Be. Then listen my own little pet Papa, and smooth your brow from its frowns again. And not with pebbles precisely ranged, but roughly thus on your fingers count The tribute paid by the subject States, and just consider its whole amount ;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="153">Scholiast. All the great prizes, he means, are carried off by the demagogues: whilst you are well satisfied if you can get only the odds and ends, the scraps and leavings of the spoil.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="154">PH. Then not one tithe of our income goes to furnish forth the Justices' pay.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.658"/>
          <p n="155">BD. No, certainly not. PH. A.nd what becomes of all the rest of the revenue, pray ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.666"/>
          <p n="156">BD. Why, bless you, it goes to the pockets of those, To the rabble of Athens I'll ever be true, I'll always battle away for the mob. 0 father, my father, 'tis owing to you : By such small phrases as these cajoled, you lift them over yourselves to reign. And then, believe me, they soon contrive some fifty talents in bribes to gain, Extorting them out of the subject states, by hostile menace and angry frown : Hand over, they say, the tribute-pay, or else my thunders shall crush your town. You joy the while at the remnants vile, the trotters and tips of your power to gnaw. So when our knowing, acute allies the rest, the scum of the Populace, saw On a vote-box pine, and on nothingness dine, and marked how lanky and lean ye grow, They count you all as a Connas's vote, and ever and ever on these bestow Wines, cheeses, necklaces, sesamè fruit, and jars of pickle and pots of honey,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.678"/>
          <p n="157">PH. That's true no doubt, for I just sent out, and bought, myself, from Eucharides three; But you wear me away by your long delay in proving my bondage and slavery.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.686"/>
          <p n="158">BD. Why is it not slavery pure and neat, when these (themselves and their parasites too) Are all in receipt of their pay, God wots, as high officials of state : whilst you Must thankful be for your obols three, those obols which ye yourselves have won In the battle's roar, by sea and by shore, 'mid sieges and miseries many a one. But 0 what throttles me most of all, is this, that under constraint you go, When some young dissolute spark comes in, some sou of a Chæreas, straddling-so With his legs apart, and his body poised, and a mincing, soft, effeminate air, And bids you Justices, one and all, betimes in the morn to the Court repair, For that any who after the signal come shall lose and forfeit their obols three.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.695"/>
          <p n="159">PH. IS THAT what they do ! 0 can it be true ! Ah me, the depths of my being are stirred, Your statements shake my soul, and I feel, I know not how, at the things I've heard.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.695"/>
          <p n="160">BD. And just consider when you and all, might revel in affluence, free as air, How these same demagogues wheel you round, and cabin and coop you, I know not where. And you, the lord of such countless towns, from Pontus to Sardo, nought obtain Save this poor pittance you earn, and this they dole you in driblets, grain by grain, As though they were dropping oil from wool, as much forsooth as will life sustain. They MEAN you all to be poor and gaunt, and I'll tell you, father, the reason why.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.695"/>
          <p n="161">PHIL. 0 what can this strange sensation mean, this numbness that over my hand is stealing ? My arm no longer can hold the sword: I yield, unmanned, to a womanish feeling.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.703"/>
          <p n="162">BDEL. Let a panic possess them, they're ready to give Eubœa at once for the State to divide, And engage to supply for every man full fifty bushels of wheat beside. But five poor bushels of barley each is all that you ever obtained in fact, And that doled out by the quart, while first they worry you under the Alien Act. And therefore it was that I locked you away To keep you in ease; unwilling that these With empty mouthings your age should bilk. And now I offer you here to-day Without any reserve whatever you please, Save only a draught of—Treasurer's milk.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.712"/>
          <p n="163">CH. 'Twas a very acute and intelligent man, whoever it was, that happened to say, Don't mate up your mind till you've heard both siles, for now I protest you have gained the fray. Our staves of justice, our angry mood, for ever and ever aside we lay, And we turn to talk to our old compeer, our choir-companion of many a day. Don't be a fool: give in, give in, Nor too perverse and stubborn be; I would to Heaven my kith and kin Would show the like regard for me. Some deity, 'tis plain, befriends Your happy lot, believe, believe it; With open arms his aid he sends, Do you with open arms receive it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.722"/>
          <p n="164">BDEL. I'll give him whatever his years require, A basin of gruel, and soft attire, And a good warm rug, and a handmaid fair, To chafe and cherish his limbs with care. -But I can't like this, that he stands so mute, And speaks not a word nor regards my suit.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="165">CHOR. 'Tis that his soberer thoughts review The frenzy he indulged so long, And (what he would not yield to you) He feels his former life was wrong. Perchance he'll now amend his plan, Unbend his age to mirth and laughter, A better and a wiser man By your advice he'll live hereafter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="166">PHIL. 0 misery ! 0 misery !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.737"/>
          <p n="167">BDEL. 0 father, why that dolorous cry ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.747"/>
          <p n="168">PHIL. Talk not of things like these to me ! Those are my pleasures, there would I be Where the Usher cries Who has not voted ? let him arise. And 0 that the last of the voting band By the verdict-box I could take my stand.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.756"/>
          <p n="169">BDEL. 0 father, father, by the Gods comply.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.756"/>
          <p n="170">PHIL. Comply with what ? name any wish, save one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.760"/>
          <p n="171">BDEL. Save what, I prithee ? PHIL. Not to judge, but that Hades shall settle ere my soul comply.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.768"/>
          <p n="172">BDEL. Well but if these are really your delights, Yet why go There ? why not remain at home And sit and judge among your household here ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.768"/>
          <p n="173">PHIL. Folly ! judge what ? BDEL. The same as There you do. Suppose you catch your housemaid on the sly Opening the door : fine her for that, one drachma. That's what you did at every sitting There. And very aptly, if the morning's fine,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.776"/>
          <p n="174">PHIL. Hah! I like that. BDEL. And then, however long An orator proses on, no need to fast, Worrying yourself (ay, and the prisoner too).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.776"/>
          <p n="175">PHIL. But do you really think that I can judge As well as now, whilst eating and digesting ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.776"/>
          <p n="176">BDEL. As well ? much better. When there's reckless swearing, Don't people say, what time and thought and trouble It took the judges to digest the case ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.784"/>
          <p n="177">PHIL. I'm giving in. But you've not told me yet How I'm to get my pay. BDEL. I'll pay you. PHIL. Good, Then I shall have mine to myself, alone ; For once Lysistratus, the funny fool, Played me the scurviest trick. We'd got one drachma Betwixt us two: he changed it at the fish-stall;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.792"/>
          <p n="178">BDEL. Then there again you'll get a great advantage.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.792"/>
          <p n="179">PHIL. Ay ay, that's something : let's begin at once.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.792"/>
          <p n="180">BDEL. Then stop a moment whilst I fetch the traps.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.792"/>
          <p n="181">PHIL. See here now, how the oracles come true. Oft have I heard it said that the Athenians One day would try their lawsuits in their homes, That each would have a little Court-let built For his own use, in his own porch, before His entrance, like a shrine of Hecate.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.800"/>
          <p n="182">BD. (Bustling in with a quantity ofjudicial properties.) Now then I hope you're satisfied: I've brought</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.800"/>
          <p n="183">PHIL. Now that I call extremely kind and thoughtful, And wondrous handy for an old man's needs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.800"/>
          <p n="184">BDEL. And heroes a fire, and gruel set beside it, All ready when you want it. PaiL. Good again. Now if I'm feverish I shan't lose my pay, For here I'll sit, and sip my gruel too. But why in the world have ye brought me out the cock ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.809"/>
          <p n="185">BDEL. To wake you, father, crowing over head In case you're dozing whilst a prisoner pleads.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.809"/>
          <p n="186">PHIL. One thing I miss, and only one. BDEL. What's that ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.809"/>
          <p n="187">PHIL. If you could somehow fetch the shrine of Lycus !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.809"/>
          <p n="188">BDEL. Here then it is, and here's the king in person.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.818"/>
          <p n="189">PHIL. 0 hero lord, how stern you are to see!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.818"/>
          <p n="190">BDEL. Almost, methinks, like great—Cleonymus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.818"/>
          <p n="191">Sos. Ay, and 'tis true the hero has no shield!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.818"/>
          <p n="192">BDEL. If you got seated sooner, I should sooner</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.826"/>
          <p n="193">BDEL. Let's see : what matter shall I bring on first ? Who's been at mischief of the household here ? That careless Thratta now, she charred the pitcher.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.826"/>
          <p n="194">PHIL. 0 stop, for goodness sake ! you've all but killed me. What! call a suit on with no railing here, Always the first of all our sacred things ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.826"/>
          <p n="195">BDEL. No more there is, by Zeus. PHIL. I'll run myself And forage out whatever comes to hand.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.826"/>
          <p n="196">BDEL. Heyday! where now ? The strange infatuation !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.834"/>
          <p n="197">XANTH. Psha ! rot the dog ! To keep a cur like this !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.834"/>
          <p n="198">BDEL. What's happened now ? XANTH. Why, has not Labes hero Got to the kitchen safe, and grabbed a cheese, A rich Sicilian cheese, and bolted it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.834"/>
          <p n="199">BDEL. Then that's the first indictment we'll bring on Before my father : yon shall prosecute.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.834"/>
          <p n="200">XANTH. Thank you, not I. This other Cur declares If there's a charge, he'll prosecute with pleasure.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.843"/>
          <p n="201">BDEL. Bring them both here. XANTH. Yes, yes, sir, so I will.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.843"/>
          <p n="202">BDEL. (To Phil.) Hallo, what's this ? PHIL. Pigrailings from the hearth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.843"/>
          <p n="203">BDEL. Sacrilege, eh ? PHIL. No, but I'd trounce some fellow (As the phrase goes) even from the very hearth. So call away : I'm keen for passing sentence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.843"/>
          <p n="204">BDEL. Then now I'll fetch the cause-lists and the pleadings.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.851"/>
          <p n="205">PHIL. 0 these delays! You weary and wear me out. I've long been dying to commence my furrows.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.851"/>
          <p n="206">BDEL. Now then! PHIL. Call on. BDEL. Yes certainly. PHIL. And who Is first in order ? BDEL. Dash it, what a bother ! I quite forgot to bring the voting urns.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.851"/>
          <p n="207">PHIL. Goodness! where now? BDEL. After the urns. PHIL. Don't trouble,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.851"/>
          <p n="208">BDEL. That's capital : then now methinks we have All that we want. No, there's no waterpiece.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.859"/>
          <p n="209">PHIL. Waterpiece, quotha ! pray what call you this ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.859"/>
          <p n="210">BDEL. Well thought on, father: and with shrewd home wit.. Ho, there within ! some person bring me out A pan of coals, and frankincense, and myrtle, That so our business may commence with prayer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.863"/>
          <p n="211">CHOR. We too, as ye offer the prayer and wine, We too will call on the Powers Divine To prosper the work begun; For the battle is over and done, And out of the fray and the strife to-day Fair peace ye have nobly won.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.863"/>
          <p n="212">BDEL. Now hush all idle words and sounds profane.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.874"/>
          <p n="213">CHOR. 0 Pythian Phcebus, bright Apollo, deign To speed this youth's design Wrought here, these gates before, And give us from our wanderings rest And peace for evermore. (The shout of Io Pœan is raised.)</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.885"/>
          <p n="214">CHOR. We in thy prayers combine, and quite give in</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.891"/>
          <p n="215">BDEL. Is any Justice out there ? let him enter. We shan't admit him when they've once begun.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.891"/>
          <p n="216">PHIL. Where is the prisoner fellow ? won't he catch it!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.891"/>
          <p n="217">BDEL. 0 yes ! attention ! (Reads the indictment.) Cur of Cydathon Hereby accuses Lobes of Æxone, For that, embezzling a Sicilian cheese, Alone he ate it. Fine, one jig-tree collar.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.891"/>
          <p n="218">PHIL. Nay, but a dog's death, an' he's once convicted.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.899"/>
          <p n="219">BDEL. Here stands, to meet the charge, the prisoner Labes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.899"/>
          <p n="220">PHIL. 0 the vile wretch ! 0 what a thievish look ! See how he grins, and thinks to take me in. Where's the Accuser, Cur of Cydathon ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.899"/>
          <p n="221">CUR. Bow! BDEL. Here he stands. Sos. Another Labes this, Good dog to yelp and lick the platters clean.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.899"/>
          <p n="222">BDEL. St! take your seat. (To Cur) Go up and prosecute.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.907"/>
          <p n="223">PHIL. Meanwhile I'll ladle out and sip my gruel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.907"/>
          <p n="224">XANTH. Ye have heard the charge, most honourable judges, I bring against him. Scandalous the trick He played us all, me and the Sailor-laddies. Alone, in a corner, in the dark, he gorged, And munched, and crunched, and Siciliced the cheese!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.915"/>
          <p n="225">PHIL. Pheugh ! the thing's evident: the brute this instant Breathed in my face the filthiest whiff of cheese. O the foul skunk ! XANTH. And would not give me any, Not though I asked. Yet can he be your friend Who won't throw anything to Me, the dog ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.915"/>
          <p n="226">PHIL. Not give you any ! No, nor Me, the state. The man's a regular scorcher, (burns his mouth) like this gruel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.915"/>
          <p n="227">BDEL. Come don't decide against us, pray don't, father, Before you've heard both sides. PHIL. But, my dear boy, The thing's self-evident, speaks for itself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="228">XAXTH. Don't let him off; upon my life he is The most lone-eatingest dog that ever was. The brute went coasting round and round the mortar, And snapped up all the rind off all the cities.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="229">PHIL. And I've no mortar even to mend my pitcher !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.926"/>
          <p n="230">XAXTH. So then be sure you punish him. For why? One bush, they say, can never keep two thieves.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.935"/>
          <p n="231">PHIL. Soh ! soh! Here's a nice string of accusations truly ! A rare thief of a man ! You think so too, Old gamecock ? Ay, he winks his eye, he thinks so. Archon ! Hi, fellow, hand me down the vessel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.935"/>
          <p n="232">BDEL. Reach it yourself ; I'll call my witnesses. The witnesses for Labes, please stand forward ! Pot, pestle, grater, brazier, water-jug, And all the other scarred and charred utensils.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.935"/>
          <p n="233">PHIL. I guess I'll finish him before I've done.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.944"/>
          <p n="234">BDEL. What ! always hard and pitiless, and that To the poor prisoners, always keen to bite !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.944"/>
          <p n="235">PHIL. Seems he's got nothing in the world to say.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.944"/>
          <p n="236">BDEL. Nay, 'tis a sudden seizure, such as once Attacked Thucydides when brought to trial. 'Tis tongue-paralysis that stops his jaws.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="237">PHIL. A thief I call him, and CONSPIRATOR.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="238">BDEL. Nay, he's the best and worthiest dog alive, Fit to take charge of any number o' sheep.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="239">PHIL. What use in that, if he eat up the cheese?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.952"/>
          <p n="240">BDEL. Use ! why, he fights your battles, guards your door ; The best do- altogether. If he filched, Yet 0 forgive : he never learnt the lyre.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.960"/>
          <p n="241">PHIL. I would to heaven he had never learned his letters, Then he'd not given us all this tiresome speech.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.960"/>
          <p n="242">BDEL. Nay, nay, sir, hear my witnesses, I beg. Grater, get in the box, and speak well out. You kept the mess; I ask you, answer plainly, Did you not grate the spoil between the soldiers ? He says he did. PHIL. Ay, but I vow he's lying.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.968"/>
          <p n="243">BDEL. 0 sir, have pity on poor toiling souls. Our Labes here, he lives on odds and ends, Bones, gristle : and is always on the go. That other Cur is a mere stay-at-home, Sits by the hearth, and when one brings aught in Asks for a share : if he gets none, he bites.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.968"/>
          <p n="244">PHIL. 0 me, what ails me that I grow so soft ! Some ill's afoot: I'm nearly giving in.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.968"/>
          <p n="245">BDEL. 0, I beseech you, father, show some pity, Don't crush him quite. Where are his little cubs ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.977"/>
          <p n="246">PHIL. (Deeply affected) Get down, get down, get down, get down. BD. I will. Yet that " get down," I know, has taken in A many men. However I'll get down.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.977"/>
          <p n="247">PHIL. Dash it! this guzzling ain't the thing at all. Here was I shedding tears, and seems to me Only because I have gorged myself with gruel.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.977"/>
          <p n="248">BDEL. Then will he not get off? PHIL. 'Tis hard to know.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="249">BDEL. 0 take, dear father, take the kindlier turn. Here, hold this vote : then with shut eyes dash by To the Far Urn. 0 father, do acquit him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="250">PHIL. No, no, my boy. I never learnt the lyre.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="251">BDEL. Here, let me lead you round the handiest way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.993"/>
          <p n="252">PHIL. Is this the Nearer ? BDEL. This is. PHIL. In she goes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.993"/>
          <p n="253">BDEL. (Aside) Duped, as I live ! acquits him by mistake ! (Aloud) I'll do the counting. PHIL. Well, how went the battle?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.993"/>
          <p n="254">BDEL. We shall soon see. 0 Labes, you're acquitted! Why, how now, father ? PHIL. (Faintly) Water, give me water!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1001"/>
          <p n="255">BDEL. Hold up, sir, do. PHIL. Just tell me only this, Is he INDEED acquitted ? BDEL. Yes. PHIL. I'm done for.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1009"/>
          <p n="256">BDEL. Don't take it so to heart: stand up, sir, pray.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1009"/>
          <p n="257">PHIL. How shall I bear this sin upon my soul ? A man acquitted ! What awaits me now ? Yet, 0 great gods ! I pray you pardon me. Unwilled I did it, not from natural bent.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1029"/>
          <p n="258">BDEL. And don't begrudge it; for I'll tend you well, And take you, father, everywhere with me, To feasts, to suppers, to the public games. Henceforth in pleasure you shall spend your days, And no Hyperbolus delude and mock you. But go we in. PHIL. Yes, if you wish it, now.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1043"/>
          <p n="259">CHOR. Yea, go rejoicing your own good way, Wherever your path may be; But you, ye numberless myriads, stay And listen the while to me. Beware lest the truths I am going to say, Unheeded to earth should fall; For that were the part of a fool to play, And not your part at all.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1051"/>
          <p n="260">NOW ALL ye people attend and hear, if ye love a simple and genuine strain, For now our poet with right good will, of you, spectators, must needs complain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1068"/>
          <p n="261">Scholiast. All the poet's early come dies, down to and including the Acharnians, were produced in one or other of these two names. It is common ly supposed that the Wasps itself was brought out in the name of Philouides; but to my mind the entire tenor of the Parabasis is absolutely conclusive against this hypothesis, which is fully discussed in the Preface.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1081"/>
          <p n="262">PHIL. No ! No ! I'll never put this off alive. With this I was arrayed, and found my safety, In the invasion of the great north wind.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1089"/>
          <p n="263">BDEL. Yon seem unwilling to accept a good.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1089"/>
          <p n="264">PHIL. 'Tis not expedient: no by Zeus it is not. 'Twas but the other day I gorged on sprats And had to pay three obols to the fuller.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1112"/>
          <p n="265">Scholiast. Sumptuous apparel would in accord with his easy life and homelyways. Already, after a debauch on , he has had to expend a triobol, a whole day's pay, in getting his soiled cleansed, and how much worse it would be with a costlier garment. Athenæus (vii. 137), after observing that these little fish were dressed with , and citing some lines of Aristophanes on the sub ject—the passage is quoted in the note on 329 supra—proceeds as follows : insertion of , and the substitution of for , would certainly give a smoother sense: but the reading is not supported by any Aristophanic MS. Possibly a line may have dropped out of the text between 11£7 and 1128.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1122"/>
          <p n="266">BDEL. Try it at all events : since once for all Into my hands you have placed yourself for good.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1122"/>
          <p n="267">PHIL. What would you have me do? BDEL. Put off that cloak And wear this mantle in a cloak-like way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1122"/>
          <p n="268">PHIL. Should we begot and bring up children then, When here my son is bent on smothering me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1131"/>
          <p n="269">BDEL. Come, take and put it on, and don't keep chattering.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1131"/>
          <p n="270">PHIL. Good heavens ! and what's this misery of a thing ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1131"/>
          <p n="271">BDEL. Some call it Persian, others Caunacès.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1131"/>
          <p n="272">PHIL. There ! and I thought it a Thymætian rug.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1139"/>
          <p n="273">BDEL. No wonder: for you've never been to Sardis, Else you'd have known it: now you don't. PHIL. Who? I? No more I do by Zeus: it seemed to me Most like an overwrap of Morychus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1139"/>
          <p n="274">BDEL. Nay, in Ecbatana they weave this stuff.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1139"/>
          <p n="275">PHIL. What! have they wool-guts in Ecbatana ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1139"/>
          <p n="276">BDEL. Tut, man : they weave it in their foreign looms At wondrous cost: this very article Absorbed with ease a talents weight of wool.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1148"/>
          <p n="277">BDEL. Quick, wrap it round you. PHIL. No, I won't, that's flat. You had better wrap me in a stove at once.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1148"/>
          <p n="278">BDEL. Come then, I'll throw it round you. (To the cloak) You, begone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1148"/>
          <p n="279">PHIL. Do keep a flesh-hook near. BDEL. A flesh-hook I why ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1156"/>
          <p n="280">PHIL. To pull me out before I melt away.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1156"/>
          <p n="281">BDEL. Now off at once with those confounded shoes, And on with these Laconians, instantly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1156"/>
          <p n="282">PHIL. What I, my boy ! I bring myself to wear The hated foe's insufferable—cloutings !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1156"/>
          <p n="283">BDEL. Come, sir, insert your foot, and step out firmly In this Laconian. PHIL. 'Tis too bad, it is, To make a man set foot on hostile-leather.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1164"/>
          <p n="284">BDEL. Now for the other. PHIL. 0 no, pray not that, I've a toe there, a regular Lacon-hater.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1164"/>
          <p n="285">BDEL. There is no way but this. PHIL. 0 luckless I, Why I shan't have, to bless my age, one-chilblain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1164"/>
          <p n="286">BDEL. Quick, father, get them on: and then move forward Thus ; in an opulent swaggering sort of way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1164"/>
          <p n="287">PHIL. Look then! observe my attitudes : think which Of all your opulent friends I walk most like.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1172"/>
          <p n="288">BDEL. Most like a pimple bandaged round with garlic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1172"/>
          <p n="289">PHIL. Ay, ay, I warrant I've a mind for wriggling.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1172"/>
          <p n="290">BDEL. Come, if you get with clever well-read men Could you tell tales, good gentlemanly tales ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1172"/>
          <p n="291">PHIL. Ay, that I could. BDEL. What sort of tales ? PHIL. Why, lots, As, first, how Lamia spluttered when they caught her, And, next, Cardopion, how he swinged his mother.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1181"/>
          <p n="292">BDEL. Pooh, pooh, no legends : give us something human, Some what we call domestic incident.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1181"/>
          <p n="293">PHIL. 0, ay, I know a rare domestic tale, How once upon a time a cat and mouse—</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1181"/>
          <p n="294">BDEL. O fool and clown, Theogenes replied</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1181"/>
          <p n="295">PHIL. What, then ? BDEL. Some stylish thing, as how you went With Androcles and Cleisthenes, surveying.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1190"/>
          <p n="296">PHIL. Why, bless the boy, I never went surveying, Save once to Pares, at two obols a day.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1190"/>
          <p n="297">BDEL. Still you must tell how splendidly, for instance, Ephudion fought the pancratiastic fight With young Ascondas : how the game old man Though grey, had ample sides, strong hands, firm flanks, An iron chest. PHIL. What humbug! could a man Fight the pancratium with an iron chest!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1190"/>
          <p n="298">BDEL. This is the way our clever fellows talk. But try another tack: suppose you sat Drinking with strangers, what's the pluckiest feat, Of all your young adventures, you could tell them ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1200"/>
          <p n="299">PHIL. My pluckiest feat ? 0 much my pluckiest, much,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1200"/>
          <p n="300">BDEL. Tcha ! poles indeed! Tell how yon slew the boar, Or coursed the hare, or ran the torch-race, tell Your gayest, youthfullest act. PHIL. My youthfullest action ? 'Twas that I had, when quite a hobbledehoy, With fleet Phayllus : and I caught him too : Won by two-votes. 'Twas for abuse, that action.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1208"/>
          <p n="301">BDEL. No more of that: but lie down there, and learn To be convivial and companionable.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1208"/>
          <p n="302">PHIL. Yes; how lie down? BDEL. In an elegant graceful way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1216"/>
          <p n="303">PHIL. How then ? BDEL. Extend your knees, and let yourself With practised ease subside along the cushions; Then praise some piece of plate : inspect the ceiling ; Admire the woven hangings of the hall.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1216"/>
          <p n="304">BDEL. The flute girl has performed ! our fellow-guests Are Phanus, Æschines, Theorus, Clean, Another stranger at Acestor's head. Could you with these cap verses properly ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1216"/>
          <p n="305">PHIL. Could I ? Ay, truly; no Diacrian better.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1224"/>
          <p n="306">BDEL. I'll put you to the proof. Suppose I'm Cleon. I'll start the catch Harmodius. You're to cap it. (Singing) “ Truly Athens never knew "</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1224"/>
          <p n="307">PHIL. (Singing) “ Such a rascally thief as you.”</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1224"/>
          <p n="308">BDEL. Will you do that ? You'll perish in your noise. He'll swear he'll fell you, quell you, and expel yon</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1232"/>
          <p n="309">BDEL. What if Theorus, lying at his feet, Should grasp the hand of Cleon, and begin, “ From the story of Admetus learn, my friend, to love the good.” How will you take that on ? PHIL. I, very neatly, “ It is not good the fox to play, “ Nor to side with both in a false friend's way."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="310">BDEL. Next comes that son of Sellus, Æschines, Clever, accomplished fellow, and he'll sing “ 0 the money, 0 the might,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="311">PHIL. " How we boasted, you and I."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="312">BDEL. Well, that will do : you're fairly up to that: So come along : we'll dine at Philoctemon's. Boy ! Chrysus ! pack our dinner up ; and now For a rare drinking-bout at last. PHIL. No, no, Drinking ain't good : I know what comes of drinking, Breaking of doors, assault, and battery, And then, a headache and a fine to pay.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1251"/>
          <p n="313">BDEL. Not if you drink with gentlemen, you know. They'll go to the injured man, and beg you off, Or you yourself will tell some merry tale,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1251"/>
          <p n="314">East. It seems that at these picnic dinners each guest brought a basket of provisions, not as a contribution to the general stock, but for his own consump tion. And Socrates, we are told, per ceiving on one such occasion that some guests had brought an insufficient supply, and others overmuch, took the insufficient supply, and divided it amongst the whole party. By this device he shamed the others into dividing their provisions also, so that all the guests shared alike (Xenophon, Mem. ii. 14).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1251"/>
          <p n="315">PHIL. 0 I'll learn plenty of those tales, if so I can get off, whatever wrong I do. Come, go we in : let nothing stop us now.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1265"/>
          <p n="316">CHOR. Often have I deemed myself exceeding bright, acute, and clever, Dull, obtuse, and awkward never. That is what Amynias is, of Curling-borough, Sellus’ son ; Him who now upon an apple and pomegranate dines, I saw At Leogoras's table Eat as hard as he was able, Goodness, what a hungry maw ! Pinched and keen as Antiphon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1284"/>
          <p n="317">XANTH. 0 lucky tortoises, to have such skins,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1292"/>
          <p n="318">CHOR. How now, my boy ? for though a man be old, Still, if he's beaten, we may call him boy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1309"/>
          <p n="319">XANTH. Was not the old man the most outrageous nuisance, Much the most drunk and riotous of all ? And yet we'd Lycon, Antiphon, Hippyllus, Lysigtratus, Theophrastus, Phrynichus; But he was far the noisiest of the lot. Soon as he'd gorged his fill of the good cheer, He skipped, he leapt, and laughed, and frisked, and whinnied, Just like a donkey on a feed of corn : And slapped me youthfully, calling Boy ! Boy ! So then Lysistratus compared him thus : Old man, says he, you’re like new winefermenting, Or like a sompnour, scampering to its bran.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1322"/>
          <p n="320">PHIL. Up ahoy ! out ahoy !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1322"/>
          <p n="321">Pierson (Mœris, p. 126) is clearly wrong in his interpretation of this passage.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1322"/>
          <p n="322">BDEL. You there ! you there ! you old lascivious dotard ! Enamoured, eh ? ay of a fine ripe coffin. Oh, by Apollo, you shall smart for this !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1332"/>
          <p n="323">PHIL. Dear, dear, how keen to taste a suit in pickle !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1332"/>
          <p n="324">BDEL. No quizzing, sir, when you have filched away The flute-girl from our party. PHIL. Eh ? what ? flute-girl ? You're out of your mind, or out of your grave, or something.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1332"/>
          <p n="325">BDEL. Why, bless the fool, heroes Dardanis beside you !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1340"/>
          <p n="326">PHIL. What, this ? why, this is a torch in the market-place !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1348"/>
          <p n="327">BDEL. A torch, man ? PHIL. Clearly; pray observe the punctures.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1348"/>
          <p n="328">BDEL. Then what's this black here, on the top of her head ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1348"/>
          <p n="329">PHIL. Oh, that's the rosin, oozing while it burns.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1348"/>
          <p n="330">BDEL. Then this of course is not a woman's arm ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1356"/>
          <p n="331">PHIL. Of course not ; that's a sprouting of the pine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1364"/>
          <p n="332">BDEL. Sprouting be hanged. (To Dard.) You come along with me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1372"/>
          <p n="333">PHIL. Hi! hiI what are you at ? BDEL. Marching her off Out of your reach; a rotten, as I think,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1380"/>
          <p n="334">BDEL. Troth, you have learned Olympia to some purpose.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1380"/>
          <p n="335">BAKING GIRL. Oh, there he is ! Oh, pray stand by me now ! There's the old rascal who misused me so, Banged with his torch, and toppled down from here Bread worth ten obols, and four loaves to boot.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1380"/>
          <p n="336">BDEL. There now, you see; troubles and suits once more Your wine will bring us. PHIL. Troubles ? Not at all. A merry tale or two sets these things right. I'll soon set matters right with this young woman.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1388"/>
          <p n="337">PRAXAGORA. How! by the Twain! Girl, have you lost your wits ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1388"/>
          <p n="338">WOMAN. Why, what's amiss? I never asked for drink.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1388"/>
          <p n="339">PRAXAGORA. You are a Man, and yet invoked the Twain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1388"/>
          <p n="340">WOMAN. I meant by Apollo."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1396"/>
          <p n="341">BAKING GIRL. No, by the Twain I you shan't escape scot-free, Doing such damage to the goods of Myrtia, Sostrata's daughter, and Anchylion's, sir !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1396"/>
          <p n="342">PHIL. Listen, good woman : I am going to tell you A pleasant tale. BAKING GIRL. Not me, by Zeus, sir, no !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1406"/>
          <p n="343">PHIL. At Æsop, as he walked one eye from supper, There yapped an impudent and drunken bitch. Then Æsop answered, 0 VOlt bitch ! you bitch ! If in the stead of that ungodly tongue You'd buy some wheat, methinks you'd have more sense.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1406"/>
          <p n="344">BAKING GIRL. Insult me too ? I summon you before The Market Court for damage done my goods,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1406"/>
          <p n="345">PHIL. Nay, nay, but listen if I speak not fair. Simonides and Lasus once were rivals. Then Lasus says, PisA, I don't care, says he.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1415"/>
          <p n="346">BAKING GIRL. You will, sir, will you ? PHIL. And you, Chærephon, Are you her sompnour, you, like fear-blanched Ino</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1415"/>
          <p n="347">BDEL. See, here's another coming, as I live, To summon you : at least he has got his sompnour.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1415"/>
          <p n="348">COMPLAINANT. 0 dear! 0 dear ! Old man, I summon you For outrage. BDEL. Outrage ? no, by the Gods, pray don't. I'll make amends for everything he has done, (Ask what you will) and thank you kindly too.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1423"/>
          <p n="349">PHIL. Nay, I'll make friends myself without compulsion. I quite admit the assault and battery. So tell me which you'll do ; leave it to me To name the compensation I must pay To make us friends, or will you fix the sum ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1423"/>
          <p n="350">COMP. Name it yourself: I want no suits nor troubles.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1423"/>
          <p n="351">PHIL. There was a man of Sybaris, do you know,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1431"/>
          <p n="352">BDEL. Ay, this is like the rest of your behaviour.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1431"/>
          <p n="353">COMP. (To Bdel.) You, sir, yourself, remember what he says.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1431"/>
          <p n="354">PHIL. Stop, listen. Once in Sybaris a girl Fractured a jug. COMP. I call you, friend, to witness.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1431"/>
          <p n="355">PHIL. Just so the jug : it called a friend to witness. Then said the girl of Sybaris, By'r Lady, If you would leave off calling friends to witness, And buy a rivet, you would, show more brains.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1441"/>
          <p n="356">COMP. Jeer, till the Magistrate call on my case.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1441"/>
          <p n="357">BDEL. No, by Demeter, but you shan't stop here, I'll take and carry you— PHIL. What now ! BDEL. What now ? Carry you in : or soon there won't be sompnours Enough for all your summoning complainants.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1441"/>
          <p n="358">PHIL. The Delphians once charged Æsop— BDEL. I don't care.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1467"/>
          <p n="359">PHIL. With having filched a vessel of their God. But Æsop up and told them that a beetle-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1467"/>
          <p n="360">BDEL. Zounds ! but I'll finish you, beetles and all. CHOR. I envy much his fortune As he changes from his dry Ungenial life and manners, Another path to try. Now all to soft indulgence His eager soul will take, And yet perchance it will not, For, ah ! ’tis hard to break From all your life-long habits; Yet some the change have made,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1474"/>
          <p n="361">XANTH. 0 Dionysus ! here's a pretty mess Into our house some power has whirligigged. Soon as the old man heard the pipe, and drank</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1482"/>
          <p n="362">PHIL. Who sits, who waits at the entrance gates ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1482"/>
          <p n="363">XANTH. More and more is this evil advancing !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1482"/>
          <p n="364">PHIL. Be the bolts undone, we have just begun; This, this is the first evolution of dancing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1490"/>
          <p n="365">XANTH. First evolution of madness, I think.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1490"/>
          <p n="366">PHIL. With the strong contortion the ribs twist round, And the nostril snorts, and the joints resound,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1498"/>
          <p n="367">PHIL. Then he kicks his leg to the wondering sky,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1498"/>
          <p n="368">XANTH. 0 look to yourself, look out, look out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1498"/>
          <p n="369">PHIL. For now in these sinewy joints of ours The cup-like socket is twirled about.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1498"/>
          <p n="370">BDEL. 'Twon't do, by Zeus : 'twon't do : 'tis downright madness.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1507"/>
          <p n="371">PHIL. Who's he, poor devil ? BDEL. 'Tis the midmost son</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1507"/>
          <p n="372">BDEL. Nothing but crabs ! 'fore Zens, nothing but crabs ! Here creeps a third of Carcinus's brood.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1507"/>
          <p n="373">PHIL. Heyday ! what's this ? a vinaigrette, or spider ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1507"/>
          <p n="374">BDEL. This is the Pinnoteer, of all the tribe</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1528"/>
          <p n="375">CH. Come draw we aside, and leave them a wide, a roomy and peaceable exercise-ground, That before us therein like tops they may spin, revolving and whirling and twirling around. O lofty-titled sons of the ocean-roving sire,</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
