<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Ecclesiazusae</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">Benjamin Bickley Rogers</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Benjamin Bickley Rogers (1919). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg010.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.12"/>
          <p n="1">THE Ecclesiazusae has come down to us unaccompanied by any didascalia or other evidence of its date, beyond what may be gathered from the play itself and the comments of the Greek Scholiasts thereon. But the information derivable from these sources makes it abundantly clear that the play was exhibited in the spring of the year B.C. 393, in the third year of the 96th Olympiad, when Eubulides was archon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.41"/>
          <p n="2">In the opening scenes of the comedy, the women, disguised as men, are practising the part which they are shortly to play in the Assembly, , of the Athenian people. And Praxagora, their leader, delivers a speech of considerable length, in the serious part of which she is doubtless expounding the poet's own views respecting the political condition of Athens. She arraigns the policy of the people for its total want of continuity; she avers that they are perpetually chopping and changing; enamoured of one course to-day, and of the opposite course to-morrow; and in illustration of her statement, she says: " Then again this Alliance, when we were deliberating about it, they vowed that not to conclude it would be the ruin of the State: but when once it was concluded, they were disgusted with it; and the orator who persuaded them into it had straightway to cut and run.” Lines 193-196.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.57"/>
          <p n="3">On this passage the Scholiasts remark, ȋ on . “ As to the Alliance, Philochorus relates that, two years before, an Alliance had been concluded between the Lacedaemonians and the Boeotians." But as the speaker is referring to an alliance entered into not by the Lacedaemonians, but by the Athenians, Petit has, with general consent, substituted for in the Scholium. And that this is really what the Scholiasts meant is made still plainer by the circumstance that the orator who fell into discredit for pushing the treaty through is by them (on line 196) declared, however wrongly, to have been the illustrious officer Conon, the inveterate enemy of the Lacedaemonians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.65"/>
          <p n="4">We get therefore so far that, according to the statement in the Scholium, the Ecclesiazusae was acted two years after an alliance had been contracted between the Athenians and the Boeotians, an alliance which was considered of momentous, and even of vital, importance to Athens : and that with this alliance the name of Conon was, or might have been, in some way connected. And we have next to consider whether we find in history, within the period admissible for the production of this play, any treaty of alliance between the Athenians and the Boeotians which will answer the foregoing conditions.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.82"/>
          <p n="5">Now the disastrous termination of the Peloponnesian War not only annihilated the Athenian empire, it reduced Athens herself to the position of a mere satellite and dependency of the Spartan leadership. The Athenians1 were bound to follow wherever Sparta might lead ; her enemies were to be their enemies, and her friends their friends; their navy was limited to twelve triremes; and the demolition of the Long Walls left them open at once to a blockade by the formidable armies of the Peloponnesian Confederacy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.90"/>
          <p n="6">In this state of humiliation Athens remained for about nine years, from B. c. 404 to B. c. 395.</p>
          <p n="7">Yet at the very moment of her fall an undercurrent was working which was ultimately to lift her, not indeed to her former supremacy, but to a position of dignity and complete independence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.126"/>
          <p n="8">At the time when Athens lay helpless at the feet of her conquerors, a great congress was held at Sparta for the purpose of deciding upon her fate. Many states, and more especially Thebes and Corinth, were urgent that no terms of any kind should be granted her; insisting that the city should be razed, and all the citizens sold into slavery; and that sheep should pasture over the ground which once was Athens. The Lacedaemonians stood resolutely between Athens and this terrible vengeance, declaring that they would not reduce to slavery an Hellenic city, a city too which had done such splendid service for Hellas in the hour of her gravest peril. And, overruling the eager hostility of the most powerful members of the Confederacy, they granted the terms of peace which have already been mentioned 1.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.151"/>
          <p n="9">No moment in all Hellenic history after the great Persian invasion was so noble as this, when Sparta saw her great antagonist prostrate at her feet, forgot the bitter rivalry of the last seven and twenty years, remembered only their comradeship in the death-struggle against the Mede, remembered the gallantry and self-devotion of Athens in those heroic days, and proved herself a worthy representative of the men of Thermopylae and Plataea. Not a life was taken; no Athenian was injured in purse or person; no trophies, not even the Spartan shields captured at Sphacteria, were reclaimed, but Athens was left with all her wealth of architecture and sculpture, with all her art-treasures, and temples, and choruses ; still an " eye" of Hellas, still the noblest and the loveliest of all Hellenic cities.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.169"/>
          <p n="10">The spirit of the dead Callicratidas must have been strong in the Spartan councils on that day, when the Peloponnesian War was closed with this great act of forbearance and magnanimity. And yet, though it displayed Sparta for the moment as the true Pan-Hellenic leader, though it invested her with a claim to our admiration even surpassing what is clue to her military glories, it undoubtedly sowed the bitter seed which culminated in her own downfall.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.205"/>
          <p n="11">Thebes and Corinth, the main props of the Confederacy which acknow ledged the leadership of Sparta, were naturally aggrieved to find their fondest wishes overruled, and their hostility to Athens rebuked, by the generous moderation of the Spartan decision. And very shortly after wards the Thebans 1 certainly, and according to Justin the Corinthians -also, received a further rebuff from Sparta: their claim to share in the wealth which Lysander had brought from Asia for the more effectual prosecution of the war being absolutely repudiated by the Spartan government. Thenceforward they began to draw away from her side. And in the following year when Sparta again summoned her allies to invade Attica, and put down the popular party under Thrasybulus, it was noticed that the only states1 which did not obey the summons were Thebes and Corinth. Nor did these two states ever again act in unison with that great group of Hellenic peoples which recognized Sparta as their chief and leader.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.213"/>
          <p n="12">Some two years later the Lacedaemonians went to war with Elis, and summoned the Confederacy to assist them. Again there were two exceptions to the unanimity with which the allies, including the Athenians, obeyed the call; and again those two exceptions2 were Thebes and Corinth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.246"/>
          <p n="13">It was, seemingly, in the year B. c. 396 that Agesilaus was planning his great expedition to Asia Minor. His mind was full of mighty projects and lofty hopes: even dreaming of those gigantic successes the achievement of which was reserved for a later period, and for a Macedonian king. He was a second Agamemnon, conducting the hosts of all Greece to conquer a mightier Troy : a Pan-Hellenic leader, retorting upon Persia the invasion of Hellas by Xerxes. He named a rendezvous to which all the troops were to repair, and sent messengers to all the Hellenic cities, both within and without Peloponnesus, fixing the particular quota which each was expected to send 3. The Boeotians appear to have returned a blunt refusal The Corinthians alleged (and Pausanias actually gives credit to their allegations) that they were most desirous of coming, but were deterred by an evil omen, the recent destruction of their Temple of Olympian Zeus. Anyhow neither. Thebans nor Corinthians came. On this occasion, too, the Athenians excused themselves, on the plea that they had not yet sufficiently recovered from the effects of the Peloponnesian War.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.285"/>
          <p n="14">So far the symptoms of alienation were merely of a negative character. Thebes and Corinth had not moved with the rest of the Confederacy at the summons, and under the leadership of Sparta, but neither had they proceeded to any overt acts of hostility. But before Agesilaus had started for Asia, the Boeotians had offered to him, and through him to Sparta, a direct and deliberate insult. The King of Sparta, in emulation of his great predecessor the King of Mycenae, was desirous of inaugurating his expedition by a preliminary sacrifice at Aulis, in honour of the Goddess Artemis 1. He left the fleet assembled at the southern promontory of Euboea, and came with a single trireme to Aulis to perform the sacrifice. The victims were slain, their thigh bones and fat were on the altar, the fire was kindled, when suddenly a squadron of Boeotian cavalry, hastily dispatched by the Boeotarchs, appeared upon the scene and put a forcible stop to the proceedings; even driving Agesilaus himself from the temple, and casting from the altar and throwing about in all directions the half-consumed sacrificial meats. It was said that the rites were not being performed in the proper and customary manner; but we are not here concerned with the right or wrong of the affair. In any case the conduct of the Boeotians was a grievous affront, and a deliberate provocation, to the Commander-in-Chief of the foremost Hellenic state. The sacrifice which was to redound to the glory of Agesilaus was turned into a bitter humiliation; and he re-embarked on his trireme in great anger, calling the Gods to witness the insulting conduct of the Boeotians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.320"/>
          <p n="15">The incident was not forgotten; and when at the commencement of the year B. C. 395 the Phocians, assailed by the Boeotians, applied for help to Sparta, the latter1 at once seized the opportunity of declaring war against Thebes, and summoned the Peloponnesian Confederacy to invade Boeotia. Only one member of the Confederacy refused to comply, and of course that member was Corinth 2. The army from Peloponnesus, led by Pausanias the King, was to invade Boeotia from the south: whilst another army, under Lysander, the greatest general and most influential personage in Hellas, was to enter it on the north-west from Phocis. The two armies were to meet at Haliartus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.328"/>
          <p n="16">Alarmed at these formidable preparations the Boeotians sent an embassy to Athens, to propose an alliance, and the formation of an Anti-Spartan League. The speech of their envoy, as preserved, or invented, for us by Xenophon, points out in strong and exaggerated language the benefits which might accrue to Athens herself from the proposed alliance. "Ye will become," says the orator, "far greater than ye ever were; ye will be leaders of all: of ourselves, of the Peloponnesians, of your former subjects, yea of the great king himself."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.363"/>
          <p n="17">The question for the Athenian Assembly to decide was one of vital and absorbing interest. Should they, or should they not, concur with Thebes in establishing an Anti-Spartan League, to which Corinth at all events was quite certain at once to accede? If they did, they would, for the first time since their fall, be moving out of the shadow of the Spartan supremacy, and would become once more a free and independent Republic. But they would be uniting themselves to their deadliest enemies, against the very Power which, nine years before, had shielded them from the relentless vengeance of those very enemies. They would be performing an act of great political ingratitude, and at the same time of great political hazard. If Thebes and Corinth were again to attack them, they had forfeited all claim to be again protected by Sparta; whilst if Thebes and Corinth were to make peace with Sparta, they would be wholly unable, in the present state of their fortifications, to make any show of resistance to the Peloponnesian armies. It must have been a time for great searchings of heart amongst the wisest Athenians; and Thrasybulus, then the most eminent leader of the people, seems to have been seriously perplexed and uncertain which course it would be more prudent to adopt. For this was doubtless the occasion on which he first promised the Lacedaemonians to speak in their favour, and then, changing his mind, excused himself on the ground of sudden1 indisposition. He does not seem however to have taken an active part against them. I do not know on what authority he is represented by Bishop Thirlwall and Mr. Grote as moving the resolution to accept the Theban proposal, or by Mr. Mitford as " countenancing the measure." He seems to have done nothing beyond communicating the resolution, when passed, to the Theban envoys, and that too in somewhat ungracious terms, showing that he was fully alive to the perilous character of the step.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.372"/>
          <p n="18">However very many, , spoke in favour of the alliance, and it was ultimately accepted by the Assembly without a dissentient vote. The Athenian troops at once started for Haliartus, and though the engagement in which Lysander was defeated and slain took place before their arrival, yet their subsequent presence had a determining influence upon the campaign, and compelled the ignominious evacuation of Boeotia, without a battle, by the army of Pausanias.</p>
          <p n="19">This great and striking event, the "march to Haliartus" as it was commonly called, made a deep and lasting impression upon the Athenian mind. " For ye, 0 men of Athens," says Demosthenes, some sixty-five years afterwards, " when the Lacedaemonians were masters of sea and land, and controlled all countries round about Attica with their har mosts and their garrisons—Euboea, Tanagra, the whole of Boeotia, Megara, Aegina, Cleonae, the other islands-whilst ye, for your part, had no ships, and your city no walls, ye marched out to Haliartus, and not many days afterwards to Corinth: though the Athenians of that time had much ill to remember against the Corinthians and the Thebans for their conduct in the Deceleian war; but they remembered it not. Far from it 1." And the name of Haliartus became so familiarly associated with the glories of Athens that more than two centuries later when the Romans, in their war against Perseus, conquered and destroyed the town, the Athenians preferred a request that the site might be given to them selves. One would infer from Polybius, who speaks of their request with some indignation, that the petition was refused; but Strabo tells us that the Romans did in fact give them the site, and that in his time it was still in their possession.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.380"/>
          <p n="20">Here then we find an alliance which precisely answers to the descrip tion given in the speech of Praxagora. That this was the one chance for Athens, that its refusal would ruin the city, is just what some, at least, of the "many orators " who advocated the alliance might reason ably be expected to urge. But Praxagora goes on to say that, when the Athenians had got the Alliance, they became disgusted with it. Can this be truly said of the Anti-Spartan League within two years of its inception, that is to say in the spring of B. c. 393 ? About this there is no doubt whatever.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.388"/>
          <p n="21">At first, indeed, everything seemed to promise well. The League was joined at once by the Corinthians and the Argives, and shortly afterwards by the Euboeans, the Acarnanians, the Leucadians, and other states1. The Spartan garrisons and alliances beyond Boeotia were swept away, and the Phocians completely defeated. And when in the following spring and summer (B. C. 394) a large 2 army, composed of contingents from all the members of the League, was gathered together at Corinth, the confidence of the leaders was unbounded. Timolaus of Corinth proposed an immediate march on Sparta: for rivers, said he, are smallest at their source, before they become swoln by the influx of their tributaries, and wasps are most easily destroyed in their nests. Doubtless too there was another reason, the hope of concluding the war off-hand before Agesilaus could return from Asia Minor. The proposal of Timolaus was adopted, and the army, leaving its great camp near Corinth, marched southward as far as the famous valley of Nemea. But they had under rated the military spirit and the military resources of their opponent. Instead of attacking Sparta at home, they were forced to retrace their steps to repel an attack by Sparta on their own headquarters. A Pelo ponnesian army, nearly as large as their own, had marched through Sicyon, and was ravaging with sword and fire () the territory of Corinth. The battle between these two mighty Hellenic armies, , as 3 Demosthenes describes it, resulted in the total rout of the army of the League, and the main body of the 1Athenian troops, assailed at once in front and on their left flank by the Lacedaemonians, suffered more severely than any other contingent. The defeated army fled for safety to the walls of Corinth, but the Lacedaemonians were following hard after them; the gates were shut in their faces, and the fugitives were compelled to take refuge in the neighbouring2 camp from which they had issued, only a few days earlier, in the confident expectation of a victorious march upon Sparta.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.405"/>
          <p n="22">The battle of Corinth was fought in the summer of B. c. 394; and its result made it evident that, even in the absence of the army of Agesilaus, Sparta was more than a match for the Anti-Spartan League. And before that summer had passed away, Agesilaus returning from Asia, and having traversed Thrace, Macedonia, and Thessaly, entered Boeotia from the north, and inflicted another defeat on the army of the League in the battle of Coronea. Here again1 an Athenian contingent formed part of the defeated army; but we have no mention made of its losses, and probably they were slight compared with those sustained in the battle of Corinth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.427"/>
          <p n="23">Thus within a few weeks 2 the entire aspect of affairs had, as regarded Athens, undergone a serious change for the worse. She had lost many citizens without any beneficial results; the whole force of the League had been defeated both in the north and in the south; the bright hopes with which the year B. c. 394 had commenced, had altogether died away; divided counsels were already making themselves felt at Corinth, and it was but natural that the Athenians should become disgusted, , at the failure of all those brilliant expectations, through which they had been induced, less than two years before, to take so active a part in the formation of the Anti-Spartan League.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.437"/>
          <p n="24">It was at this juncture, at the commencement of the year B. c. 393, that Praxagora comes forward, in the play before us, to condemn the vacillating policy of the men, and to propose that the government of Athens shall be henceforth entrusted to the women, as the more stable and conservative sex. But before we discuss her proposals, there are two other points to be mentioned.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.471"/>
          <p n="25">We have already seen that, according to the Scholiast, the orator who persuaded the Athenians to contract the alliance with Thebes, and was, in consequence, obliged to leave the country, was none other than Conon ; , is his comment on line 196. This, of course, is a mere delusion. Conon had never set foot in Athens since the disaster at Aegospotami; Aristophanes would not have described that gallant officer simply as one ; nor did he ever fall into discredit with the Athenian people. Why then, it may be asked, was his name so intimately connected, in the mind of the Scholiast, with the Anti-Spartan League ? It was because, whatever benefit accrued to Athens from the League, she derived through the intervention of Conon. Already, before the com mencement of B. c. 393, whilst the horizon was so dark and threatening at home, it was known that he had won a great victory over the Lacedae monian fleet at Cnidus, a victory which was speedily followed by the downfall of the Lacedaemonian power in the islands and beyond the sea. This victory, however, was not won for Athens; it was achieved by the Persian fleet, consisting of Greek and Phoenician triremes, under the joint command of Conon and Pharnabazus ; and the isles of Greece and cities of Asia Minor delivered from the Spartan harmosts and garrisons were not handed over to Athens, but were left as free and independent states. But before another year had rolled away, before the spring of B. c. 392 had arrived, a brilliant and marvellous change, on-- might almost say a resurrection, had taken place in the affairs of Athens. Conon had returned, bringing the Persian fleet, and an ample supply of Persian gold to secure her safety; the other members of the League had readily assisted, Thebes alone sending 500 skilled workmen; the Long Walls had risen again, the fortifications of Peiraeus were restored, and Athens was entirely delivered from the doubts and the dangers which had so long beset her. At the commencement of B. c. 393 Athens was in a state of disquiet and perplexity, still halting between two courses. There was no doubt or wavering at the commencement of B. c. 392. Her safety was assured. She had been finally launched on a new career of prosperity.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.504"/>
          <p n="26">The foregoing considerations might of themselves be sufficient to show that Petit and Mr. Fynes Clinton, in giving B. c. 392 as the date of the Ecelesiazusae, have fixed it a year too late. The deservedly high reputa tion of Mr. Fynes Clinton in chronological questions has obtained universal acceptance for that date, although the speech of Praxagora, from begin ning to end, cries out against it, and demands the previous year. And clear as the internal evidence is in favour of B. C. 393, the external evidence is almost equally clear. The subjoined table of the years of the 96th Olympiad may assist us in an examination of the grounds on which those two distinguished chronologers have come to a wrong conclusion : The question is whether the Ecclesiazusae was exhibited in the archonship of Eubulides, or in that of Demostratus. And this to a great extent depends upon another question, viz. whether , which is said to have been concluded two years before its exhibition, was concluded in the archonship of Phormio, or in that of Diophantus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.514"/>
          <p n="27">Now Petit (to consider his theory first) fixes on the wrong . He treats the , to which Praxagora refers, as being not the original Anti-Spartan League, but the subsequent accession to the League of Corinth and Argolis. And true it is that Diodorus, who has spoken of the original Anti-Spartan League and the march to Haliartus in the 81st chapter of his XIVth Book, does, when he returns to the subject in the following chapter, speak of an alliance being made, during the archonship of Diophantus, between the Athenians, Boeotians, Corinthians, and Argives. But it is impossible that these accessions to the League can have been the alliance of which Praxagora speaks. They were contem plated from the first; to them no opposition was possible; no orator was required to push them through; no one could have argued that the rejection of these new members would ruin the state, for the idea of rejecting them could not have occurred to anybody; nor were the Athenians afterwards vexed () at having admitted them. In no one point does Petit's answer to Praxagora's . This mistake as to the alliance is the sole foundation for Petit's date of the play, and the foundation being removed the superstructure falls.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.547"/>
          <p n="28">Mr. Fynes Clinton of course avoids the error into which Petit, and after him Paulmier, fell. He recognizes that by the alliance Praxagora must mean the original Anti-Spartan League and the march to Haliartus, but he places these events a year too late, viz. in the archonship of Diophantus. His sole authority is an observation of Plutarch 1 that an oracle was thought to refer to the two battles of Delium and Haliartus, the latter than the former. But Plutarch's authority on a matter of chronology is of very slight value; and Mr. Fynes Clinton seems to have overlooked the express statement of Diodorus2 that the formation of the Anti-Spartan League and the march to Haliartus took place during the archonship of Phormio. Diodorus arranges his facts in the form of annals, prefixing (in this part of his history) to the events of each successive year the names of the Athenian archon and the Roman consuls for that particular year. And his positive statement as to the date of an event very greatly outweighs an incidental remark of Plutarch. And here it is in entire accord with the conviction which must be borne in upon the mind of every thoughtful reader, from a careful perusal of the arguments and allegations of Praxagora.</p>
          <p n="29">It seems therefore on every ground absolutely certain, that the play was exhibited in February or March, B. C. 393, after the reverses sustained by the Anti-Spartan League, and before the arrival of Conon, and the rebuilding of the Long Walls of Athens.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.571"/>
          <p n="30">Reverting now to Praxagora and her scheme for the future govern ment of Athens, we find that the main argument put forward in support of her proposed is based on the more conservative character of the female sex. lien, she says, are always in quest of novelty and cliange. Women abide by their principles, and the women of the present day use the same customs and follow the same practices that their predecessors have used and followed throughout all generations. Athens, imperilled by the restlessness of men, will be saved by the steadfast and sober adherence of women to ancient methods and venerable traditions. Yet no sooner does Praxagora by these arguments and for these purposes obtain the reins of power, than she spontaneously develops a scheme so startling and so novel, as to throw altogether into the shade the wildest extravagances of the men. It is a scheme of naked socialism, involving the community of goods, the abolition of marriage, and (what is one sidedly called) the community of women.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.588"/>
          <p n="31">How can we account for this singular phenomenon? It has no parallel in any other comedy of Aristophanes. The Chorus indeed will frequently go over to the side which it began by opposing, and some times one of the principal characters will yield to argument, or the stress of circumstances: but there is always enough in the play itself to determine and explain the change. Here, however, the heroine, who has been earnestly seeking power for one purpose, immediately employs it for the opposite purpose: her special mission being to put a stop to all political novelties, she at once introduces a political novelty so vast and revolutionary, that she doubts if the men can be brought to accept it. And there is not a syllable in the play to justify or account for her sudden change. It is therefore necessary to look for the determining cause in something outside the play itself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.614"/>
          <p n="32">And it seems impossible to doubt that the cause is to be found in the appearance, whilst Aristophanes was engaged on the Ecclesiazusae, of the Republic of Plato, or at all events of that part of the work which now constitutes Books II to V (inclusive)1 of the Republic. After the death of Socrates, an event which occurred in June, B.C. 399, Plato, we are told1, retired to Megara, then travelled to some other well- known philosophic centres, Cyrene, Italy, and Egypt, and was con templating a visit to the Magians, but finally, , gave up the idea, and returned to Athens. If by we are to understand, as seems unquestionable, the expeditions of Dercyllidas and Agesilaus (which would naturally render it unsafe for an Hellenic citizen to journey into the interior of the Persian empire), Plato must have returned to Athens a year or two before the date of the present play. And this would be in accordance with the tradition that he took part in the battle of Corinth, B. c. 394, though, as we have already seen, the tradition itself rests on no very certain foundation. But, however this may be, it is clear that his Republic, either in its present, or in an incomplete, shape came into the hands of the Athenian people before the termination of that year.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.638"/>
          <p n="33">Praxagora, therefore, having obtained supreme power at Athens, with, apparently, authority to remodel its institutions at her will, suddenly finds, all ready to her hand, as a delightful subject for caricature, the elaborate communistic schemes developed with such detail in this new philosophical treatise. Aristophanes was not the man to let such an opportunity escape him. What mattered Praxagora's consistency com pared with this brilliant opening for philosophic chaff? And so the greatest novelty of all, a system of undiluted communism, is at once introduced, by the opponent of all novelty, into the practical everyday life of the people of Athens. Plato had foreseen that these theories were likely to attract the ridicule of the wits, ra , and though he could not have anticipated the form which that ridicule would take, yet the epigram prefixed to this Introduction shows that he Lore the poet no malice for the humorous and impersonal caricature.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.646"/>
          <p n="34">It seems strange that any one should ever have doubted or ignored the very obvious fact that in the latter half of the Ecclesiazusae, Aristophanes is laughing at the communistic theories of the Platonic Republic. Many similarities of thought and diction between the Praxagorean and Platonic schemes will be found pointed out in the Commentary : and it really is quite inconceivable1 that two writers, one a philosopher and one a comic poet, approaching the subject from such different points of views, should, independently of each other, by a mere fortuitous coincidence, have travelled over so exactly the same ground in (allowing for the grave purpose of the one and the comic purpose of the other) so exactly the same way. It will be sufficient here to consider a single instance. In both systems, though for widely different reasons, children will be unable to recognize their parents, and parents their children. In both cases this fact is only brought out in answer to a question. In both cases the question is propounded in the same form, not Will they recognize? but How will they recognize? (, Plato; at , Aristophanes) the answer being, of course, that no recognition is possible; all youths must consider themselves the children of all the old people. Out of this novel state of things a variety of strange and startling results might arise; but in both cases one, and one only, and that by no means the most obvious, is selected, viz. the greater security of the old people. For now, if a youth should assault (, Plato, Aristo phanes) his elder, the bystanders would at once interfere; since, for all they can tell, they may themselves be the children (Plato adds "or the brothers or the parents ") of the sufferer. Is the identity of this peculiar train of thought, couched, as it is, in such similar phraseology, merely the result of an accident? Credat Judaeus Apella. Non ego.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.662"/>
          <p n="35">Still a caricature, by its very nature, cannot be a fair representation of the thing caricatured: and no one would gather from Praxagora's wild proposals any notion of the real tone and spirit of the great philosophers dream. Let us briefly touch upon some of the more salient points of difference between the two schemes.</p>
          <p n="36">And in the first place, the Platonic communism did not extend to the population at large, it was entirely confined to the , or guardians of the state. These were a specially selected class of (say) 1,000 persons, of whom the elder and wiser were to be the governors, and the remainder the military protectors of the New Republic. And the question which Plato set himself to solve was how he could best ensure that these guardians should faithfully fulfil the high duties assigned them, and not themselves become a danger to the citizens they were intended to protect. Plato knew no better way, and probably there was no better way, of achieving this end, than to detach them as far as possible not only from all human frailty and all human passion, but even from all human sympathies and associations however innocent in themselves. Every detail of their training and education is elaborated by Plato with extraordinary care. From their earliest infancy they were to be surrounded by no influences other than those of beauty and goodness, and to be anxiously preserved " from all evil thoughts which may assault and hurt the soul." And when they were grown up, and enrolled among the actual guardians, they were to stand in the position of the Christian knights of former times, who had taken upon them selves the vow of poverty. They were to renounce all private property, and the ties of a separate family and home: they were to live in common, and have all things in common. And thus, it was hoped, they would be free from all private interests and predilections, and be qualified to carry out with a single mind the duties which they were selected to perform.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.670"/>
          <p n="37">This then is the first great distinction between the system of Praxa gora and the system of Plato. The former applied to all the citizens for their own enjoyment; the latter only to a special class for the purpose of enabling them to fulfil more efficiently their special duties towards the state.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.704"/>
          <p n="38">And secondly even as regards this special class of guardians, there was nothing, until its members had passed their prime (which Plato limits to the age of fifty-five for a man, and of forty for a woman), in any way resembling that promiscuous intercourse between the sexes which formed so prominent a feature in the system of Praxagora. On the contrary, until that limit of age was reached 1, no intercourse whatever was permitted excepting under the sanction of marriage, a marriage solemnized amid sacrifices and choral hymns, and invested with all possible sanctity. It is true that the marriage was merely a temporary one; the pairs were brought together for marriage by a professed sortition, secretly overruled, if necessary, by the judgement of the , and on the next solemn marriage-sortition, the husband and wife would in all probability find themselves assorted with, and married to, different partners. But however unsatisfactory2 were the marriage laws of the Platonic Republic, however strangely they ignored the family, the true unit on which society is based, they were designed not to gratify, but to eradicate, all evil concupiscence and lust; to suppress all private desires and inclinations; to subordinate the feelings of the individual to the interests of the state. They were as far removed, as the east is from the west, from the universal licence accorded by the system of Praxagora. The guardians were to act, in all things, not as they themselves desired, but as the state prescribed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.725"/>
          <p n="39">It If somebody were to object," asks Adeimantus, when Socrates has unfolded his views on this topic, It that you are not giving your guardians a very happy life, what would you say to that?" "I should say," replies Socrates, It that it would not surprise me, if they were to be the happiest people in the world: but that however this may be, it is with a view not to the pre-eminent happiness of one particular class, but to the common happiness of the entire state, that we are building up our Republic."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.730"/>
          <p n="40">And, thirdly, it must never be forgotten that the Republic of Plato was avowedly an unattainable 1 ideal: a heavenly vision, to be cherished indeed in the soul as a counsel of perfection, but quite impracticable in the grosser atmosphere of the earth and amidst the sordid passions of mankind.</p>
          <p n="41">"You are speaking," says Glaucon to Socrates, at the close of the Ninth Book, "you are speaking of that Republic which we have just been creating, a Republic which exists indeed in theory, but which has no local habitation, I imagine, in any region of this earth." " But in heaven perchance," rejoins the Master, "a pattern is laid up for him that will see, and seeing will enrol himself a citizen therein. But whether it now exists, or shall hereafter exist, is a matter with which we need not concern ourselves; for be it real or be it not, by its maxims and by none other will a wise man order his goings." ITo that I readily assent," says Glaucon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.754"/>
          <p n="42">Even in the philosophic pages of the Republic these topics cannot be discussed without the introduction of much that is distasteful to a delicate mind, and this drawback is greatly increased when the subject is transferred to the comic stage. The old Attic Comedy was the direct outcome of the phallic1 songs, which were sung, as part of a religious ceremony, at the festivals of Dionysus; and an Athenian audience would never permit it to forget its origin, or to use other than the broadest and most plain-spoken language with regard to the relations of the sexes, and other matters on which we are happily now more reticent. Twice 2 at least, in the Clouds and in the Birds, Aristophanes endeavoured to lift the comic art into an altogether different atmosphere; but in each case, although to modern taste these are amongst the most brilliant and successful of his efforts, the play was refused the prize. The Athenians could not have objected to the Ecclesiazusae on that score ; and it seemed at first that there must be so many and such considerable gaps In the translation, including the omission of an entire scene, that it would have, like the translations of the Lysistrata and the Thesmophoriazusae, to folloto the Greek text, instead of appearing on the opposite page. Consequently various liberties were taken in the translation; some lines were omitted, and others inserted; it was not thought necessary to preserve with such accuracy as in other cases the exact meaning of the original; and, above all, the long Aristophanic lines, the special favourites of the poet, were unworthily represented by mere anapaestic dimeters. However the only other1 translation in English verse of which I am aware gives the play in its entirety; and ultimately, after much hesitation, it seemed possible to follow that example without giving any just cause of offence. And, indeed, the coarsest passages of Aristophanes are mere comic buffoonery, enacted in the open air, not by actors and actresses before a mixed audience of men and women, but by men only before the male population of Athens, no woman being present. They are broad and plain-spoken, but never morbid and seductive, and could not be injurious to anybody, who did not come to their study with a mind already corrupted and debased.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.770"/>
          <p n="43">As regards the observation just made that, at all events in the time of Aristophanes, no women were present at the performance of a comedy; it may be permissible to conclude this Introduction with a more minute examination of that question than it has hitherto received. And this seems the more desirable because a very able scholar, Mr. A. E. Haigh, in his most instructive and agreeable work " On the Attic Theatre," has recently expressed a contrary opinion.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.778"/>
          <p n="44">That the solution of the question is to be found, if anywhere, in the hints afforded by the comedies of Aristophanes appears to be universally acknowledged. It is certain that the indecorum of the comic stage would not have deterred Athenian women from attending its representations. An Athenian maid or matron, walking through the streets of her own city, could not choose but witness on every side, and indeed at every door, signs and symbols of (to Christian minds) " unspeakable pollution." The pure and honourable maiden, who obtained the coveted distinction of bearing the Holy Basket in the procession at the Dionysia, walked through the admiring crowds accompanied by symbols and songs of, what we should consider, the most appalling immodesty. Yet to them selves the question of decency or indecency would not even occur. It was their traditional religion; it was " the very orthodoxy of the myriads who had lived and died" in the city. And we know that ladies of all sorts and conditions attended the Roman Mimes 2, which had more than all the grossness, without the counterbalancing radiancy and patriotic elevation, of Athenian comedy. In discussing therefore the question before us the character of the entertainment is not a factor that requires to be taken into consideration. Nor must we be influenced in the opposite direction by the circumstance that in later times dramatic performances were regularly attended by men and women together; for the old Attic comedy was part of a religious festival, and in religious observances nothing was more common than the separation of the sexes. We must, therefore, approach the question without any a priori prejudice on the one side or on the other, and merely consider what Aristophanes tells us with regard to the composition of his audience.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.820"/>
          <p n="45">And twice, at least, he appears to enumerate the various classes of which the audience was composed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.838"/>
          <p n="46">In Peace 50-53 an actor is desirous of putting the audience in posses sion of the state of affairs at the commencement of the action; and he says, I will tell it to the loys, and to the mall men, and to the men, and to the most exalted men, and to the most overweeningly exalted men. He mentions males of every sort and condition, but he makes no allusion to women. See also lines 765, 766 of the same play.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.855"/>
          <p n="47">Just so in the play before us, 1141, 1144-1146, Praxagora's waiting- maid invites to the banquet all such of the audience as are well disposed to the play, V . Her master will not hear of any exceptions, and says, Why not invite them all and omit nobody, ? Why not freely ask old man, youth, and boy ? All the audience are to be invited, but again there is no mention of women.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.877"/>
          <p n="48">There are two other passages in the Ecclesiazusae which have some bearing on the subject. In lines 435-441, Chremes is telling Blepyrus that in the assembly a speaker (who was in reality Praxagora the wife of Blepyrus) had been saying everything in dispraise of men, and every thing in praise of women. "She called you," says he, " a rascal, a thief, a common informer !" " What, me only ?" asks Blepyrus. " You and the crowd there," To , explains Chremes. "' But the woman,' said the speaker, ' was a wit-fraught thing,' &amp;c." That by we are to understand the audience, is universally admitted, and is, indeed, obvious. Yet they are all treated as men, and all contrasted with women.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.921"/>
          <p n="49">In the rehearsal at the beginning of the play, one of the speakers, addressing the audience in the theatre as if they were the assembly in the Agora, commences her speech by saying, It seems to me, 0 women sitting there. Praxagora at once interrupts her, What in the world makes you call them women, when they are men ? Oh, says the other, it was all along of Epigonus there (pointing to an effeminate citizen); glancing his way, I really thought that I was speaking to women. Eccl. 165-168. There would have been no point in this sally if she was actually speaking to women as well as to men. Epigonus was doubtless the most womanlike object in the theatre then, as Cleisthenes had been thirty years before, at the time of the representation of the Clouds. There the Clouds are described as changing their form and figure in accordance with the objects they behold. Many instances are given. Yesterday they saw Cleonymus, , and assumed the appearance of timid deer ; to-day, they behold Cleisthenes amongst the audience, and change themselves into women. Clouds 348-355. The Clouds would behold in the theatre nothing more womanly than Cleisthenes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.937"/>
          <p n="50">That the audience are always described in the masculine gender, , is of course quite unimportant. But when Dicaeopolis commences his elaborate speech in the Achamians with the words ot (497), and Euelpides commences his explanation in the Birds with the words (30), is it con ceivable that they are either including women under the description of , or else addressing a section only of the audience ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.966"/>
          <p n="51">There is hardly a play wherein we do not find numerous passages which seem to take for granted that all the spectators are men, such as, for example, Knights 228 , the catechism in Clouds 1096-1104, the various appeals to the audience to take political proceedings, which men alone can take, of which the Parabasis of the Achamians and the Epirrhema and Antepirrhema of the Frogs are sufficient instances. Conversely, we find passages relating to women which seem to take for granted that they are not present in the theatre. Thus in the Antepirrhema to the first Parabasis of the Birds, the Birds are setting forth the many advantages of wings. And they say, amongst other things, " If a man is in love with a councillor's wife, and see the councillor in the theatre, he can fly off at once and pay court to the wife." They do not say, " If the councillor is in the theatre, and his wife is not;" the latter circumstance they take for granted.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1001"/>
          <p n="52">But perhaps the clearest and most convincing evidence is afforded by the Parabasis of the Thesmophoriazusae. The Chorus in that play represent Athenian matrons, and in the Parabasis they are turning to the audience, and pleading the cause of the women as against the men. And throughout their address they contrast the women sometimes with men in general and sometimes with the audience, quite indifferently, as though the two classes-the audience and the men—were for this purpose identical. "All men," they aver, "say that we are a plague" (and, indeed, this is a commonplace of Hellenic poetry). " Well, then, if we are a plague, why do YE," they say to the audience, " marry us, ; Why do ye forbid us to walk abroad, , &amp;c.? Why are ye so anxious to preserve a plague, TO ; " And after several similar observations, they propose a test. " We say that we are much better than you, , and this we will show by taking the name of an individual man and the name of an individual woman, and comparing them with each other." They accordingly make several witty comparisons, and conclude by saying . It was at the beginning, it is at the end. But, indeed, almost every line of the Parabasis postulates that the audience are all of the male sex.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1021"/>
          <p n="53">In every comedy of Aristophanes (with the exception of the Plutus) there are constant appeals to the audience; and frequently, as in Wasps 74-84, particular individuals are singled out for personal satire. Yet nowhere is there the slightest indication of the presence of a woman amongst the spectators. Contrast with this the case of Shakespeare. How rarely does he address the audience ! How plain he makes it that women, as well as men, were spectators of his plays!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1037"/>
          <p n="54">The passages cited might easily be doubled : and against them there is not a syllable1 to be set from the first line of the Acharnians to the last line of the Plutus. And there seems, therefore, no doubt that no women were present at the performance of any of these comedies.</p>
          <p n="55">Whether they were present at the representations of the later phases of Athenian comedy, is quite another matter, and on this point I express no opinion. But the two passages most commonly cited to prove their presence seem to be altogether beside the mark.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1071"/>
          <p n="56">Pollux (ix. 5. segm. 44), to illustrate the word , which, like the Latin cunem, meant one of the wedge-shaped sections into which the auditorium was cut by gangways ascending from the bottom to the top, quotes a couplet from the of Alexis, a poet of the Middle Comedy, Undoubtedly this looks as though the women were taking their seats in the theatre, seemingly as envoys from some foreign state. But this is in a , where everything is topsy-turvey, where the men and women have changed places, and the women undertake the duties, and enjoy the privileges, which under other forms of government would be undertaken and enjoyed by the men. In line 460 of the Ecclesiazusae it is announced that the wife, and not the husband, will henceforth attend the dicastery; and had the subject been pursued, it would doubtless have been elicited that the wife, and not the husband, was thenceforth to attend the theatre. No inference can be drawn from this passage as to the attendance of women at the Athenian theatre.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1112"/>
          <p n="57">The other passage comes from the Epistles of Alciphron, a writer of great wit and ingenuity, in many respects closely resembling Lucian. He composed various fictitious letters, generally between fictitious people, but sometimes he selected historical personages to be his assumed cor respondents. And one of his letters is feigned to be written by Menander to his mistress Glycera, on his receiving a summons to attend the Court of King Ptolemy in Egypt. And Alciphron makes the great comedian say that no diadem which Ptolemy can give him is to be compared with the ivy-wreaths with which he has so often been crowned at the Dionysia' "whilst Glycera. was looking on, and sitting in the theatre," . Now if this passage stood alone, we might consider it "conclusive proof," not indeed, as Mr. Haigh says, " that women were present at the New Comedy," but that Alciphron who flourished, probably, 500 or 600 years afterwards, was of that opinion. But the passage does not stand alone. Alciphron also composed an answer from Glycera to Menander's supposed letter. And he makes her say, " What is Menander without his Glycera, who gets ready his masks, and arrays him in his actors robes, and stands in the " (the wings from which the actors entered the stage) " nervously pinching her fingers, until the theatre breaks out into ringing applause, and then trembling all over, by Artemis, she revives, and clasps him in her embrace ? " Is it not plain that Alciphron pictured Glycera not amongst the audience, but in the wings of the theatre; not only not amongst the audience, but not even in their sight ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1155"/>
          <p n="58">These passages, therefore, seem to have no bearing on the question, whether women did or did not sit as spectators in the Athenian theatre, during the representation of what are known as the Middle and the New Comedies.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="59">EASTWOOD, STRAWBERRY HILL, October, 1901.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
