<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moschus, Idylls</title>
        <author>Moschus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0035.tlg002.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">1‘ My son Eros,' Venus was loudly calling, 'Eros, if any one has seen straying in the cross-roads, he is my runaway: the informer shall have a reward. The kiss of Venus shall be your pay; and if you shall have brought him, not the 2 bare kiss, but, stranger, you shall have even more: now the lad is very notable; you would know him among 3twenty together: in complexion indeed he is not fair, but like to fire; and his eyes are piercing and fiery-red: evil his heart, pleasant his speech. For he does not speak the same as he thinks; his voice is as honey, 4but if he be wroth, his mind is ruthless; deceiving, telling truth in nothing, wily child, he 5 sports cruelly. His head has goodly curls, but "impudent is the face he wears: his little hands are tiny, 'tis true, yet they shoot far; shoot even to Acheron, and to the king of Hades. He is naked indeed so far as his body is concerned, but his mind is 7 shrouded. And being winged, as a bird, he flies upon now one party of men and women and now another, and settles on their inmost hearts. He has a very small bow, and upon the bow an arrow: small is his arrow, yet it carries even to the sky: and a golden quiver above his back, and within it are the bitter shafts, with which he often wounds even me. All, all is cruel; but far most a little torch that he has, 8with which he kindles the sun himself. If you at any rate shall have caught him, bind and bring him, and do not pity him. And if ever you shall have seen him weeping, be ware lest he beguile you ; and if he smile, do you drag him on : and if he should desire to kiss you, avoid it; his kiss is mischievous, 9his lips poison. But should he say, ‘ Take these, I present thee all the arms I have,' do not touch them, de ceitful gifts; for they have all been dipt in fire.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">My mother, why dost thou thus wound thy spirit, being sad beyond measure, and why is the former bloom no longer preserved on thy cheeks ? Why, I pray thee, art thou vexed so much? Is it in sooth because thine illustrious son suffers countless annoyances from 1 a man of no account, even as a lion from a fawn ? Alas me I why then have the immortal gods thus so far dishonoured me ? why then did my parents beget me to a fate thus adverse ? Ill-fated am I, who, since I have come to the bed of a faultless hero, whom I did honour indeed like my own eyes, ay, even now both worship and reverence him in my heart. But than him has no other of living beings been more ill-starred, or tasted so many cares in his own thoughts ; wretched man, who with the 2bow and arrows, which Apollo himself had provided for him, dire weapons either of one of the Fates, or of Erinnys, 3 slew his own children, and robbed them of their dear life, as he raged about his house, and it was full of slaughter. Them indeed I, wretched woman, beheld with mine own eyes, stricken by their father; and this bath befallen no other even in a dream: nor was I able to succour them, though they loudly called upon their mother; for re sistless evil was nigh. 4 And even as a bird laments over her nestlings as they perish, which while still in infancy a fierce snake devours amid the thick bushes, while she, kind mother, hovers over them shrieking very shrilly, yet is not able, I ween, to succour her children ; for in truth, she herself hath a great dread of coming nigher to the ruthless monster; so I, most wretched mother, wailing for mine own offspring, with frantic feet kept running to and fro through my house fre quently. Yes, and would that dying along with my children I too had lain low, having through my heart a poisonous arrow, thou, Artemis, mighty ruler to women, the gentler beings. So, when they had mourned for us, would our parents with their own hands have placed us on a common pile with many funeral honours; and having collected into one golden urn the bones of all, would have buried us, where we first were born. But now they indeed inhabit horse-breeding Thebes, plough ing the deep rich 5 clods of the Aonian plain ; but I at Tiryns, Juno's rocky city, wretched woman that I am, am ever in the same manner wounded at heart by many griefs; and there is present to me no rest from tears. But my husband indeed I behold with mine eyes only for a brief space in our house; for a work is prepared for him of many labours, at which he toils, as he roams over land and sea, yes, for he has within his breast a strong heart of iron or stone; 6 but thou meltest away like water, weeping both at night, and as many days as come from Jove. None other, however, of my kinsfolk can stand by and comfort me; for it is not a wall between houses that shuts them in; no! but all dwell right beyond the 7piny Isthmus: nor have I to whom, having looked, as an ill-fated woman, I could unfold my heart, except at least, 'tis true, my sister Pyrrha: but she herself, too, is grieving more about her husband, thy son, 8 Iphiclus; for most woeful children of all I deem that you have borne both to a god and a mortal man. Thus in sooth spake she : and 9the warmer tears poured the more down from her eyelids on her lovely bosom, as she called to mind her children, and her own parents afterwards. And in like manner Alcmena was 10bedewing her white cheeks with tears; and deeply while she groaned even from her heart, with wise words thus did she reply to her dear daughter-in-law: 11 Unhappy in thy children, why then, I pray, bath this fallen upon thy sharp thoughts ? how is it that thou wishest to disturb us both, by speaking of our unceasing sorrows ? for not now have they been wept for the first time. Are not the woes enough, in which we are involved as they arise, ever and anon, each second day? Yes, fond indeed of laments would be the man, who 12 would wish to add to the numbei of our woes. Cheer up then! such fate as this we have met by Heaven's behest; and in truth I see thee, dear child, la bouring under unabating griefs: yet I am ready to pardon your woe; for in fact I suppose 13 even of joy there is satiety. And I very exceedingly lament and pity thee, for that thou hast partaken of our dismal destiny, which also hangs heavily over our heads. For be Proserpine and richly-robed Demeter witnesses, (by whom with great hurt to himself would any of our foes Swear wilfully a false oath,) that in mine heart I love thee not a whit less, than if thou hadst come from out my womb, and wert to me in mine house a 14late-born daughter: nor do I imagine that, for thine own part, this at any rate altogether escapes thee. Wherefore say not ever,15 my young shoot, that I care not for thee, not even if I wail more con stantly than fair-haired Niobe: for 'tis no cause of blame for a mother to weep over an afflicted son: since for ten months did I labour, before even I first beheld him, whilst I had him in my womb, and he brought me near to 16 Hell's gate-keeper Pluto; so severe throes did I endure when about to travail hard with him. But now my son is gone to accomplish a fresh toil on a foreign land, nor know I, ill-starred woman, whether I shall welcome him again having returned hither, or not. And besides also a fearful dream has scared me during sweet sleep; and I fear exceedingly, having seen a hurtful vision, lest it betide something untoward to my chil dren. For my son, stout Hercules, seemed to me to hold in both his hands a well-made spade, with which he was delving, as one that had taken the work for hire, a dyke at the outskirt of some flourishing field, stripped, without cloak, and well girdled tunic: but when he had arrived at the end of all the work, labouring at the strong fence of a levelled plot for vines, in truth, he was about, having placed his 17shovel upon the projecting raised bank, to put on the garments, in which he had been clad before; when, on a sudden, above the deep trench there blazed up a fierce fire, and a vast flame was gathering round him: but he kept ever drawing back with swift feet, desiring to escape the destructive weapon of He phaestus ; and continually in front of his person he was brand ishing, as a 18 shield, his spade: and with his eyes he kept looking around hither and thither, lest in truth the hostile fire should burn him. High-souled Iphiclus, desiring, as me thought, to lend him help, tripped and fell upon the ground, ay, before he came up to him: nor could he raise himself erect again, but lay 19 still, like a feeble old man, whom even against his will joyless age has forced to fall; and there he lies fixedly on the ground, till some passer-by maintaining 20 ancient re verence for the hoary beard, has upraised him by the hand ; so on the ground had spear-brandishing Iphiclus 21 fallen. But as I beheld my two sons in sore distress, I did weep, till sound sleep at length was dispelled from mine eyes, and forth with bright dawn came. Such dreams, dear one, have thoroughly affrighted my mind all night long : 22 but may they all turn from our house upon Eurystheus ; and may my spirit become a prophet to him, nor fate accomplish otherwise aught else.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">SWEET is the music which the whispering pine Makes to the murmuring fountains; sweet is thine, Breathed from the pipe: the second prize thy due— To Pan, the horned ram; to thee, the ewe; And thine the yearling, when the ewe he takes- A savoury mess the tender yearling makes. Sweeter thy song than yonder gliding down Of water from the rock's o'erhanging crown ; If a ewe-sheep for fee the Muses gain, Thou, shepherd! shalt a stall-fed lamb obtain ; But if it rather please the tuneful Nine To take the lamb, the ewe shall then be thine. 0 wilt thou, for the Nymphs’ sake, goatherd ! fill Thy pipe with music on this sloping hill, Where grow the tamarisks ? wilt sit, dear friend, And play for me, while I thy goats attend ? We must not pipe at noon in any case; For then Pan rests him, wearied from the chase. Him, quick to wrath we fear, as us befits; On his keen nostril sharp gall ever sits. But thou-to thee the griefs of Daphnis known, And the first skill in pastoral song thine own- Come to yon elm, into whose shelter deep Afront Priapus and the Naiads peep- Where the thick oaks stand round the shepherd's seat There, sitting with me in that cool retreat, If thou wilt sing, as when thou didst contest With Libyan Chromis which could sing the best, Thine, Thyrsis, this twin-bearing goat shall be, That fills two milk-pails thrice a-day for me ; And this deep ivy-cup with sweetest wax Bedewed, twin-eared, that of the graver smacks. Around its lips lush ivy twines on high, Sprinkled with drops of bright cassidony ; And as the curling ivy spreads around, On every curl the saffron fruit is found. With flowing robe and Lydian head-dress on, Within, a woman to the life is done- An exquisite design ! on either side Two men with flowing locks each other chide, By turns contending for the woman's love, But not a whit her mind their pleadings move. One while she gives to this a glance and smile, And turns and smiles on that another while. But neither any certain favour gains- Only their eyes are swollen for their pains. Hard by, a rugged rock and fisher old, Who drags a mighty net, and seems to hold, Preparing for the cast: he stands to sight, A fisher putting forth his utmost might. A youth's strength in the gray-head seems to dwell, So much the sinews of his neck outswell. And near that old man with his sea-tanned hue, With purple'grapes a vineyard shines to view. A little boy sits by the thorn-hedge trim, To watch the grapes-two foxes watching him: One through the ranges of the vines proceeds, And on the hanging vintage slyly feeds ; The other plots and vows his scrip to search, And for his breakfast leave him—in the lurch. Meanwhile he twines and to a rush fits well A locust trap with stalks of asphodel; And twines away with such absorbing glee, Of scrip or vines he never thinks-not be ! The juicy curled acanthus hovers round Th' Æoliancup-when seen a marvel found. Hither a Calydonian skipper brought it, For a great cheese-cake and a goat I bought it; Untouched by lip—this cup shall be thy hire, If thou wilt sing that song of sweet desire. I envy not: begin ! the strain outpour ; 'Twill not be thine on dim Oblivion's shore. Begin, dear Muses ! the bucolic strain ; For Thyrsis sings, your own Ætneän swain. Where were ye, Nymphs ! when Daphnis pined away, Where through his Tempe Peneus loves to stray, Or Pindus lifts himself ? Ye Were not here- Where broad Anapus flows or Acis clear, Or where tall Ætna looks out on the main. Begin, dear Muses ! the bucolic strain. From out the mountain-lair the lions growled, Wailing his death-the wolves and jackals howled Begin, dear Muses ! the bucolic strain : Around him in a long and mournful train, Sad-faced, a number of the horned kind, Heifers, bulls, cows, and calves, lamenting pined. First Hermes from the mountain came and said, " Daphnis, by whom art thou disquieted ? For whom dost thou endure so fierce a flame ?" Then cowherds, goatherds, shepherds, thronging came, And asked what ailed him. E'en Priapus went, And said : " Sad Daphnis, why this languishment ? In every grove, by fountains, far and near, Thee the loved girl is seeking every where. Ah, foolish lover ! to thyself unkind, Miscalled a cowherd, with a goatherd's mind ! The goatherd when he sees his goats at play, Envies their wanton sport and pines away. And thou at sight of virgins, when they smile, Dost look with longing eyes and pine the while, Because with them the dance thou dost not lead." No word he answered, but his grief did feed, And brought to end his love, that held him fast, And only ended with his life at last. Then Cypris came-the queen of soft desire, Smiling in secret, but pretending ire, And said : "To conquer love did Daphnis boast, But, Daphnis ! is not love now uppermost ?" Her answered he : " Thou cruel sorrow-feeder ! Curst Cypris ! mankind's hateful mischief-breeder ! 'Tis plain my sun is set: but I shall show The blight of love in Hades' house below. ‘Where Cypris kiss'd a cowherd’—men will speak— Hasten to Ida ! thine Anchises seek. Around their hives swarmed bees are humming here, Here the low galingale—thick oaks are there. Adonis, the fair youth, a shepherd too, Wounds hares, and doth all savage beasts pursue. Go ! challenge Diomede to fight with thee 'I tame the cowherd Daphnis, fight with me.' " Ye bears, who in the mountain hollows dwell, Ye tawny jackals, bounding wolves, farewell! The cowherd Daphnis never more shall rove In quest of you through thicket, wood, and grove. Farewell, ye rivers, that your streams profuse From Thymbris pour ; farewell, sweet Arethuse ! I drove my kine—a cowherd whilom here- To pleasant pasture, and to water clear. Pan ! Pan ! if seated on a jagged peak Of tall Lycæus now ; or thou dost seek The heights of Mænalus—leave them awhile, And hasten to thy own Sicilian isle. The tomb, which e'en the gods admire, leave now- Lycaon's tomb and Helice's tall brow. Hasten, my king ! and take this pipe that clips, Uttering its honey breath, the player's lips. For even now, dragged downward, must I go, By love dragged down to Hades' house below. Now violets, ye thorns and brambles bear ! Narcissus now on junipers appear ! And on the pine-tree pears ! since Daphnis dies, To their own use all things be contraries ! The stag trail hounds ; in rivalry their song The mountain owls with nightingales prolong !" He said, and ceased: and Cypris wished, indeed, To raise him up, but she could not succeed ; His fate-allotted threads of life were spent, And Daphnis to the doleful river went. The whirlpool gorged him—by the Nymphs not scorned,, Dear to the Muses, and by them adorned. Cease! cease, ye Muses! the bucolic strain. Give me the cup and goat that I may drain The pure milk from her ; and, for duty's sake, A due libation to the Muses make. All hail, ye Muses ! hail, and favour me, And my hereafter song shall sweeter be. Honey and honey-combs melt in thy mouth, And figs from Ægilus! for thou, dear youth, The musical cicada dost excel. Behold the cup ! how sweetly doth it smell ! ' Twill seem to thee as though the lovely Hours Had newly dipt it in their fountain-showers. Hither, Cissætha !milk her !yearling friskers, Forbear-behold the ram's huge beard and whiskers !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">I AND the Loves Adonis dead deplore: The beautiful Adonis is indeed Departed, parted from us. Sleep no more In purple, Cypris ! but in watchet weed, All-wretched! beat thy breast and all aread— " Adonis is no more." The Loves and I Lament him. Oh ! her grief to see him bleed, Smitten by white tooth on his whiter thigh, Out-breathing life's faint sugh upon the mountain high! Adown his snowy flesh drops the black gore ; Stiffen beneath his brow his sightless eyes; The rose is off his lip ; with him no more Lives Cytherea's kiss-but with him dies. He knows not that her lip his cold lip tries, But she finds pleasure still in kissing him. Deep is his thigh-wound ; hers yet deeper lies, E'en in her heart. The Oread's eyes are dim; His hounds whine piteously ; in most disordered trim, Distraught, unkempt, unsandalled, Cypris rushes Madly along the tangled thicket-steep ; Her sacred blood is drawn by bramble-bushes ; Her skin is torn; with wailings wild and deep She wanders through the valley's weary sweep, Calling her boy-spouse, her Assyrian fere. But from his thigh the purple jet doth leap Up to his snowy navel; on the clear Whiteness beneath his paps the deep-red streaks appear. " Alas for Cypris !" sigh the Loves, " deprived Of her fair spouse, she lost her beauty's pride; Cypris was lovely whilst Adonis lived, But with Adonis all her beauty died." Mountains, and oaks, and streams, that broadly glide, Or wail or weep for her; in tearful rills For her gush fountains from the mountain side ; Redden the flowers from grief; city and hills With ditties sadly wild, lorn Cytherea fills. Alas for Cypris ! dead is her Adonis, And Echo " dead Adonis " doth resound. Who would not grieve for her whose love so lone is ? But when she saw his cruel, cruel wound, The purple gore that ran his wan thigh round, She spread her arms, and lowly murmured: " Stay thee, That I may find thee as before I found, My hapless own Adonis ! and embay thee, And mingle lips with lips, whilst in my arms I lay thee. “Up for a little ! kiss me back again The latest kiss-brie as itself that dies In being breathed, until I fondly "drain"" The last breath of my soul, and greedy-wise Drink it into my core. I will devise To guard it as Adonis-since from me To Acheron my own Adonis flies, And to the drear dread king; but I must be A goddess still and live, nor can I follow thee. " But thou, Persephona! my spouse receive, Mightier than I, since to thy chamber drear All bloom of beauty falls: but I must grieve Unceasingly. I have a jealous fear Of thee, and weep for him. My dearest dear! Art dead, indeed ? away my love did fly, E'en as a dream. At home my widowed cheer Keeps the Loves idle; with thy latest sigh My cestus perished too; thou rash one ! why, oh why " Did'st hunt? so fair, contend with monsters grim?" Thus Cypris wailed ; but dead Adonis lies ; For every gout of blood that fell from him, She drops a tear; sweet flowers each dew supplies- Roses his blood, her tears anemonies. Cypris ! no longer in the thickets weep ; The couch is furnished! there in loving guise Upon thy proper bed, that odorous heap, The lovely body lies-how lovely! as in sleep. Come ! in those softest vestments now array him In which he slept the live-long night with thee ; And in the golden settle gently lay him,— A sad, yet lovely sight; and let him be High heaped with flowers ; though withered all when he Surceased. With essences him sprinkle o'er And ointments ; let them perish utterly, Since he, who was thy sweetest, is no more. He lies in purple ; him the weeping Loves deplore. Their curls are shorn : one breaks his bow ; another His arrows and the quiver ; this unstrings, And takes Adonis' sandal off; his brother In golden urn the fountain water brings ; This bathes his thighs; that fans him with his wings. The Loves, " Alas for Cypris !” weeping say: Hymen hath quenched his torches ; shreds and flings The marriage wreath away ; and for the lay Of love is only heard the doleful " weal-away. Yet more than Hymen for Adonis weep The Graces ; shriller than Dione vent Their shrieks; for him the Muses wail and keep Singing the songs he hears not, with intent To call him back: and would the nymph relent, How willingly would he the Muses hear! Hush! hush ! to-day, sad Cypris and consent To spare thyself-no more thy bosom tear- For thou must wail again, and weep another year.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <p n="1">HER Eros thus proclaimed the Cyprian Queen " If any one has in the highway seen My straying Eros, and reports to me His whereabouts, he shall rewarded be; A kiss for him ; but if it shall betide One bring him me, a kiss-and more beside. Midst twenty he is notable to view; Not fair, but flamy, is his dazzling hue ; Sharp are his eyes, and flame their glances fleet; His mind is wicked, but his speech is sweet. His word and meaning are not like at all ; His word is honey, and his meaning gall. He is a mischievous, deceitful child ; Beguiles with falsehood, laughs at the beguiled. He has a lovely head of curling hair, But saucy features, with a reckless stare. His hands are tiny, but afar they throw, E'en down to Dis and Acheron below. Naked his form, his mind in covert lies; Winged as a feathered bird, he careless flies From girls to boys, from men to women flits, Sports with their heart-strings, on their vitals sits. Small is his bow, his arrow small to sight, But to Jove's court it wings its ready flight. Upon his back a golden quiver sounds, Full of sharp darts, with which e'en me he-wounds. All cruel things by cruel Love are done ; His torch is small, yet scorches e'en the sun. But should you take him—fast and safely bind him, And bring him to me with his hands behind him. If he should weep, take heed-he weeps at will; But should he smile--then drag him faster still And should he offer you a kiss, beware ! Evil his kiss, his red lips poisoned are ! And should he say, with seeming friendship hot, ' Accept my bow and arrows,' touch them not ! Tears, smiles, words, gifts, deceitful wiles inspire, And every thing he has is dipt in fire."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="2">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <p n="1">VENUS once sent upon Europa a sweet dream, what time the third portion of night sets in, and dawn is near; what time sleep sweeter than honey settling on the eyelids, limb-relaxing though it is, fetters down the eyes with soft bond; 2what time moreover the tribe of truthful dreams is roving abroad. Then as she slumbered in a chamber next the roof, the daugh ter of Phoenix, yet a maiden, Europa, fancied 3 that two conti nents were contending for her, Asia and the opposite coast, and they were in shape as women. Now of these the one had the form of a foreign woman, whilst the other in truth re sembled a native, and hugged her more closely as her own child; and kept saying that she-was her mother, and that herself had nurtured her. But the other, using violence with strong hands, was drawing her away, nothing loth: for she said that 'twas fated by ægis-bearing Jove that Europa should be her prize. She then started in affright from 4her strown couch, quak in- at heart, for she had beheld the dream as a real appear ance ; and seating herself she kept silence a long time, yet still had she before her waking eyes both the women. And late at length the maiden uplifted a timid voice, Who of the ce lestials has sent upon me such phantoms ? What manner of dreams are these which have exceedingly scared me, as I slumbered right sweetly in my chamber on my strown couch ? And who was that foreign woman, whom I beheld in my sleep? How did a yearning toward her strike me at heart! How graciously did she too welcome me, and regard me as her own child! But may the blessed gods decide the dream to me for good.' Thus saying, she sprang up; and went to seek her dear companions, in the prime of life, 'her equals in years, well-pleasing, and nobly-born, with whom she was ever wont to sport, 5when she was making ready for the choir, or when she might be washing her skin at the mouths of 6the Anaurus, or whensoever 7 she might be culling odorous lilies from the mead. And these quickly showed themselves to her, and they had each in their hands a basket for-holding-flowers; and they proceeded to go to the meadows by-the-shore, where too they were ever wont to gather themselves in one troop, delighting both in the growth of the roses and in the roaring of the sea. But Europa herself was carrying a basket wrought of gold, and ad mirable, a great wonder, a great work of Hephæstus, which he had bestowed on 8 Libya as a gift, when she went to the bed of the Earth-shaker; and she gave it to very-beauteous Telephas sa, who was of near kin to her; and upon Europa, yet unwed ded, her mother, Telephassa, bestowed it as a famous present. Whereon many sparkling curious-works had been wrought; on it indeed was wrought 9 of gold Io the daughter of Inachus, while still a heifer, and she had not the figure of a woman. And frantic she was going afoot over the briny paths, like unto one swimming; and a sea had been wrought of dark blue. And aloft, upon the brow of the shore, were standing two men together, and they were watching the sea-traversing heifer. On it moreover was 10Jupiter, son of Saturn, patting gently with his hand the heifer daughter of Inachus, whom beside seven-mouthed Nile he was transforming again to a woman from a horned cow. Of silver indeed was the stream of Nile; and the heifer, I ween, of brass; but Jove himself was fashioned of gold. 11 And about the crown of the rounded basket Hermes had been formed ; and near to him Argus had been represented stretched, distinguished by his sleepless eyes ; and from his deep-red blood was springing up a bird exulting in the many-hued colour of his wings, having spread wide the plumage of his tail, and like some ship speeding through the sea, he was covering all round with feathers the rims of the golden basket. Such was very-beauteous Europa's basket. Now these, when in truth they had entered the flowery meads, were then pleasing their fancy each with various kinds of flowers; one of them was plucking odorous narcissus, another hyacinth, another the violet, and another the creeping thyme: and on the ground were falling many leaves of spring-nursed 12 meadows. But others again were culling in rivalry incense-laden tufts of yellow crocus; in the midst however stood the princess, gathering with her hands the beauty of the bright-red rose, 13like as foam-born Venus shone conspicuous among the Graces. Not long however was she destined to please her fancy on flowers, or to 14 preserve, I wot, her virgin zone undefiled. For of a truth the son of Saturn, when he observed her, had then been smitten at heart, subdued by the unforeseen darts of Venus, who alone can overcome even Jove: wherefore now, both as desiring-to- avoid the wrath of jealous Here, and wishing to beguile the young fancy of the maiden, he concealed the god, and trans formed his body, 15 and became a bull; not such a one as feeds in the stalls, nor indeed such a one as cleaves a furrow, drag ging the curved plough; nor like one that grazes in the herds, no, nor of such a kind as the bull that is tamed and draws the heavy-laden wain. But of a truth the rest of his body was chestnut-coloured, whilst a silvery ring was gleaming on his mid forehead, and his eyes were 16 sparkling from under, flashing through desire; and horns equal one to the other were branching up from his head, like orbs of the horned moon, her disc cut in half; so came he into the meadow, and did not alarm the maidens by his appearance: 17but a longing to draw near to him arose in all, and to touch the lovely bull; for his divine scent from afar surpassed even the sweet odour of the meadow. And he stood before the feet of faultless Europa, and began to lick her neck, and to soften the maiden's heart. Then would she stroke him, and gently with her hands wipe off from his lips much foam, and she kissed the bull. But he 18 lowed softly: you might say that you heard a 19Mygdonian flute, uttering distinctly a clear sound; then he bent the knee before her feet, and began to look keenly on Europa, with his neck turned towards her, and to display to her his broad back. Then she bespoke her maidens with-thick-falling hair thus, ‘ Come, dear playmates of like age, that we may delight ourselves in sitting on the bull here; for in sooth he will spread his back beneath us, and take us all up, even as a ship; mild is he to look upon, and gentle, nor is he at all like to other bulls ; 20 and a right mind, as of a man, surrounds him, and he wants but speech.' Thus saying, 21 she took her seat smilingly on his back ; and the rest were about to do so; when straightway the bull sprang up, having carried off her whom he wished, and speedily he came to the sea. But she having turned her round began to call her dear companions, outstretching her hands; and they could not reach her, for having set foot on the strand he ran forward as a dolphin, and the Nereids emerged from out the brine, ay, the whole of them, I wot, arrayed themselves in line, 22 sitting on the backs of whales. And moreover heavily-roaring Earth-shaker himself above the sea, levelling the waves, led the briny way for his brother; and 23 the Tritons, dwellers in deep-flowing ocean, were gathered round him, sounding on long conches a nuptial melody. But she truly, sitting on the bull-like shoulders of Jupiter, with one hand indeed kept holding the bull's long horn, whilst in the other hand she was drawing back the folds of her purple-flowing robe, in order that the countless spray of the hoary brine might not wet the skirt of it when drawn towards her. Now the deep robe of Europa had been formed into loose folds at the shoulders, like the sail of a ship, and was wont to lighten the maiden. But when at length she was far from her fatherland, and 24 there appeared neither any sea- dashed shore, nor tall mountain, but air indeed above, and boundless ocean beneath, peering round about her, she gave vent to words like these: ‘ Whither bearest thou me, divine bull ? Who art thou ? Or how dost thou traverse the way 25 with untiring feet, and yet not shudder at the sea ? For by swift ships the sea is overrun, but bulls dread the briny path. What kind of drink is sweet to thee ? what food wilt thou get from the sea ? Art thou in truth, I wonder, some god ? For 26 thou dost acts beseeming the gods. Neither do marine dolphins walk upon land, nor bulls in any wise on the sea. But thou rushest unwetted over land and sea, and thine 27 hoofs are oars to thee. Nay, haply also lifted aloft above the azure air, thou wilt take flight, resembling swift birds. Ah me! ill-fated assuredly in a high degree; 28even I who, having left afar my father's house, and followed this bull, am pursuing a strange voyage, and roaming alone. But mayest thou, earth-shaking regent of the hoary sea, graciously light upon me ! I hope to behold this god directing my voyage, as my forerunner. For not without a god's help do I traverse these watery paths.' Thus spake she; and her the broad homed bull addressed thus: 'Take heart, maiden, fear not ocean's billow: I myself, look you, am Jove, though near at hand I seem to be a bull; yes, for I am able to appear whatso ever I choose. Now desire of thee hath impelled me to measure so much sea, taking the appearance of a bull: but Crete shall receive thee presently, Crete, which reared even myself; where shall be thy nuptials: and by me thou shalt bear illustrious sons, who shall all of them be sceptre-bearers among the dwellers upon earth. So said he: and what he said found fulfilment: Crete indeed at length appeared: and Jove again assumed his own form. And he loosed her girdle, and the 29 Hours prepared her bed, and she who was aforetime a maiden became presently bride of Jove. 30 And she bore sons to Jove and became a mother forthwith. [In connexion with this Idyll, Ovid Met. vi. 103, and Fast. v. 605— 612, may be read with advantage. See Chapman's notes.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <p n="1">WHERE are the laurels ? where the philters ? roll The finest purple wool around the bowl. Quick ! Thestylis, that I with charms may bind The man I love, but faithless and unkind. This is the twelfth day he my sight hath fled, And knows not whether I be quick or dead; The twelfth day since he cross'd my threshold o'er, Nor, cruel! once hath knocked upon my door, In all that time. His fancy, apt to change, Cypris and Love have elsewhere made to range. I'll go-to see and chide him for my sorrow- To Timagetus' wrestling-school to-morrow. Now will I charm him with the magic rite: Come forth, thou Moon! with thy propitious light; Cold, silent goddess ! at this witching hour To thee I'll chant, and to th' Infernal Power, Dread Hecate; whom, coming through the mounds Of blood-swoln corses, flee the trembling hounds. Hail, Hecate ! prodigious demon, hail! Come at the last, and make the work prevail; That this strong brewage may perform its part No worse than that was made by Circe's art, By bold Medea, terrible as fair, Or Perimeda of the golden hair. Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! First in the fire is burnt the barley meal; Quick ! Thestylis, quick ! sprinkle more-yet more; Wretch ! wither do thine idle fancies soar ? Am I thy scorn and mock ? sprinkle and say " The bones of Delphis thus I shred away." Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! Delphis has made me fiercest tortures feel; I burn the laurel over Delphis now: As crackles loud the kindled laurel bough, Blazes, and e'en its dust we not discern- So may the flesh of Delphis dropping burn ! Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! As by the help divine, which I appeal, I melt this wax, may Myndian Delphis melt! As whirls this wheel, may he, love's impulse felt, At my forsaken door be made to reel! Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! Bran now I offer: thou, Queen Artemis ! Canst move aught firm, e'en Adamantine Dis. Hark! the dogs howl; the goddess now doth pass The cross-roads through: ring, ring the sounding brass! Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! The sea is silent; not a breath doth steal Over the stillness; but the troubled din Of passion is not hushed my heart within; I burn for him, who hath defamed my life, Undone a virgin, made me not his wife. Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! Thrice the libation poured, I thrice unseal My lips, August One ! thrice these words I speak ; Whoever lies with Delphis, cheek by cheek, May he forget her so much as they say Theseus forgot, and left in Dia's bay The bright-haired Ariadne—fast away Sailing from Dia with his rapid keel. Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! A little herb in Arcady there grows, Which colts and mares doth strangely discompose, (Hence called Hippomanes) ; for this they skurry O'er mountain-ranges with a frantic hurry: Thus from the wrestling-school, all bright with oil, May Delphis madly rush-with thoughts that boil; May he for me this maddening passion feel! Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! This fringe he dropt, that ran his cloak across, I tear, and to the furious fire I toss. Ah, love! ah, cruel love! why dost outsuck All of my blood, like marsh-leech firmly stuck ? Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! A draught whose ill none antidote can heal From a bruised lizard I'll to-morrow make: Now, Thestylis, this poisonous brewage take, And smear his threshold-there my mind must be, As thereto bound; but he cares not for me: And having smeared the door-way, spitting there, Then say, " The bones of Delphis thus I smear." Him hither, hither draw, my magic wheel! How, left alone, shall I with sorrow deal ? Or where begin with my grief-plighted thought ? Who first on me this love-this mischief brought ? Anaxo came, on whom it fell this year The basket to Diana's grove to bear: She came for me and told me, in the show 'Mid many a beast a lioness would go. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: Theucharila, whose life did lately end, My Thracian nurse, now numbered with the blest, Came also to me, prayed me, strongly prest To go and look upon the splendid show. At last I went—ah, doomed to bitter woe ! My linen tunic, never worn before, And Clearista's glistering robe I wore. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: Whilst I along the public road did wend, Midway by Lycon's house, I saw, alas ! Delphis and youthful Eudamippus pass. The beards of both were of a yellower dye Than the bright gold-bedropt cassidony. Twain wrestlers, lately breathed, their breasts, bright Queen ! Outshone the sparkles of thy golden sheen. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: I saw, loved, maddened! raging love did rend My very soul; my bloom of beauty bright Withered at once as by a sudden blight: The pomp I saw not passing in my view, And how I reached my home I never knew ; A fiery torment on my vitals fed; Ten days and nights I lay upon my bed. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: Such hues and juices of the thapsus lend Gloomed on my cheek ; off dropt my crown of hair; I was but skin and bones; in my despair Whom sought I not ? what magic-dealing crone Consulted not ? but I found help from none: On hastened time, that brings all things to end. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: Then to my hand-maid I revealed my mind; " Some remedy for ray sore sickness find ; I pine for, dote upon, the Myndian youth, Am altogether his in very sooth; At Timagetus' school watch, bring him me, For there he visits-there he loves to be. And when you see him from the rest apart, Then nod and softly whisper him, Sweetheart! Simætha calls you’—guide him here, my friend." Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend: She went and found the remedy I sought, And to my house the blooming Delphis brought. But when I saw him o'er my threshold-sill Pass with light foot, I sudden grew more chill Than wintry snow; and from my forehead burst Sweat like the dew the melting South hath nurst; I could not utter—e’en the murmur fine That sleeping infants to their mothers whine; Senseless I stiffened in my strange affright, Like a wax-doll, the girl-child's dear delight. Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend : The heartless minion first on me did bend His eager eyes, then sitting on the bed He turned them on the ground, and softly said :— “In calling me before I came self-moved, Thou hast as much outpast me, my beloved, As I did lately with swift foot out-pace The beautiful Philinus in the race."- (Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend:) " For, by sweet Eros ! with a second friend, Or with a third, I should have come to-night, Bringing sweet apples, crowned with poplar white, Careful the wreath with purple stripes to blend:" (Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend:) " Had you received me—well ;for me, 'mid all, The handsome, active bachelor they call; A kiss from those rich lips, that sweetly pout, Had been enough ; but had you shut me out, And your barred doors had interposed delay, Axes and torches then had forced a way." (Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend:) “To Cypris first in gratitude I bend, Thou, next to her, hast snatched me from the fire, In calling me half burnt with fierce desire; For Eros oft a fiercer flame awakes Than those Sicilian fires Hephæstus makes.' (Whence grew my love, divinest Moon ! attend :) " He from her bed the virgin oft doth send, Stung by his furies ; and the new-made bride Scares from the warm couch and her husband's side." These words he spoke; but I with credulous mind Held his dear hand, and on the bed reclined : Our bodies did by touching warmer grow, And on our cheeks there came a hotter glow : Sweetly we whispered ; and, in short, dear Moon ! By Eros fired, we gained Cythera's boon. Nor any blame on me could Delphis lay, Nor haply I on him—’till yesterday. I only learned to-day his yester ill: While yet up-prancing the high eastern hill, Her fiery-footed steeds from ocean's dew With rosy-armed Aurora upward flew, There came the mother of the festive pair, Sweet-voiced Philista and Melixo fair, And told me :—" Delphis loves elsewhere, I know, But whom I know not; yet enamoured so, That from the banquet suddenly he fled, To hang his lady's house with flowers, he said." My old friend told me this, and told me truth : For twice or thrice a day once came my youth, And often left his Dorian pyx with me ; This the twelfth day since him I last did see. Has he forgot me for another love ? With philters will I try his soul to move; But if he still will grieve, betray me, mock, He shall, by fate! the door of Hades knock. That chest has drugs shall make him feel my rage ; The art I learned from an Assyrian sage. Thy steeds to ocean now, bright Queen, direct; What I have sworn to do I will effect. Farewell, clear Moon ! and skyey cressets bright, That follow the soft-gliding wheels of Night.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <p n="1">HUNTING the birds within a bosky grove, A birder, yet a boy, saw winged Love Perched on a box-tree branch; rejoicing saw What seemed a large bird, and began to draw His rods together, and he thought to snare Love, that kept ever hopping here and there. Then fretting that he could not gain his end, Casting his rods down, sought his aged friend, Who taught him bird-catching-his story told, And showed Love perching. Smiled the ploughman old, And shook his head, replying to the boy. " Against this bird do not your rods employ ; It is an evil creature ; shun him—flee ; Until you take him, happy will you be. But if you ever come to manhood's day, He that now flies you and still bounds away, Will of himself, by no persuasion led, Come suddenly and sit upon your head."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.55"/>
          <p n="1.0">CYPRIS, when all but shone the dawn's glad beam, To fair Europa sent a pleasant dream ; When sleep, upon the close-shut eyelids sitting, Sweeter than honey, is eye-fetters knitting, The limb-dissolving sleep ! when to and fro True dreams, like sheep at pasture, come and go. Europa, sleeping in her upper room, The child of Phoenix, in her virgin bloom, Thought that she saw a contest fierce arise Betwixt two continents, herself the prize ; They to the dreamer seemed like women quite, Asia, and Asia's unknown opposite. This was a stranger, that a native seemed, And closer hugged her-so Europa dreamed ; And called herself Europa's nurse and mother, Said that she bore and reared her; but that other Spared not her hands, and still the sleeper drew, With her good will, and claimed her as her due, And said that Zeus Ægiochus gave her, By Fate's appointment, that sweet prisoner. Up-started from her couch the maiden waking, And felt her heart within her bosom quaking ; She thought it true, and sat in hushed surprise- Still saw those women with her open eyes ; Then to her timid voice at last gave vent : " Which of the gods to me this vision sent ? What kind of dream is this that startled me, And sudden made my pleasant slumber flee ? Who was the stranger that I saw in sleep ? What love for her did to my bosom creep ! And how she hailed me, as her daughter even ! But only turn to good my vision, Heaven !" So said, and bounded up, and sought her train Of dear companions, all of noble strain, Of equal years and stature ; 'gentle, kind, Sweet to the sight, and pleasant to the mind ; With whom she sported, when she led the choir, Or in the river's urn-like reservoir She bathed her limbs, or in the meadow stopt, And from its bosom odorous lilies crept. And soon around her shone the lovely band, Her flower-basket in each maiden's hand ; And to the meadows near the pleasant shore They sped, where they had often sped before, Pleased with the roses growing in their reach, And with the waves that murmured on the beach. A basket by Hephæstus wrought of gold, Europa bore-a marvel to behold ; He gave it Libya, when, a blooming bride, She went to grace the great Earth-shaker's side; She gave it Telephassa fair and mild, Who now had given it to her virgin child. Therein were many sparkling wonders wrought— The hapless Iö to the sight was brought; A heifer's for a virgin's form she wore ; The briny paths she frantic wandered o'er, And was a swimming heifer to the view, While the sea round her darkened into blue. Two men upon a promontory stood, And watched the heifer traversing the flood. Again where seven-mouthed Nile divides his strand, Zeus stood and gently stroked her with his hand, And from her horned figure and imbruted To her original form again transmuted. In brass the heifer—Zeus was wrought in gold ; Nile softly in a silver current rolled. And to the life was watchful Hermes shown Under the rounded basket's golden crown ; And Argus near him with unsleeping eyes Lay stretched at length ; then from his blood did rise The bird, exulting in the brilliant pride Of his rich plumes and hues diversified, And like a swift ship with her out-spread sail, Expanding proudly his resplendent tail, The basket's golden rim he shadowed o'er: Such was the basket fair Europa bore. They reached the mead with vernal blossoms full, And each began her favourite flowers to pull. Narcissus one ; another thyme did get; This hyacinth, and that the violet; And of the spring-sweets in the meadow found Much scented bloom was scattered on the ground. Some of the troop in rivalry chose rather The sweet and yellow crocuses to gather ; Shining, as mid the Graces Cypris glows, The princess in the midst preferred the rose: Nor long with flowers her gentle fancy charmed, Nor long she kept her virgin flower unharmed. With love for her was Saturn's son inflamed, By unexpected darts of Cypris tamed, Who only tames e'en Zeus. To shun the rage Of Here, and the virgin's mind engage, To draw her eyes and her attention claim, He hid his godhead and a bull became ; Not such as feeds at stall, or then or now, The furrow cuts and draws the crooked plough ; Not such as feeds the lowing kine among, Or trails in yoke the heavy wain along ; His body all a yellow hue did own, But a white circle in his forehead shone ; His sparkling eyes with love's soft lustre gleamed ; His arched horns like Dian's crescent seemed. He came into the meadow, nor the sight Fluttered the virgins into sudden flight. But they desired to touch and see him near; His breath surpassed the meadow-sweetness there. Before Europa's feet he halted meek, Licked her fair neck, and eke her rosy cheek; Threw round his neck her arms the Beautiful, Wiped from his lips the foam and kissed the bull; Softly he lowed ; no lowing of a brute It seemed, but murmur of Mygdonian flute ; Down on his knees he slunk ; and first her eyed, And then his back, as asking her to ride. The long-haired maidens she began to call : " Come let us ride, his back will hold us all, E'en as a ship ; a bull unlike the rest, As if a human heart were in his breast, He gentle is and tractable and meek, And wants but voice his gentleness to speak." She said, and mounted smiling, but before Another did, he bounded for the shore. The royal virgin, struck with instant fear, Stretched out her hands and called her playmates dear ; But how could they the ravished princess reach ? He, like a dolphin, pushed out from the beach. From their sea-hollows swift the Nereids rose, Seated on seals, and did his train compose ; Poseidon went before, and smooth did make The path of waters for his brother's sake ; Around their king in close array did keep The loud-voiced Tritons, minstrels of the deep, And with their conchs proclaimed the nuptial song. But on Jove's bull-back as she rode along, The maid with one hand grasped his branching horn, The flowing robe, that did her form adorn, Raised with the other hand, and tried to save From the salt moisture of the saucy wave ; Her robe, inflated by the wanton breeze, Seemed like a ship's sail hovering o'er the seas. But when, her father-land no longer nigh, Nor sea-dashed shore was seen, nor mountain high, But only sky above, and sea below- She said, and round her anxious glance did throw :— " Whither with me, portentous bull ? discover This and thyself: and how canst thou pass over The path of waters, walking on the wave, And dost not fear the dangerous path to brave ? Along this tract swift ships their courses keep, But bulls are wont to fear the mighty deep. What pasture here ? what sweet drink in the brine ? Art thou a god ? thy doings seem divine. Nor sea-born dolphins roam the flowery mead, Nor earth-born bulls through Ocean's realm proceed; Fearless on land, and plunging from the shores Thou roamest ocean, and thy hoofs are oars. Perchance anon, up-borne into the sky, Thou without wings like winged birds wilt fly ! Ah me unhappy! who my father's home Have left and with a bull o'er ocean roam, A lonely voyager ! my helper be, Earth-shaking regent of the hoary sea ! I hope to see this voyage's cause and guide, For not without a god these things betide." To her the horned bull with accent clear :— " Take courage, virgin ! nor the billow fear ; The seeming bull is Zeus; for I with ease Can take at will whatever form I please ; My fond desire for thy sweet beauty gave To me this shape—my footstep to the wave. Dear Crete, that nursed me, now shall welcome thee; In Crete Europa's nuptial rites shall be ; From our embrace illustrious sons shall spring, And every one of them a sceptred king."- And instantly they were in Crete: his own Form Zeus put on-and off her virgin zone. Strewed the glad bed the Hours, of joy profuse; The whilom virgin was the bride of Zeus. YE mountain valleys, pitifully groan! Rivers and Dorian springs, for Bion weep! Ye plants, drop tears ! ye groves, lamenting moan ! Exhale your life, wan flowers ; your blushes deep In grief, anemonies and roses, steep ! In softest murmurs, Hyacinth ! prolong The sad, sad woe thy lettered petals keep; Our minstrel sings no more his friends among- Sicilian Muses ! now begin the doleful song. Ye nightingales, that 'mid thick leaves let loose The gushing gurgle of your sorrow, tell The fountains of Sicilian Arethuse That Bion is no more-with Bion fell The song, the music of the Dorian shell. Ye swans of Strymon, now your banks along Your plaintive throats with melting dirges swell For him who sang like you the mournful song: Discourse of Bion's death the Thracian nymphs among; The Dorian Orpheus, tell them all, is dead. His herds the song and darling herdsman miss, And oaks, beneath whose shade he propt his head : Oblivion's ditty now he sings for Dis: The melancholy mountain silent is ; His pining cows no longer wish to feed, But mourn for him : Apollo wept, I wis, For thee, sweet Bion ! and in mourning weed The brotherhood of Fauns, and all the Satyr breed. The tears by Naiads shed are brimful bourns ; Afflicted Pan thy stifled music rues ; Lorn Echo 'mid her rocks thy silence mourns, Nor with her mimic tones thy voice renews : The flowers their bloom, the trees their fruitage lose No more their milk the drooping ewes supply; The bees - to press their honey now refuse ; What need to gather it and lay it by, When thy own honey-lip, my Bion ! thine is dry ? SicilianMuses ! lead the doleful chaunt: Not so much near the shore the dolphin moans ; Nor so much wails within her rocky haunt The nightingale; nor on their mountain thrones The swallows utter such lugubrious tones ; Nor so much Cëyx wailed for Halcyon, Whose song the blue wave, where he perished, owns; Nor in the valley, neighbour to the sun, The funeral birds so wail their Memnon's tomb upon- As these moan, wail, and weep, their Bion dead. The nightingales and swallows, whom he taught, For him their elegiac sadness shed; And all the birds contagious sorrow caught; The sylvan realm was all with grief distraught. Who bold of heart will play on Bion's reed, Fresh from his lip, yet with his breathing fraught ? For still among the reeds does Echo feed On Bion's minstrelsy. Pan only may succeed To Bion's pipe; to him I make the gift: But lest he second seem, e'en Pan may fear The pipe of Bion to his mouth to lift. For thee sweet Galatea drops the tear, And thy dear song regrets, which sitting near She fondly listed; ever did she flee The Cyclops and his song; but far more dear Thy song and sight than her own native sea : On the deserted sands the nymph without her fee Now sits and weeps, or weeping tends thy herd. Away with Bion all the muse-gifts flew— The chirping kisses breathed at every word : Around thy tomb the Loves their playmate rue; Thee Cypris loved more than the kiss she drew And breathed upon her dying paramour. Most musical of rivers ! now renew Thy plaintive murmurs : Meles ! now deplore Another son of song, as thou didst wail of yore That sweet, sweet mouth of dear Calliope: The threne, 'tis said, thy waves for Homer spun With saddest music filled the refluent sea ; Now melting wail and weep another son ! Both loved of fountains-that of Helicon Gave Melesigenes his pleasant draught; To this sweet Arethuse did Bion run, And from her urn the glowing rapture quaft: Blest was the bard who sang how Helen bloomed and laught: On Thetis' mighty son his descant ran, And Menelaus ; but our Bion chose Not arms and tears to sing, but Love and Pan; While browsed his herd, his gushing music rose ; He milked his kine ; did pipes of reeds compose ; Taught how to kiss; and fondled in his breast Young Love and Cypris pleased. For Bion flows In every glorious land a grief contest: Ascra for her own bard, wise Hesiod, less exprest: Bœotian Hylæ mourned for Pindar less; Teos regretted less her minstrel hoar, And Mytelene her sweet poetess ; Nor for Alcæus Lesbos suffered more; Nor lovely Pares did so much deplore Her own Archilochus. Breathing her fire Into her sons of song, from shore to shore For thee the Pastoral Muse attunes her lyre To woeful utterance of passionate desire. Sicelidas, the famous Samian star, And he with smiling eye and radiant face, Cvdonian Lycidas, renowned afar, Lament thee ; where quick Hales runs his race, Philetus wails ; Theocritus, the grace Of Syracuse, thee mourns ; nor these among Am I remiss Ausonian wreaths to place Around thy tomb : to me doth it belong To chaunt for thee from whom I learnt the Dorian song. Me with thy minstrel skill as proper heir Others thou didst endow with thine estate. Alas ! alas !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.72"/>
          <p n="1.1">when in a garden fair Mallows, crisp dill, or parsley yields to fate, These with another year rcgerminate ; But when of mortal life the bloom and crown, The wise, the good, the valiant, and the great Succumb to death, in hollow earth shut down We sleep-for ever sleep-for ever lie unknown. Thus art thou pent, while frogs may croak at will; I envy not their croak. Thee poison slew- How kept it in thy mouth its nature ill ? If thou didst speak, what cruel wretch could brew The draught ? He did, of course, thy song eschew. But justice all o'ertakes. My tears fast flow For thee, ray friend ! Could I, like Orpheus true, Odysseus, or Alcides, pass below To gloomy Tartarus, how quickly would I go ! To see and haply hear thee sing for Dis ! But in the Nymph's ear warble evermore, My dearest friend ! thy sweetest harmonies : For whilom, on her own Etnæan shore, She sang wild snatches of the Dorian lore. Nor will thy singing unrewarded be ; Thee to thy mountain haunts she will restore, As she gave Orpheus his Eurydice. Could I charm Dis with songs, I too would sing for thee.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="3">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.111"/>
          <p n="1">PLAINTIVELY groan at my bidding, ye woodland dells, and thou Dorian water, and weep, rivers, the lovely Bion; now wail at my bidding, ye plants, and now, groves, utter a wail ; now may ye flowers breathe forth your life in sad clusters ; 1 blush now sorrowfully, ye roses, now, thou anemone ; 2 now, hyacinth, speak thy letters, and with thy leaves lisp ‘ ai,' ‘ ai,' more than is thy wont: a noble minstrel is dead. Begin Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Ye nightingales, that wail in the thick foliage, tell the news to the Sicilian waters of 3Arethusa, that Bion the herdsman is dead, that with him both the song is dead, and perished is Doric minstrelsy. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Plaintively wail beside the waters, Strymonian swans, and with mournful voices sing a sorrowful ode, with as sweet a sound as was that of old, wherewith he used to sing to your lips. 4 And tell, again, to Æagrian maids, tell to all Bistonian nymphs, that the Dorian Orpheus has perished. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. That darling of the herds no longer sings: no longer does he warble, as he reclines beneath the solitary oaks: but in Pluto's realm he chants 5 a song of forgetfulness. And voice less are the hills; and the heifers, which roam with the bulls, lament and will not go to pasture. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Thy sudden fate, 0 Bion, even Apollo bewailed, and the , Satyrs grieved, and the dark-robed Priapi; and Pans sigh for thy melody, whilst the fountain nymphs through the wood mourned for thee, 6 and their tears became waters ; and Echo amid the rocks laments, because thou art mute, and mimics no more thy lips ; and at thy death the trees have cast off their fruit, and the flowers have all withered; good milk bath not flowed from ewes; nor honey from hives; but it has perished in the wax wasted with grief; for no longer is it meet, now that thy honey is lost, to gather that. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. 7Not so much did the dolphin lament beside the shores of the sea, nor so sang the nightingale ever on the rocks, no, nor* so much complained the swallow along the high mountains 8neither did Ceyx wail so much over the griefs of Halcyon. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. ' Neither did Cerylus sing so much in the gray-green waves, nor so much 9did the bird of Memnon, fluttering around his tomb, deplore the son of Aurora in the valleys of the East, as they have bewailed Bion, having perished. Begin, Silician Muses, begin the lament. Nightingales, and all swallows, which once he was wont to delight, which he was teaching to speak, sitting on the branches, of trees, kept wailing opposite to each other, whilst the other birds kept responding, Grieve, ye doves, but we will do so too. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Who shall sing to thy pipe, 0 thrice-regretted ? And who shall apply his lip to thy reeds ? Who so bold ? For even yet they breathe of thy lips and thy breath: and Echo amid the reeds feeds upon thy songs. To Pan I bear 10the pipe : haply even he would fear to set his mouth to it, lest he should carry off a second prize after thee. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. 11 Galatea too weeps for thy lay, she whom of old thou didst lelight, as she sat in thy company along the sea-beach. For lot like Cyclops didst thou sing: from him indeed the fair Galatea used to fly; but thee she was wont to regard 12with ore sweetness than the sea. And now, forgetful of the ve, she sits on the lonely sands, and even yet leads thy n to pasture. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. All along with thee, 0 herdsman, have perished the Muses' gifts, charming kisses of maidens, lips of boys : and around thy tomb weep sad-visaged Loves. Venus loves thee far more than the kiss, with which lately she kissed dying Adonis. This is a second grief to thee, most musical of rivers ! This, 3 0 Meles, is a fresh grief; to thy sorrow perished Homer foretime, that 14 sweet mouth of Calliope, and men say thou lidst deplore thine illustrious son in streams of much weeping, and didst fill all the sea with thy voice: now again thou deepest another son, and pinest over a fresh woe. Both were beloved by the fountains; the one indeed was wont to drink )f the Pegasean .spring ; the other, to enjoy a draught of the Arethusa. And the one sang the fair daughter of Tyndarus, and the mighty son of Thetis, and Menelaus, son of Atreus: but the other would sing not of wars, nor tears, but Pan; and would sound the praise of herdsmen, and feed the herd as he sang : and he was wont to fashion Pan's-pipes, and to milk the sweet heifer, and to teach the lips of youths, and to cherish Eros in his bosom, 'and rouse a passion in Aphrodite. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Every famous city laments thee, 0 Bion, as do all the towns: 16Ascra indeed wails for thee, far more than for Hesiod : not so much does Bœotian Hylæ regret Pindar ; nor so much did pleasant Lesbos weep about Alcæus: no, nor bath the Ceian town wept for her bard so much. Pares regrets thee more than Archilochus ; and Mitylene yet plaintively utters thy melody instead of Sappho's. All, as many as have a clear-sounding voice, all singers of pastorals by the Muses' favour, weep for thy fate, now thou art dead. 17 Sicelidas, the glory of Samos, weeps; and among the Cydonians, he who was aforetime cheerful to look on with his smiling eye, Ly cidas, yet sheds tears as he wails : whilst among the citizens of Cos, Philetas mourns beside the river Halens ; and among Syracusans, Theocritus : but I sing for thee a strain of 18 Au sonian sorrow, I, no stranger to the pastoral song, but heir to the Doric Muse, which thou didst teach thy scholars : honouring me, to others indeed thou didst leave thy wealth, but to me thy song. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Alas, alas, when once in a garden the mallows have died, or the green parsley, or blooming crisp dill, they live again after, and spring up another year. But we, the great, and brave, or wise of men, after we have once died, unheard of in hollow earth, sleep a right long and boundless slumber, from which none are roused.19 And in the earth thou indeed wilt be covered in silence, but it has seemed good to the Nymphs that the frog should croak for ever. Yet I envy him not: for 'tis no pretty song he sings. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. Poison came, 0 Bion, to thy lip: thou knewest poison. How did it find access to thy lips, yet not become sweet ? or what mortal was so far ruthless, as to mix for thee, or to give thee the poison, if thou didst speak ? He shunned the power of song. Begin, Sicilian Muses, begin the lament. But justice has overtaken all. And I, shedding tears over this woe, bewail thy fate; yet were I able, like 20 Orpheus, having gone down to Tartarus, like Ulysses once, or as Al cides in days of yore, I too would haply descend to the home of Pluto, that I might see thee, and, if thou singest to Pluto, that I might hear what thou singest. Nay, but in the pre sence of the damsel (Proserpine) warble some Sicilian strain, sing some pleasant pastoral. She too, being Sicilian, 21 sport - ed on the Ætnæan shores, and knew the Doric song: nor will thy strain be unhonoured; and as of old to Orpheus, sweetly singing to his lyre, she gave Eurydice to return, so will she send thee, Bion, to thy hills. Yes, if even I could avail aught by singing to my pipe, I too would sing before Pluto.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.111"/>
          <p n="1">I GO to serenade my charming fair, Sweet Amaryllis; Tityrus, to your care I leave my goats, that on the mountain feed ; But of yon Libyan tawny ram take heed, Lest with his horn he butt you ; careful tend, And to the fountain drive them, heart-dear friend ! Sweet Amaryllis! why dost thou no more, Peeping from out thy cavern as before, Espy and call to thee thy little lover ? Dost hate me ? or do I myself discover Flat-nosed, or with a length of chin, when near ? Thy scorn will make me hang myself, I swear. Behold, ten apples, nymph ! I bring for thee, Plucked from the place where thou didst order me To pluck them; others will I bring to-morrow. Consider now my heart-devouring sorrow : Oh ! that I were a little humming bee, To pass through fern and ivy in to thee, Where in thy cave thou dost thyself conceal! I now know love-a grievous god to feel; He surely sucked a savage lioness, Reared in the wild, who works me such distress, Eating into the marrow of the bone. 0 sweet in aspect! altogether stone ! Nymph ! with thine eye-brows of a raven hue, Clasp me, that I may suck the honey-dew From off thy lip : mere kisses yield some joy. Now wilt thou make me the sweet crown destroy, This wreath of ivy which for thee I brought, With rose-buds and with parsley sweet inwrought. Ah me ! what shall I do ? I plead in vain- Thou nearest not: I'll plunge into the main, My jerkin stript, where Olpis sits on high, Watching the tunnies. Should I even die, 'Twill please thee. This the sign I lately found For the struck pop-bell gave me back no sound, (When by that proof thy doubtful love I tried,) But withering on my elbow shrunk and dried. Agræo, the diviner by the sieve, Forewarned me also what I now believe, (Binding the sheaves, the reapers followed she,) That I loved wholly one who loved not me. A white twin-bearing goat, which the brunette, Old Memnon’s child, Erithacis, would get By wheedling from me, I have kept as thine ; But since thou scornest me with airs so fine, It shall be hers. A throbbing, I declare, In my right eye-shall I behold my fair ? My ditty, leaning on this pine, I'll chant; She'll haply look, since she's not adamant. When in the race, mistrustful of his knees, To win the virgin ran Hippomenes ; Three golden apples in his hand he took, And Atalanta could not help but look- She saw, and maddened instant at the sight, And rushed into the gulf of love outright. The seer Melampus from Mount Othrys drove The stolen herd to Pylos. Thence did Love His brother Bias crown-for in his arms Alphesibæa’s mother lodged her charms. Did not Adonis, the fair shepherd youth, So madden Cypris that for very ruth, E'en when she had received his dying gasp, She could not bear to loose him from her clasp ? Thrice blest, methinks, was that Endymion, Now laid asleep ; thrice blest Iäsion, Who in his life did those sweet joys obtain, Of which ye must not, shall not hear, profane ! How my head aches ! my anguish doth not move thee ; I'll sing no more, and since in vain I love thee, Here will I lie—me here the wolves shall eat; 'Twill be to thee like melting honey sweet.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.111"/>
          <p n="1">By me in my fresh prime did Cypris stand, Leading the child Love in her lovely hand ; He kept his eyes fixt, downcast on the ground, While in mine ears his mother's words did sound:— " Dear herdsman, take and teach for me, I pray, Eros to sing;" she said, and went her way. Him, as one fain to learn, without ado I then began to teach whate'er I knew- Fool that I was ! how first great Pan did suit With numerous tones his new-invented flute ; Athene wise the straight pipe's reedy hollow; Hermes his shell; his cithern sweet Apollo. I taught him this; he heeded not my lore, But sang me his love-ditties evermore- His mother's doings—how Immortals yearn With fond desires, and how poor mortals burn. All I taught Eros I have quite forgot; But his love-ditties—I forget them not.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.139"/>
          <p n="1">WHOSE are these kine ? Philondas's, my friend ? No—Ægon’s,and he gave them me to tend. Do you not milk them privily at eve ? I could not the old man's quick eyes deceive ; And her own calf he puts to every one. But whither has the master cowherd gone ? Have you not heard ? with Ægon by his side, Milon has gone where Alpheus loves to glide. When did e'er Ægon see th' Olympian oil ? In strength for every feat of manly toil, They say he is a match for Hercules. My mother said, believe her if you please, That I surpassed e'en Pollux. Hence he hied, Taking a spade, and twenty sheep beside. Nor needed much persuasion, I engage, Ægon to wrestle-and the wolf to rage. His lowing heifers for their master pine. They have a worthless keeper-wretched kine f Poor creatures ! they no longer wish to feed. Here is a calf but skin and bones indeed- Like a cicada, does she feed on dew ? Not she, by Earth ! but whiles the fodder new Eats from my hand ; or else with us she goes, Cropping the verdant bank, where Æsar flows ; Or up Latymnus bounds away at will, Frisking along the thickly wooded hill. How lean that red bull is ! just such another May Lampra have to offer to the mother Of Mars ! it is a tribe compact of ill. Yet at the lake-mouth he doth take his fill, Browses on Physcus, or at times doth go Where the sweet waters of Neæthus flow ; There the best herbs are freshened by the shower, Wild thyme, and fleabane, and the honey-flower. Ah, wretched Ægon ! thy poor kine will die, Whilst thou dost aim at evil victory. Even the pipe, which thou didst whilom make, Lying neglected, doth defilement take. No ! by the Nymphs ! he gave it me the day When he to glorious Pisa went away. The songs of Pyrrhus and dear Glauca's lays I know to sing, and Croton love to praise. Fair is Zacynthus ; lovely ever shone To the bright east up-heaved Lacinion, Where the bold boxer Ægon at a meal Ate eighty cakes ; where from the mountain's heel He seized and dragged a proud bull by the hoof, And gave it Amaryllis ; then aloof Shouted the women, and the cowherd smiled Sweet Amaryllis ! though by death defiled, Thee shall I ne'er forget: dear to my heart As are my frisking goats, thou didst depart, To what a lot was I, unhappy, born ! Take heart; there will be yet a brighter morn. While there is life there's hope ; the dead, I ween, Are hopeless. One while Zeus shines out serene, Another while is hid in mist and shower. I do take heart. But see ! yon calves devour The olive branches : pelt them off, I pray ; Confound the calves ! you white-skin thief, away! Hist! to the hill, Cymaetha ! don't you hear ? If you don't get away, by Pan ! I swear I will so give it you ! now only look ! She comes again—I wish I had my crook ! Here, Corydon ! a thorn has wounded me- How long and sharp these distaff-thistles be ! Confound the calf! gaping at her I got The wound : under the ankle-see you not ? Ay ! I have hold of it; see ! here it is ! How small a wound tames man so tall as this ! Unshod you must not on the mountain go ; For on the mountain thorns and prickles grow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.139"/>
          <p n="1">THE Muses fear not, but with heart-love true Affect wild Eros, and his steps pursue. And if one sings with cold and loveless heart, They shun him, and will never teach their art. But if one sings Love's agitated thrall, To him in flowing stream they hasten all. Of this myself am proof; for whensoe'er For some Immortal else or mortal here I would the glowing path of song explore, Stammers my tongue, and sings not as before ; But glad and gushing flows the strain from me, Whene'er I sing of Love or Clymene.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.139"/>
          <p n="1">" WHY dost thou vex thy spirit, mother mine ? Why fades thy cheek ? at what dost thou repine ? Because thy son must serve a popinjay, As though a lion did a fawn obey ? Why have the gods so much dishonoured me ? Why was I born to such a destiny ? Spouse of a man I cherished as mine eyes, For whom heart-deep my vowed affection lies, Yet must I see him crossed by adverse fate, Of mortal men the most misfortunate ! Who with the arrows, which Apollo-no ! Some Fate or Fury did on him bestow, In his own house his own sons raging slew- Where in the house was not the purple dew ? I saw them slain by him ; I—I, their mother, Did see their father slaughter them ; none other Had e'er a dream like this; to me they cried, ‘ Mother! save us !' what could I do ? they died. As when a bird bewails her callow young, O'er whom, unfeathered yet, she fondly hung, Which now a fierce snake in the bush devours- Flies round and round-shrieks-cannot help them-cowers, Nor nearer dares approach her cruel foe: Thus I, most wretched mother! to and fro Rushed madly through the house, my children dear, My dead, dead children wailing every where. Would that I too had with my children died, The poisoned arrow sticking in my side ! Then with fast tears my mother and my sire Had laid me with them on the funeral pyre ; And to my birth-land given, on their return, Our mingled ashes in one golden urn: But they in Thebes, renowned for steeds, remain, And still they farm their old Aonian plain ; But in steep Tiryns I must dwell apart, With many sorrows gnawing at my heart; Mine eyes are fountains, which I cannot close; I seldom see him, and but brief repose My hapless husband is allowed at home ; By sea or land he must for ever roam; None but a heart of iron, or of stone, Could bear the labours he has undergone. Thou, too, like water, meltest still away, For ever weeping every night and day. None of my kin is here to comfort me, For they beyond the piny isthmus be ; There's none to whom I may pour out my woes, And like a woman all my heart disclose, But sister Pyrrha ;-but she too forlorn For her Iphicles, thine and hers doth mourn; Unhappiest mother thou ! in either son— Twin stamps of Zeus, and of Amphitryon." And, while she spoke, from either tearful well The large drops faster on her bosom fell, While she her slaughtered children called to mind, And parents in her country left behind. With tear-stained cheek, and many a groan and sigh, Alcmena to her son's wife made reply " Why, hapless mother ! with this train of thought Dost thou provoke the grief that comes unsought ? Why dost thou talk these dreadful sorrows o'er, Now wept by us—as we have wept before ? Are not the new griefs that we look to see From day to day, enough for you and me ? Lover of dole were he, who would recount Our tale of woes, and find their whole amount! Take heart, and bear those ills we cannot cure, But by the will of heaven we must endure. And yet I cannot bid thee cease to grieve, For even joy to spend itself has leave. For thee I wail, why wert thou doomed, oh why, To be a partner in our misery ? I mourn that fate with ours thy fortune blends Under the woe that over us impends. Ye ! by whose names unpunished none forswear, Persephona and dread Demeter, hear ! Not less on thee has my true love reposed, Than if my womb thy body had enclosed; I love thee, sweetest! as an old-age child, That has, beyond hope, on its mother smiled ; Thou knowest this ; then say not, I implore, I love thee not, or foster sorrow more, Or in my grief I careless am of thee, Though I weep more than e'er wept Niobe. No blame is due to her with anguish wild, Who hapless weeps for her unhappy child. Ten weary months within my womb he lay- What pains I suffered ere he came to day! What pangs ! I all but said farewell to earth, While yet my unborn lingered in the birth. New toils now task him in a foreign plain- Oh shall I ever see my son again ? Besides, an awful vision of the night, Scaring my sleep, hath filled me with affright, And much I fear, when I my dream recall, Lest some untoward thing my sons befall. Methought, aside his cloak and tunic laid, My Hercules with both hands grasped a spade, And round a cultured field a mighty dyke He delved, as one that toils for hire belike. But when the dyke around the vineyard run, And he was just about (his task now done, The shovel thrown on the projecting rim,) With his attire again to cover him ; Sudden above the bank a fire burst out, Whose greedy flames enclosed him round about: He to the flames with rapid flight did yield, Holding the spade before him as a shield, And here and there he turned his anxious eye, If he might shun his scorching enemy. High-souled Iphicles, I remember well As it me-seemed, rushing to help him, fell; Nor could he raise himself from where he rolled, But helpless lay there like some weak man old, Tript up by joyless age against his will; Stretched on the ground he was, and seeming still Hopeless of rising, till a passer-by In pity raised the hoar infirmity. Thus helpless lay the warrior brave in fight; And I did weep to see that sorry sight- This son stretched feeble, that engirt with flame, Till sleep forsook me and the day-dawn came. Such frightful visions on my sleep did fall; Ye gods ! on curst Eurystheus turn them all! Oh be this presage true my wish supplies, And may no god ordain it otherwise! ”</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="5">
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.91"/>
          <p n="1">WHEN the breeze gently strikes the gray-green sea, 1 I am roused in my fearful mind, and no longer is land dear to me, 2 but the calm sea attaches me to it far more : but whensoever the hoary deep has resounded, and the sea-water foams up 3 into an arch, and the waves rage afar, I look out for land and trees, and flee the brine : and welcome to me is earth ; then does the shady wood delight me, where though the wind should blow violently, 4 yet the pine tree sings. Surely a hard life lives the fisherman, whose house is his bark, the sea his occupation, fish his slippery prey. But sweet to me is sleep beneath a leafy plane, and I should love to hear the sound of the fountain hard by, which, as it babbles, delights, not alarms, the rustic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.91"/>
          <p n="1">LACON my goat-skin filched ; by timely flight Avoid, my goats! the thievish Sybarite. Lambs ! from the fountain, do you not perceive Conatas, who my pipe did lately thieve ? What sort of pipe ? when, slave of Sybaris ! Didst own a pipe ? are you not fain to hiss Still through a pipe of straw with Corydon ? 'Twas Lycon's gift, good freeman ! worthy one ! From you when and what sort of skin stole I ? Your master has not one whereon to lie. The gift of Crocylus, when late he gave The Nymphs a goat in sacrifice : you, slave Did steal my spotted skin from envy sheer. No !no ! by the shore-guarding Pan I swear- Or from that rock into the waters deep Of rapid Crathis may I madly leap ! Nor, by the Nymphs, the guardians of the lake, Did ever I the pipe of Lacon take- So may the Nymphs look kindly to my weal. If I believe you, be it mine to feel The griefs of Daphnis ! will you stake a kid, (It is none enterprise to men forbid,) And I'll out-sing you, till you cry " Enough !" Athene challenged by a sow of scruff! Here is my kid, which, when you beat me, take ! A lamb, fat from the pasture, be your stake. How is this fair ? in this you are no fool; ' Who ever thought of shearing hair for wool, Or passed a goat to milk a sorry bitch ? Who has for conquest a prevailing itch, Like you conceited, is a wasp that rings His buzzing horn when the cicada sings. But since my kid seems insufficient stake, Behold this ram ! at once the song awake. Softly ! you are not walking over fire: Here you may sing whatever your muse inspire More sweetly in this grove, beneath the shade Of the wild olive ; here a couch is laid Of softest herbage ; locusts babble here ; Cool water flows a little onward there. I'm cool-but feel annoyance at your daring To look at me, yourself with me comparing, Who taught you when a boy. What thanks one gains ! Rear a wolf-whelp-to rend you for your pains ! Envious and shameless babbler ! any thing Learnt, heard I from you worth remembering ? Come hither, now, and learn from your defeat No more with pastoral singers to compete. Not thither—here are oaks and galingale ; And round their hives the bees, soft-humming, sail; Two springs of coolest water murmur near; A deeper shade and singing birds are here; And from aloft her nuts the pine-tree throws. On fleece and lambskins here your may repose, Softer than sleep ! your goat-skins smell more ill— E'en than yourself. I for the Nymphs will fill A bowl of white milk, of sweet oil an urn. On flowering pennyroyal and soft fern You here may tread ; on skins of kids lie down Softer than lambskins. I to Pan will crown Eight jars of white milk, and as many more Of honeycombs with honey running o'er. Each from his place pour out his rival strain ; Keep to your oaks, and I will here remain. But who shall judge between us ? How I wish The herdsman, good Lycopas, with us- Pish! I want him not: but, if you please, we'll cry, And summon to us yonder man doth tie The broom in bundles near you. What dost say ? "Tis Morson. I'm agreed. Then bawl away. Ho ! Morson ! hasten hither, and decide Which sings the best-a wager to be tried With you for judge : only impartial be! Now, by the Nymphs ! nor favour him nor me. Thurian Sybartas owns the sheep in sight; The goats Eumaras claims-the Sybarite. You good-for-nothing babbler ! answer this, Who asked you whose the sheep were, mine or his ? I vaunt not, and I speak the simple truth ; But you are very scurrilous, in sooth. Sing-if you have a song : don't kill with babble Our friend here ; by Apollo ! how you gabble ! Me more than Daphnis love the Muses true : Two yearling kids to them I lately slew. Apollo loves me much ; for him I rear A goodly ram—his festival is near. I milk my goats, twin-bearing all but twain : A sweet girl cries, " Why milk alone, fond swain ?" Some twenty baskets Lacon fills with cheese, And gets him kisses wheresoe'er he please. Me with sweet apples Clearista pelts, While round her lips a honey-murmur melts. On me a blooming beauty fondly dotes, Round whose white neck the hair bright-shining floats. With the screened garden-roses cannot vie The common dog-rose, nor anemony. The mountain-apples most delicious are- Who crabbed beech-nuts would with them compare ? I for my love will snare, and give to her A ring-dove brooding on a juniper. Wool for a mantle will I give my dear, Soon as my sober-suited sheep I shear. From the wild-olive, bleaters ! feed at will, Where grow the tamarisks, on this sloping hill. Off from that oak Cynætha and Conarus ! Feed eastward-yonder where you see Phalarus. A cypress milk-pail for my girl I have, And bowl-which old Praxiteles did grave. A hound, wolf-strangling keeper of the sheep, A faithful guardian, for my love I keep. Locusts, that overleap my fences, spare My vines-their shoots yet weak and tender are. Cicadæ ! see this goatherd I provoke : So to their toil ye wake the reaping folk. I hate the bush-tailed foxes—nightly troop, That Mycon's vineyard, grape-devouring, swoop. I hate the scarabs-air-borne host, that mow Philonda's fig-trees, fig-devouring foe. Do you remember when I smote you, fellow, How you did wriggle round the oak, and bellow ? No ! but I do remember when with scourge Eumaras did your peccant humours purge. Some one, my Morson, into rage is dashing ; Go ! from the tomb pluck gray squills—for a lashing. I too prick some one, Morson ; do you take ? Hasten to Hales ; and for sowbread rake. Flow Himera with milk, and Crathis flow Purple with wine ! and fruit on cresses grow! Fountain of Sybaris, to honey turn, And fill with honeycombs the maiden's urn ! On goat's-rue feed, my goats, and cytisus ; On lentisk tread, and lie on arbutus ! Of the rose-eglantine there blooms a heap, And eke the honey-flower—to feed my sheep. Alcippe for my ring-dove gave no kiss, Holding my ears—I love her not for this. I love my love because a sweet lip paid With kisses for my pipe-the gift I made. Nor whoop the swan, nor jay the nightingale May rival; still you challenge, still to fail. Cease, shepherd ! Morson gives the lamb to thee, Comatas ; fail not to remember me, And let my portion of the flesh be nice, When to the Nymphs you make your sacrifice. By Pan ! I'll send it. Snort and gambol round. My buck-goats all! hark ! what a mighty sound I peal of ringing laughter at the cost Of Lacon, who to me his lamb has lost! I too will skip. My horned goats, good cheer! To-morrow in the fountain, cool and clear, Of Sybaris I'll bathe you. Hark! I say, White butting ram! be modest, till I pay The Nymphs my offering. Ha ! then blows I'll try— Or may I like the curst Melanthius die.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.19"/>
          <p n="1.0">MENALCAS met, while pasturing his sheep, The cowherd Daphnis on the highland steep ; Both yellow-tressed, and in their life's fresh spring,— Both skilled to play the pipe, and both to sing. Menalcas, with demeanour frank and free, Spoke first: " Good Daphnis, will you sing with me ? I can out-sing you, whensoe'er I try, Just as I please." Then Daphnis made reply: Shepherd and piper ! that may never be, Happen what will, as you on proof will see. Ah, will you see it, and a wager make ? I will to see this, and to pledge a stake. And what the wager, worthy fame like ours ? A calf my pledge, a full-grown lamb be yours. At night my cross-grained sire and mother use To count the sheep-that pledge I must refuse. What shall it be then ? What the victor's prize ? I'll pledge a nine-toned pipe, that even lies In the joined reeds, with whitest wax inlaid, The musical sweet pipe I lately made ; This will I pledge-and not my father's things. I, too, have got a pipe that nine-toned rings, Compact with white wax, even-jointed, new,- Made by myself: a split reed sudden flew, And gashed this finger—it is painful still. But who shall judge which has the better skill ? Suppose we call that goatherd hither—see! Yon white dog at his kids barks lustly. He came when called ; and, hearing their request Was willing to decide which sung the best. Clearly their rival tones responsive rung, Each in his turn, but first Menalcas sung. Ye mountain-vales and rivers !race divine ! If aught Menalcas ever sung was sweet, Feed ye these lambs ; and feed no less his kine, When Daphnis drives them to this dear retreat. Fountains and herbs, growth of the lively year ! If Daphnis sings like any nightingale, Fatten this herd ; and if Menalcas here Conduct his flock, let not their pasture fail. Pastures and spring, and milkful udders swelling, And fatness for the lambs, is every where At her approach : but if the girl excelling Departs, both herbs and shepherd wither there. The sheep and goats bear twins ; the bees up-lay Full honey-stores, the spreading oaks are higher, Where Milto walks : but if she goes away, The cowherd and his cows themselves are drier. Uxorious ram, and flat-nosed kids, away For water to that wilderness of wood : There, ram without a horn ! to Milto say, Proteus, a god too, fed the sea-calf brood. Nor Pelops' realm be mine, nor piles of gold, Nor speed fleet as the wind ; but at this rock To sing, and clasp my darling, and behold The seas blue reach, and many a pasturing flock. To forest-beast the net, to bird the noose, Winter to trees, and drought to springs is bad ; To man the sting of beauty. Mighty Zeus! Not only I—thou, too, art woman-mad. Their sweet notes thus, in turn, they did prolong; Menalcas then took up the closing song. Spare, wolf ! my sheep and lambs ;nor injure me, Because I many tend, though small I be. Sleepest, Lampurus ? up! no dog should sleep That with the shepherd-boy attends his sheep. Be not to crop the tender herbage slow, Feed on, my sheep! the grass again will grow. Fill ye your udders, that your lambs may have Their share of milk,—I some for cheese may save. Then Daphnis next his tones preluding rung, Gave to the music voice, and sweetly sung. As yesterday I drove my heifers by, A girl, me spying from a cavern nigh, Exclaimed, " How handsome !" I my way pursued With down-cast eyes, nor made her answer rude. Sweet is the breath of cows and calves-and sweet To bask by running stream in summer heat. Acorns the oak; and apples on the bough Adorn the apple-tree ; her calf the cow; His drove of kine, depasturing the field, His proper honour to the cowherd yield. Th' admiring goatherd then his judgment spake: Sweet is thy mouth, and sweetest tones awake From thy lips, Daphnis ! I would rather hear Thee sing, than suck the honeycomb, I swear. Take thou the pipe, for thine the winning song. If thou wilt teach me here my goats among Some song, I will that hornless goat bestow, That ever fills the pail to overflow. Glad Daphnis clapped his hands, and on the lawn He leaped, as round her mother leaps the fawn. But sad Menalcas fed a smouldering gloom, As grieves a girl betrothed to unknown groom. And first in song was Daphnis from that time, And wived a Naiad in his blooming prime. DAPHNIS !begin the pastoral song for me; Begin, and let Menalcas follow thee. Meanwhile the calves the mother-cows put under, Let the bulls feed-but not roam far asunder, Scorning the herd-and crop the leafy spray ; And leave the heifers to their frolic play. Begin for me the sweet bucolic strain, And let Menalcas take it up again. " Sweet low the cow and calf-the tones are sweet, The pipe, the cowherd and myself repeat. My couch is by cool water, and is strown With skins of milk-white heifers ; them threw down, While they crept arbutus, the south-west wind From the bluff crag. There stretched, no more I mind The scorching summer than a loving pair Their parents sage, who bid them each ‘beware !'" Thus Daphnis sweetly sung at my request; Menalcas next his dulcet tones exprest. " Ætna ! my mother ! in the hollow rock My pleasant mansion is; I own a flock Of many yearlings and of many sheep, Numerous as those the dreamer sees in sleep. Fleeces are lying at my head and feet; On an oak-fire are boiling entrails sweet; And on my hearth in winter-time I burn Fagots of beech. I have no more concern For winter-than the toothless elder cares For walnuts, whose old dame his pap prepares." Both I applauded, and made gifts to both, A crook to Daphnis—the spontaneous growth Of my own father's field, yet turned so well, None could find fault with it; a sounding shell I gave Menalcas; four besides myself Fed on its flesh—I snared it from a shelf Amid th' Icarian rocks. The conch he blew, And far abroad the blast resounding flew. Hail, pastoral Muses ! and the song declare, Which then I chanted for that friendly pair. “ On your tongue's tip may pustules never grow, For speaking falsely what for false you know ! Cicale the cicale loves; and ant loves ant; Hawk, hawk; and me the muse and song enchant. Of this my house be full! nor sudden spring, Nor sleep is sweeter ; nor to bees on wing The bloom of flowers more dear delight diffuses, Than to myself the presence of the Muses. On whomsoe'er they look and sweetly smile, Him Circe may not harm with cup or wile." PLOUGHMAN, what is the matter with you, pray ? You cannot draw the furrow straight to-day, Nor with your neighbour even do you keep, But lag behind like a thorn-wounded sheep. If you cannot the furrow now devour, What will you be, my friend, at evening hour ? You rock-chip, reaping till the sun's descent, Did you some absent darling ne'er lament ? Never. A labourer's heart with love-grief ache ! Did you ne'er chance for love to lie awake ? No-never may I! When a dog has eaten Meat for his master, the poor dog is beaten. I'm deep in love-almost eleven days. From a full wine-cask you your fancies raise; I have not even vinegar enough. Thence lie the sweepings of all sort of stuff Before my door. Who is your mischief-bringer ? The child of Polybotas—the sweet singer, Who for the mowers at Hippocoon's chaunted. Sinners heaven pricks—you have what long you wanted ; A dry tree-frog will hug you close in bed. None of your jibes : care-breeding Love is said, And not old Plutus only, to be blind. Don't talk too big. I do not-only mind To cut the corn down, and some love-song try About your girl; you'll work more pleasantly : And Battus once, at least, was musical. To sing my charmer, slender, straight, and tall, Best Muses ! aid me ; for, with skill divine, Ye, whatsoe'er ye please to touch, refine. Lovely Bombyce! though all men beside Call you a Syrian sun-embrowned, and dried, I call you a transparent sweet brunette. The lettered hyacinth and violet Are dark; yet these are chosen first of all For the sweet wreath and festive coronal. The goat the cytisus, the wolf the goat, And cranes pursue the plough-on thee I dote. Would that I had the wealth report bath told Belonged to Croesus ! wrought in purest gold, Statues of both of us should then be seen, Due dedications to the Cyprian Queen : Thou with a flute, an apple, and a rose ; I sandalled, in a robe that proudly flows. Lovely Bombyce! beautiful your feet, Twinkling like the quick dice; your voice is sweet ; But your sweet nature language cannot tell. He privily hath learned to sing-how well! But my poor chin in vain this great beard nurses; List to a snatch or two of Lytierses. Damater; fruit-abounding ! grant this field Be duly wrought, and rich abundance yield. Bind without waste, sheaf-binder ! lest one say, These men of fig-wood are not worth their pay. Let the sheaf-hillock look to north or west; The corn, so lying, fills and ripens best. Ye threshers! let not sleep steal on your eyes At noon-for then the chaff most freely flies.. Up with the lark to reap, and cease as soon As the lark sleeps-but rest yourself at noon. Happy the frog's life ! none, his drink to pour, He looks for-he has plenty evermore. Boil, niggard steward ! the lentil; and take heed, Don't cut your hand-to split a cumin-seed. Men toiling in the sun such songs befit; Your puling love, poor rustic little-wit! Is only fit—to whisper in her ears, When your old mother wakes as dawn appears. NICIAS ! there is no remedy for love, Except the Muses; this alone doth prove A sweet and gentle solace for the mind Of love-sick man—not easy though to find. Full knowledge of this truth I deem is thine, Physician, and beloved of all the Nine ! Thus, Polypheme of yore, our Cyclops, found The power of song on love's uneasy wound ; With the first down that budding youth discloses On cheek and chin, he doted-not with roses And apples for his love, and the trim curl To please her eye, but with delirious whirl, Neglecting all things else. Oft to the stall His sheep from pasture came without his call, While he from dawn mid sea-weeds and the spray Of Galatea sung, and pined away, By mighty Cypris wounded at the heart, Who in his liver fixed her cruel dart. He found the cure while from the cliff he flung His glances seaward, and his ditty sung :— " Why, Galatea, scorn for love dost render ? Whiter than fresh curds, than the lamb more tender; More skittish than the calf, more clearly bright Than unripe grape transparent in the light ! Here dost thou show thyself when sleeps thy lover, Still flying ever as my sleep is over, E'en as the sheep, the gray wolf seeing, flees. I loved when with my mother from the seas Thou first didst come, and seek the mountain-side To gather hyacinths—and I thy guide. Since then I never yet have ceased to love thee, Although my passion never yet did move thee.. I know the reason why the beauty flies— One shaggy eye-brow on my forehead lies Over one eye, stretched out from tip to tip Of either ear, and overhangs my lip A nostril broad. Such as I am, I keep, Drinking their best of milk, a thousand sheep; My cheeses fail not in their hurdled row In depth of winter nor in summer's glow. No Cyclops here can breathe the pipe like me, Who sing, when I should sleep, myself and thee, Sweet-apple ! I for thee four bear-whelps rear, And eke eleven fawns that collars wear. Come live (thou shalt not fare the worse) with me, And to its murmurs leave that azure sea. Thy nights will sweeter pass within my cave, Where the tall cypress and the laurel wave ; The sweet-fruit vine and ivy dark are there ; From the white snow its waters cool and clear Thick-wooded AEtna sends : whom would it please In sea to dwell, when land has joys like these ? Though rough I seem in Galatea's eyes, My wealth of oak a constant fire supplies ; O fire of love ! I could be well content That life and precious eye at once were brent. Had I but fins ! then would I dive and kiss Thy dainty hand, though daintier lip I miss ; In different seasons take thee different flowers, The summer lily white in summer hours, And while it winter was, what winter bred, The tender poppy with its pop-bells red. From some sea-ranger I will learn to swim, To see what charms you in your ocean dim. Come, Galatea ! sparkling from the foam, And then, like me, forget to turn thee home. Would that the shepherd and his life could please- To milk my ewes, with runnet fix the cheese. My mother is in fault, and only she— She never spake a friendly word for me ; Although she sees me pining fast away, Thinner and thinner still from day to day. I'll tell her that my feet and temples throb, That she, as I have done, with grief may sob. O Cyclops ! Cyclops ! whither dost thou hover ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.28"/>
          <p n="1.1">To weave thy baskets would more wit'discover, And get thy lambs green leaves. Milk the near ewe ; Why one that faster flies in vain pursue ? A fairer Galatea you may find; Others are fair, and all are not unkind: For many a damsel, when eve's shadow falls, Me to sport with her fondly, sweetly calls ; And all of them, with eyes that brightly glisten, Giggle most merrily, whene'er I listen: That I am somebody on earth is plain." Thus Polypheme with song relieved love's pain And from his ails himself did safer free, Than had he given a leech a golden fee. ART come, dear youth ? Two days and nights away I For love who passion, wax old-in a day. As much as apples sweet the damson crude Excel; the bloomy spring the winter rude; In fleece the sheep her lamb; the maid in sweetness The thrice-wed dame; the fawn the calf in fleetness; The nightingale in song all feathered kind- So much thy longed-for presence cheers my mind. To thee I hasten, as to shady beech The traveller, when from the heaven's reach The sun fierce blazes. May our love be strong, To all hereafter times the theme of song ! " Two men each other loved to that degree, That either friend did in the other see A dearer than himself. They lived of old, Both golden natures in an age of gold." O father Zeus! ageless Immortals all! Two hundred ages hence may one recall, Down-coming to the irremeable river, This to my mind, and this good news deliver: " E'en now from east to west, from north to south, Your mutual friendship lives in every mouth." This, as they please, the Olympians will decide: Of thee, by blooming virtue beautified, My glowing song shall only truth disclose ; With falsehood's pustules I'll not shame my nose. If thou dost sometime grieve me, sweet the pleasure Of reconcilement, joy in double measure To find thou never didst intend the pain, And feel myself from all doubt free again. And, ye Megarians, at Nisæa dwelling, Expert at rowing, mariners excelling, Be happy ever! for with honours due Th' Athenian Diodes, to friendship true, Ye celebrate. With the first blush of spring The youth surround his tomb: there who shall bring The sweetest kiss, whose lip is purest found, Back to his mother goes with garlands crowned. Nice touch the arbiter must have, indeed, And must, methinks, the blue-eyed Ganymede Invoke with many prayers-a mouth to own True to the touch of lips, as Lydian stone To proof of gold,-which test will instant show The pure or base, as money-changers know. FRIEND! not for us alone was love designed, Whoe'er his parent of immortal kind ; Nor first to us fair seemeth fair to be, Who mortal are, nor can the morrow see. But e'en Amphitryon's brazen-hearted son, Who stood the lion's rage, did dote upon The curled and lovely Hylas—made his joy To train him as a father would his boy, And taught him all whereby himself became A minstrel-praised inheritor of fame ; Nor left him when the sun was in mid-air, Or Morn to Jove's court drove her milk-white pair; Or when the twittering chickens were betaking Themselves to rest, her wings their mother shaking, Perched on the smoky beam; that, trained to go In the right track, he might a true man grow. When Jason sailed to find the golden fleece, And in his train the choicest youth of Greece; Then with the worthies from the cities round, Came Hercules, for patient toil renowned, And Hylas with him: from Iölcos they, In the good Argo ploughed the watery way. Touched not the ship the dark Cyanean rocks, That justled evermore with crashing shocks, But bounded through, and shot the swell o' the flood, Like to an eagle, and in Phasis stood: Thence either ridgy rock in station lies. But at what times the Pleiades arise: When to the lamb the borders of the field (The spring to summer turning) herbage yield ; The flower of heroes minded then their sailing ; And the third day, a steady south prevailing, They reached the Hellespont; and in the bay Of long Propontis hollow Argo lay : Their oxen for Cianians dwelling there The ploughshare in the broadening furrow wear. They land at eve ; in pairs their mess they keep ; And many strow a high and rushy heap: A meadow broad convenient lay thereby, With various rushes prankt abundantly. And gold-tressed Hylas is for water gone For Hercules and sturdy Telamon, Who messmates were: a brazen urn he bore, And soon perceived a fountain straight before. It was a gentle slope, round which was seen A multitude of rushes, parsley green, And the close couch-grass, creeping to entwine Green maiden-hair, and pale-blue celandine. Their choir the wakeful Nymphs, the rustics' dread, In the mid sparkle of the fountain led ; Malis, and young Nychea looking spring, And fresh Eunica. There the youth did bring, And o'er the water hold his goodly urn, Eager at once to dip it and return. The Nymphs all clasped his hand; for love seized all, Love for the Argive boy ; and he did fall Plumping at once into the water dark, As when a meteor glides with many a spark Plumping from out the heavens into the seas- And then some sailor cries, " A jolly breeze, Up with the sail, boys !" Him upon their knees The Nymphs soft held; him dropping many a tear With soft enticing words they tried to cheer. Anxious Alcides lingered not to go, Armed like a Scythian with his curved bow. He grasped his club ; and thrice he threw around His deep, deep voice at highest pitch of sound; Thrice called on Hylas ; thrice did Hylas hear, And from the fount a thin voice murmured near ; Though very near, it very far appeared : As when a lion, awful with his beard, Hearing afar the whining of a fawn, Speeds to his banquet from the mountain-lawn ; In such wise. Hercules, the boy regretting, Off at full speed through pathless brakes was setting. Who love, much suffer : what fatigue he bore! What thickets pierced ! what mountains clambered o'er i What then to him was Jason's enterprise ? With sails aloft the ship all ready lies; Midnight they sweep the decks and oft repeat, " Where, where is Hercules ?" Where'er his feet Convey him, there the frantic mourner hurries, For a fierce god his liver tears and worries. Fair Hylas thus is numbered with the blest: Their friend, as ship-deserter, all the rest Reproach ; while trudges be (and sad his case is) To Colchos and inhospitable Phasis. Health to Thyonichus! The same to you. How late you are! Late ? what concernment new ? It is not well with me. And therefore lean, With beard untrimmed and dry straight hair you're seen. But lately one, in seeming much the same, Who called himself Athenian, hither came, A barefoot, pale Pythagorean oaf, In love, methought, and longing-for a loaf. You'll have your jest: Cynisca flouts me so, That I shall madden unawares, I know- There's but a hair's-breadth now 'twixt me and madness. Extreme in changes ever-brooding sadness, Or moody violence-as the whim makes you Sport of the time: but what new care o'ertakes you ? The Argive, I, and the Thessalian knight Good Apis, and Cleunicus, brave in fight, Were drinking at my farm. We had for fare Two pullets and a sucking pig; and rare Rich Biblian wine (near four years old) I drew, And fragrant still, as from the wine-press new. A Colchian onion gave the brewage zest; As mirth with drink advanced, we thought it best To quaff the wine's pure juice, each to his flame, And every one was bound to tell her name. So said, so done: we drank to them we loved: But she, my she ! by all my love unmoved, Said nothing, though I then and there named her. Think what a tempest did my temper stir! “Won’t speak?" I said : "or, as the wise man spoke, Hast seen a wolf ? " another said in joke. From her red burning face (it kindled so) You might have lit a lamp. Lycus, you know, Is name for wolf; and there is such an one, Tall, delicate, my neighbour Laba's son ; And many think him handsome : for this youth, And his fine love my damsel pined in sooth. I heard a whisper, nor I sifted it, Having a man's beard without manly wit. But Apis—we were at our cups again- Sang out “ My Lycus !" a Thessalian strain. Then sudden into tears Cynisca burst- The girl of six years for the breast that nurst Her tender infancy, not so much weeps. You know me, how no bound my temper keeps ; With doubled fist once and again I struck Both of her cheeks. She thereat did up-tuck Her skirts and quickly bolted through the door. Do I not please thee ? hast a paramour Nearer thy heart ? plague o' my life ! go, go ! Hug him for whom your tears, like beads, thick flow. As for her callow brood, that nested lies Under the roof, the swallow swiftly flies To bring them food, and flies for more again : From her soft couch more swift she fled amain, Through hall, court, gate, as fast as she was able: " The bull into the wood," as runs the fable. Add two to this, the eight and fiftieth day, 'Twill be two full months since she went away; And since we parted, as a sign of woe, My hair has, Thracian-like, been left to grow. But only Lycus is her sole delight; For him her door is open e'en at night. But hapless I, with the Megarian lot, Am held in none account, and quite forgot. All would be well, could I my love restrain ; But mice, they say, the taste of pitch retain. I cannot cure myself, however I try ; For hapless love I know no remedy; Except that Simus sailed across the water, When smitten with old Epichalcus' daughter, And came back whole. I too will cross the wave, Nor best nor worst of soldiers, but a brave. May all be as you wish, my Æschines ! But if you will depart beyond the seas, Gladly king Ptolemy brave hearts engages, Best man of all that gives the soldier wages. What sort of man is he in other things ? To brave and noble souls the best of kings ; Has a discerning spirit; takes delight In all the Muses ; courteous to the height; Who loves him and who loves him not, he knows ; And many gifts on many men bestows. When asked a boon, he king-like not denies ; But oft to ask is neither right nor wise. Then if you wish a martial cloak to fold Around your shoulders, and in station bold, Firm on both feet, abide the shielded foe On-rushing-instantly to Egypt go. Soon we grow old, and Time steals on apace, Whitening the hair, and withering the face. We ought to do what us behoves, I ween, While yet our knee is firm, our strength is green Is Praxinoa at home ? Dear Gorgo, yes ! How late you are ! I wonder, I confess, That you are come e'en now. Quick, brazen-front! [To EUNOA. A chair there-stupid ! lay a cushion on't. Thank you, 'tis very well. Be seated, pray. My untamed soul! what dangers on the way ! I scarce could get alive here : such a crowd ! So many soldiers with their trappings proud ! A weary way it is—you live so far. The man, whose wits with sense are aye at war, Bought at the world's end but to vex my soul This dwelling-no ! this serpent's lurking-hole, That we might not be neighbours : plague o' my life, His only joy is quarrelling and strife. Talk not of Dinon so before the boy ; See ! how he looks at you ! My honey-joy! My pretty dear ! 'tis not papa I mean. Handsome papa! the urchin, by the Queen, Knows every word you say. The other day- For this in sooth of every thing we say- The mighty man of inches went and brought me Salt-which for nitre and ceruse he bought me. And so my Diocleide—a brother wit, A money-waster, lately thought it fit To give seven goodly drachms for fleeces five— Mere rottenness, but dog's hair, as I live, The plucking of old scrips-a work to make. But come, your cloak and gold-claspt kirtle take, And let us speed to Ptolemy's rich hall, To see the fine Adonian festival. The queen will make the show most grand, I hear. All things most rich in rich men's halls appear. To those who have not seen it, one can tell What one has seen. 'Tis time to go—'tis well For those who all the year have holidays. Eunoa ! my cloak—you wanton ! quickly raise, And place it near me—cats would softly sleep ; And haste for water-how the jade does creep ! The water first—now, did you ever see ? She brings the cloak first: well, then, give it me. You wasteful slut, not too much-pour the water ! What! have you wet my kirtle ! sorrow's daughter ? Stop, now: I'm washed-gods love me : where's the key Of the great chest ? be quick, and bring it me. The gold-claspt and full-skirted gown you wear Becomes you vastly. May I ask, my dear, How much in all it cost you from the loom ? Don't mention it: I'm sure I did consume More than two mince on it: and I held on The work with heart and soul. But when done, well done! Truly—you're right. My parasol and cloak- Arrange it nicely. Cry until you choke, I will not take you, child;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.53"/>
          <p n="1.2">horse bites, you know- Boo ! Boo ! no use to have you lame. Let's go. Play with the little man, my Phrygian ! call The hound in ; lock the street-door of the hall. Gods, what a crowd : they swarm like ants, how ever Shall we work through them with our best endeavour ? From when thy sire was numbered with the blest, Many fine things, and this among the rest, Hast thou done, Ptolemy ! No villain walks The street, and picks your pocket, as he talks On some pretence with you, in Egypt's fashion : As once complete in every style, mood, passion, Resembling one another, rogues in grain, Would mock and pilfer, and then -mock again. What will become of us, dear Gorge ? see ! The king's war-horses ! Pray, don't trample me, Good sir ! the bay-horse rears ! how fierce a one ! Eunoa, stand from him: dog-heart! won't you run ? He'll kill his leader ! what a thought of joy, That safe at home remains my precious boy ! Courage ! they're as they were-and we behind them. I nearly lost my senses ; now I find them, And am myself again. Two things I hold In mortal dread-a horse and serpent cold, And have done from a child. Let us keep moving ; 0 ! what a crowd is on us, bustling, shoving. (To an old woman.) Good mother, from the palace ? Yes, my dear. Is it an easy thing to get in there ? Th' Achæans got to Troy, there's no denying ; All things are done, as they did that-by trying The old dame spoke oracles. Our sex, as you know, Know all things—e'en how Zeus espoused his Juno. Praxinoa! what a crowd about the gates ! Immense ! your hand; and, Eunoa, hold your mate's ; Do you keep close, I say, to Eutychis, And close to us, for fear the way you miss. Let us, together all, the entrance gain : Ah me ! my summer-cloak is rent in twain. Pray, spare my cloak, heaven bless you, gentleman ! 'Tis not with me—I will do what I can. The crowd, like pigs, are thrusting. Cheer thy heart, 'Tis well with us. And for your friendly part, This year and ever be it well with you ! A kind and tender man as e'er I knew. See ! how our Eunoa is prest—push through- Well done ! all in-as the gay bridegroom cried, And turned the key upon himself and bride. What rich, rare tapestry ! Look, and you'll swear The fingers of the goddesses were here. August Athene ! who such work could do ? Who spun the tissue, who the figures drew ? How life-like are they, and they seem to move ! True living shapes they are, and not inwove ! How wise is man ! and there he lies outspread In all his beauty on his silver bed, Thrice-loved Adonis ! in his youth's fresh glow, Loved even where the rueful stream doth flow. Cease ye like turtles idly thus to babble : They'll torture all of us with brogue and gabble. Who's you ? what's it to you our tongues we use ? Rule your own roost, not dames of Syracuse. And this too know we were in times foregone Corinthians, sir, as was Bellerophon. We speak the good old Greek of Pelop's isle : Dorians, I guess, may Dorian talk the while. Nymph ! grant we be at none but one man's pleasure ; A rush for you—don't wipe my empty measure. Praxinoa, hush ! behold the Argive's daughter, The girl who sings as though the Muses taught her, That won the prize for singing Sperchis' ditty, Prepares to chaunt Adonis; something pretty I'm sure she'll sing : with motion, voice, and eye, She now preludes-how sweetly, gracefully ! Of Eryx, Golgos, and Idalia, Queen ! My mistress, sporting in thy golden sheen, Bright Aphrodite ! as the month comes on Of every year, from dureful Acheron What an Adonis-from the gloomy shore The tender-footed Hours to thee restore ! Hours, slowest of the Blest! yet ever dear, That wished-for come, and still some blessing bear. Cypris! Dione's daughter ! thou through portal Of death, 'tis said, hast mortal made immortal, Sweet Berenice, dropping, ever blest! Ambrosial dew into her lovely breast. Wherefore her daughter, Helen-like in beauty, Arsinöe thy love repays with duty ; For thine Adonis fairest show ordains, Bright Queen, of many names and many fanes ! All seasonable fruits ; in silver cases His gardens sweet; and alabaster vases Of Syrian perfumes near his couch are laid ; Cakes, which with flowers and wheat the women made ; The shapes of all that creep, or take the wing, With oil or honey wrought, they hither bring ; Here are green shades, with anise shaded more ; And the young Loves him ever hover o'er, As the young nightingales, from branch to branch, Hover and try their wings, before they launch Themselves in the broad Air. But, 0! the sight Of gold and ebony ! of ivory white Behold the pair of eagles! up they move With his cup-bearer for Saturnian Jove. And see yon couch with softest purple spread, Softer than sleep, the Samian born and bred Will own, and e'en Miletus: that pavilion Queen Cypris has-the nearer one her minion, The rosy-armed Adonis; whose youth bears The bloom of eighteen or of nineteen years ; Nor pricks the kiss-the red lip of the boy ; Having her spouse, let Cypris now enjoy. Him will we, ere the dew of dawn is o'er, Bear to the waves that foam upon the shore ; Then with bare bosoms and dishevelled hair, Begin to chant the wild and mournful air. Of all the demigods, they say, but one Duly revisits Earth and Acheron— Thou, dear Adonis ! Agamemnon's might, Nor Aias, raging like one mad in fight; Nor true Patroclus ; nor his mother's boast, Hector, of twenty sons famed, honoured most; Nor Pyrrhus, victor from the Trojan siege- Not one of them enjoyed this privilege ; Nor the Deucalions ; nor Lapithae ; Argive Pelasgi ; nor Pelopidæ. Now, dear Adonis, fill thyself with glee, And still returning, still propitious be. Praxinoa, did ever mortal ear A sweeter song from sweeter minstrel hear ? O happy girl ! to know so many things- Thrice happy girl, that so divinely sings ! But now 'tis time for home : let us be hasting ; My man's mere vinegar, and most when fasting: Nor has he broken yet his fast to-day ; When he's a-hungered, come not in his way. Farewell, beloved Adonis ! joy to see ! When come, well come to those who welcome thee. JOVE'S daughters hymn the gods; and bards rehearse The deeds of worthies in their glowing verse. The heaven-born Muses hymn the heavenly ring; Of mortals, then, let mortal poets sing. Yet who-as many as there be that live Under the grey dawn, will a welcome give To our sweet Graces, or the door-latch lift, Or will not send them off without a gift ? Barefoot, with wrinkled brows, and mien deject, They chide me for the way of chill neglect; Though loath, into their empty chest they drop, And on cold knees their heavy heads they prop ; And dry their seat is, when no good they earn, But from a fruitless journey back return. What living man the poet will repay With generous love for his ennobling lay ? I know not: men no longer, as before, Would live for good deeds in poetic lore; But are overcome by detestable gain ; Close-fisted, every one doth fast retain His money, thinking how to make it grow, Nor freely would the smallest mite bestow; But says : " the knee is nearer than the shin ; Some good be mine ! from gods bards honour win. But who will hear another ? one will do-- Homer, best poet, and the cheapest too-- He costs me nothing." Fools ! what boots the gold Hid within doors in heaps cannot be told ? Not so the truly wise their wealth employ: With some 'tis fit one's natural man to joy ; Some to the bard should freely be assigned, To kin—and many others of mankind. The gods their offerings ; guests should have their dues, Welcome to come and go whene'er they choose. But most of all the generous mind prefers The Muses' consecrate interpreters. So may you live to fame, when life is done, Nor mourn inglorious at cold Acheron, Like one from birth to poverty betrayed, Whose palms are horny from the painful spade. To many a serf Antiochus the great, To many king Aleuas in his state, Measured the monthly dole. Much kine to see Lowed at the full stalls of the Scopadæ. Innumerous flocks to some cool green retreat The shepherds drove, to screen them from the heat, O'er Cranon's plain-choice flocks in choicest place, The wealth of Creon's hospitable race. No pleasure had been theirs these things about, When once their sweet souls they had emptied out Into the broad raft of drear Acheron ; But they, sad with the thoughts of life foregone, Had lain-their treasures left and memory hid— Long ages lain the wretched dead amid, Had not the glorious Ceian breathed the fire Of his quick spirit to the stringed lyre, And would not let them altogether die, But made them famous to posterity : And e'en their swift-foot steeds obtained renown, Which in the sacred race-course won the crown. Who would have known the noble Lycian pair- The sons of Priam with their pomp of hair- Or Cycnus, as a woman fair to ken, Had no bard sung the wars of former men ? Nor that Odysseus, who went wandering round, Twice sixty moons, wherever man is found, And, while alive, to farthest Hades sped, And from the cavern of the Cyclops fled, Had been aye famed; the keeper of the swine, Eumæus, and the man the herded kine Had in his watchful care, Philœtius, And e'en Laertes the magnanimous, Had been in a perpetual silence pent, But for that old Ionian eloquent. The Muses best renown on men bestow: The living waste the wealth of those below. It were all one the waves to number o'er, As many as wind and blue sea drive ashore, Or wash with water from the spring's dark urn The clay of unbaked brick, as try to turn The money-lover from his wretched pelf- But let us leave the miser to himself. May countless pieces swell his silver store ! And let him ever have a wish for more ! But may I still prefer bright honour's meed, And man's good will, to many a mule and steed! I am in quest of one whose willing mind I may, by favour of the Muses, find. Without the Jove-born sisters, harsh and hard Are all approaches found by every bard. Not weary yet revolving heaven appears Of bringing round the months and circling years. The car shall yet be moved by many a steed; And me shall some one as a minstrel need ; Than him more deeds heroic never wrought Achilles, or stout Alas, when they fought, Where in his tomb the Phrygian Ilus lies, On the broad plain of mournful Simoeis. Who, where the sun sets, dwell-on Libya's heel, The bold Phœnicians shuddering terror feel ; For Syracuse against them takes the field, Each with his ready spear and willow shield. Amidst them arms heroic Hieron, Equal to heroes of the times foregone ; Floats o'er his helm, in wavy darkness loose, His horse-hair crest—Athene ! mightiest Zeus ! And thou, who with thy mother reignest queen O'er Ephyra the wealthy, where is seen Lysimeleia's water, may the blow Of harsh Necessity rebuke the foe, And scatter them from our sweet island back O'er the Sardonian ocean's yeasty track ; And out of many, few return to tell Their wives and children how the perished fell! In the foe-ruined cities of the plain Soon may their former dwellers live again, And till the fruitful fields ! unnumbered sheep. And fat, bleat cheerily ! the cattle creep Herded in safety to the wonted stalls, Warning the traveller that evening falls ! For sowing-time be wrought the fallow lea, When the cicada, sitting on his tree, Watches the shepherds in the open day, And blithely sings, perched on the topmost spray ; O'er martial arms may spiders draw their train, And of fierce war not e'en the name remain ; And famous Hieron illustrious be, By poets hymned, beyond the Scythian sea ; Or where Semiramis her station chose, And her huge walls, asphaltos-built, arose ! I am but one: but many others are Dear to the Muses-may it be their care To praise the warrior-king (as poets use), And people, and Sicilian Arethuse ! Ye goddesses ! whose loving favours wait On that Orchomenos, the Thebans' hate, No where unbidden, but to court or hall Bidden, with you will I attend the call, Through your dear presence confident to please, Enchanting daughters of Eteocles ! What good, what fair can men without you see ? Oh ! may I ever with the Graces be ! MusES ! begin and end the song with Zeus, When of immortals we the chief extol: Of men the name of Ptolemy produce First, last, and midst-for he is chief of all. For their exploits the seed heroical Of demigods life-giving minstrels found : I, skilled to sing, will Ptolemy install Theme of my song-and glowing hymns redound E'en to their praise, who dwell th' Olympian heights around.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.86"/>
          <p n="1.3">In Ida's thick of wood, perplexed with choice, Which to begin with, the wood-cutter flings His glance around : to what shall I give voice First out of all the many blessed things, With which the gods have graced the best of kings ? How great the son of Lagus from his birth ! Born for what deeds ! what great imaginings His mind conceived beyond the sons of earth ! Up to the gods by Zeus exalted for his worth ! In Jove's own house his golden couch is spread, And by him sits his friend in royal pride, Great Alexander, the portentous dread Of Persians glittering with the turban pied : And Hercules, the vast Centauricide, Sits opposite on adamantine throne ; There with the gods he banquets gratified, In his sons' sons rejoicing as his own, Made free of age by Zeus, and as immortals known. For from heroic Hercules the twain Descended : therefore when he goes content From the gods'.banquet to his wife again, Sated with nectar of a fragrant scent, To one his quiver and his bow unbent Ever he hands, and to that other blest His iron-shotted club, with knobs besprent ; And so they marshal him unto his rest In his ambrosial home, white-ankled Hebe's nest. How excellent of dames was Berenice ! To her dear parents what a wealth of pleasure ! Dionis wiped her fingers on the spicy Swell of her bosom. No man in such measure E'er loved his wife, as Ptolemy's best leisure Doted on her ; and she with him contended In love—yea ! loved him more : his house and treasure Thus to his sons he with full trust commended, Since, loving, he the couch of loving wife ascended. Some stranger draws the wanton's fancy flighty— Her children many, like the father none ! Loveliest of goddesses ! bright Aphrodite ! Through thee, the way of wailful Acheron Was ne'er by lovely Berenice gone : Her, thy sweet care, from the Cyanean river, And death's grim ferryman, the gloomy one ! Thou didst, soft-placing in thy fane, deliver, And a conceded share of thine own honours give her. Soft loves on mortal kind she breathes benign, And makes his love-care light to every lover. Thou, who in Argos didst with Tydeus twine, Dark brows thy gentle eye-lids arching over, Didst Diomede to light of day discover ; To Peleus the full-bosomed Thetis bore Achilles; thee, (for there the birth-pang drove her The aid of Eileithuia to implore,) Bright Berenice brought forth on the Coan shore: The Woman-helper stood benignant by, Her limbs from pain composing, till she smiled On thee new-born to warrior Ptolemy— And like his father was the lovely child. Exulting Cos, with jubilant rapture wild, Fondled the babe, loud-hymning at the sight: — " Boy ! be thou blest; for me be honours piled On thy account, such as the Delian bright Hung round the blue-crowned isle, on which he sprung to light. “From thee to Triop's hill such honour follow, And no less to the Dorians dwelling nigh, As his Rhenæa had from King Apollo ! " Thus Cos: the bird of Zeus, up-poised on high, Under the clouds, well-omened thrice did cry: From king-protecting Zeus the sign was sent; But when from birth he marks a royalty, That king surpassingly is excellent For wealth, wide rule by sea and o'er much continent. In many a region many a tribe doth till The fields, made fruitful by the shower of Zeus ; None like low-lying Egypt doth fulfil Hope of increase, when Nile the clod doth loose, O'er-bubbling the wet soil: no land doth use So many workmen of all sorts, enrolled In cities of such multitude profuse, More than three myriads, as a single fold Under the watchful sway of Ptolemy the bold. Part of Phoenicia ; some Arabian lands ; Some Syrian ; tribes of swart Æthiopes ; All the Pamphylians, Lycians he commands, And warlike Carians ; o'er the Cyclades His empire spreads ; his navies sweep the seas ; Ocean and rivers, earth within her bounds Obeys him : and a host of chivalries, And shielded infantry, with martial sounds Of their far-glittering brass, the warrior-king surrounds, His wealth, that daily flows from every side, The treasure of all other kings outweighs ; His busy people's days in quiet glide: The monster-breeding Nile no hostile blaze Doth overpass, the war-shout there to raise. Nor hath armed foeman from swift ship outleapt To seize the kine Egyptian pastures graze ; For o'er the broad lands of that happy sept The bright-haired Ptolemy strict ward hath ever kept. His whole inheritance he cares to keep, As a good king : himself hath garnered more: Nor useless in his house the golden heap, Increased like that of ants; for of his store The gods have much, since them he doth adore Ever with first-fruits, and his love commends With other gifts ; his bounty ne'er is poor; To noble-minded princes much he sends, ,And gives to cities much, and much to worthy friends. None in the sacred games e'er took a part, Skilled the melodious song to modulate, Without a royal recompense of art: Whence Ptolemy the muse-priests celebrate For his munificence. What meed more great Than good renown can wealthy man befall ? This meed doth on the dead Atridæ wait; Their infinite spoil from Priam's ravaged hall In the thick gloom lies hid, from whence is no recall. Only this prince hath in his fathers' ways Exactly walked, and doth their stamp retain ; Whence he to both his parents loved to raise Temples, and placed their statues in each fane, Of gold and ivory-never sought in vain By prayer of mortals; on their altars red Fat thighs of oxen burn the royal twain, Himself and consort-one more furnished With love and excellence ne'er clasped her spouse in bed. Such were the nuptials of the royal pair, Whom Rhea bore, the royalties divine Of blest Olympus : Iris spread with care, Iris the virgin yet, whose fingers shine With fragrant brightness, when they would recline The marriage couch. Hail, Ptolemy ! to thee And other demigods I will assign Due praise. One word for after-men ; to me It seems, whatever good there is, from Zeus must be. TWELVE Spartan virgins, the Laconian bloom, Choired before their Helen's bridal room, New hung with tapestry : entwined the fair With hyacinths their hyacinthine hair ; When Menelaus, Atreus' younger pride, Locked in sweet Tyndaris, his lovely bride ; To the same time with cadence true they beat The rapid round of intertwining feet; One measure tript, one song together sung- Their hymenæan all the palace rung. So early, bridegroom ! fix'd in slumber deep ? So heavy-limbed, with such a love for sleep ? Thyself, wine-heavy, on the bed hast thrown For only rest ? thou shouldst have slept alone, And with her mother left the girl to play With only girls until the break of day. She's thine from day to day, and year to year- Thrice-happy bridegroom ! on thy way 'tis clear Good demon sneezed, that only thou shouldst gain The prize so many princes would obtain, Only of demigods, whose bosomed love Her husband makes the son-in-law of Jove ! Jove's daughter, peerless beauty-bud of Greece, Now lies with thee beneath one broidered fleece. What offspring to thy hopes will she prefer- Could her dear offspring but resemble her ! Where flows Eurotas in his pleasant place, Thrice eighty virgins, we pursued the race, Like men, anointed with the glistering oil, A bloom of maiden buds—love's blushing spoil: Of equal years ; but, seen by Helen's side, Not one in whom some blemish was not spied. As rising Morn, oh, venerable Night ! Shows from thy bosom dark her face of light ; As the clear spring, when winter's gloom is gone, So mid our throng the golden Helen shone. As of a field or garden ornament, The lofty cypress shoots up eminent; As of the chariot the Thessalian steed, So rosy Helen of the Spartan breed Is ornament and grace. Like Helen none Draws the fine thread around the spindle spun, And in the ready basket piles so much ; None interlaces with so quick a touch The woof and warp ; for other never came A web so perfect from the broidering frame. Like Helen none the cithern knows to ring, Of Artemis or tall Athene sing, Like Helen, in whose liquid-shining eyes Desire, the light of love, dissolving lies. O fair and lovely girl! a matron now- Where meadow-flowers in dewy brightness grow, We'll hie with early dawn, and fondly pull Sweets to twine garlands for our beautiful ; Remembering Helen with our fond regrets, As for the absent ewe her suckling frets. Of lotuses we'll hang thee many a wreath Upon the shady plane, and drop beneath Oil from the silver pyx ; and on the bark, In Doric, shall be graved for all to mark, “To me pay honour—I am Helen's tree." Hail, bride ! high-wedded bridegroom, hail to thee! Fruitful Latona fruit of marriage give ; Cypris in bonds of mutual love to live; And Zeus the wealth that shall without an end From high-born sire to high-born son descend! Sleep, happy pair ! in love enjoy your rest, Breathing desire into each other's breast. But wake at dawn ; for we'll present us here At the first call of crested chanticleer. Hymen, 0 Hymenaean ! joyful spread With love's contentment sweet this marriage-bed. As from a hive the thieving Eros drew A honey-comb, a bee his finger stung ; Then in his anguish on his hand he blew, Stamped, jumped-and then to Cytherea sprung; Showed her the wound, and cried: " A thing how wee, How great a wound makes with its little sting ! " His mother smiled: “Art thou not like a bee, Such great wounds making-such a little thing ? ” EUNICA, smiling with a bitter scoff, When I would sweetly kiss her, bade me " off ! Fool cowherd ! would you kiss me ? not to kiss Rude clowns, but city lips, I've learnt, I wis. You never, man ! shall kiss my lovely mouth- Not in a dream. You are—O how uncouth ! Your look offends me, and your speech provokes; Your play is horse-play ; vulgar are your jokes. How smooth in speech ! how delicate an air ! How soft your beard ! how odorous your hair ! Your lips are sickly ; and your hands are black, And you smell rank: don't foul me; back, clown, back! Thrice on her breast she spat, these hard words saying, Me scornfully from head to foot surveying; Pouting and muttering proudly looked askaunt, Before mine eyes did plume her form and flaunt, And mocking smiled with lips drawn far apart. My blood boiled fiercely from my grief of heart, And red my cheeks from passionate anguish grew, As vernal roses from the morning dew. She left me then : but angry feelings glow Within my heart, because she used me so. Am I not handsome, shepherds ? tell me truly; Or has some god transformed my person newly ? For as lush ivy clips the stem o' the tree, The bloom of beauty lately covered me. My curls, like parsley, round my temples clung ; A shining forehead my dark brows o'erhung; My eyes were bluer than Athene's own ; My mouth than new cheese sweeter ; every tone Sweeter than honeycombs: and sweet I take My song to be; the sweetest sounds I wake From all wind instruments, in very deed- Straight pipe or transverse, flute or vocal reed. The girls upon the hills me handsome call; They kiss me lovingly-they love me all. But ah ! my city-madam never kist me ; And for I am a cowherd she dismist me. That Dionysus in the valleys green Once tended kine, she never heard, I ween ; Nor knows that Cypris on a cowherd doted, And on the Phrygian hills herself devoted To tend his herd; nor how the same Dionis In thickets kist, in thickets wept Adonis. Who was Endymion ? him tending kine Stooped down to kiss Selena the divine, Who from Olympus to the Latmian grove Glided to slumber with her mortal love. Didst thou not, Rhea, for a cowherd weep ? And didst thou not, high Zeus ! the heaven sweep, In form of winged bird, and watch indeed To carry off the cowherd Ganymede ? Only Eunica (daintier she must be Than were Selena, Cypris, Cybele,) Won't kiss a cowherd. May'st thou ne'er uncover Thyself, self-worshipt Beauty! to a lover In town or country ; but, vain poppet! ever Sleep by thyself-despite thy best endeavour. THE nurse of industry and arts is want; Care breaks the labourer's sleep, my Diophant! And should sweet slumber o'er his eyelids creep, Dark cares stand over him, and startle sleep. Two fishers old lay in their wattled shed, Close to the wicker on one sea-moss bed; Near them the tools wherewith they plied their craft, The basket, rush-trap, line, and reedy shaft, Weed-tangled baits, a drag-net with its drops, Hooks, cord, two oars, an old boat fixt on props. Their rush-mat, clothes, and caps, propt either head; These were their implements by which they fed, And this was all their wealth. They were not richer By so much as a pipkin or a pitcher. All else seemed vanity: they could not mend Their poverty-which was their only friend.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="3.107"/>
          <p n="1.4">They had no neighbours ; but upon the shore The sea soft murmured at their cottage door. The chariot of the moon was midway only, When thoughts of toil awoke those fishers lonely: And shaking sleep off they began to sing. The summer-nights are short, when Zeus the king Makes the days long, some say-and lie. This night I've seen a world of dreams, nor yet 'tis light. What's all this ? am I wrong ? or say I truly ? And can we have a long, long night in July? Do you the summer blame ? The seasons change, Nor willingly transgress their wonted range. From care, that frightens sleep, much longer seems The weary night. Can you interpret dreams ? I've seen a bright one, which I will declare, That you my visions, as my toil, may share. To whom should you in mother-wit defer ? And quick wit is best dream-interpreter. We've leisure, and to spare: what can one do, Lying awake on leaves, as I and you, Without a lamp ? they say the town-hall ever Has burning lights—its booty fails it never. Well: let us have your vision of the night. When yester-eve I slept, outwearied quite With the sea-toil, not over-fed, for our Commons, you know, were short at feeding hour, I saw myself upon a rock, where I Sat watching for the fish—so eagerly ! And from the reed the tripping bait did shake, Till a fat fellow took it-no mistake : ('Twas natural-like that I should dream of fish, As hounds of meat upon a greasy dish :) He hugged the hook, and then his blood did flow; His plunges bent my reed like any bow ; I stretched both arms, and had a pretty bout, To take with hook so weak a fish so stout. I gently warned him of the wound he bore ; " Ha ! will you prick me ? you'll be pricked much more.” But when he struggled not, I drew him in; The contest then I saw myself did win. I landed him, a fish compact of gold ! But then a sudden fear my mind did hold, Lest king Poseidon made it his delight, Or it was Amphitrite's favourite. I loosed him gently from the hook, for fear It from his mouth some precious gold might tear, And with my line I safely towed him home, And swore that I on sea no more would roam, But ever after would remain on land, And there my gold, like any king, command. At this I woke; your wits, good friend, awaken, For much I fear to break the oath I've taken. Fear not: you swore not, saw not with your eyes The fish you saw ; for visions all are lies. But now no longer slumber : up, awake ! And for a false a real vision take. Hunt for the foodful fish that is, not seems ; For fear you starve amid your golden dreams. THE twins of Leda, child of Thestius, Twice and again we celebrate in song, The Spartan pair, stamped by Ægiochus, Castor and Pollux, arming with the thong His dreadful hands ; both merciful as strong Saviours of men on danger's extreme edge, And steeds tost in the battle's bloody throng, And star-defying ships on ruin's ledge, Swept with their crews by blasts into the cruel dredge. The winds, where'er they list, the huge wave drive, Dashing from prow or stern into the hold ; Both sides, sail, tackle, yard, and mast, they rive, Snapping at random: from Night's sudden fold Rushes a flood; hither and thither rolled, Broad ocean's heaving volumes roar and hiss, Smitten by blasts and the hail-volley cold: The lost ship and her crew your task it is, Bright pair ! to rescue from the terrible abyss. They think to die—but lo! a sudden lull 0' the winds ; the clouds disperse; and the hush'd sheen Of the calmed ocean sparkles beautiful: The Bears, and Asses with the Stall between, Foreshow a voyage safe and skies serene. Blest Brothers ! who to mortals safety bring, Both harpers, minstrels, knights, and warriors keen: Since both I hymn, with which immortal king Shall I commence my song ? of Pollux first I'll sing. The justling rocks, the dangerous Euxine's mouth, Snow-veiled, when Argo safely passed, and ended Her course at the Bebrycian shore, the youth Born of the gods from both her sides descended, And on the deep shore, from rude winds defended, Their couches spread ; and strook the seeds of fire From the pyreion. Forthwith unattended Did Pollux, of the red-brown hue, retire With Castor, whose renown for horsemanship was higher. L'On a high hill a forest did appear: The brothers found there a perennial spring, Under a smooth rock, filled with water clear, With pebbles paved, which from below did fling A crystal sheen like silver glistering : The poplar, plane, tall pine, and cypress, grew Hard by : and odorous flowers did thither bring Thick swarm of bees, their sweet toil to pursue, As many as in the meads, when spring ends, bloom to view. There lay at ease a bulky insolent, Grim-looked : his ears by gauntlets scored and marred ; His vast chest, like a ball, was prominent; His back was broad with flesh like iron hard, Like anvil-wrought Colossus to regard ; And under either shoulder thews were seen On his strong arms, like round stones which, oft jarred In the quick rush with many a bound between, A winter torrent rolls down through the cleft ravine. A lion's hide suspended by the feet Hung from his neck and o'er his shoulders fell: Him the prize-winner Pollux first did greet: " Hail, stranger! in these parts what people dwell ? " " The hail of utter stranger sounds not well, At least to me." “We're not malevolent, Nor sons of such, take heart." “You need not tell Me that—I in myself am confident." " You are a savage, quick to wrath and insolent." " You see me as I am ; upon your land I do not walk." " Come thither, and return With hospitable gifts." " I've none at hand For you, nor want I yours." “Pray, let me learn, Wilt let me drink from out this fountain urn ?" " You'll know, if your thirst-hanging lips are dry." " How may we coax you from your humour stern, With silver or what else ?" " The combat try—” " How, pray, with gauntlets, foot to foot and eye to eye ?" " In pugilistic fight, nor spare your skill." - " Who is my gauntlet-armed antagonist ? " " At hand ! he's here ; you see him if you will, I, Amycus, the famous pugilist." " And what the prize of the victorious fist ? " " The vanquished shall become the victor's thrall." " Red-crested cocks so fight, and so desist." " Cock-like or lion-like the combat call; This is the prize for which we fight, or none at all." Then on a conch he blew a mighty blast: The long-haired Bebryces, hearing the sound, Under the shady planes assembled fast; And likewise Castor, in the fight renowned, Hastened and called his comrades to the ground, From the Magnesian ship. With gauntlets both Armed their strong hands ; their wrists and arms they bound With the long thongs; with one another wroth, Each breathing blood and death, they stood up nothing loth. First'each contended which should get the sun Of his antagonist; but much in sleight That huge man, Pollux! was by thee outdone; And Amycus was dazzled with the light; But raging rushed straight forward to the fight, Aiming fierce blows ; but wary Pollux met him, Striking the chin of his vast opposite, Who fiercer battled, for the blow did fret him, And leaning forward tried unto the ground to get him. Shouted the Bebryces ; and, for they feared The man like Tityus might their friend down-weigh In the scant place, the heroes Pollux cheered: But shifting here and there Jove's son made play, And struck out right and left, but kept away From the fierce rush of Neptune's son uncouth, Who, drunk with blows, reeled in the hot affray, Out-spitting purple blood; the princely youth Shouted, when they beheld his battered jaws and mouth. His eyes were nearly closed from the contusion Of his swoln face ; the prince amazed him more With many feints, and seeing his confusion, Mid-front he struck a heavy blow and sore, And to the bone his forehead gashing tore; Instant he fell, and at his length he lay On the green leaves ; but fiercely as before, On his uprising, they renewed the fray, Aiming terrific blows, as with intent to slay. But the Bebrycian champion strove to place His blows upon the broad breast of his foe, Who ceaselessly disfigured all his face: His flesh with sweating shrunk, that he did show, From huge, but small; but larger seemed to grow The limbs of Pollux, and of fresher hue The more he toiled: Muse ! for 'tis thine to know, And mine to give interpretation true. Tell how the son of Zeus that mighty bulk o’verthrew. Aiming at something great, the big Bebrycian The left of Pollux with his left hand caught, Obliquely leaning out from his position, And from his flank his huge right hand he brought, And had he hit him would have surely wrought Pollux much damage; but escape he found, Stooping his head, and smote him, quick as thought, On the left temple; from the gaping wound A bubbling gush of gore out-spurted on the ground. Right on his mouth his left hand then he dashed; Rattled his teeth ; and with a quicker hail Of blows he smote him, till his cheeks he smashed: Stretched out he lay; his senses all did fail, Save that he owned the other did prevail By holding up his hands: nor thou didst claim The forfeit, Pollux, taking of him bail Of a great oath in his own father's name, Strangers to harm no more with word or deed of shame. To Castor now belongs my votive strain, The brass-mailed, shake-spear knight. The twins of Zeus, It chanced, had carried off the daughters twain Of old Leucippus; wroth for which abuse, The two bold brothers, sons of Aphareus, Pursued the ravishers incontinent- Their plighted bridegrooms, Idas and Lynceus. They overtook them at the monument Of the dead Aphareus, as on their way they went. With shields and spears all from their chariots leapt, And Lynceus through his helmet loudly spoke: " Why not let brides be by their bridegrooms kept ? Why with your drawn swords, ready for the stroke, Do you so eagerly the fight provoke ? To us their sire betrothed them, and did swear An oath thereto-which oath he only broke Persuaded by your gifts, (foul shame to hear In case of others' brides,) kine, mules, and divers gear. " Oft have I said, although no speechifier, Before you both ; my friends ! it is not right Princes for wives those maidens should desire, Whose bridegrooms wait them and the nuptial night; Sparta, sweet Arcady with fleeces white, Equestrian Elis, famous Argolis, The Achæan towns, Messenia's ample site, And all the shore-reach of rich Sisyphis, Are all of great extent with choice of maids, I wis. " And you may pick and choose at will of these, Who are in mind, form, feature, excellent; Good men for sons-in-law most fathers please, And you 'mid heroes are pre-eminent, On either side ennobled by descent. Come, let our nuptials to their end proceed ; We'll find brides for you to your heart's content: The wind to wave swept off my useless rede ; might as well have preached unto the winds indeed. " You are ungentle in your wilful mood ; Be now persuaded for your own behoof; Though we are cousins-if it seems you good This strife to finish by the battle-proof, Let Idas and brave Pollux stand aloof, While Castor and myself, the younger, try The battle; thus to the parental roof We shall not leave an utter misery- One death is quite enough for one sad family. " Those who survive shall gladden all their friends, (Bridegrooms, not corses,) and these virgins wed: Good is small ill that great contention ends." And Providence fulfilled the words he said. That elder pair their arms deposited; But Lynceus shook, under his shield's broad rest, His quivering lance, and Castor likewise sped To meet him : to the conflict fierce they prest; On either martial head nodded the horse-hair crest. First with their spears they aimed full many a blow, Where'er an exposed part came into sight, But ere they injured one another so, The spear-heads broke in either broad shield pight: Then from the sheaths they drew their swords outright, And fiercely on the other either prest, Nor paused a moment in the furious fight; And each at shield or helm their blows addrest, 3ut quick-eyed Lynceus maimed-only the purple crest. At Castor's left knee then he fiercely strook, Who, 'scaping, smote the threatening hand away; He, running, to his father's tomb betook Himself, dropping the hand : there Idas lay Watching the cousins ply the bloody fray; But eager Castor drove his thirsty sword Through flank and navel; out-gushed to the day His bowels, where out-spread he lay begored ; And down his eyelids dim the heavy sleep was poured. Nor was it fated that his mother dear Should see the other wed to her content; For Idas at that hapless sight did tear A pillar from his father's monument, To slay his brother's slayer;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.11"/>
          <p n="1.5">but Zeus sent, In aid of Castor, his devouring fire, Made drop the marble, and himself up'-brent. So they did to none easy task aspire, Who fought those mighty ones-the sons of mighty sire. Hail, sons of Leda ! give my hymns renown : To you and Helen, dear the minstrel's claim, And dear to all who threw proud Ilion down. The Chian minstrel, princes! gave you fame, Of Troy, th' Achæan ships that thither came, The war, and the war's tower, Achilles brave, Hymning the song : may mine be free from blame! I give you what to me the Muses gave; And gods prefer the song to all the gifts they have! A YOUTH was love-sick for a maid unkind, Whose form was blameless, but not so her mind. She scorned her lover and his suit disdained; One gentle thought she never entertained. She knew not Love-what sort of god, what darts From what a bow he shoots at youthful hearts ! Her lips were strangers to soft gentleness, And she was difficult of all access. She had no word to soothe his scorching fire, No sparkle of the lip ; no moist desire To her bright eyes a dewy lustre lent; Blushed on her cheek no crimson of consent; She breathed no word of sighing born-no kiss That lightens love, and turns its pain to bliss. But, as the wild game from his thicket spies The train of hunters with suspicious eyes, So she her lover ; ever did she turn Toward him scornful lip, and eye-glance stern. She was his fate: and on her glooming face, The scorn that burned within her left its trace. Her colour fled; and every feature showed Pale from the rage that in her bosom glowed. Yet even so she was - how fair to see! The more she scorned him, still the more loved he. At last by Cypris scorched without her cure, He could no more the raging flame endure. He went and kist her door, and tears he shed, And, 'midst his tears and kisses, sadly said: " Harsh, cruel girl! stone-heart and pitiless! The nurseling of some savage lioness, Unworthy love! my latest gift I bring, This noose-no more will I thine anger sting. But now I go where thou hast sentenced me— The common road which all reports agree Must at some time by all that live be gone, And where love's cure is found-Oblivion. Ah ! could I drink it all, I should not slake My passionate longing: at thy gates I take My last farewell, thereto commit indeed My latest sigh. The future I can read- The rose is beautiful, the rose of prime, But soon it withers at the touch of time; And beautiful in spring-time to behold The violet, but ah ! it soon grows old; White are the lilies, but they soon decay; White is the snow, but soon it melts away; And beautiful the bloom of virgin youth, But lives a very little time in sooth. Thy time will come-thou too at last shalt prove, And weep most bitterly, the flames of love. But grant, I pray thee, grant my latest prayer: When thou shalt see me hanging high in air, E'en at thy door—O pass not heedless by ! But drop a few tears to my memory. From the harsh thong unloose thy hapless lover, And from thy limbs a garment take and cover The lifeless body, and the last kiss give ; Fear not that haply I may come alive At thy lip's touch—I cannot live again ; Thy kiss, if given in love, were given in vain ! Hollow a mound to hide my love's sad end, And thrice on leaving, cry, 'Here lie, my friend And, if thou wilt, by thee this word be said, ‘Here lies my love, my beautiful is dead.' And let this epitaph mine end recall, Just at the last I scratch it on thy wall: ‘Love slew him : stop and say,- Who here is laid Well but not wisely loved a cruel maid.' " Then in the doorway for its cruel use He set a stone; he fitted next the noose ; Put in his neck, and eagerly he sped, Spurning the stone away-and swung there dead. But when she saw the corse her doorway kept, She was not moved in spirit, nor she wept: She felt no ruth, but, scornful to the last, She spat upon the body, as she past; And careless went to bathe her and adorn, Where stood a statue of the god, her scorn. From the bath's marble edge whereon it stood, The statue leapt and slew her: with her blood The water was impurpled, and the sound Of the girl's dying accent swam around :— " Ah lovers ! she that scorned true love is slain ; Love is revengeful: when loved, love again." ALCMENA having washed her twin delight, Her Hercules, who then was ten months old, And her Iphicles, younger by a night, Gave them the breast, then laid them in the hold Of a brass shield won by Amphitryon bold- The spoil of Pterelas in battle slain; And, touching either head, her blessing told : “Sleep, healthful sleep enjoy my blessed twain ; Sleep happy ! happy wake at coming dawn again." And with these words she rocked the mighty shield, And sleep came over them: in the midnight, What time the Bear, watching Orion's field, (Who then his shoulder shows uprising bright,) To setting turns, vex'd Hera's wily spite, With many threats of her revengeful ire, To eat the infant Hercules outright, Sent to the chamber-door two monsters dire, Each bristling horribly with his dark-gleaming spire. They their blood-gorging bellies on the ground Uncoiling rolled ; their eyes shot baleful flame, And evermore they spat their poison round; But when, quick brandishing with evil aim Their forked tongues, they to the children came, They both awoke : (what can escape Jove's eye ?) Light in the chamber shone ; and who can blame Or wonder that Iphicles did outcry, Screaming, when he did their remorseless teeth espy ? He kicked aside the woollen coverlet, Struggling to flee ; but Hercules comprest, Relaxing not the gripe his hand did get, With a firm grasp the throat of either pest, Where is their poison, which e'en gods detest. The boy, that in the birth was long confined, Who ne'er was known to cry, though at the breast A suckling yet, they with their coils entwined : Infolding him they strained their own release to find, Till wearied in their spines they loosed their fold. Alcmena heard the noise and woke in fear :— " Amphitryon, up ! for me strange fear doth hold- Up ! up ! don't wait for sandals ; don't you hear Iphicles screaming ? see ! the walls appear Distinctly shining in the dead of night, As though 'twere dawn. There is some danger near ; I'm sure there is, dear man !" He then outright Did leap from off the bed to hush his wife's affright. And hastily his costly sword he sought; Suspended near his cedar-bed it hung ; With one hand raised the sheath of lotus wrought, While with the other he the belt unswung. The room was filled with night again : he sprung, And for his household, breathing slumber deep, He loudly called ; his voice loud echoing rung : " Ho! from the hearth bring lights ! quick ! do not creep ! Fling wide the doors-awake ! this is no time for sleep." They hastened all with lights at his command ; But when they saw (their eyes they well might doubt) A serpent clutched in either tender hand Of suckling Hercules, they gave a shout, And clapped their hands : he instantly held out The serpents to Amphitryon, and wild With child-like exultation leaped about, And laid them at his father's feet and smiled- Laid down those monsters grim, in sleep of death now mild. Alcmena to her fragrant bosom drew Iphicles screaming and with fear half-dead ; The lamb-wool coverlet Amphitryon threw O'er Hercules and went again to bed. The cocks, the third time crowing, heralded The day-dawn: then Alcmena sent to call Tiresias the seer, who truly said Whate'er he said would be ; and told him all, And bade him answer her what thing would thence befall: " Hide not, I pray, from reverence for me If aught of ill the gods design : 'tis clear What fate has spun for him no man can flee ; But saying this I teach the wise, good seer !” He answered : " Woman ! privileged to bear The noblest offspring, princess of the blood Of Perseus, by my own sweet light I swear, Which once was in these eyes, as name for good Shall be remembered long Alcmena's womanhood. " The Achæan women while they spin, I wis, Alcmena's name to latest eve shall sing ; And famous shalt thou be in Argolis ; For this thy son to star-paved heaven shall spring : All that contend with the broad-breasted king, Or man or beast, shall yield the victory. Twelve labours wrought, him Destiny shall bring To Jove's own house, but all of him can die On the Trachinian pyre shall perish utterly. " And he the son-in-law of her shall be, Who sent these dragons to destroy the child ; Then in his lair the sharp-toothed wolf shall see The fawn, nor harm it, wonderfully mild. In the hearth-ashes let there now be piled All sorts of thorn, bramble, and prickly pear, And dry, wind-shaken twigs of buck-thorn wild ; And at the midnight burn these dragons here, Since they to slay the child at midnight did appear. " A maid must cast these ashes with the wind At morn from yon rock to the rushing tide, Then hasten home and never look behind. With sulphur let the house be purified ; Pure water, mixed with salt, from side to side Then from a full urn sprinkle on the floor : For so the holy custom doth provide ; And sacrifice to Zeus supreme a boar, That o'er your foes you may be victors evermore." Then, rising from the ivory chair, withdrew Tiresias, and bent with years was he. But Hercules with his fond mother grew, As grows a young plant in a fruitful lea, And still Amphitryon's boy was thought to be : Linus, Apollo's son, heroic name ! Instructed him in letters carefully. And Eurytus, who from rich parents came, Taught him to bend the bow and take unerring aim. To move his fingers on the harp with ease, And to the music minstrelsy to sing, Him taught Eumolpus Philammonides: And with what sleights the men of Argos fling Each other, wrestling fiercely in the ring, And every sort of pugilistic sleight, Him taught the son of the Cyllenian king, Harpalicus, whose dreadful brow did fright Men from afar, that few would dare with him to fight. To drive the chariot, and impel, control The rapid-bounding steeds, and how to shun Dashing his axle-nave against the goal, He was instructed by Amphitryon, Who willingly did teach his hopeful son : In Argos oft, whose praises are far-spoken For generous steeds, himself had prizes won ; And of his skill there was this certain token, Though time had marred the reins, his chariot was unbroken. In stationary fight to aim the lance, Shielding himself; to bide swords flashing round ; To draw his battle out, and bid advance The cavalry; to scan the foeman's ground, While to the charge the troops impetuous bound,- He learned from Castor, who, till he was old, Of demigods was warrior most renowned, Exiled from Argos then, which Tydeus bold With all the vine-land broad did from Adrastus hold. Alcmena thus had taught her Hercules. His sleeping-place was near his father's bed; And, what did most of all his fancy please, For the bold boy a lion's hide was spread. His morning meal, roast meat and Dorian bread- No ploughman would a larger loaf desire; His evening meal (the day already sped) Was very light; nor such as needed fire. He always wore, bare to his knees, a plain attire. WHEN, to perform his fated lord's behest, Amphitryon's son, with toils and perils tried, Hero with the prodigious breadth of breast,- In his right hand his club, the lion's hide Hung from his shoulders by the fore-feet tied,- To the rich vale of fruitful Elis came, Where the sweet waters of Alphëus glide, Seeing herds, flocks, and pastures, none might claim, But only wealthiest lord, some prince well known to fame, He asked a countryman, whose watchful care O'erlooked the grounds, (his task was his delight,) “Good friend! wilt tell a traveller, whose are These herds, and flocks, and pastures infinite ? He is, I well may guess, the favourite Of the Olympian gods. Here should abide Those I am come to seek." The man, at sight And claim of stranger, quickly laid aside The work he had in hand, and courteously replied : " What thou dost ask I willingly will tell, Good stranger ! for I fear the heavy wrath Of Hermes, the way-god ; of all who dwell Above us, most is he provoked, when scath Or scorn is done to him who asks his path. Not in one pasture all the flocks appear, Nor in one region, King Augeias hath: Some pasture where Elisson glides ; some, where Alpheus ; at vine-clad Buprasion some ; some, here : " And every flock has its particular fold. Their pasture never fails his numerous kine In the green lowlands that receiving hold The gush of Peneus, and the dew divine: As in the genial moisture they recline, The meads throw up soft herbage, which supplies The strength of the horned kine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.36"/>
          <p n="1.6">Beyond the shine Of the far-gliding river-turn your eyes A little to the left-their stalled enclosure lies ; " Yonder, where the perennial planes elate Stand lordly, and the green wild-olives grow,- A grove to King Apollo dedicate, The pastoral god, most perfect god we know. Hard by, our dwellings in a lengthened row ; Our labour an immense revenue yields To our good lord, as often as we sow, When thrice or four times ploughed, the fallow fields : Each of his husbandmen the spade or hoe that wields, " Earthing the vine-roots, or at vintage-tide Toils at the wine-press, knows where the domain Of rich Augeias ends on every side. For his is all the far-extended plain, Orchards thick-set with trees, and fields with grain, E'en to the fount-full hill-tops far away ; All which we work at (as behoves the swain, Whose life is spent a-field) through all the day. Why thou art come-to tell may be thy profit-say. " Dost seek Augeias, or some one of those Who serve him ? I will give an answer clear, And to the point, as one that fully knows. Not mean art thou, nor of mean sires, I'd swear, So grand thy form. The sons of gods appear Such among men." To him Jove's son replied : " In truth, old man ! for that did bring me here, Augeias I would see : if it betide Th' Epeän chief doth in the city now abide, " And, caring for the folk, as j udge fulfils True judgment; bid his trusty steward me speed, With whom as guide I may converse. God wills That mortal men should one another need." To him the husbandman : " It seems, indeed, Thy way was heaven-appointed : in thine aim, E'en to thy wish, thou dost at once succeed; For yesterday Augeias hither came, With his illustrious son, Phyleüs hight by name. "After long time, his rural wealth to see, He came: to this e'en princes are not blind, The master there, his house will safer be. But let us to the stall; there shall we find Augeias." Led the way that old man kind : Seeing the great hand-filling club, and spoil Of the wild beast, he puzzled much his mind, Who he could be, come from what natal soil; And with desire to ask him this did inward boil, But caught the word just to his lips proceeding, For fear he might with question indiscreet, Or out of place, annoy the stranger speeding: 'Tis a hard thing another's thought to weet. The hounds both ways, by scent and fall of feet, Perceived them from afar. At Hercules They flew, loud barking at him, but did greet The old man, whining gently as you please, And round him wagged their tails, and fawning licked his knees. But he with stones-to lift them was enough- Scared back the hounds, their barking did restrain, And scolded them ; but, though his voice was rough, His heart was glad they did such guard maintain, When he was absent. Then he spoke again: " Gods ! what an animal! what faithful suit He does to man ! if he where to abstain, Where rage, but knew, none other might dispute With him in excellence ; but 'tis too fierce a brute." And soon they reached the stall. The sun his steeds Turned to the west, bringing the close of day. The herds and flocks, returning from the meads, Came to the stables where they nightly lay. The kine in long succession trod the way, Innumerous ; as watery clouds on high, By south or west wind driven in dense array, One on another press, and forward fly, Numberless, without end, along the thickened sky; So many upon so many impels the wind; Others on others drive their crests to twine: So many herds so many pressed behind ; The plain, the ways, were filled in breadth and line; The fields were straitened with the lowing kine. The sheep were folded soon ; the cattle, too, That inward, as they walk, their knees incline, Were all installed, a multitude to view : No man stood idle by for want of work to do. Some to the kine their wooden shoes applied, And bound with thongs; while some in station near To milk them took their proper place beside : One to the dams let go their younglings dear, Mad for the warm milk; while another there The milk-pail held, the curds to cheese one turned: Meanwhile Augeias went by every where, And with his own eyes for himself he learned What revenue for him his cattle-keepers earned. With him his son and mighty Hercules Through his exceeding show of riches went. And, though his mind Amphitryonides Was wont to keep on balance and unbent, At sight thereof he was in wonderment: Had he not seen it, he'd have thought it fable, That any one, however eminent For wealth, or any ten, in fold, stall, stable, The richest of all kings, to show such wealth were able. Hyperion gave unto his son most dear, That he should all in flocks and herds excel. His care increased them more from year to year; For on his herds no sort of ailment fell, Such as destroys the cattle: his grew well, In pith improving still. None cast their young, Which almost all were female. He could tell Three hundred white-skinned bulls his kine among, And eke two hundred red, that to their pastime sprung. Twelve swan-white bulls were sacred to the sun, All inknee'd bulls excelling; these apart Cropped the green pasture, and were never done Exulting; when from thicket shag did dart Wild beasts, among the herds to play their part, These twelve first rushed, death-looking, to the war, Roaring most terribly. In pride of heart And strength great Phaethon (men to a star Did liken him) was first, mid many seen afar. When this bull saw the tawny lion's hide, He rushed on watchful Hercules, intent To plunge his armed forehead in his side: But then the hero grasped incontinent The bull's left horn, and to the ground back-bent His heavy neck; then backward pressed his might. The bull, more struggling as more backward sent, At last stood, stretching every nerve, upright. The king, and prince, and swains, all marvelled at the sight. But to the city, on the following day, Bold Hercules and prince Phyleüs sped. At first their path through a thick vineyard lay, Narrow, and 'mid the green, through which it led, Half-hid. This past, Phyleüs turned his head O'er his right shoulder, soon as they did reach The public road, and to the hero said, Who walked behind him : “Friend, I did impeach Myself as having lost, concerning thee, some speech " I long since heard : now I remember me, A young Achæan hither on a day From Argos came, from sea-shore Helice, Who, many Epeans present, then did say He saw an Argive man a monster slay, A lion, dread of all the country round, Whose lair in grove of Zeus the Nemean lay: I am not sure if on Tirynthian ground, Or else in Argos born, or in Mycenian bound; "But said, if I remember rightly now, The hero sprung from Perseus: I confess Methinks none other Argive man but thou Dared that adventure: yea! that piece of dress, The lion's hide, avows that hardiness. Then, hero, first of all explain tome, That I may know if right or wrong my guess, Whether thou art in truth that very he, Whose deed was told us by the man of Helice. " Next, tell how thou didst slay the dreadful beast, And how his way to Nemean haunt he found: One, if he searched in Apian land at least, Such monster could not find, though bears abound, Boars and destructive wolves, the country round: Wherefore all marvelled at the man's recital, And thought the traveller, with idle sound Of his invented wonders, in requital Of hospitable rites, was striving to delight all." Then from the mid-path to the road-side near Phyleüs kept, that both abreast might find Sufficient room, and he might better hear What Hercules should say, who, still behind, To him replied: " Not from the truth declined, But with just balance thou hast judged it well: Since thou would'st hear, I with a willing mind Will tell, Phyleüs, how the monster fell, But whence he came nor I, nor Argive else can tell. “Only we think that some immortal sent, For holy rites profaned or left undone, That ill on the Phoronians; forth he went, And the Piseäns, like a flood, o'errun : The Bembinaeans least of all could shun His fateful wrath; they, nearest, fared the worst: To slay that terrible redoubted one Was task enjoined me by Eurystheus erst; His wish I undertook, of my set toils the first. "My flexile bow I took, and quiver full Of arrows, and my club, the bark still on, The stem of a wild olive I did pull Up by the roots, when thither I was gone, Under the brow of holy Helicon. But when I came to the huge lion's lair, I to the tip the string did straightway don, And fix'd one of the arrows which I bare: To see, ere I was seen, I looked around with care. “It was the mid-day, and not yet I found His traces ; nor could hear his mighty roar. I saw no herdsman, ploughman on the ground, To point me where I should his haunt explore: Green fear kept every man within his door. Nor till I saw him and his vigour tried, Ceased I to search the sylvan mountain o'er; And ere came on the cool of eventide, Back to his cavern, gorged with flesh and blood, he hied. "His dew-lap, savage face, and mane, were gory; He licked his beard, while I, yet unespied, Lurked in a thicket of the promontory ; But as he nearer came, at his left side I shot an arrow, but it did not glide, Though sharp, into his flesh, but with rebound Fell on the grass. The thick he closely eyed, His bloody head up-lifting from the ground, And ghastly grinned, showing his teeth's terrific round. " Then on the string another shaft I placed, And shot—vext that the former idly flew : Mid-breast I hit him, where the lungs are placed: His hide the sharp, sharp arrow pierced not through, But at his feet fell ineffectual too : Again a third I was in act to shoot, Enraged to think in vain my bow I drew, When I was seen by the blood-thirsty brute, Who to the battle-thought his angry signs did suit. " With his long tail he lashed himself; and all His neck was filled with wrath: the fiery glow Of his vext mane up-bristled ; in a ball He gathered up himself, till like a bow His spine was arched : as when one, who doth know Chariots to build, excelling in his art, Having first heated in a fire-heat slow Bends for his wheel a fig-branch ; with a start The fissile wild-fig flies far from his hands apart. "Collected for the spring, and mad to rend me, So leapt the lion from afar : I strove With skin-cloak, bow, and quiver to defend me With one hand; with the other I up-hove My weighty club, and on his temple drove, But broke in pieces the rough olive wood On his hard shaggy head : he from above Fell ere he reached me, by the stroke subdued, And nodding with his head on trembling feet he stood. "Darkness came over both his eyes : his brain Was shaken in the bone ; but when I spied The monster stunned and reeling from his pain, I cast my quiver and my bow aside, And to his neck my throttling hands applied, Before he could recover. I did bear me With vigour in the death-clutch, and astride His body from behind from scath did clear me, So that he could not or with jaw or talons tear me. "His hind feet with my heels I pressed aground ; Of his pernicious throat my hands took care ; His sides were for my thighs a safe-guard found From his fore-feet: till breathless high in air I lifted him new sped to hell's dark lair. Then many projects did my thoughts divide, How best I might the monster's carcass bare, And from his dead limbs strip the shaggy hide : Hard task it was indeed, and much my patience tried. " I tried and failed with iron, wood, and flint; For none of these his skin could penetrate ; Then some immortal gave to me a hint With his own talons I might separate The carcass and the hide : success did wait The trial of this thought; he soon was flayed. I wear his hide, that serves me to rebate Sharp-cutting war. The Nemean beast was laid Thus low, which had of men and flocks much havoc made." THREE troops three sisters to the mountain led; Agavé with' her cheeks that blossomed red The bloom of apple ; and in wildest mood Autonöa and Ino. From the wood They stript oak-leaves and ivy green as well, And from the ground the lowly asphodel; In a pure lawn with these twelve altars placed; Nine Dionysus, three his mother graced; Then from the chest the sacred symbols moved, And, as their god had taught them and approved, Upon the leafy altars reverent laid. Hid in a native mastic's sheltering shade, Them from a steep rock Pentheus then surveyed. Him perched aloft Autonöa first discerned, And dreadful shrieked, and spurning overturned The sacred orgies of the frenzied one, Which none profane may ever look upon. She maddened, maddened all: scared Pentheus fled, And they, with robes drawn up, pursued : He said: " What want ye, dames !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.56"/>
          <p n="1.7">" Autonöa then: " Thou, fellow ! Shalt know, not hear "-and mightily did bellow, Loud as a lioness her brood defending ; His mother clutched his head, whilst Ino rending Tore off his shoulder, trod and trampled o'er him ; Autonöa likewise: limb from limb they tore him. Then all returned to Thebes; defiled with gore, They of their Pentheus only fragments bore, Their after-grief. This troubles not my mind : Not let another, impotent and blind, Name Dionysus as hereby defiled,— Nor though he harsher used some curious child. May I my life to holy courses give, Dear to the holy who reproachless live ! This omen, sent from aegis-bearing Jove, Shows what he hates, and what his thoughts approve ; Blest are the children of the godly-ever ; Blest are the children of the godless-never. Hail, Blessed! whom Jove's thigh enclosed for us, Till thou wert born on snowy Dracanus. Hail, Semele ! Cadmean sisters, hail ! Whose names in songs of heroines prevail. By Dionysus this (no need of shame) Possest ye did. The gods let no man blame. A COWHERD with chaste Helen ran away. This Helen here was kist by one to-day. Boast not: they say there's nothing in a kiss. But in mere kissing is some touch of bliss. I wipe my mouth-and off thy kiss is ta'en. Wipe you your mouth ? then let me kiss again. Calves, not a maid, to kiss doth you beseem. Boast not: thy youth is flying like a dream. Ripe grapes are raisins, and dry roses sweet. Come to yon olives : I would fain repeat- I will not : you deceived me once indeed. Come to yon elms, and hear me play my reed. Play to yourself: nought wretched pleases me. Take heed: the Paphian will be wroth with thee. A fig for her, if Artemis be kind. Hush ! lest she smite you and for ever bind. Not me—my guard is Artemis the wise. Canst thou fly Love-none other virgin flies ? By Pan ! I fly him : he doth ever drive you. I fear that Love to some worse man may give you. Many have woo'd me, but have pleased me—none. And I am come-of many wooers one. What can I do ? marriage brings only care. Not pain, nor grief, but joys which sweetest are. They say that women fear their wedded dears. They rule them rather: show me one that fears. Lucina's bolt-the child-bed pang I dread. Thy sovran, Artemis, puts wives to bed. Child-bearing will my fine complexion blight. Thy children will become thy bloom and light. If I consent, what spouse-gifts shall be mine ? My pastures, groves, and herd, shall all be thine. Swear, when 'tis done, thou never wilt forsake me. By Pan ! not even shouldst thou try to make me. Chamber and hall will you for me provide ? Chamber and hall, and fleeces fine beside. What ? what shall I my aged father tell ? Hearing my name, he'll like thy marriage well. Repeat it: oft a name sweet influence has. Daphnis, Nomæa's son by Lycidas. A good descent, but than mine own not higher. I know it well—Menalcas is thy sire. Show me thy grove, where stands thy wealthy stall. See where for me flowers many a cypress tall. Feed, goats! while I my lover's wealth inspect. Feed, bulls ! while I the virgin's way direct. Hands off! what business have they in my dress! First these love-apples will I gently press. By Pan ! I shudder-take your hand away. Dear little trembler ! your alarm allay. The ditch is dirty: would you throw me down ? I spread a soft white fleece beneath your gown. Why do you loose my zone ? what do you mean ? This first I offer to the Paphian queen. Some one will see us : hist! I hear a sound. The cypresses thy marriage whisper round. My dress is spoiled: ah me! what shall I do ? I'll give thee, love, a better one and new. Perhaps e'en salt you will not give to me. Would I could give my very soul to thee! Pardon, Queen Artemis ! my broken vow. Eros a calf, Cypris shall have a cow. I go a woman, who a virgin came. For virgin thine a wife's and mother's name. Thus whispered they, their youthful prime enjoying, With their fresh limbs in furtive marriage toying. She rose and to her flock went, seeming sad, Blushing and shamefaced, but at heart was glad ; And to his herd the happy Daphnis sped, Rejoicing greatly in his marriage-bed. DISTAFF ! quick implement of busy thrift, Which housewives ply, blue-eyed Athene's gift! We go to rich Miletus, where is seen The fane of Cypris 'mid the rushes green: Praying to mighty Zeus for voyage fair, Thither to Nicias would I now repair, Delighting and delighted by my host, Whom the sweet-speaking Graces love the most Of all their favourites ; thee, distaff bright! Of ivory wrought with art most exquisite, A present for his lovely wife I take. With her thou many various works shalt make; Garments for men, and such as women wear Of silk, whose colour is the sea-blue clear. And she so diligent a housewife is, That ever for well-ankled Theugenis Thrice in a year are shorn the willing sheep Of the fine fleeces which for her they keep. She loves what love right-minded women all ; For never should a thriftless prodigal Own thee with my consent: 'twere shame and pity ! Since thou art of that most renowned city, Built by Corinthian Archias erewhile, The marrow of the whole Sicilian isle. But in the house of that physician wise, Instructed how by wholesome remedies From human-kind diseases to repel, Thou shalt in future with Ionians dwell, In beautiful Miletus ; that the fame For the best distaff Theugenis may claim, And thou may'st ever to her mind suggest The memory of her song-loving guest. The worth of offering from friend we prize Not in the gift but in the giver lies. THEY say, my dear, that wine and truth agree: To speak truth in my cups beseemeth me. And I will tell you all my secret thought; You do not wholly love me as you ought. All of my life-the half that is not fled, Lives only in your form-the rest is dead. Just as you will, my life is one delight, Like that of gods,-or glooms in thickest night. How is it right to vex one loves you so ? Take my advice ; you will hereafter know, That I your elder taught you for the best, And, to believe me, was your interest. In one tree build one nest; so shall not creep Some crawling mischief to disturb your sleep. See ! how you change about for ever now, Never two days together on one bough. And if one .chance to praise your lovely face, Him more than friend of three years proof you grace : To him that loved you first you are as cold, As to a mere acquaintance three days old. But now you breathe of wantonness and pride ; Like should love like ; in love be this your guide ; So do, and good renown you shall obtain, And Love will never visit you with pain, Who mortal hearts can easily subdue, And made me, heart of iron, dote on you. In all the changes of your fitful will, Unchanged I live but in your kisses still. Remember that you were last year, last week, Younger than now : we grow old while we speak. Wrinkles soon come; and Youth speeds on amain, Wings on her shoulders, ne'er to come again: We, slow-foot mortals, cannot overtake Birds, or what else a winged passage make. Take thought, and be more mild : to me, who burn In love for you, a guileless love return, That when your bloom of youthful beauty ends, We may be time-enduring, faithful friends. But if you cast my words unto the wind, Or piqued to anger murmur in your mind, " Why dost thou trouble me ?" I for thy sake, And thy much scorn, myself will straight betake, Where the gold apples their sweet fragrance spread, To Cerberus, the keeper of the dead. Then freed from love, and all its anxious pain, E'en at thy call, I could not come again. CYPRIS, when she saw Adonis Cold and dead as any stone is, All his dark hair out of trim, And his fair cheek deadly dim, Thither charged the Loves to lead The cruel boar that did the deed. And they, swiftly overflying All the wood where he was lying, Soon the hapless creature found, And with cords securely bound. One the captive dragged along Holding at its end the thong; While another with his bow Struck behind and made him go. Path of fear they made him tread- Aphrodite was his dread. Him the goddess thus addrest: " Of all beasts thou wickedest! Thou ! didst thou this white thigh tear ? Didst thou smite my husband dear ? " Fearfully, then, answered he : “Cypris ! I do swear to thee By thyself and husband dear, By the very bonds I wear, By these huntsmen, never I Meant to tear thy husband's thigh ; Thinking there a statue stood, In the fever of my blood, I was mad a kiss to press On the naked loveliness : But my long tusk pierced the boy: Punish these, and these destroy, Tusks that worse then useless prove- What had they to do with love ? And if this suffice not, pray, Cypris ! cut my lips away- What had they to do with kissing ? " Cypris then, her wrath dismissing, Pitied him that knew no better ; And she bade them loose his fetter. The boar, from that time of her train, Went not to the wood again ; But, approaching to the fire, Fairly burned out his desire. IF for good sport one prays and lucky gains, Who from the sea his livelihood obtains, His nets his plough ; let him at evening-fall, Offering a “white fish," on this goddess call- The fish called " white " as brightest that doth swim ; Nor shall his prayer be without fruit for him : For let him throw his nets into the sea, And he shall draw them full as they can be. THICK-GROWING thyme, and roses wet with dew, Are sacred to the sisterhood divine Of Helicon : the laurel, dark of hue, The Delphian laurel, Pythian Pæan, thine! For thee shall bleed the white ram which doth chew The downward hanging branch of turpentine. To Pan, the fair-cheeked Daphnis, whose red lip To his sweet pipe the pastoral wild notes married, Offered his pipe, crook, fawn-skin, spear, and scrip, Wherein he formerly his apples carried. Daphnis ! thou sleepest on the leaf-strown ground- Thy hunting-nets are on the mountain pight: Thee Pan is hunting-thee Priapus crowned With ivy and its golden berries bright: Into the cavern both together bound: Up ! shake off sleep, and safety find in flight. Where yon oak-thicket by the lane appears, A statue newly made of fig is seen, Three-legged, the bark on still, but without ears, Witness of many a prank upon the green. A sacred grove runs round ; soft-bubbling near, A spring perennial from its pebbly seat Makes many a tree to shoot and flourish there, The laurel, myrtle, and the cypress sweet; And the curled vine with clusters there doth float: Their sharp shrill tones the vernal blackbirds ring, And yellow nightingales take up the note, And, warbling to the others, sweetly sing. There, goatherd ! sit, and offer up for me Prayer to the rural god : if from my love He only will consent to set me free, A kid shall bleed in honour of his grove. If I must love, then, should my love succeed By his good grace, the fattest lamb I rear, A. heifer, and a ram for him shall bleed: Freely I offer, may he kindly hear! For the Nymphs’ sake thy double flute provoke To breathe some sweetness: I the harp will take, And make it vocal to the quill's quick stroke ; And Daphnis from the pipe sweet sounds will shake. Come ! let us stand beside the thick-leaved oak, Behind the cave, and goat-foot Pan awake. What boots it thee to weep away both eyes, Sad Thyrsis ! of thy pretty kid bereft: The wild wolf seizes it, and bounding flies, And the dog barks-at his successful theft. What profit now from weeping can arise ? For of the kid, nor bone nor dust is left. The son of Paean to Miletus came, And with the best physician, Nicias, staid, Who, daily kindling sacrificial flame, From fragrant cedar had this statue made. The highest price was paid Eëtion's fame, Who all his skill upon the work outlaid. Stranger! the Syracusian Orthon gives thee charge: Walk not o' winter nights, with many a cup Reeling : from this, instead of country large, I have a foreign mound-that shuts me up. Man! spare thy life, nor out of season be A voyager: man's term of life soon flies. For Thasus Cleonicus put to sea From Cœlesyria with his merchandise: What time the Pleiad hastes to set, went he, And, with the Pleiad, sunk-no more to rise. To you, this marble statue, Muses nine ! Xenocles placed ; the harmonist, whose skill No man denies : owning your aid divine, He by your aid is unforgotten still. This is the monument of Eusthenes, Who from one's face his mind and temper knew. In a strange land all rites the dead can please He had-and he was dear to poets too. Nothing was wanting to his obsequies: Homeless, he had dear friends and mourners true. UPON A TRIPOD DEDICATED TO BACCHUS BY DEMOTELES. Sweet Dionysus ! sweetest god of all!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.65"/>
          <p n="1.8">To thee this tripod and thy statue placed The leader of the choir, Damoteles. Only small praise did on his boyhood fall, But now his manhood is with victory graced, And more, that him virtue and honour please The heavenly Cypris, not the popular this: So call her bending lowly on thy knees. The chaste Chrysogona, for nuptial bliss, Had it set in the house of Amphicles, Her life-long spouse-his home, heart, children, hers: Their life, begun with thee, from year to year Was happier, goddess! They are ministers Of their own blessings, who the gods revere. Leaving a little son, Eurymedon ! Dead in thy prime, thou in this tomb dost lie; Thou dwellest with the blest: thy little son The state will prize for thy dear memory. Traveller ! by this it will be understood, If thou dost equal hold the bad and good : If not, then say: " Light lie this mound upon The sacred head of good Eurymedon." Stranger! this statue view with care, And say, when homeward you repair: " In Teos lately saw these eyes The statue of Anacreon wise. If ever bard in bower or hall Sang sweetly, sweetest he of all. Most of all things he loved in sooth The unblown loveliness of youth." Thus will you, stranger, in a little Express the whole man to a tittle. We Dorian Epicharmus praise in Dorian, Who first wrote comedy, but now, alas! Instead of the true man, the race Pelorian, Bacchus! to thee present him wrought in brass. Here stands he in their wealthy Syracuse, Known for his wealth and other service true : To all he many a saw of practic use Declared: and mighty honour is his due. Medeius to his Thracian nurse had made This way-side monument, scored with her name: Her nursing cares are to the woman paid : Why not ? her usefulness shall live to fame. Stay, and behold the old Iambic poet, Archilochus, of infinite renown- That he is known to east and west doth show it: The Muses and Apollo him did crown With choicest gifts : his was the poet's fire, And he could sing his verses to the lyre. The poet of Camirus, first to sing The labours of the lion-slaying king, The quick-hand son of Zeus omnipotent, Was our Pisander : this his monument. They suffered many months and years to pass After his death-but now 'tis done in brass. The bard Hipponax, traveller! lies here: If wicked, keep aloof; if in the number Of good men thou, of good men born, draw near, Sit down, and, if thou wilt, in safety slumber. I am Theocritus, not he that was Of Chios, but a man of Syracuse. Philina bore me to Praxagoras: I never flirted with another's muse. With stranger and with citizen the same I deal: your own deposit take away, Paying the charge: excuse let others frame; His debts Caïcus e'en at night will pay. ,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.91"/>
          <p n="1">IF sweet my songs, or these sufficient be Which I have sung to give renown to me, I know not: but it misbeseems to strain At things we have not learned, and toil in vain. If sweet these songs are not, what profit more Have I to labour at them o'er and o'er ? If Saturn's son and changeful Fate assigned A double life-time to our mortal kind, That one in joys and one in woes be past, Who had his woes first would have joys at last. But since Heaven wills one life to man should fall, And this is very brief-too brief for all We think to do, why should we fret and moil, And vex ourselves with never-ending toil ? To what end waste we life exhaust our health On gainful arts, and sigh for greater wealth ? We surely all forget our mortal state- How brief the life allotted us by Fate !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.91"/>
          <p n="1">WHEN on the wave the breeze soft kisses flings, I rouse my fearful heart, and long to be Floating at leisure on the tranquil sea ; But when the hoary ocean loudly rings, Arches his foamy back and spooming swings Wave upon wave, his angry swell I flee : Then welcome land and sylvan shade to me, Where, if a gale blows, still the pine-tree sings. Hard is his life whose nets the ocean sweep, A bark his house—shy fish his slippery prey; But sweet to me the unsuspicious sleep Beneath a leafy plane-the fountain's play, That babbles idly, or whose tones, if deep, Delight the rural ear and not affray.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="6">
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.118"/>
          <p n="1">PAN loved his neighbour Echo, and Echo was 6 enamoured of the frisky Satyr, while the Satyr was mad after Lyda : as Echo Pan, so did the Satyr inflame Echo, and Lyda the Satyr : and love was smouldering in each in their turns. For as strongly as any one of them hated the lover, so strongly in like manner was he, loving, hated, and was suffer ing 1 a requital. These lessons speak I to all them that love not, 2' Cherish them that love you, that if ye love, ye may be loved again.’</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.118"/>
          <p n="1">To the same field, Aratus, bard divine ! Once Daphnis and Damœtas drove their kine. This on the chin a yellow beard did show: On that the down had just begun to grow. During the noontide of the summer heat, They by a fountain sung their ditties sweet. But Daphnis first (to whom it did belong As challenger) began the pastoral song. " With apples Galatea pelts thy sheep, Inviting one, whose pulses never leap To love, whilst thou, cold Polypheme ! dost pipe, Regardless of the sea-born beauty ripe. And lo ! she pelts the watch-dog—with a bound He barking starts, and angry looks around- Then bays the sea ; the waves soft-murmuring show An angry dog fast running to and fro. Take heed he leap not on her, coming fresh From the sea-wave, and tear her dainty flesh. But like the thistle-down, when summer glows, The sportive nymph, soft moving, comes and goes; Pursues who flies her, her pursuer flies, And moves the landmark of love's boundaries. What is not lovely, lovely oft doth seem To the bewildered lover, Polypheme." Preluding then, Damœtas thus began. “ I saw her pelt my flock, by mighty Pan ! Not unobserved by my dear single eye, Through which I see, and shall see till I die. Prophet of ill! let Telemus at home Keep for his own sons all his woes to come. I, to provoke her, look not in return, And say that for another girl I burn.. At hearing which with envy, by Apollo ! The sea-nymph pines; and her eye-quest doth follow, Leaping from out the sea like one that raves, Amid my flocks, and peeps into the caves. I make the dog bark just to discompose her; He, when I loved her, whining used to nose her. Noting my action, she perchance will find Some messenger to let me know her mind. I'll shut my door, till she on oath agree To make her sweet bed on this isle with me. Nor am I that unsightly one they say: For in the calm, smooth wave the other day I saw myself: and handsome was my beard, And bright, methought, my single eye appeared. And from the beautiful sea-mirror shone My white teeth, brighter than the Parian stone. To screen myself from influence malign, Thrice on my breast I spat. This lesson fine I learned from that wise crone Cotyttaris." This sung, Damœtas gave his friend a kiss. Of pipe and flute their mutual gifts they made- Daphnis the pipe, the flute Damœtas played. Thereto the heifers frisked in gambols rude: And neither conquered; both were unsubdued.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.118"/>
          <p n="1">WHAT sweet for you has Summer or the Spring, What joy does Autumn or the Winter bring ? Which season do you hail with most delight ? Summer, whose fulness doth our toils requite ? Or the sweet Autumn, when but slight distress From hunger falls on mortal wretchedness ? Or lazy Winter-since but few are loath To cheer themselves with fire-side ease and sloth ? Or the Spring, blushing with its bloom of flowers ? Tell me your choice, since leisure-time is ours. For man to judge things heavenly is unmeet, And all these seasons holy are and sweet. But I to please you will indulge your ear, And tell my favourite season of the year. Not Summer-then I feel the scorching sun ; Nor Autumn-then their course diseases run ; And hard I find to bear the Winter frore. The chilling snow I fear, and crystal hoar. Of all the year the Spring delights me most, Free from the scorching sun, and bitter frost. All life-containing shapes conceive in Spring, And all sweet things are sweetly blossoming ; And in that season of the year's delight There is for men an equal day and night. PHŒBUS tried all his means, and thought of new, Scarce knowing what he did in his distress ; With nectar bathed him, with ambrosial dew; But Fate made remedies remediless. HAPPY is love or friendship when returned- The lovers whose pure flames have equal burned, Happy was Theseus, e'en in Tartarus, With his true heart-friend, good Pirithous. His Pylades Orestes lorn did bless Amid th' inhospitable Chalybes. Blest was Achilles in a friend long tried; Him living loved, for his sake gladly died ! Yourself to artists always to betake, And on yourself in nothing to rely Is misbeseeming: friend ! your own pipe make The work is easy, if you will but try. May Love the Muses evermore invite, The Muses bring me Love ! and to requite My passion, may they give sweet song to me, Than which no sweeter remedy can be. When drop on drop, they say, doth ever follow, 'Twill wear the stone at last into a hollow. I to the sandy shore and seaward slope Will go, and try with murmured song to bend The cruel Galatea : my sweet hope I'll cast away-when life itself doth end. Oh, leave me not unhonoured ! Artists aim And reach at excellence, provoked by Fame. Woman's strength is in her beauty;- Man's—to bear and dare for duty. WILL you, my Lycidas, now sing for me A soothing, sweet Sicilian melody- A love-song, such as once the Cyclops young On the sea-shore to Galatea sung ? I'll pipe or sing for you : what shall it be ? The song of Scyros dearly pleases me, Sweet love-the pleasant life Pelides led- His furtive kisses, and the furtive bed. How he, a boy, put on a virgin's dress, Assumed a virgin's mien, and seemed no less ; And how Deïdamia, maiden coy, Found her girl bedmate was a wicked boy. The herdsman, Paris, on an evil day, To Ida bore the lovely Helena. CEnone grieved; and Lacedæmon raged, And all th' Achæan s in the feud engaged: Hellenes, Elians, and Mycenians, came, And brave Laconians, to retake the dame. When Greece her battle led across the deep, Himself at home no warrior then might keep. Achilles only went not then, indeed, Hid with the daughters of king Lycomede. A seeming virgin with a virgin's bloom, Instead of arms his white hand plied the loom. No virgin of them all had airs more fine, A rosier cheek, or step more feminine : He veiled his hair; but Mars and fiery Love, That stings young manhood, all his thoughts did move. He lingered by Deidamia's side, Close as he could, from morn till eventide: Often he kissed her hand, and often raised Her broidered work: her work and fingers praised. Of all the maids his only messmate she; And he would fain his bedmate have her be. And thus he sued with furtive meaning deep :— " With one another other sisters sleep ; In station, love, and age, we twain are one, Why should we, maidens both, each sleep alone ? Since we together are all day, I wonder Why we are made at night to sleep asunder ? ” HESPER! sweet Aphrodite's golden light! Hesper ! bright ornament of swarthy Night, Inferior to the Moon's clear sheen, as far As thou outshinest every other star; Dear Hesper, hail! and give thy light to me, Leading the festive shepherd company. For her new course to-day began the Moon, And is already set—O much too soon ! 'Tis not for impious theft abroad I stir, Nor to way-lay the nightly traveller : I love ; and thou, bright star of love ! shouldst lend The lover light-his helper and his friend. BRIGHT Cypris! goddess ever meek and mild, Of mightiest Zeus and loveliest sea-nymph child, Why with Immortals and our mortal kind Art thou so wroth ? what stung thy gentle mind To bring forth Love ? who wills at all to strike, His cruel heart his person how unlike ! Winged and far-darter why didst make him, why, That we the cruel one can never fly ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.118"/>
          <p n="1">PAN Echo loved ; she loved the frisky Faun ; The Faun to Lyda by strong love was drawn; As Echo Pan, the Faun did Echo burn, And Lyda him: all fell in love in turn. And with what scorn the loved the lover grieved Was that one scorned, and like for like received. Hear, heart-free ! let who love you love obtain, That if you love, you may be loved again.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="7">
          <milestone unit="section" n="5.7"/>
          <p n="1">3 ALPHEus, when he glides along the sea, past Pisa, comes to Arethusa, bringing his waters 4 laden with wild-olives, bearing as a dower fair leaves and flowers and sacred dust; and he enters the waves deeply and runs in under the sea beneath, and water mingles not with waters ; and the sea is not conscious of it, as the river passes through. Love, knavish boy, plotter of ill, teacher of fearful things, has taught through his spell even a river to dive. 5 HAVING laid aside torch and bow, mischievous Eros took up an ox-goad, and he had a wallet slung-on-his-shoulders ; and having joined under the yoke the toil-enduring necks of oxen, he sowed the furrow of Ceres, that it should bear grain. And looking up he said to Jove himself, I‘ Make full the sown fields, lest I place thee, Europa's bull, under the plough.' 2 WOULD that my sire had taught me to tend fleecy sheep, in which case, seated beneath the elms, or under the rocks, playing on my pipes, I would solace my cares with reeds. Let us fly, ye Pierides : seek we another well-built city for our country; yet in sooth I will speak out to all, that ruinous drones have harmed the honey-bees.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="5.7"/>
          <p n="1">'TWAS when Amyntas, Eucritus, and I, Did from the city to sweet Haleus hie; The harvest-feast by that abounding river Was kept, in honour of the harvest-giver, By Phrasidamus and Antigenes, Sons of Lycopeus both, and good men these, If good there is from old and high descent, From Clytia and from Calchon, who, knee-bent Firmly against the rock, did make outflow The spring Burinna with a foot-struck blow, Near which a thickly wooded grove is seen, Poplars and elms, high overarching green. Midway not reached, nor tomb of Brasilas, We chanced upon Cydonian Lycidas, By favour of the Muses : who not knew That famous goatherd as he came in view ? A tawny, shaggy goat-skin on his back, That of the suppling pickle yet did smack ; Bound by a belt of straw the traveller wore An aged jerkin ; in his hand he bore A crook of the wild olive coming nigh, With widely parted lips, and smiling eye- The laughter on his lip was plain to see- He quietly addressed himself to me: " Whither so fast at noon-tide, when no more The crested larks their sunny paths explore, And in the thorn-hedge lizards lie asleep ? To feast or to a wine-press do you leap ? The stones ring to your buskins as you pass." To him I made reply—“ Dear Lycidas ! All say you are the piper-far the best 'Mid shepherds and the reapers; this contest Gladdens my heart; and yet (to put in speech My fancy) I expect your skill to reach. Our way is to a harvest-feast, which cater Dear friends of ours for richly robed Damater, Offering their first-fruits—since their garner-floor Her bounteous love hath filled to running o'er. Let us with pastoral song beguile the way ; Common the path, and common is the day. We shall each other, it may be, content; For I, too, am a mouth-piece eloquent Of the dear Muses ;and all men esteem, And call me minstrel good-not that I deem, Not I, by Earth ! Philetas I surpass, Nor the famed Samian bard, Sicelidas, A frog compared with locusts. I beguile The time with song." He answered with a smile “This crook I give thee—for thou art all over An imp of Zeus, a genuine truth-lover. Who strives to build, the lowly plain upon, A mansion high as is Oromedon, I hate exceedingly; and for that matter The muse-birds, who like cuckoos idly chatter Against the Chian minstrel, toil in vain: Let us at once begin the pastoral strain ; Here is a little song, which I did late, Musing along the highlands, meditate: " To Mitylene sails my heart-dear love: Safe be the way, and fair the voyage prove, E'en when the south the moist wave dashes high on The setting Kids, and tempest-veiled Orion Places his feet on ocean ; and, returned, My love be kind to me by Cypris burned; For hot love burns me : may the Halcyons smooth The swell o' the sea, the south and east winds soothe, That from the lowest deep the sea-weed stir- Best Halcyons ! whom of all the birds that skir The waves for prey, the Nereids love the most. Safe may my loved one reach the Lesbian coast, And on the way be wind and weather fair! With dill or roses will I twine my hair, Or on my head will put a coronet, Wreathed with the fragrance of the violet. I by the fire will quaff the Ptelean wine, And one shall roast me beans, while I recline Luxurious, lying on a fragrant heap Of asphodel and parsley, elbow deep ; And mindful of my love the goblet clip, Until the last lees trickle to my lip. Two swains shall play the flute ; and Tityrus sing How love for Xenea did our Daphnis sting, How on the mountain he was wont to stray, How wailed for him the oaks of Himera, When he, dissolving, passed away from us, Like snow on Hæmus, or far Caucasus, Athos or Rhodope : or in his song Recite, how by his master's cruel wrong The swain was in a cedar ark shut up, While quick-and how from many a flower-cup The flat-nosed bees to his sweet prison flew, And there sustained him with the honey-dew, For that the Muse into his lip distilled Sweet nectar: blest Comatas! that fulfilled A whole spring, feeding on the bag o' the bee, Shut in an ark! How had it gladdened me, (Would only thou wert of the living now !) To tend thy goats along the mountain's brow, And hear thee sweetly sing, 0 bard divine ! Lying at leisure under oak or pine !” He ceased: I in my turn : " Dear Lycidas ! Whilst on the highlands with my herd I pass, The Nymphs have taught me precious ditties oft, Which haply Fame has borne to Zeus aloft. I choose for you the very best I know; Now listen, since the Muses love you so: " The Loves, ill omen ! sneezed on me, who dote On lovely Myrtis, as on spring the goat. Aratus, whom of men I love the best, Loves a sweet girl. Aristis, minstrel blest, And worthiest man, whom his own tripod near Phœbus himself would not disdain to hear Sing to the harp, knows that Aratus feels This scorching flame. Pan !whose rich music peals On Homolus, place in his longing arms Of her own will the blushing bloom of charms. So may the youth of Arcady forbear With squills thy shoulders and thy side to tear, When fails the chase. If thou wilt not, then weep, By nails all mangled, and on nettles sleep ! Where Hebrus flows, in frost-time of the year Dwell on the mountains 'neath the polar bear; In summer with swart Æthiop, at the pile Of Blemyan rocks, beyond the springs of Nile ! Ye loves ! from Hyetis and Byblis flown, Who make Dione's lofty seat your own; Ye loves ! that are to blushing apples like, The blooming Phyllis with your arrows strike- Strike her, because she pities not my friend; Though softer than a pear, her bloom shall end: Ah, Phyllis ! Phyllis ! now the bachelors say, Behold thy flower of beauty drops away ! Let us, my friend Aratus ! pace no more, Nor keep our painful watch beside her door; Let Chanticleer, that crows at dawn, behold Some other lover there benumbed with cold : Such watch be Molon's, and be his alone ; But rest be ours-and eke a friendly crone, Who may by spitting and by magic skill Quick disenchant us from foreshadowed ill." Ended my song, he, smiling as before, The friendly muse-gift gave-the crook he bore; Then turning to the left pursued the way To Pyxa; speeding, presently we lay, Where Phrasidamus dwelt, on loosened sheaves Of lentisk, and the vine's new-gathered leaves. Near by, a fountain murmured from its bed, A cavern of the Nymphs :elms overhead, And poplars rustled; and the summer-keen Cicadæ sung aloft amid the green ; Afar the tree-frog in the thorn-bush cried; Nor larks nor goldfinches their song denied ; The yellow bees around the fountains flew; And the lone turtle-dove was, heard to coo: Of golden summer all was redolent, And of brown autumn ; boughs with damsons bent, We had ; and pears were scattered at our feet, And by our side a heap of apples sweet. A four-year cask was broached. Ye Nymphs excelling Of Castaly, on high Parnassus dwelling, Did ever Chiron in the Centaur's cave Give draught so rich to Hercules the brave ? Through Polypheme did such sweet nectar glance, That made the shepherd of Anapus dance, The huge rock-hurler—as the generous foam, Which, Nymphs, ye tempered at that harvest-home ? 0 be it mine again her feast to keep, And fix the fan in good Damater's heap ; And may she sweetly smile, while spikes of corn And up-torn poppies either hand adorn !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="5.7"/>
          <p n="1">ALPHEUS, gliding by old Pisa's towers, Deep in the sea his eager way pursues, With sacred dust, and olive-leaves, and flowers, With which he hastens to his Arethuse. Smoothly he runs ; the sea not feels the river With soft unmingled stream its water rive ; Eros it was, that subtle counsel-giver, Who taught a river how for love to dive. His torch and quiver down sly Eros flung, An ox-goad took in hand, a wallet slung, Then yoked strong bulls and made the plough to train, And as he went the furrow sowed with grain. And looking up he said to Zeus, “ Make full The harvest, or I'll yoke Europa's bull." WOULD that my sire had brought me up to feed The happy bloaters of the fleecy flocks ! 'Twould soothe my sorrow then to breathe the reed Beneath the shade of elms or hanging rocks. Now let us fly ; and other cities seek To be our country, dear Pierides : But I my mind to all will plainly speak- Injurious drones have harmed the honey-beea. 1 Now it is noble for a 2brave man to die, having fallen opposite the foremost ranks, whilst fighting for his father-land. But most grievous of all is it for a man 3 to be a beggar, hav ing quitted his own city and fertile fields, and wandering with a loved mother and aged father, with little children and 4 wedded wife. For to whomsoever he shall have come, among them will he be hateful, yielding to need and to wretched poverty. He disgraces his race, and 5 belies his fair beauty ; and every kind of 6 dishonour and woe follows him. Besides, for a man thus vagrant, look you, there is no care, nor has he 1 This is not a fragment, though yap is so placed. Frequent examples of the same usage occur in Homer and Herodotus. Cf. Matt. Gr. Gr. § 615. Compare the use of " Nam " among the Latins. Virgil, Geor. iv. 445, Nam quis te, juvenum confidentissime,.nostras jussit adire domes : and of “ quisnam " in Plautus, Curcul. 398, Nam quid id refert meâ. Terent. Andr. iii. 5, 6.—, noble. Cf. Soph. Antig. 72, . ,Virg. Æn. ii. 317, Pulchrumque mori succurrit in armis. Æn. xi. 24; ix. 286. Horat. Od. ii. 2, 13, Dulce et decorum est pro patriâ mori. respect in time to come. 7 With spirit let us fight for this land, and for our children die, being no longer chary of our lives. Fight then, young men, standing fast one by another, nor 9be beginners of cowardly flight, or fear. But rouse a great and valiant spirit in your breasts, and love not life, when ye contend with men. And the elders, whose limbs are no longer active, the old, I say, desert not or forsake. For surely this were shameful, that fallen amid the foremost champions, in front of the youths, an older man should lie low, 10 having his head now white and his beard hoary, and breathing out a valiant spirit in the dust; whilst 11 he covers with his hands his gory loins, (which were a shame, and would make one wroth to behold with his eyes:) and is stript as to his person: 12 yet all this befits the young, whilst, I wot, he enjoys the 13brilliant bloom of youth; to mortal men and women he is lovely to look upon, whilst he lives ; and noble when he has fallen in the foremost ranks. Then let 14every one with firm stride await the foe, having both feet fixed on the ground, 15 biting his lip with his teeth. BUT since ye are the race of I invincible Hercules, be ye of good courage; not yet hath Zeus 2 turned his neck aside from you. Neither fear ye, nor be affrighted at a host of men, but let hero hold his shield right against the foremost fighters ; having counted life hostile, and 3 the dark fates of death dear as the rays of the sun. For ye know that the 4 works of Ares of-many-tears are much-seen, and well have ye learned the 5 temper of troublous war. Ye have been, 0 young men, with the flying and the pursuing, and have pushed on to a full measure of both. Now of those, who dare, abiding one be side another, to advance to the close fray, and the foremost champions, fewer die, and they save the people in the rear; but in men 6 that fear, all excellence is lost. No one could ever in words go through those several ills, which befall a man, 7 if he has been actuated by cowardice. For 'tis grievous to wound in the rear the back of a flying man in hostile war. Shameful too is a corpse 8lying low in the dust, 9wounded behind in the back by the point of a spear. Rather let every one with firm stride await the enemy, having both feet fixed on the ground, biting his lip with his teeth, and having covered with the 10hollow of his broad shield thighs and shins below, and breast and shoulders. But in his right hand let him brandish a heavy lance, and 11shake above his head a threaten in- crest. Then let him learn war, by doing bold deeds, nor let him stand with his shield out of the range of weapons. But let each, drawing nigh in close fray, 12hit his foe, wound ing him with long lance or sword. 13 And having set foot beside foot, and having fixed shield against shield, and crest on crest, and helmet on helmet, and breast against breast, struggle in fight with his man, having seized either the hilt of his sword, or his long lance. But do ye, 140 light-armed soldiers, crouching under your shields, some from one quarter, some from another, make them fall with huge stones, and with polished spears, as ye dart at them, and stand near to the 15 heavy-armed troops. 1 I WOULD neither commemorate, nor hold in account a man, either for excellence in running, or for wrestling; no, nor though he should have the bulk and strength of the Cyclopes, and in speed surpass 2 Thracian Boreas. No, nor though he should in personal appearance be more graceful than 3 Titho nus, and should be more rich than Midas or 4 Cinyras. Nor though he should be more kingly than Pelops, son of Tantalus, and have the 5 soft-voiced tongue of Adrastus; nor yet if he should have all glory, save that of resistless valour; for he is not a man brave in war, 6 unless he have the courage to face bloody slaughter, and standing near attack the foemen. But this is excellence, this the best prize among men, and noblest for a young man to carry off. And this is a common good to a city, and all its people, namely, whatsoever man standing firm bides unceasingly in the front ranks, and is wholly for getful of base flight, when he has 7 staked his life, and en during spirit; but has the heart to fall, standing beside his next neighbour. This man is good in war. And quickly does he turn in flight the sturdy phalanxes of foemen, and 8 zeal ously stem the wave of battle. He too himself having fallen amid the foremost, loses his life, and (at the same time) having brought renown to his city and people and sire: pierced in many places through breast, and round shield, and through his cuirass in the front. Him young alike and old lament, and the whole state is distressed for him with painful regret. His 9tomb and children are famous among men, ay, 10his children's children, and his race after him. Never does his fair fame or his name perish, but though he be on earth, be becomes immortal, whom, bravely bearing himself, standing firm, and fighting for country and for children, impetuous Ares shall have destroyed. But should he have escaped the fate of death that-lays-men-out-at-length ; and as victor, have borne off the splendid boast of battle won, all honour him, young and old alike; and 11after tasting many delights, he comes to Hades. Growing old, he is eminent amid the citizens, nor does any one wish to hurt him in point of respect or justice. And all 12on the seats, alike young, and those of his age, and they who are still older, give place to him. Let every one now strive in his spirit to reach the summit of 13excellence like this, not 14slackening warfare. How long lie ye inactive ? when will ye have a brave spi rit, young men ? and are ye not 1ashamed of the dwellers all around, since ye dally thus exceedingly ? For ye think ye 2sit secure in peace, yet war possesses the whole land. 3 And let a man, as he dies, discharge his javelin for the last time. For it is both honourable and noble for a man to fight for land, and children, and wedded wife, with his foes,; and death will come at some time, whensoever in truth the fates shall have allotted. But let every one, having lifted aloft his lance, and 4 gathered up his stout heart under his shield, go right forward, when the battle first is joined. For it is not fated by any means that a man should escape death at least, no, not though he be by family of immortal ancestry. Often 5 he comes forth, after having escaped battle-strife and din of javelins, and in his home fated death found him. Now the latter is not in like manner a friend 6 to the commonalty, nor regretted by them, whilst the former, the brave man, small and great bewail, if aught shall have happened to him. For the whole people together regrets a stout-hearted hero, when he dies, and living he is worthy of the demigods. For they be hold him with their eyes even as a 7 tower, since, though single- handed, he performs deeds worth those of many. THESE twain were contending unceasingly for nineteen years, ever having a stout-hearted spirit, warrior sires of our sires. But in the twentieth year they indeed (the Messe nians) fled from the great mountains of Ithome, having abandoned their 2rich fields. FOR Zeus himself, son of Cronos, husband of beautiful- crowned Herè, hath given this city to the Heracleids. Along with whom, having left 2 windy Erineès, we arrived at the broad isle of Pelops.' EVEN as asses worn with heavy burdens, carrying to their 4 masters, by reason of sad constraint, 5the half entirely of whatsoever the soil produces. MOURNING their masters, even though they are so, both themselves and their wives, when the destructive fate of death seizes any of them. To our king Theopompus, dear to the gods, through whom we took Messene the spacious. HAVING heard Phœbus from Pytho, 2 they brought home oracles and perfect words of a god. That divinely-honoured kings should rule the senate, kings to whom the lovely city of Sparta is a care; and reverend old men, and afterwards men of the people, 3 replying to straight-forward maxims. YOUTHS, citizens of Sparta abounding in good men, first with left hand indeed thrust forward shield and lance, throw ing them with good courage, and not sparing. life in behalf of your father-land. BEFORE he has drawn nigh the bounds of glory or death. AND having in his breast the courage of a fiery lion.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
