<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Peace (Pax)</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">Benjamin Bickley Rogers</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>Benjamin Bickley Rogers (1919). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg005.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.29"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.38"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.47"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.56"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.64"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.72"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.80"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.88"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.96"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.104"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.113"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.122"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.131"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.140"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.149"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.157"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.166"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.174"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.182"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.190"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.198"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.207"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.215"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.223"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.231"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.240"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.248"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.256"/>
          <p n="1">THE spring of the year B. c. 421 found Athens and Sparta alike weary of the long continuance of the Peloponnesian War, and alike disposed to put an end to the conflict upon any fair and honourable terms. The War had now lasted exactly ten years: and as its fortunes alternated from side to side, Athens at one time, and Sparta at another, had been reduced to offer conditions of peace ; but hitherto the very events, which had caused the offer to be made by one combatant, had themselves ensured its rejection by the other. Now, for the first time, the wishes of both coincided; both felt that they had far more to lose than to gain by a further prolongation of hostilities; both were therefore eager to terminate the War, and the desire of Peace was as ardent and as genuine on the one side as on the other.</p>
          <p n="2">The LACEDAEMONIANS had commenced the war with the reputation of invincible prowess, and with the general sympathy of Hellas strongly manifested in their favour. And notwithstanding the warnings of their wiser and more experienced counsellors, they had imagined that it would be but an easy task for their great Confederacy to chastise and humble the Imperial Republic which had dared to subjugate, and was holding in tributary vassalage, so many Hellenic cities, formerly as free and inde pendent as herself. They looked forward to a few1 short and decisive cam paigns which would win them immortal glory, and the thanks and gratitude of a liberated Hellas. These visions had been rudely and completely dis pelled. The Peloponnesian vessels had been swept from the seas by the Athenian navy : the Peloponnesian army had found no enemy to encounter, no fame to acquire : its main occupation had consisted in ravaging the harvests, and despoiling the homesteads, of Attica ; an occupation in glorious in itself, and unlikely, as it seemed, to be productive of any substantial effect upon the ultimate issue of the War. No doubt much suffering and many losses were inflicted upon the Athenian people by this series of devastations; but these were speedily and amply avenged by incessant1 and destructive descents upon the Peloponnesian coasts, ex tending even into the proper territories of Sparta herself. Far from crumbling to pieces before the imposing forces of the Peloponnesian Confederacy, the Republic of Athens, when once she had shaken off the despondency occasioned in the earlier stages of the War by the pestilence and the invasions, seemed to gather fresh elasticity from the dangers which environed her, and almost to vindicate her right to empire, by the intrepid activity with which she carried the War into the enemies! country, assailing them on every side with strokes so nimble and rapid, as completely to baffle and confound the proverbial slowness of the Spartan operations. During the seventh, and the greater part of the eighth, years of the War, the tide was setting strongly and steadily against the Lacedaemonian cause. The happy audacity of the Athenian Demosthenes in occupying and fortifying Pylus, was rewarded by the unlooked-for capture of the Spartan troops upon the islet of Sphacteria, a disaster which shook the Spartan reputation throughout Hellas, and inspired the numerous families, who were in any way connected with the captives, with a personal interest in the restoration of Peace. Henceforth the one idea of the Lacedaemonian Government was to get rid of the War, and recover the captives. Embassy after embassy was sent, to solicit peace from Athens: embassy after embassy returned, to report that no peace could be obtained. The Athenians declared that, if a Spartan army again crossed the borders of Attica, the captives should at once be led out to execution; and having thus secured immunity for their own country, they proceeded to assail and ravage the coasts of Peloponnesus more incessantly and more system atically than ever. Towards the close of the eighth year of the War we find Athens the undisputed mistress of the seas; her triremes infesting the whole Peloponnesian seaboard; her garrisons established in strongholds commanding the peninsula on every side, at Nisaea, Methone, Cythera, Pylus. We find peaceful Laconian towns surprised and sacked by her flying detachments; the Aeginetans pursued into their Laconian asylum, and massacred to a man j the Messenians, the deadliest enemies of the Spartan name, firmly planted at Pylus ; the Helots deserting in numbers; Ionian trophies erected on the very soil of Laconia itself; and the scattered Spartan garrisons unable successfully to cope with their nimble and ubiquitous adversaries. No wonder that the Lacedaemonians were dis tressed and bewildered, when they found themselves I hemmed in on every side by a system of warfare so novel and unexpected: whilst their own prestige had suffered, and their high position been perceptibly lowered, even amongst their own allies.</p>
          <p n="3">In this strait a diversion was made in their favour by the brilliant exploits of Brasidas towards the close of the eighth year of the War. Throwing himself boldly into the midst of the Athenian dependencies on the north-west shores of the Aegean, he detached city after city from the Athenian empire, as much by his wise and conciliatory policy, his winning and attractive character, and the confidence which his presence everywhere inspired, as by his consummate military skill. But his countrymen, 1, were unable to appreciate his schemes and combinations, which passed far beyond the contracted horizon of their own narrow political traditions: it was mainly as affording an outlet for their discontented and unoccupied soldiery, and as drawing out of the country the most daring, and therefore the most dangerous, of the Helots, that they had originally encouraged, or rather, perhaps, acquiesced in, his adventurous enterprise: and his unlooked-for success was welcomed, not for its own sake, but because it seemed to open a prospect of at length recovering the Sphacterian captives. And hence it was that they were unwilling to rely too much on the chances of war. Successes so easily obtained might perhaps be as easily lost: Perdiccas, who had originally invited their troops, had fallen off again to the Athenian alliance: the passage through Thessaly was barred to reinforcements : and the Spartans were eager to conclude a Peace while yet they had a fair equivalent to offer in exchange for the captives.</p>
          <p n="4">There was yet another circumstance which rendered the Spartan Government peculiarly anxious at this moment to be at peace with Athens. Their treaty with Argos, which had lasted for thirty years, was on the eve of expiring, and grave apprehensions were entertained lest the Argives were preparing to seize the opportunity of regaining, with the assistance of Athens, their old traditionary predominance amongst the Dorians of the Peloponnesus.</p>
          <p n="5">The ATHENIANS, on their part, were equally desirous of effecting a termination of hostilities. They had nothing to gain from the War, which had, in fact, been forced upon them, and in which the struggle on their side had been commenced merely to maintain, and not to extend, their existing empire. At the first their hope had only been that they might come out of the conflict with undiminished power and importance : they had entered upon it with undisguised reluctance, and, indeed, a large and powerful party had always been opposed to its continuance. And the War had, from the outset, entailed upon them great and peculiar sacrifices. The surrender of all the local institutions and country homes to which they, beyond all other Hellenic peoples, had from time immemorial been devotedly attached : the spectacle which met their eyes, as they gazed from their city walls, of a rude and hostile soldiery pillaging their farms and vineyards, hacking down their olives and fig-trees, and destroying all that they held most dear: the exchange of the ease and freedom, the thousand pleasures of a country life for stifling huts and cells, or rather for any hastily extemporized shelter which they could find or construct (for there were no roofs to accommodate the multitudes which kept pressing into the city): and above all, the appalling visitation of the Pestilence which burst forth with unprecedented fury amidst these overcrowded immigrants, cooped and penned together in their miserable dwellings, so that " they died like sheep," says the historian, " corpses piled on corpses about the wells, and in the open spaces of the city": such were to Athens the immediate results of the declaration of War. Her spirit sank before these accumulated calamities, and she attempted to open negotiations for Peace. But her offers were rejected: and stricken by disease, not only in the city but also in her fleets and armies, she was compelled to carry on the War with an impoverished treasury and a desponding population. Her energy, however, remained unabated : and gradually the pestilence wore itself out; the Peloponnesian invasions lost, by repetition, much of their terrors; and the Athenians, at length, found their gallantry and perseverance rewarded by a series of successes, culminating in that great and astonishing event-the capture of the Spartan troops upon the islet of Sphacteria.</p>
          <p n="6">The surrender of a Spartan army, an event unprecedented in History, created a profound sensation throughout Hellas, and seems to have stimulated to a prodigious degree the hopes and aspirations of Athens; her ambition began to take a wider flight ()1: and whereas she had hitherto sought merely to maintain and secure her maritime empire, she appears now for the moment to have conceived the idea of estab lishing her supremacy over the Hellenic race as well by land as by sea.</p>
          <p n="7">An invasion of Boeotia was the natural stepping-stone to the accom plishment of these high designs. It was not the first time that Athens had cast a longing eye upon those rich pasturages, those lakes and plains swarming with fish and fowl; and she had on one occasion succeeded in acquiring, and actually maintained for nearly ten years, an ascendancy over the whole Boeotian territory. The Boeotians, always inert and sluggish, had never attempted to retaliate: they were content to repel, as best they might, the efforts made for their subjugation, and never thought of overstepping their own frontiers to carry on an aggressive warfare against their active and enterprising enemy. And the Athenians, therefore, now proposed, by a vigorous attempt, to reduce Boeotia wholly beneath their influence and control. But their scheme, however well conceived, was ill carried into execution; the various detachments failed to co-operate with each other, and the ambitious hopes of Athens were at once dashed to the ground by the signal overthrow which the Boeotians gave to the whole Athenian army among the deep 1 ravines and sloping shrub-covered hills over which the modern traveller passes as he journeys from Delium to Oropus. All the military forces of Athens (excepting such as were at the moment actually engaged on foreign service) seem to have been present on that fatal field : and all were overcome and borne down by the sturdy Boeotians, whose habit of gross and heavy eating () 2 dulled, in- deed, their mental faculties ; but endowed their bodies with a weight and strength which rendered them almost irresistible in the push of shields () with which Hellenic armies closed. Delium was the grave of those splendid hopes to which Sphacteria had given birth. So great and irreparable an overthrow not only 1 destroyed the newly-gained reputation of the Athenian arms, but seems also to have given rise for the first time to painful and distressing apprehensions at Athens 2, lest the Boeotians, flushed with success, should throw off the singular reluctance which they had hitherto always displayed to cross their own frontier (and which had even wellnigh withheld them from attacking the invading Athenian host on that border-land whereon the battle of Delium was fought) and should lead their victorious forces into the defenceless fields of Attica. And it would seem that the Athenian army became, to a certain extent, demoralized 3 by its defeat, and lost those habits of obedience and discipline which still distinguished the efficient and well-trained Athenian navy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.264"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.282"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="8">A still heavier blow was awaiting the Athenians. Brasidas was in the midst of their invaluable possessions on the north-west coast of the Aegean : city after city was falling away to him, each wishing to be the first to revolt; Acanthus, Stagirus, the great and important town of Amphipolis, Torone, Scione, Mende, were already in his hands; the whole fabric of their empire was shaken to its centre. The flower of the Athenian army was dispatched, under Cleon, to recapture Amphipolis; but the troops were disorganized, the leader was incompetent, and they were totally routed under the walls of Amphipolis, almost without striking a blow. What effect this crushing defeat might have upon the Athenian allies, it was of course impossible to conjecture; and Athens began to repent that she had not, while yet on the vantage-ground of success, accepted the favourable terms which the Spartans had then been ready to give.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.301"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.309"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.318"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.326"/>
          <p n="9">Thucydides1 tells us that the two chief obstacles to peace had been Cleon, the Athenian demagogue, and Brasidas, the Spartan general: Brasidas, because of the success and the glory which he was gaining in the War; Cleon, because in quiet times his malpractices would be more apparent and his calumnies less easily believed. It was, indeed, chiefly through the restless activity of Brasidas that the armistice for one year, which had been concluded in the spring of B.C. 423 (very shortly after the battle of Delium), had been rendered abortive; nor can we wonder if, with the brilliant career which was then opening before him, he strained every nerve to prevent its being closed by the ill-timed advent of Peace. The battle of Amphipolis removed both these obstacles: Cleon was slain by a Myrcinian targeteer as he fled from the field of combat: Brasidas was one of the seven who fell on the Lacedaemonian side.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.334"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.346"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.357"/>
          <p n="10">And now arose throughout Hellas an earnest and impatient yearning after the Peace which, it was obvious, could not be long withheld 1. So strong was the feeling that the War was about to determine, that hostili ties were suspended by tacit consent, and the Spartan reinforcements, under Rhamphias, turned back from Thessaly of their own accord : partly, no doubt, for other reasons, but 2 " chiefly," says Thucydides, " because they knew that, when they left Sparta, their Government was bent upon making a peace."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.383"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.392"/>
          <p n="11">It was at this moment, when the prospect of the restoration of Peace to Hellas was the one great topic which engrossed all hearts and tongues, that Aristophanes composed the Comedy which, from its subject, he named " The Peace." It was exhibited 3 at the great city Dionysia, in the archonship of Alcaeus, March, B.C. 421. And hardly had it been produced upon the stage, when the Peace of which it sang dawned upon the Hellenic world. The Peace of Nicias was concluded in March or April, B.C. 421, immediately after the great city Dionysia in the same archonship of Alcaeus 1. It was no mere five years' truce, savouring of tar, and dockyards, and naval preparations—no mere ten years truce, savouring of intrigues and political combinations-not even a mere thirty years' truce, to which the hopes of Aristophanes had, four winters earlier, been limited—it was a Peace for fifty years, a term of which few, who had served in the War, could reasonably expect to see the expiration.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.405"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.414"/>
          <p n="12">Almost immediately after the Peace, a defensive alliance was made between the Athenians and Lacedaemonians, and the prisoners on each side were released.</p>
          <p n="13">So ended the first period of the Peloponnesian War, a period which, by way of distinction, was subsequently, from the King who led the Spartan armies at its commencement, called the Archidamian War.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.431"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.439"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.447"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.455"/>
          <p n="14">It is said in line 990 of this Play that the Athenians had for thirteen years been languishing for want of Peace. And it was, therefore, at one time contended by Paulmier and others that, inasmuch as the Pelopon nesian War did not formally commence until the year B.C. 431, the Play could not have been written until the year B. c. 419 or 418. But this objection assumes that the peace between the Athenian Empire and the Peloponnesian Confederacy had remained undisturbed by any hostilities until the formal commencement of the Peloponnesian War: whereas, in truth, for a period of fully three years before the actual declaration of war on the part of the whole Confederacy, Athens had been incessantly coming into collision with some of its principal members. Not only had the Megarians, by a formal interdict, been excluded from all intercourse with the Athenian empire; but the forces of Athens and Corinth had clashed in open and undisguised conflict, both on the east and on the west coasts of Hellas, at Potidaea on the one side and at Corcyra on the other. No less than ten States had taken part with Corinth in the first expedi tion to Corcyra; and, when Athens actively interposed in favour of the Corcyraeans, it was felt on all sides that the War was virtually begun. The period which intervened before the Peloponnesian Confederacy, as a whole, could be set in motion against Athens was anything but a period of peace and tranquillity. Thucydides clearly regarded it as a mere prelude to the more formal War: a season of trouble and uneasiness, of broken treaties, of complaints and recriminations, of wars and rumours of wars: the skirmishing which preceded the actual conflict of the great Hellenic powers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.463"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.472"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.481"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.489"/>
          <p n="15">It is, therefore, strictly accurate to say that in the year B. c. 421 the Athenians had for thirteen years been deprived of the blessings of Peace : nor is there any real contradiction, as has been alleged by some, between such a statement as this, and those contained in the Acharnians and the Knights 2. There the poet is referring to events-the exclusion of the products of Boeotia from the Athenian market, and the flocking of the country population into Athens-which happen to have been almost exactly coincident in date with the formal commencement of the Pelo ponnesian War. Here he is speaking of a state of conflict and disquietude which had existed for a considerable period prior to such formal com mencement.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.497"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.505"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.513"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.521"/>
          <p n="16">The correct view was ably and successfully maintained yei, Gray, and others. And the controversy is now set at rest, and the date of the Play fixed'for the year B.C. 421, by the discovery of the valuable chronological notice which forms the concluding portion of the Second Argument (infra, page xli), and which was first transcribed by Bekker from the Venetian MS., and published in the year 1829. The last distinguished supporter of Paulmier's theory was Mr. Fynes Clinton, in his " Fasti Hellenici," and he, in the Compendium published shortly before his death, acknowledged his error and adopted the correct date. And, indeed, it is surprising that any doubt should ever have been entertained on the subject. The entire Play would have been an anachronism in any other year. Not only do all the incidental historical notices scattered throughout the scenes, the various circumstances of the several Hellenic peoples, and the motives by which they were respectively actuated in the negotiations for Peace, accord with this epoch, and with none other: not only does the general tone of thought suit no other period of the War: but the cardinal historical fact on which the Play itself is founded absolutely excludes the possibility of any other date. Brasidas and Cleon were dead (they died in the summer of B.C. 422): the Peace was not yet made (it was made in the spring of B.C. 421).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.529"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.543"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.551"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.560"/>
          <p n="17">«The Peace" is, in my judgement, the tamest 2 and (if the expression is allowable) the most un-Aristophanic of all the extant Comedies of Aristophanes. It has little of the inexhaustible merriment, the exuberant vivacity, of his other Plays; and still less of that keen satire, that exquisite wit, that occasional sublimity of sentiment, that grace and elegance of thought and diction, which render his great masterpieces such unrivalled combinations of almost every poetical excellence. The plot is loose and disjointed; an important part of the Parabasis is repeated from one of his earlier plays; and the production of a colossal image of Peace is a somewhat clumsy and inelegant device, and, as such, was justly assailed with ridicule by his able and witty antagonists 1, Eupolis and the comedian Plato.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.568"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.582"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.601"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.609"/>
          <p n="18">Yet the Play is not without its own special and characteristic excel lences. Its very defects were in some degree occasioned by the all absorbing importance, at the moment, of the subject with which it was dealing; and by the strong and earnest feelings which that subject was everywhere calling forth. It was the gravity of the crisis in which and for which the Play was written, which, to a certain extent, dulled the vivacity and cramped the vigour of the great comedian. For years he had been labouring in furtherance of peace, and in opposition to the turbulent policy of Cleon; and now that Cleon was no more, the eager anxiety with which men looked for the restoration of peace and goodwill among the Hellenic peoples was almost too serious and too real for the lighthearted raillery and ridicule in which, at all other times, Aristo phanes loved to indulge.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.617"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.625"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.640"/>
          <p n="19">The Play breathes throughout a genuine appreciation of, and desire for, the enjoyments of rural life ; a yearning such as all true countrymen, pent within the limits of a great city, must at times experience for " the fragrance of their old paternal fields." Few country scenes of antiquity have received more hearty commendation, in modern times, than the second instalment of the Parabasis of this Play ; " ou 1on respire, . says M. Pierron, "une des plus fraîches senteurs de la campagne. "Je demande," asks M. Fallex, " s'il y a rien de plus gracieux que les scenes ravissantes de la Paix, d'ou s'exhale je ne sais quel parfum d'idylle antique." I</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.649"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.657"/>
          <p n="20">And the Play abounds also, like all the writings of Aristophanes, with genuine kindly Panhellenic sentiments, occasionally rising, amidst all the burlesque with which they are surrounded, into a strain of almost solemn and pathetic dignity, as in that beautiful address to Peace which may be called the Consecration hymn.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.665"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.673"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.681"/>
          <p n="21">It is a serious defect in the constitution of the plot that the Play naturally divides itself into two distinct sections, differing from each other in purpose, in character, and even in locality. The first half of the Play represents the Recovery of Peace from the celestial abodes: the second exhibits the festivities and social enjoyments which welcome her restoration to the earth. The Parabasis separates the two sections.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.689"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.697"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="22">The first half of the Play, at times, almost assumes the character of a didactic historical poem, and becomes a most interesting supplement to and illustration of the graver history of the Peloponnesian War. The harmony which exists in all substantial points between the statements of Aristophanes and those of Thucydides is only rendered more valuable from the circumstance that the writers are regarding the same events from totally different points of view. The historian records accomplished events : the poet, for a moment, lifts the veil and gives us a glance at the same events whilst yet in the process of accomplishment, an instan taneous but complete and vivid glimpse of the underlying forces, of the hopes, the fears, the suspicions, the doubts, the rivalries, which were co-operating in their formation. The poet writes of the ever-shifting panorama before his eyes, whilst the waves are yet in motion, the wind perpetually changing, and it is all uncertain what the results may be. The historian records the results when they have passed into the irrevocable domain of fact, when the winds are laid, and the waves have again settled down into a state of calm and motionless tranquillity. So much the more striking is the accord which we everywhere find between the light offhand touches of Aristophanes, and the well-considered judge ments of Thucydides; and that, not merely when they are treating of actual events, or estimating the conduct and character of individuals, but also when they are tracing the various dispositions and tendencies of the several Hellenic States.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="23">The historical portion of the Play terminates with the commencement of the Parabasis : the social scenes which follow, though censured1 as not directly advancing the action of the piece, yet exhibit much more of that genial and mirthful pleasantry, which is one distinguishing characteristic of Aristophanic Comedy.</p>
          <p n="24">" The Peace " of Aristophanes was placed second at the Great Dionysia: the prize was awarded to " The Flatterers" () of Eupolis, and " The Clansmen " () of Leucon was placed third.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.739"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.748"/>
          <p n="25">The Flatterers of Eupolis 2 appears to have fully deserved the victory which it obtained. It was one of those vigorous outbursts of bitter indignant satire for which that great poet was distinguished among his contemporaries : its object being Callias, the brother-in-law of Alcibiades, and the wealthiest Athenian of his day, a voluptuary who squandered his colossal fortunes with profuse and reckless extravagance upon every kind of luxury and sensual pleasure, and who was attended wherever he went by a crowd 1 of fawning sophists, poets, rhetoricians, and other sycoph ts and parasites. These formed the Chorus of the Play, and were described as men whom neither fire nor sword could keep from their patron's table 2. Meineke cites from Maximus Tyrius (Diss. xx, section 7) the statement that Kaa Kal Kat Kal , and refers to this practice the nineteenth fragment of the Play-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.759"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.767"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.781"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.797"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.819"/>
          <p n="26">The Comedy was much esteemed by ancient critics, and more than thirty fragments of it have survived to our own times.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.827"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.835"/>
          <p n="27">Little is known of the dramatic writings of Leucon. Meineke 3 cites but three quotations from, or rather perhaps references to, his comedies; and all three belong to this play of the Clansmen.</p>
          <p n="28">In one point the three Comedies seem to have concurred: the Flatterers, the Peace, the Clansmen alike contained an attack upon the greedy and fawning character of the tragedian 4 Melanthius.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.845"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.853"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.863"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.871"/>
          <p n="29">The first of the Arguments prefixed to this Play contains the following statement :—"( Aristophanes is said in the didascaliae to have exhibited an on two5 distinct occasions: it is uncertain, therefore, says Eratosthenes, whether he exhibited the same Play a second time, or produced another which has not come down to us. Crates, however, recognized two plays, writing thus : at all events in the Acharnians, or in the Babylonians, or in the second Peace. And, indeed, there are many scattered passages cited as from the Peace which are not to be found in the existing Play."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.879"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.887"/>
          <p n="30">This is, I believe, the only passage in the whole range of ancient literature in which any allusion is made to a second Play of the same name as the present: and on this passage we may fairly make the following observations:-</p>
          <p n="31">(1). That beyond twice recording the success ', the didascaliae would probably give no information on the subject.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.908"/>
          <p n="32">(2). That the writer of the Argument had certainly never seen any second Peace.</p>
          <p n="33">(3). That Eratosthenes had certainly never seen any second Peace, and had no grounds, excepting such as were furnished by the entries in the didascaliae, for suspecting that such a Play had ever in fact existed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.916"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.922"/>
          <p n="34">(4). That the language attributed to Crates does not by any means necessarily imply that he had ever seen any second Peace; and, indeed, it is highly improbable that he should have been acquainted with a Play, the very existence of which had escaped the investigation of so learned and industrious a student as Eratosthenes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.930"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.938"/>
          <p n="35">(5). That the passages to which the author of the Argument refers must have been invariably cited as from the Peace simpliciter, and cannot in any instance have been cited as from the second Peace eo nomine.</p>
          <p n="36">(6). That the old grammarians, citing passages from memory, are constantly referring them to the wrong play ; and therefore the mere fact that passages, cited as from the Peace, are not to be found in the existing Play, raises little or no presumption of the existence of another play of that name.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.946"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.956"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.964"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="37">The fragments of Aristophanes have been collected by Canter, Coddaeus, Brunck, Dindorf, and Bergk 1. Their united researches have brought together six passages only cited as from the Peace, and not found in the existing Play. Of these six fragments, one is from Pollux, one from Stobaeus, one from Suidas, and the remaining three from Eustathius. The earliest of these writers lived centuries after the time of Eratosthenes; and it is very unlikely that they should have seen the play which the research of that great scholar was unable to discover: and even had they done so, it is absolutely incredible that after the doubts expressed by Eratosthenes (with whose works they were well acquainted) they should have invariably spoken of it simply as the Peace, without ever in any way distinguishing it from the more celebrated Play of that name, which had always been well and familiarly known.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.981"/>
          <p n="38">Let us now examine seriatim the six passages in question:-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.993"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1002"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1015"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1023"/>
          <p n="39">The first is found in Pollux x, Segm. 188, where it is said, 'Ev yovv []</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1032"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1040"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1048"/>
          <p n="40">The words are omitted in some of the MSS. of Pollux; and whether they are clue to Pollux himself or to some copyist, it is, I think, highly probable that the reference intended is to the existing Play, the writer recollecting that, towards the close of the Comedy, Trygaeus does in truth recommend the conversion of the shield to certain domestic purposes, though a well-cover is not among them.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1056"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1067"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1077"/>
          <p n="41">Stobaeus (Florilegium, Tit. lvi, ed. Gaisford) cites the two following passages in commendation of the art of husbandry:-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1086"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1094"/>
          <p n="42">The second passage is vv. 556, 557, of the existing Play. And it has been suggested with great probability that the heading ' has been accidentally misplaced, " qui plurimorum," says Dindorf 1, " in Stobaeo fons errorum fuit," and that the first passage is really taken from the (Farmers) of Aristophanes.</p>
          <p n="43">The next passage is gleaned from Suidas, who explains to be</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1102"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1110"/>
          <p n="44">Here we can fortunately at once detect and rectify the error; for Suidas is but transcribing the Scholiast on Clouds, 699, where the line is cited as being not but (a play of a kindred character, see the second Argument infra, p. xli). The transcriber was no doubt misled from thinking of the exclamations of War in lines 243, &amp;c., of this play.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1119"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1127"/>
          <p n="45">Eustathius, Comment, on Il. x. 249, speaking of the word , says . The word or does not occur in the Peace, but it seems to have been used in the . See Bergk's note on Fragm. ix of the in Meineke's collection.</p>
          <p n="46">In the same Commentary, xxiii. 123, Eustathius, explaining the word , says ; This would seem to be a correct reference to line 1164 of the present Play; the verse which follows in Eustathius being cited from some other play, the name of which has accidentally dropped out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1140"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1149"/>
          <p n="47">In the Commentary on Od. vii. 120, Eustathius says, ' at . This is certainly an error: Eustathius should have said ‛', not . ‛' ‛', says Athenaeus xiv, chap. 68. See also Id. ix, chap. 14 1. Even Bergk2 admits that this passage cannot be claimed for the second . Indeed, it is simply incredible that Eustathius, who flourished in the twelfth century after Christ, should be familiarly citing under the name of the Peace, that comedy of which the vast research and prodigious learning of Eratosthenes could in the third century before Christ detect no traces whatever.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1170"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1182"/>
          <p n="48">On the whole, therefore, we must, I think, come to the conclusion that if any such play as the second ever existed, it had ceased to exist, at all events under that name, before the time of Eratosthenes, and we have no more materials than be had for deciding what was the exact meaning of that entry in the didascaliae whereby it appeared that Aristopbanes had, on two distinct occasions, exhibited a Comedy under the name of the Peace. Did he exhibit the same play twice ? or did he really write a second Play of that name ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1191"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1202"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1210"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1218"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1226"/>
          <p n="49">Any answer which we may give to these questions must, of course, be of a purely conjectural character; but to me it seems extremely im probable that the present Play should have been produced on the stage a second time. It was written for the particular crisis which was occurring in B.C. 421 , and would have lost all its point and piquancy when repeated on any subsequent occasion. Moreover it did not pretend to any very special merits, was not greatly successful at its first appearance, and bad been made a subject of ridicule by the poet's contemporaries. On the other hand, it is in no way improbable that Aristophanes should, at some later epoch, have endeavoured to work out in a bappier vein and with improved execution the general conception embodied in this Comedy, omitting the devices which had been censured for their extravagance or impropriety, and adapting the incidents of the drama to the altered circumstances of the times. And if he retained his , he would be likely enough to have followed his usual practice of naming the Play from the Chorus (as is the case in eight out of his eleven extant comedies), so that the second would, for distinction's sake, be also called the , or the Farmers. And since we know that Aristophanes1 did in fact write a comedy under that name, and since the fragments of it which still remain do in fact bear in many points a singularly close resemblance to the Play before us, there is nothing unreasonable in the conjecture (and, of course, it is merely a conjecture) that the Play, which when acted bore the same name as the present, is that which was afterwards called by the distinctive appellation of the .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1250"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1258"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1268"/>
          <p n="50">Fritzsche, in one 2 of those instructive Aristophanic tracts in which he was accustomed to pour out upon every subject which came in his way a copious flood of learning and acuteness, not always guided by sound judgement, made the following observations on the fourth of the above-mentioned passages:—" Eustathius de disserens p. 801 TO inquit . Etiam hie locus Brunckii Dindorfiique1 praeclaram diligentiam latuit. Pertinet ad hexametrum (Pollux x. 187) quern jam Brunckius e exemptum esse intellexit . — Nimirum jam veteres earn Comici fabulam quae plerumque appellatur, etiam nomine inscripserunt, Eustathius ipse p. 1291, Crates, Stobaeus, Pollux. Verissime. Etenim fabula nihil aliud fuit quam Pads ejus quae aetatem tulit editio altera, id quod mox alibi certis argumentis demonstrabo." I am not aware that Fritzsche ever resumed this hastily conceived idea, or fulfilled the promise which he made at the close of the foregoing passage. And Bergk, although in his treatise 2 on the Remains of the Old Comedy he was inclined to adopt the idea, yet subsequently, in his Collection 3 of Aristophanic fragments, treated it as altogether without foundation. To me it seems in the highest degree improbable that the grammarians in question should have intentionally cited the , as Fritzsche supposes them to have done, under the simple name of the Peace : I believe that it was by a mere unintentional oversight that the six passages, which we have been considering, were attributed to the Peace, and that the Peace from which they were supposed to come was, in fact, the existing Comedy of that name. But I think it not unlikely that Aristophanes did write a second Play on the same subject, which was acted under the same name; but which, long before the time of Eratosthenes, either was altogether lost, or had assumed and was passing under a different title; and, if the latter view be correct, I know of no play with which we can so reasonably identify it as we can with the .</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1276"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1284"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1292"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1300"/>
          <p n="51">Little or nothing has been done, since the commencement of this century, to assist in a right understanding of the Peace of Aristophanes. The notes of Bothe and Richter, the only two editors who have attempted at any length to explain it, are of very moderate value; and we are still for all practical purposes left to the old commentaries of Florent Chretien, Bergler, and Brunck. The Play has, however, largely participated in the general improvement of the Aristophanic text, which resulted from the collation of the Ravenna and Venetian MSS.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1305"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1315"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1329"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1337"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1347"/>
          <p n="52">In the present edition, the first complete edition of the Peace which has ever been published by an Englishman, I have endeavoured to adhere more closely than has hitherto been done to the reading of those two excellent MSS. The various readings and conjectures are collected at the end of the Play• whilst in the notes which are subjoined to the text, I have attempted to bring out the purpose and meaning of the poet, to illustrate the historical bearings of the Comedy, and to explain such phrases and passages as seemed to require an explanation, carefully dis tinguishing, in every instance, whatever I have borrowed from previous writers. The translation, though generally literal, is not uniformly so: it is designed to be readable as a whole, without reference to the original Greek: and I have not hesitated to sacrifice strict verbal accuracy when ever such a course seemed desirable for the carrying out of that primary object. The translation retains the anapaestic, trochaic, and iambic measures, the heroic hexameters, and the other familiar metres of the original. And in one instance, vv. 775-818, I have endeavoured to reproduce with exactness a more complicated Choral system, but the attempt was not so successful as to encourage a repetition.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
