<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moschus, Idylls</title>
        <author>Moschus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0035.tlg001.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.18"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.26"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.10"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.18"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="2.27"/>
          <p n="1">1‘ My son Eros,' Venus was loudly calling, 'Eros, if any one has seen straying in the cross-roads, he is my runaway: the informer shall have a reward. The kiss of Venus shall be your pay; and if you shall have brought him, not the 2 bare kiss, but, stranger, you shall have even more: now the lad is very notable; you would know him among 3twenty together: in complexion indeed he is not fair, but like to fire; and his eyes are piercing and fiery-red: evil his heart, pleasant his speech. For he does not speak the same as he thinks; his voice is as honey, 4but if he be wroth, his mind is ruthless; deceiving, telling truth in nothing, wily child, he 5 sports cruelly. His head has goodly curls, but "impudent is the face he wears: his little hands are tiny, 'tis true, yet they shoot far; shoot even to Acheron, and to the king of Hades. He is naked indeed so far as his body is concerned, but his mind is 7 shrouded. And being winged, as a bird, he flies upon now one party of men and women and now another, and settles on their inmost hearts. He has a very small bow, and upon the bow an arrow: small is his arrow, yet it carries even to the sky: and a golden quiver above his back, and within it are the bitter shafts, with which he often wounds even me. All, all is cruel; but far most a little torch that he has, 8with which he kindles the sun himself. If you at any rate shall have caught him, bind and bring him, and do not pity him. And if ever you shall have seen him weeping, be ware lest he beguile you ; and if he smile, do you drag him on : and if he should desire to kiss you, avoid it; his kiss is mischievous, 9his lips poison. But should he say, ‘ Take these, I present thee all the arms I have,' do not touch them, de ceitful gifts; for they have all been dipt in fire.'</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
