<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aristophanes, Knights</title>
        <author>Aristophanes</author>
        <editor role="translator">William James Hickie</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>William James Hickie (1853). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0019.tlg002.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="1">
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="1">DEMUS, an old citizen of Athens, and in whom the Athenian people are typified.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="2">THE PAPHLAGONIAN, (Cleon,) Steward to Demus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="3">SAUSAGE-SELLER (afterwards Agoracritus).</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1"/>
          <p n="4">THIS Comedy was performed at the Lenæan Festival, in the Archonship of Stratocles, 01. Ixxxix. 1, in January, B. C. 424. " In the eighth year of the war: Aristoph. Equit. 793, , computed from the battle of Potidæa, E. C. 432. The sixth year, mentioned Aristoph. Acharn., (vide a. 425,) was computed from the invasion of Attica, eight months afterwards.”—Clinton's Fast. Hell. p. 69.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="5">■ In the Acharnians, vs. 300, we have,</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="6">In this Drama, which was the first represented in his own name, the Poet fulfilled his promise, and with the assistance of the Knights, who here constitute the Chorus, carried off the first prize, and showed the Demagogue to be , (Thucyd. lib. iii. 36,) for he still remained as great a favourite as ever. The second prize was ad judged to Cratinus, for the Satyrs: the third to Aristomenes, for the Lamentations. As no artist would make a mask for the character of Cleon, Aristophanes was obliged to perform the part himself. In some measure to give an idea of the flushed and bloated countenance of that Demagogue, he smeared his face with lees of wine, and thus stood forth in the double capacity of Poet and Actor. A. W. Schle gel (Dramatic Literature, p. 159) remarks, " He bad the prudence never to name Cleon, though he portrayed him in such a way that it was impossible to mistake him. No one of his plays, perhaps, is more historical and political; and its rhetorical power in exciting our indignation is almost irresistible : it is a true dramatic Philippic. However, in point of amusement and invention, it does not appear to me the most fortunate." To understand fully the historical allu sions, it will be necessary to have a recollection of the affair of Pylos, as recorded by Thucydides, lib. iv. See also Thirlwall, Hist. Greece, iii. 235—244.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.9"/>
          <p n="7">As there is no plot, the Dramatis Personæ will be a sufficient explanation.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <p n="8">DEM. ALAS ! alas ! for our misfortunes, alas ! alas ! May the gods miserably destroy the Paphlagonian,1 the newly- purchased pest, together with his schemings ! For since the time that he entered into our family, he is always inflicting blows upon the domestics.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <p n="9">NIC. (approaching cautiously). Aye, verily, may this pri mate of Paphlagonians perish most miserably, together with his calumnies.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <p n="10">DEM. 0 wretched man ! how are you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.17"/>
          <p n="11">Nic. Miserable, like you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.26"/>
          <p n="12">DEll. Come hither then, that we may weep in concert a stave of Olympus.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.26"/>
          <p n="13">DEM. and Nic. Mumu, mumu, mumu, mumu, mumu, mumu.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.26"/>
          <p n="14">DEM. Why do we lament to no purpose ? Ought we not to have sought some means of safety, and not5 weep any more ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.26"/>
          <p n="15">Nic. What safety then can there be ? do you say.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="16">DEM. Nay, rather, do you say, that I may not quarrel with you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="17">Nic. By Apollo, not I. But speak boldly, and then I also will give my opinion.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="18">DEM. " Would that thou wouldst say what I should say.”1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="19">Nic. But the spirit's2 not in me. How then, pray, can I ever speak it with Euripidean prettiness ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="20">DEM. Nay, do not; do not; do not dose me with Eu ripides.3 But find some way of dancing off from our master.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.34"/>
          <p n="21">Nic. Say now in a breath “ Sert," pronouncing it in this way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="22">DEM. Well now, I say it; “ Sert."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="23">Nic. Now after the “ Sert,” say “ De."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="24">Nic. Very well! Now first say “ Sert" slowly, and then " De," bringing it rapidly after it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="25">DEM. " Sert—de, sert, DESERT."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="26">Nic. See ! is it not pleasant ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.46"/>
          <p n="27">DEM. Yes, by Jove : but I fear this omen for my hide.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="28">DEM. Because the hide in such cases is apt to depart.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="29">Nic. It is best for us, therefore, in the present state of things, to go and fall before the statue of some god.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="30">DEM. Before what statue ? Pray, do you believe in gods ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="31">DEM. Where's your proof ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="32">Nic. Because I am hateful to the gods. Is it not1 with good reason I do so ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.61"/>
          <p n="33">DEM. You persuade me rightly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.69"/>
          <p n="34">Nic. But we must look elsewhere.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.69"/>
          <p n="35">DEM. Will you that I state the matter to the spectators ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.69"/>
          <p n="36">Nic. It would not be amiss :3 but one thing let us require of them, to show us by their countenances if they are pleased with our discourse and matter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.69"/>
          <p n="37">DEM. I will now tell them. We have a master surly in his temper, bean-fed,4 passionate, Demus of the Pnyx, a crab bed old man, somewhat deaf. He at the previous new5 moon bought a slave, a tanner of Paphlagonia, most villanous and most calumniating. This Leather-Paphlagonian, when he had fully learnt the old man's disposition, by fawning on our master, used to wheedle,6 cajole, flatter, and deceive him with tips of leather parings, using such words—“ 0 Demus, when you have first tried one7 cause, bathe, eat, gobble up, devour, take the three obols. Would you that I serve up supper to you ?" Then, having snatched up what any of us may have prepared, the Paphlagonian makes a present of this to our master. And lately too, when I bad kneaded a Spartan cake at Pylos, he somehow circumvented me most knavishly and filched it away, and served up himself what had been knead ed by me. Us he drives away, and does not suffer any one else to wait on our master, but with a leather fan, when at supper, stands and drives away the orators.8 And he re cites oracles, while the old man gets old-womanish. And when he sees him grown spoony, he has devised his trick; for he falsely accuses the household to their face, and then we are scourged; while the Paphlagonian runs around the servants, and asks, confounds, takes bribes, using these words, “ Do you see that Hylas has been scourged through my influ ence ? Unless you make a friend of me, you shall die to-day." So we make him presents ; otherwise, we are trampled upon and kicked by the old fellow eight times more than before.2 Now therefore, my good friend, let us quickly consider to what road we must turn, and to whom.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.69"/>
          <p n="38">Nic. We had4 best turn to that " Sert-Road," my good sir.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.77"/>
          <p n="39">DEM. But it is not possible for any thing to escape the Paphlagonian's notice, for he overlooks all things himself: he keeps one leg at Pylos, the other in the assembly; and when he has straddled thus far, his hinder parts are really and truly among the Chaonians,5 his hands among the Ætolians, and his mind with the Clopidæ.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.77"/>
          <p n="40">Nic. Then it is best for us to die. But consider how we may die most manfully.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.77"/>
          <p n="41">DEM. How, pray, how can it be done, most manfully ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.77"/>
          <p n="42">Nic. It is best for us to drink bull's blood, for the death7 of Themistocles is more preferable.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.85"/>
          <p n="43">DEM. No, by Jove, but pure wine to1 the good Genius; for perhaps we may devise some good plan.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.85"/>
          <p n="44">Nic. " Pure wine," quoth'a ! Are your thoughts then on drinking?2 How could a man devise any good plan when drunk?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.85"/>
          <p n="45">DEM. Is it so, fellow? You are a pourer forth3 of weak, washy twaddle. Have you the audacity to abuse wine for witlessness ? Can you find any thing more business-like than wine ? Do you see ? when men drink, then they are rich, they transact business, gain causes, are happy, assist their friends. Come, bring me out quickly a stoup of wine, that I may moisten my intellect, and say something clever.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.85"/>
          <p n="46">Nic. Woe's me! What in the world will you do to us with your drinking ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.95"/>
          <p n="47">DEM. What's good. Come, bring it forth, and I will lay myself down. [Exit Nicias.] For if I get drunk, I shall sprinkle all these with little schemes, and little notions, and little thoughts. [Re-enter Nicias with a pitcher of wine and a cup.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.95"/>
          <p n="48">Nic. How fortunate that I was not caught stealing the wine from within !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.95"/>
          <p n="49">DEM. Tell me, what is the Paphlagonian doing ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.95"/>
          <p n="50">Nic. The slanderer having licked up some confiscated4 cakes, snores like a drunkard, lying on his back on his hides.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="51">DEM. Come now, pour in abundant pure wine as a libation.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="52">Nic. Take it now, and make a libation to the good Genius. Drain, drain the draught of the Pramnian god.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="53">DEM. (taking a hearty draught). 0 good Genius! the scheme is yours, not mine.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="54">Nic. Tell me, I beseech you. What is it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="55">DEM. Steal quickly the oracles of the Paphlagonian, and bring them from within, while he sleeps.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.103"/>
          <p n="56">Nic. Aye,' aye, sir. But I fear that I shall find the Genius an evil Genius. [Exit Nicias.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.112"/>
          <p n="57">DEM. Come now, I'll apply the stoup to my lips, that I may moisten my, intellect, and say something clever.2 [Re- enter Nicias with a bundle of papers.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.112"/>
          <p n="58">Nic. How mightily the Paphlagonian blows and snores, so that I escaped his notice in stealing the sacred oracle, which he used to guard with the greatest caution !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.112"/>
          <p n="59">DEM. 0 thou most clever, bring it, that I may read it! and do you quickly pour in for me to3 drink. Come, let me see what there is then in here. 0 oracles ! Give me, give me the cup quickly. [Drinks.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="60">Nic. Well! what says the oracle?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="61">DEM. Pour me in another. [Drinks.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="62">Nic. Is “ Pour in another " among the oracles ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="63">DEM. Give me the cup quickly. [Drinks.J</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="64">Nic. Aye, Bacis was in the habit of using the cup fre quently.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.120"/>
          <p n="65">DEM. 0 rascally Paphlagonian ! it was this then that you were guarding against this long while, dreading the oracle about yourself!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.128"/>
          <p n="66">DEM. There is in here how he himself is ruined.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.128"/>
          <p n="67">DEM. How?5 The oracle directly declares that first there arises a hemp-seller, who shall be the first to hold the admin istration of the state.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.128"/>
          <p n="68">Nic. This is one seller. What next ? Say on.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.128"/>
          <p n="69">DEM. After him, again, is to arise a second, a sheep-seller.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.128"/>
          <p n="70">Nic. These are two sellers. What must this one do ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="71">DEM. Rule, until another1 man more abandoned than he arise ; and after this he is destroyed. For the Paphlagonian leather-seller succeeds, the robber, the bawler, with the voice of Cycloborus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="72">Nic. It is fated, then, that the sheep-seller perish at the hands of the leather-seller.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="73">Nic. Ah me, unhappy! Whence therefore can there be only one seller more?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="74">DEM. There is still one, with a wondrous trade.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="75">Nic. Tell me, I entreat you, who is he ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.136"/>
          <p n="76">DEM. A sausage-seller is the person who is to3 destroy him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="77">Nic. A sausage-seller ? Neptune, what4 a trade ! Come, where shall we find out this man ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="78">DEM. Let us seek for him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="79">Nic. But see, here he comes to market, providentially, as it were!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="80">DEM. 0 happy sausage-seller ! hither, hither, dearest of men; come up, you who have appeared a saviour to our city and to us !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="81">S. S. What's the matter ? Why do you call me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.144"/>
          <p n="82">DEM. Come hither, that you may learn how fortunate you are, and how great is your bliss. [Sausage-seller comes up. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.152"/>
          <p n="83">Nic. Come now, take away his dresser, and expound6 unto him the racle itself of the god, how it runs ;1 while I will go and watch the Paphlagonian. [Exit Nicias.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.152"/>
          <p n="84">DEM. Come now, first lay down your implements on the ground, and then adore the earth, and the gods.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.152"/>
          <p n="85">S. S. Well! what's the matter ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.152"/>
          <p n="86">DEM. 0 happy, 0 wealthy man ! 0 thou who art to-day a nobody, but to-morrow immensely great! 0 thou ruler of happy Athens !2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.160"/>
          <p n="87">S. S. My good sir, why don't you let me wash my pud dings, and sell my sausages, and not make game3 of me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.160"/>
          <p n="88">DEM. 0 foolish man, what4 puddings? Look here! Do you see the rows of people there ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.160"/>
          <p n="89">DEM. Of all these you shall be alone the chief, and of the market-place, and of the harbours, and of the Pnyx. You shall trample on the senate, and humble the generals; you shall imprison, put under ward, and in the Prytaneum you shall—wench.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.168"/>
          <p n="90">DEM. Aye, you ; and you do not yet see all. But mount up even upon this dresser here,6 and survey all the islands round about. [ Sausage-seller mounts up upon his dresser.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.168"/>
          <p n="91">DEM. What then ? the marts and merchant ships ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.168"/>
          <p n="92">DEM. How then are you not greatly blessed ? Further now, turn your right eye to Caria, and your other to Chalcedon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.168"/>
          <p n="93">S. S. Shall I be blest if I squint ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.176"/>
          <p n="94">DEM. No ; but through you all these are on1 sale ; for you shall become, as this oracle here asserts, a very great man.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.176"/>
          <p n="95">S. S. Tell me; why, how shall I who am a sausage-seller become a great man ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.176"/>
          <p n="96">DEM. For this very reason,2 truly, shall you even become great; because you are a knave, and from the market-place, and impudent.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.176"/>
          <p n="97">S. S. I do not consider myself worthy to have great power.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.176"/>
          <p n="98">DEM. Alas ! whatever's the reason that you say you are not worthy ? \ou seem to me to be conscious of something gentlemanly. Are you of gentle birth ?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.184"/>
          <p n="99">S. S. No, by the gods, unless4 to come of blackguards be so.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.184"/>
          <p n="100">DEM. 0 happy in your fortune ! What an advantage5 you have for statesmanship !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.184"/>
          <p n="101">S. S. But, my good sir, I don't even possess any education, beyond my letters, and them, to be sure, as bad as bad can be.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.184"/>
          <p n="102">DEM. This alone is an obstacle to you, that you do know them, even as bad as bad can be. For the character of popular leader no longer belongs to a man of education, nor yet to one good in his morals, but7 to the ignorant and abominable. Then don't neglect what the gods in their oracles offer you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.184"/>
          <p n="103">S. S. How, pray, does the oracle speak ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.195"/>
          <p n="104">DEM. Well, by the gods, and ambiguously, in a way, and learnedly wrapped in riddles. "But when the leather-eagle with crooked claws shall seize in his beak a serpent, a stupid fellow, a drinker of blood, just then8 the garlic-pickle of the Paphlagonians is at an end, while to the sellers of puddings the god grants great glory, unless they choose rather to sell sausages."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.195"/>
          <p n="105">S. S. How then does this relate to me ? Instruct me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.203"/>
          <p n="106">DEM. This Paphlagonian here is the “ leather-eagle."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.203"/>
          <p n="107">S. S. Why is he " with crooked claws ?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.203"/>
          <p n="108">DEM. It means, I ween, that he snatches and takes away with his hands curved.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.203"/>
          <p n="109">S. S. But what's the import of the " serpent?”</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.203"/>
          <p n="110">DEM. This is very clear; for the “ serpent " is long, and the “ sausage " again is long: then both the sausage2 and the serpent are “ drinkers of blood." It says, therefore, that the serpent shall immediately conquer the leather-eaglet unless it be cajoled with words.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="111">S. S. The oracles please me: but I wonder how I am able to manage the people.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.211"/>
          <p n="112">DEM. A very easy affair ! Act as you act now; jumble and mince together all state-affairs, and always win over the peo ple to your side, coaxing it with little cookish words. But the other requisites for a demagogue you possess - a foul tongue, you are of vulgar birth, a low fellow; you possess all things which are requisite for statesmanship. The oracles and the Delphic shrine conspire in your favour. Crown yourself then, and offer a libation to Dulness, and see that you punish the fellow.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.219"/>
          <p n="113">S. S. And who will be my ally ? for the rich fear him, and the poor people are afraid of him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.219"/>
          <p n="114">DEM. But there are a thousand brave knights5 who hate him, who will aid you, and the well-born citizens, and of the spectators whoever is a clever man, and I along with them, and the god will6 assist you. And do not fear, for he is not represented by a likeness ; for, through fear, none of the mask-makers7 was willing to make a likeness of him. Never- theless, he will be certainly recognised; for the audience is clever.!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.230"/>
          <p n="115">S. S. (in great fright). Ah me, miserable ! the Paphla gonian is coming forth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.230"/>
          <p n="116">CLEON. By the twelve gods, you certainly shall not go un punished, in that you have been long conspiring together against the democracy. What's this Chalcidian cup doing here ? You are certainly causing a revolt of the Chalcidians.2 You shall perish, you shall die, you brace of rogues. [ Saus age-seller runs out.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.238"/>
          <p n="117">DEM. Ho you ! why do you fly ? will you not stop ? 0 noble sausage-seller, do not betray the cause ! 0 ye Knights,3 support us ! Now's the time ! Simony Panætius, will you not ride to the right wing ? [ To the Sausage-seller.] The men are near; come, resist him, and return to the charge again ! Their dust shows that they5 are approaching in a body. Come, resist, and pursue, and put him to flight. [Enter Chorus of Knights.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.242"/>
          <p n="118">CiO. Strike, strike the villain, and troubler of the Knights, and publican, and sink, and Charybdis of plunder, and villain, and villain ; for I will use the same expressions many times. For this fellow was a villain many times in the day.-Come, strike, and pursue, and disturb, and confound, and detest him,6 for we do so ; and press on him, and shout aloud. But take care, lest he escape you, for he knows the paths by which Eucrates fled straight to the bran.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.250"/>
          <p n="119">CLE. (turning to the audience). Veteran Heliasts, clans men of the three-obol-piece, whom I feed by bawling right or wrong, come to the rescue, since I am being beaten by conspirators.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.258"/>
          <p n="120">CiO. Aye, with justice; since you devour1 the public goods before they are distributed by lot, and you press and squeeze those under account, seeing which of them is green, or ripe, or not yet ripe; and if you perceive any of them to be an easy quiet man, and a gaper, you recall him from the Chersonese2 and seize him by the waist and lock him ;3 and then having twisted back his shoulder, you fall heavily upon him. And you observe, too, which of the citizens is a simple ton, and rich, and no rascal, and fearing state-affairs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.258"/>
          <p n="121">CLE. Do you join in attacking me ? while I am beaten, sirs, on your account, because I was intending to deliver an opinion, that it is proper to erect in the city a memorial on account of your valour.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="122">CHO. What5 an impostor ! what a supple knave ! You see how he fawns upon us as if we were old dotards, and cajoles us. But if in this way he be victorious, he shall be beaten in that and if he dodge this way,6 my leg shall strike him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="123">CLE. 0 city and people, by what beasts am I punched in the belly!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="124">CiO. What! do you cry out, who are ever turning the city upside down? [Re-enter Sausage-seller.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="125">S. S. But with this shout I will first put you to flight.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.266"/>
          <p n="126">CHe. If, in truth, you conquer him in bawling,l you are a conqueror ; but if you surpass him in impudence, ours is the meed of victory.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="127">CLE. I inform against this fellow, and assert that he ex ports broths3 for the Peloponnesian triremes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="128">S. S. Aye,4 by Jove, and I inform against this man, that he ran into the Prytaneum with his belly empty, and then runs out again with it full.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="129">DEM. Yes, by Jove, bearing out forbidden exports, bread and meat at the same time, and sliced salt-fish, of which Pericles was never at any time thought worthy.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="130">CLE. You shall die forthwith.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="131">S. S. I will shout three times as loud as you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.274"/>
          <p n="132">CLE. I will silence you with bawling.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="133">S. S. I will scream you down with screaming.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="134">CLE. I will calumniate you if you be general.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="135">S. S. I will beat your back like a dog.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="136">CLE. I will harass you with impostures.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="137">S. S. I will cut off your roads.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.284"/>
          <p n="138">CLE. Look at me without winking.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="139">S. S. I too have been reared in the market-place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="140">CLE. I will tear you in pieces if you mutter at all.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="141">S. S. I will cover you with dung if you speak.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="142">CLE. I confess myself a thief, while you do not.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="143">S. S. Aye, that do I, by Mercury, who presides over the market-place, and perjure myself too, though men see it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.292"/>
          <p n="144">CLE. Then you play the sophist in another's province, and I will impeach you to the Prytanes for possessing untithed puddings sacred to the gods.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.303"/>
          <p n="145">CrO. 0 rascally and abominable, and bawler! every land is full of thy audacity, and every assembly, and imposts, and indictments, and law-courts. 0 thou mud-stirrer, and having disturbed2 our whole state, who hast deafened our Athens with thy bawling, and watching for the tribute-money, like tunny-fish, from the rocks above.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.303"/>
          <p n="146">CLE. I know this affair, whence it has been long ago getting cobbled Up.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.303"/>
          <p n="147">S. S. If you do not know shoe-soles, neither do I sausages; you who cheatingly-cut-up and sold the hide of a diseased ox to the country people, with fraudulent design, so that it should seem stout; and before they had worn it a day, it was greater than the foot by two spans.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.319"/>
          <p n="148">DEM. By Jove, he did the very same thing to me too, so that I also afforded much mirth to my fellow-tribesmen and friends ; for, ere that I had reached Pergasæ, 1 I was swimming in my shoes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.319"/>
          <p n="149">CHO. Have you not, pray, from the first, displayed impu dence,2 which alone is the guardian of orators? on which you relying, drain the wealthy foreigners, you the first; while the son of Hippodamus3 melts into tears at the sight. But indeed another fellow much more rascally than you has showed himself, so that I rejoice, who will immediately put an end to you and surpass you, as he plainly shows, in villany and im pudence and knavish tricks. [ To the Samage-seller. ] But come, you who have been educated 4 whence men arise, such as they are,5 now demonstrate that Modest Education" is nothing to the purpose.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.319"/>
          <p n="150">S. S. Well now, hear what sort of a citizen this fellow is.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="151">CLE. Will you not in turn permit me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="152">S. S. No, by Jove, since I too am a blackguard.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="153">CHO. If he do not yield in this point, say that you are also come of blackguards.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="154">CLE. Will you not in turn permit me ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="155">CLE. Yes, by Jove, you shall.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.333"/>
          <p n="156">S. S. No, by Neptune, but I will fight it out first, with respect to who shall speak first.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="157">CLE. Alas, I shall burst.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="158">S. S. But I will not permit you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="159">CHO. Permit him, by the gods, permit him to burst.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="160">CLE. Relying1 on what do you dare to speak against me?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="161">S. S. Because I too am able to speak, and to make a rich sauce.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.341"/>
          <p n="162">CLE. " To speak," quoth'a ! Finely,2 upon my word, would you take up and properly handle a case which fell to you, so as to be torn in pieces raw.3 But do you know how you seem to me to be circumstanced ? Like the mass.4 If you have any where pleaded some little suit well against a resident-alien, babbling the live-long night, and talking to. yourself in the streets, and drinking water, and showing yourself off, and boring your friends, you fancied you were a a dab at oratory-Fool for your folly !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.351"/>
          <p n="163">S. S. By drinking what, pray, have you worked upon the city, so as now to be silent, having been talked down by you alone?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.351"/>
          <p n="164">CLE. Why, do you match any man against me ? who, immediately after I have devoured hot slices of the tunny- fish, and then drank besides a gallon of neat wine, will abuse like a strumpet the generals at Pylos.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.351"/>
          <p n="165">S. S. And I, after I have swallowed down a cow's paunch and a pig's belly, and then drank the broth besides, without washing, will throttle1 the orators, and terrify Nicias.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.359"/>
          <p n="166">CHO. You please me in the rest of your words; but one part of your conduct does not please me, in that you will gulp down your broth alone.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.359"/>
          <p n="167">CLE. But you will not distract the Milesians, after having devoured a sea-wolf.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.359"/>
          <p n="168">S. S. Nay, but when I have devoured ribs 3 of beef, I will farm the mines.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.359"/>
          <p n="169">CLE. And I will spring into the senate and confound it with violence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.359"/>
          <p n="170">S. S. And I will kick your rump instead of a foot-ball.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="171">CLE. And I will drag you out of doors, head foremost, by the crupper.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="172">CHO. By Neptune, you shall drag me too, if you drag him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="173">CLE. How I will fasten you in the stocks !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="174">S. S. I will prosecute you for cowardice.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="175">CLE. Your hide5 shall be tanned.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.367"/>
          <p n="176">S. S. I will flay you for a thief's pouch.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <p n="177">CLE. You shall be stretched out on the ground with pegs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <p n="178">S. S. I will make mince-meat of you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <p n="179">CLE. I will pluck out your eye-lashes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <p n="180">S. S. I will cut out your crop.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.375"/>
          <p n="181">DEM. And, by Jove, we will put a skewer into his mouth, in cook's fashion, and then draw out his tongue from within, and examine his inside well and manfully, while he gapes, if it be pimply.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.388"/>
          <p n="182">Cno. It appears, then, there are other things hotter than fire ; and in our state words more shameless than the shame less ;1 and the affair, then, not so trifling a one. But attack him, and twist him about; do nothing in a small way: for now he is held by the middle. Since if now you hide 2 him in the onset, you will find him a craven; for I know his dis position.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.388"/>
          <p n="183">S. S. Yet, nevertheless, this fellow, though he has been such a one during the whole of his life, then appeared to be a hero, when he reaped the harvest of another. And now he has bound in the wooden collar, and is drying, and wishing to sell those ears of corn which he brought from thence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.388"/>
          <p n="184">CLE. I fear you not as long as the senate subsists, and the face of Demus4 remains stolid.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.398"/>
          <p n="185">CHO. What impudence he has for every thing ! and changes nothing of his present5 colour! If I do not hate you, may I become a sheep-skin of Cratinus,6 and may I be taught to sing the songs in a tragedy of Morsimus.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.398"/>
          <p n="186">O thou, who on every occasion, and in all cases of bribery,' settlest upon flowers, would that you'd disgorge the mouth ful as easily as you found it; for then would I sing only, "drink,2 drink, at the happy event;" and I fancy the son of Julius, an aged ogler of wheat,3 being delighted, would cry, " lo Paean," and sing, " Bacchus, Bacchus !"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.407"/>
          <p n="187">CLE. By Neptune, ye certainly shall not surpass me in impudence; or never may I be present at the sacrificial feast of Jupiter, who presides over the market-place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.407"/>
          <p n="188">S. S. By the thumps, which I have many times,4 indeed, and on many occasions, endured from my childhood, and by the strokes of the knives, I fancy I shall surpass you in these, or to no purpose should I be grown to this size by feeding on finger-muffins.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="189">CLE. On finger-muffins, like a dog ? 0 thou most villanous, how then, fed on dog's meat, shall you battle with a dog-faced baboon ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="190">S. S. And, by Jove, there are other knavish tricks of mine, too, when I was a child; for I used to deceive the butchers by saying such words, " Look, boys! do you not see ? early Spring is come. Theres a swallow !" They looked, and I in the mean time used to steal some meat.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.415"/>
          <p n="191">CHO. 0 most clever meat!. shrewdly did you plan be forehand ! You stole before the swallows, as if eating nettles.'</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <p n="192">,S. S. And I used to escape notice too, when doing this. At any rate, if any of them were to see me, I used to hide it in my drawers, and deny it upon oath of the gods, so that an oratory having seen me doing this, exclaimed, " This boy will certainly rule the people."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <p n="193">CHO. Aye, he conjectured it well: but it is clear from what he drew his inference; because you perjured yourself after stealing, and your drawers had the meat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <p n="194">CLE. I will make you cease from your impudence,—or rather, I fancy, both of you: for I will issue forth against you, coming down 3 now fresh and mighty, confounding at the same time both land and sea at random.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <p n="195">S. S. And I will furl my sausages and then commit myself to the favouring waves,4 having bid you a long farewell.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.423"/>
          <p n="196">DEM. And I, if it leak at all, will watch the bilge-water.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="197">CLE. By Ceres, you certainly shall not go off unpunished, after having stolen many talents of the Athenians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="198">CiO. Look sharp, and slack away the sheet !5 since now this north-easter is even blowing informations.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="199">S. S. I well know that you have ten talents from Potidæa.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="200">CLE. What then ? Will you take one of the talents, and hold your tongue ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="201">CiO. The man would gladly take it. Let out your sail-ropes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.432"/>
          <p n="202">S. S. The wind is lulling.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="203">CLE. You shall be a defendant in four suits of a hundred talents.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="204">S. S. And you in twenty for shunning service, and in more than a thousand for theft.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="205">CLE. I assert that you are descended from those who of fended against the goddess.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="206">S. S. I assert that your grandfather was one of the body- guards.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="207">CLE. What body-guards? Explain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.440"/>
          <p n="208">S. S. Of Byrsina, the mother of Hippias.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.450"/>
          <p n="209">CLE. You are an impudent rogue.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.450"/>
          <p n="210">S. S. You are a villain.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.450"/>
          <p n="211">CHO. Strike manfully. [ They all fall on him and beat him.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.450"/>
          <p n="212">CLE. Alas ! alas ! The conspirators are beating me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.450"/>
          <p n="213">CHO. Strike him most manfully, and punch him in the belly, both with your guts and with your tripe, and see that you punish the fellow. 0 thou most noble bit of flesh, and bravest of all in soul, and who hast appeared4 a saviour of the state, and of us the citizens, how well and cunningly with your words you supplanted the fellow! Would I could praise thee as much as we are delighted.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.461"/>
          <p n="214">CLE. By Ceres, these transactions did not escape my notice in the carpentering, but I was aware of them all in the nailing and the gluing.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.461"/>
          <p n="215">CHO. (turning to the Sausage-seller). Alas ! can you talk nought of cart-wright's 7 slang !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.461"/>
          <p n="216">S. S. Then, what he is doing at Argos does not escape me. In pretence he is making the Argives1 our friends, but se cretly he is there treating with the Lacedæmonians. And I know for what purpose this is getting welded; for it,is get ting forged on account of the prisoners.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.461"/>
          <p n="217">CHO. Bravo ! bravo! Forge in return for his gluings.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.470"/>
          <p n="218">S. S. And in return4 men from thence join in welding it;., and neither by giving silver or gold, or by sending friends, shall you persuade me, so that I shall not denounce these things to the Athenians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.470"/>
          <p n="219">CLE. I therefore will go forthwith to the senate, and tell them of the conspiracies of you all, and your nightly meet ings in the city, and all that ye are plotting with the Medes5 and the king of Persia, and these transactions which are being concocted amongst the Bœotians.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.480"/>
          <p n="220">S. S. What, then, is the price of cheese among the Bœ otians ? 7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.480"/>
          <p n="221">CLE. By Hercules, I will lay you flat! [Exit Cleon.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.480"/>
          <p n="222">CHO. Come now, what mind, or what spirits have you ?1 Now you shall show, if formerly you concealed the meat in your drawers, as you yourself assert. For you must run in haste into the senate-house, since this fellow will rush in thither, and calumniate us all, and bawl aloud.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.488"/>
          <p n="223">S. S. Well, I will go: but first I will lay down ray pud . dings and my knives here, just as I am.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="224">CHO. Stop now, anoint your neck with this, that you may be able to slip out of his calumnies. [Hands him a flask of oil.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="225">S. S. Well, you say this well, and like a gymnastic master.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="226">CHO. Stop now, take and eat up this. [Hands him. a head of garlic.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.498"/>
          <p n="227">CiO. In order that you may fight the better, my friend, having been primed with garlic. And now2 hasten quickly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.507"/>
          <p n="228">CHO. Remember now to bite, to libel, to eat up his crests ; and see that you come back again, having devoured his wat tles. But go, and joy3 be with you, and may you succeed according to my wish, and may Jove, who presides over the market-place, protect you; and when you have conquered, may you come back again to us from thence besprinkled with chaplets. [Exit Sausage-seller.] Do ye, on the other hand, give your attention to our anapaests, 0 ye, who of yourselves4 have already essayed every kind of learning.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.537"/>
          <p n="229">If any of the old comic writers had been for compelling us to come forward to the audience to recite his verses, he would not easily have obtained this. But now our poet is worthy of it, inasmuch as he hates the same with us, and dares to say what is just, and nobly advances against the Typhon, and the hurricane.1 But with respect to what2 he says many of you coming to him wonder at, and inquire about, that he did not long since ask for a chorus3 for himself, about this matter he bade us explain to you. For the man says that he did not make the delay because he was affected in this way by want of understanding, but because he thought the comic poet's art to be the most difficult task of all; for that, after many, indeed, had courted her, she had granted favours to few; and be cause he long since perceived that you were in nature changing with the year,4 and betrayed 5 the former poets as soon as they grew old. On the one hand6 knowing what Magnes suffered, as soon as grey hairs came upon him, who set up very many trophies of victory over the choruses of his rivals; and though he uttered every kind of sound,7 both " Harping," and " Fluttering," and representing the " Ly dians," and playing the " Fig-fly," and dyeing himself a " Frog colour," did not suffice ; but at last, in his old age, for it had not been so in his youth,8 he was driven off the stage, when he was an old man, because he was wanting in jesting: next, remembering Cratinus,1 who formerly having flowed with a full stream of praise used to flow through the level plains, and carrying away from their places, used to bear away the oaks and the plane-trees, and his enemies by the roots. And it was not permitted to sing any thing at a banquet except " Oh fig-sandaled2 Doro," and "builders3 of ingenious songs;" so much did he flourish. But now, when you see him in his dotage, you do not pity him, since the pegs fall out,4 and the tone is no longer there, and the harmony is dissonant.5 But old as he is, he wanders about like Connas,6 having, it is true, a withered chaplet, but dying with thirst; who ought to drink in the Prytaneum on account of his former victories, and not to be doting, but in splendid apparel to be a spectator7 beside the statue of Bacchus. And remembering8 what bursts of displeasure and abuse of yours Crates endured, who gave you a breakfast at a slight expense, and sent you home, kneading the wittiest thoughts with a most clear-sounding voice. And yet he only just held out, at one time falling, at another not. Dreading this, he 9 always hesitated, and in addition to this used to say, a man should first be a rower ere he set his hand to the rudder, and then after this look out ahead, and observe the winds, and then pilot for himself. Therefore, on account of all these things, because he acted modestly, and did not foolishly rush in and talk nonsense, raise for him shouts of applause in abundance, and waft him a good Lenæan cheer with eleven oars,2 that your poet may depart in joy, having succeeded according to his wish, joyous with smiling counte nance.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.551"/>
          <p n="230">O Neptune, equestrian king, whom the clatter of brazen hoofed horses, and their neighing delights, and dark-beaked swift triremes manned with mercenaries,3 and the contest of youths who distinguish themselves in the chariot race, and of youths who are grievously unlucky, come hither to our chorus, O thou of the golden trident, 0 thou ruler of dolphins, thou who art worshipped at Sunium,4 0 god of Geræstus,5 child of Cronos, and most dear to Phormio,6 and to the Athenians at present above the other gods.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.575"/>
          <p n="231">We wish to eulogize our fathers, because they were men worthy of this land and of the peplus,7 who ever every where victorious in land-fights and in naval actions, adorned this city. For none of them ever at any time, when he saw his foes, counted them; but his spirit was immediately on its guard. And if, by chance, they fell upon their shoulders in any fight, they used to wipe this off, and then deny they had fallen, and go on wrestling again. And no one of those before this used when general to demand his maintenance, entreating Cleænetus.8 But now, unless they obtain precedence in seats, and their maintenance, they say they will not fight; while we think it right gratuitously and nobly to defend our city and our country's gods. And in addition, we ask nothing, except thus much only,—if ever there be peace, and we cease from our toils, do not grudge our being long-haired, or clean scraped.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.590"/>
          <p n="232">0 PaRas, guardian of the city, 0 thou that rulest over the most holy land, which excels all others in war and poets and in might, hither come, bringing with you Victory, our assistant in expeditions and battles, who is the companion of our choral songs, and sides with us against our enemies.2 Now, therefore, show thyself hither; for it behoveth thee by all means to grant victory to these men now if ever.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.598"/>
          <p n="233">We4 wish to praise what we are cognizant of respecting our horses. And worthy are they of being eulogized. For, in truth, they have gone through many affairs with us, both incursions and battles. But their exploits on land we do not so much admire, as when they leaped courageously into the transports,5 some of them having purchased drinking- cups,1 others garlic and onions. Then they took their oars,2 like us men, and laid to them, and shouted aloud for joy,— " Gee wo ho! 3 Who will lay to? We must take better hold. What are we about ? Won't you row, you Sampho ras ? "4 and leapt ashore at Corinth. Then the youngest set a digging beds with their hoofs, and went to fetch bed-clothes. And they ate crabs5 instead of Median grass, if any crept out of doors, even searching for them in the deep; so that Theo rus6 declared a Corinthian crab said—" It is dreadful, 0 Neptune, if neither in the deep,7 nor on land, nor in the sea, I shall be able to escape the Knights."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.606"/>
          <p n="234">CiO. 0 dearest and stoutest of men, how much anxiety in your absence have you given us ! And now, since you have come back safe, tell us how you contested the matter.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.606"/>
          <p n="235">S. S. What else,8 but that I became conqueror of the senate ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.611"/>
          <p n="236">CHO. Now, then, it is meet for all to shout for joy. 0 thou who speakest noble words, but hast done deeds still far superior to your words ! would that you would go over all the details clearly to me ! since methinks I would9 even travel a long journey, so as to hear.-Wherefore, my good sir, speak with confidence, since we all are delighted with you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.632"/>
          <p n="237">S. S. Well now, 'tis worth while to hear the circumstances : for I rushed directly after him from hence. He then within making words break forth, hurled like thunder, was hurling them at the Knights, playing the marvellous, blurting out precipices, and calling1 them conspirators most plausibly; while the whole Senate, listening to him, got crammed by him with false-orach, and looked mustard,2 and contracted their brows. And I, just when I perceived that they were approving 3 of his words, and deceived by his impositions " Come now, ye Lechers, and Impostors," said I, "and Boo bies, and mischievous Goblins, and God of Impudence, and thou Market-place, in which I was educated when a child, now give me impudence, and a ready tongue, and a shameless voice." As I was musing thus, a lewd fellow broke wind on my right; and I did reverence.4 Then with my buttocks I struck and broke the barriers, and gaping wide, shouted aloud, " 0 Senate, I bring you good news, and wish to announce the glad tidings first to you. For since what time the war broke out, I never at any time saw anchovies cheaper." Imme diately they made their faces quite calm, and then were for crowning me for the good news. And I having hastily in vented a secret plan, in order that they might purchase the anchovies in great numbers for an obol, told them to seize the dishes of the artificers.5 And they applauded vehemently, and gaped at me. So he, the Paphlagonian, having perceived it, and knowing in what speeches the Senate most delights, made a proposal: " Sirs, I now move, that on the occasion of the happy events which have been announced to us, we sacrifice a hundred oxen 6 to the goddess for the good news." Again the Senate inclined towards him. And I, just when I per ceived I was overcome by the ox-dung, overshot him with two hundred oxen; 1 and advised to make a vow to sacrifice a thousand goats to Diana on the morrow, if sprats went at a hundred for the obol. Again the Senate looked eagerly at me. And when he heard this, being struck with astonishment, babbled nonsense; and then the Prytanes and the Police be gan to drag him out, while they stood and wrangled about the anchovies. But he besought them " to wait a short time, in order that you may hear2 what the herald from Lacedæmon says, for he has come treating of peace." But they all cried out with one mouth,—" Now do they talk of peace ? Aye, poor fool, since they have heard that anchovies are cheap with us. We don't want peace; let the war go on." And they shouted that the Prytanes should dismiss the assembly. Then they leaped over the barriers in every direction. While I slipped out and bought up all the coriander-seed, and the leeks, as much as there was in the market: and then gave it gratis to them who were in want, as seasoning to the anchovies, and made presents of it. So they all praised me above measure, and caressed me to such a degree, that I have come, having gained over the whole senate for an obol-worth 3 of coriander- seed.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.640"/>
          <p n="238">CHO. Of a truth you have acted in every respect 4 as be comes a man favoured of fortune. The villain has found another adorned with much greater rascalities and artful de ceits and wily words. But take care that you contest what remains in the best manner possible; and you know long ago that you have us as your friendly allies.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.651"/>
          <p n="239">S. S. Well now, see! here comes 1 the Paphlagonian, pushing a heavy wave, and disturbing and confounding, as if, forsooth, he was going to swallow me up. A fig for his courage !2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.671"/>
          <p n="240">CLE. If I do 3 not destroy you, provided any of the same lies be in me, may I utterly fail in every way.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.680"/>
          <p n="241">S. S. I like your threats,4 laugh at your empty bluster, dance a fling, and cry cuckoo all round.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.688"/>
          <p n="242">CLE. By Ceres, if I do not eat you up out of this land, I will certainly never survive.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.688"/>
          <p n="243">S. S. " If you do not eat me up?" And neither will I, if I do not drink you up, and then gulp you down and burst after it myself.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.696"/>
          <p n="244">CLE. By the precedence which I gained at Pylos, I will destroy you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.696"/>
          <p n="245">S. S. " Precedence," quoth'a ! How I shall behold you 6 after your precedence a spectator on the last bench !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.696"/>
          <p n="246">CLE. By heaven, I will fasten you in the stocks !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.696"/>
          <p n="247">S. S. How choleric you are! Come, what shall I give you to eat? With what sauce would you like best to eat it? With a purse ?1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <p n="248">CLE. I will tear out your entrails with my nails. A-</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <p n="249">S. S. I will tear with my nails your maintenance in the Prytaneum.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <p n="250">CLE. I will drag you before Demus, that you may give me satisfaction.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <p n="251">S. S. And I will also drag you and calumniate you more.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.705"/>
          <p n="252">CLE. But he does not believe you at all, you wretch, while , I laugh at him as much as I please.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <p n="253">S. S. How completely you imagine Demus to be yours !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <p n="254">CLE. For I know with what pap he is fattened.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <p n="255">S. S. And then, like nurses,4 you feed him grudgingly. For you chew and put a little into his mouth, while you your self swallow down three times as much as he.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <p n="256">CLE. And, by Jove, by my dexterity I am able to make Demus fat or lean.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.713"/>
          <p n="257">S. S. And my posteriors are clever at this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="258">CLE. You shan't fancy, my good sir, you're going to in sult me in the Senate.6 Let us go to Demus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="259">S. S. There's nothing to hinder1 us. There, go, let nothing detain us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="260">CLE. O Demus ! come forth hither.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="261">S. S. O father, by Jupiter, pray come forth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.721"/>
          <p n="262">CLE. Come forth, 0 dearest little Demus, that you may know how I am wantonly insulted. [ They both go and knock at Demus' door.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="263">DEM. Who are those that are bawling ? Will you not depart from my door ? You have torn down my harvest wreath.2 Who's injuring you, my Paphlagonian ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="264">CLE. I am beat on your account by this fellow here, and by these striplings.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="265">CLE. Because I love you, Demus, and am your admirer.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.729"/>
          <p n="266">DEM. (turning to the Sausage-seller). Pray, who are you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.738"/>
          <p n="267">S. S. This man's rival in love, who have loved you this long time, and wished to do you a good turn, and so have many other gentlemen. But we are not able, on account ot this fellow. For you are like unto youths who have lovers: gentlemen you do not receive, but give yourself up to lamp sellers 3 and coolers and shoemakers and tanners.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.738"/>
          <p n="268">CLE. For I benefit the people.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.738"/>
          <p n="269">S. S. Say now, by doing what ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.738"/>
          <p n="270">CLE. Because I deceived the generals at Pylos and sailed thither and brought the Lacedæmonians.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.746"/>
          <p n="271">S. S. And I, while walking about,4 stole the pot from a workshop, while another was boiling it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.746"/>
          <p n="272">CLE. Well now, Demus, convene an assembly forthwith, in order that you may know which of us two is better inclined to you, and decide between us, that you may love this one.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.746"/>
          <p n="273">S. S. Yes, yes, do decide between us, pray ! but not in the Pnyx.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.746"/>
          <p n="274">DEM. I can't sit in any other place. But you must come forwards to the Pnyx.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.746"/>
          <p n="275">S. S. Ah me, miserable man, how I am undone! for the old fellow, when at home, is the shrewdest of men, but when he takes his seat upon this here stone, he gapes 1 as if he were stringing figs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.756"/>
          <p n="276">CHO. Now it behoves you to let out every rope,2 and to carry an impetuous spirit and arguments, admitting no escape, wherewith you shall overcome him: for the man is crafty, and devises efficient contrivances out of impracticable ones.3 Wherefore take care that you go forth vehement and fresh4 against the man. But be on your guard, and ere he comes up to you, do you first raise aloft5 your dolphins, and put forward your pinnace.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.756"/>
          <p n="277">CLE. I pray to our mistress Minerva, who rules over our city, that, if I am the best man towards the Athenian people, next to Lysicles,6 and Cynna, and Salabaccho, I may, as now, dine in the Prytaneum, without having done any thing for it. But if I hate you, and do not fight for you, singly standing in the gap, may I perish, and be sawn in two, and cut up into yoke-straps.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.767"/>
          <p n="278">S. S. And may I, Demus, if I do not love you, and do not admire you, be cut up and cooked in mince-meat; and if you do not put faith in this, may I be grated down upon this dresser in an olio with cheese, and with the flesh-hook may I be dragged to the Ceramicus by my testicles.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.767"/>
          <p n="279">CLE. Why, how can there be a citizen, Demus, who loves you more than I do ? who in the first place, when I was a senator, collected very much money in the treasury, by tor turing some, strangling others, and begging of others; not caring for any private man, provided I gratified you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.777"/>
          <p n="280">S. S. This, Demus, is no way grand; for I will do this to you. For I will snatch away and serve up to you other peo ple's loaves.2 But I will first teach you this very thing, that he neither loves you, nor is well-disposed towards you, except on account of this very thing, that he enjoys your fire-side. For he does not care about your sitting so uncomfortably upon the rocks, who fought to the death with the Persians at Ma rathon for our country, and when victorious, permitted us to bepraise it mightily.3 Not like me, who have sewed and brought you this cushion. Come, raise yourself, and then sit down at your ease, that you may not gall that which fought at Salamis.4 Slips a soft cushion under Demus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.786"/>
          <p n="281">DEM. Man, who are you ? Are you a son of those well- known5 descendants of Harmodius ! Certainly, Indeed, this deed of yours is truly noble and patriotic.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.786"/>
          <p n="282">CLE. From what petty bits of flattery have you become well-disposed towards him !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.786"/>
          <p n="283">S. S. For you also caught him with baits much less than these.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.786"/>
          <p n="284">CLE. Well now, I am willing to wager my head, if any where there bath appeared a man who fights more for the people, or loves you more than I.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.786"/>
          <p n="285">S. S. Why, how love you him? who, though you see him dwelling for the eighth year 1 in the casks and crannies and little turrets, do not pity him, but shut him in and plunder his hive. And when Archeptolemus2 was offering peace, yon scattered it abroad; and you drive away the embassies from the city, slapping them on the buttocks, who make pro posals of peace.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.797"/>
          <p n="286">CLE. Aye, that he may rule over all the Greeks ; for it is in the oracles, " that this man must some time or other act the Heliast in Arcadia at3 five obols a day, if he bide his time." At all events, I will nourish and tend him, finding out by fair means or foul, whence he shall receive the three obols.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.797"/>
          <p n="287">S. S, Not taking thought, by Jove, that he may rule over Arcadia, but that -you may plunder the more, and receive bribes from the cities; and that Demus, by reason of the war and the mist, may not observe your knavish tricks,4. but through necessity, at the same time, and need, and pay, may gape at you. But if ever he return to the country and spend his time in peace,5 and eat his toasted groats and re gain his courage, and come to a conversation with oil-cake, he will perceive what blessings you swindled him out of by your system of pay; and then he will come against you fierce and rough, searching for a pebble against you. Of which being aware, you impose upon him, and cheat6 him by dreams about yourself.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.805"/>
          <p n="288">CLE. Is it not then, pray, a shameful thing that you should say this of me, and calumniate me before the Athenians and Demus, who have already, by Ceres, done far more good ser vices to the state than Themistocles ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.813"/>
          <p n="289">S. S. “ 0 city of Argos, hear what he says.”1 Do you match yourself with Themistocles ? who made our city full, when he found it up to the brim, and in addition to this kneaded up the Piræus beside for it while it was at break fast,2 and having taken away nothing of the old, set before it new fishes.—But you sought to make the Athenians citizens of a petty town,3 by dividing the town 4 with a wall, and uttering oracles, you who match yourself with Themistocles! And he is an exile from his country, while you wipe your hands on cakes of fine barley.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="290">CLE. Is it not then a shameful thing, 0 Demus, that I should be called these names by this fellow, because I love you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="291">DEM. Stop, stop,6 you fellow, and don't talk Billingsgate. For much too long a time and even now have you been acting underhand without my knowing it.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="292">S. S. He is a most abominable fellow, my little Demus, and one who commits very many knavish tricks, whenever you yawn; 1 and he crops the stalks of those under account and swallows them down, and with both hands ladles out the public money.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.822"/>
          <p n="293">CLE. You shall not escape with impunity, but I will con vict you of stealing thirty thousand drachmæ.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.830"/>
          <p n="294">S. S. Why do you make much ado about nothing, and make a splash, you who are most abominable towards the Athenian people?2 And, by Ceres, I will prove,3 or may I not live, that you have received as a bribe more than forty minæ from Mitylene.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.841"/>
          <p n="295">CHO. 0 thou who hast appeared the greatest advantage to all men !4 I envy you for your fluency of speech ; for if you shall attack him in this way, you will be the greatest of the Greeks, and alone will bear sway in the city, and rule over the allies, having a trident, shaking and disturbing,5 with which you will make much money. And do not let the man go, since he has given you a hold, for you will easily make an end of him, with such sides as yours.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.841"/>
          <p n="296">CLE. These matters, good sirs, are not yet come to this, by Neptune; for I have wrought such a work, so as to curb my enemies every one,6 so long as any thing is left of the bucklers captured at Pylos.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.850"/>
          <p n="297">S. S. Stop at your bucklers, for you have given me a handle. For you ought not, if indeed you love the people, purposely to have let them be dedicated together with the handles. But this, Demus, is a device, that, if you wish to punish this fellow here, it may not be in your power j for you see what a troop of young tanners are with him ; and around these dwell sellers of honey and sellers of cheese. Now this body is leagued together; so that if you were to snort with anger, and look ostracism,1 they would pull down the buck lers by night, and run and seize the entrances for importing your barley.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.858"/>
          <p n="298">DEM. Ah me, miserable man ! Why, have they handles ? You rascal, how long a time you have been cheating me, deluding me in such a manner !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.858"/>
          <p n="299">CLE. My good sir, be not led3 away by every speaker, nor think that you will ever find a better friend than I, who with my single hand put down the conspirators. And no con spiracy arises in the city without my perceiving it, but I bawl out that instant.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.866"/>
          <p n="300">S. S. For you are circumstanced like those who fish for eels.4 When the lake is still, they catch nothing ; but if they stir the mud up and down, they take. And you catch, if your disturb the city. But just answer me this single question : though you sell so many hides, have you ever5 given to this man here a sole from your private stock for his slippers, you who profess to love him ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.866"/>
          <p n="301">DEM. Certainly not, by Apollo.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.866"/>
          <p n="302">S. S. Then have you perceived, pray, what sort of a fel low he is ? But I have bought this pair of shoes for you, and give them you to wear. [Gives him a pair of shoes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.866"/>
          <p n="303">DEM. I j udge you to be the best man towards the people of all I know, and very well disposed towards the city, and to wards my toes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.876"/>
          <p n="304">CLE. Is it not then, pray, a shameful thing that slippers should have so much power, and that you should have no re collection of all the kind offices I have done you ? who put a stop to the lewd people, having utterly destroyed Gryttus.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.876"/>
          <p n="305">S. S. Is it not then, pray, a shameful thing that you should watch them so,' and put a stop to the lewd people ? It must be that through envy you stopped them, lest they might be come orators. And though you saw this man without a tunic at his time of life, you never at any time deemed Demus worthy of a sleeved-coat, though it were winter. But I pre sent you with this one here. [ Gives him a coat.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.884"/>
          <p n="306">DEM. Themistocles never once thought of such a device. And yet that device of his, too, was a clever one, his Piræus. Yet, however, it does not appear to me to be a greater con trivance than the coat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.884"/>
          <p n="307">CLE. Ah me, miserable man ! with what jackanape's tricks you harass me !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.884"/>
          <p n="308">S. S. Not so; but as is the case with a man in liquor when nature calls, I am using your manners2 as I would your slippers.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.884"/>
          <p n="309">CLE. You shall not surpass me in flattery, for I will put this on him besides. [Turning to the Sausage-seller.] A plague take you, you rascal!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.892"/>
          <p n="310">DEM. Bah ! will you not be gone, with a plague to you ? smelling most abominably of the tan-yard.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.892"/>
          <p n="311">S. S. And on purpose, too, was he for putting this around you, that he may smother you. And before this he plotted against you. Do you know that stalk of silphium,l which became so cheap ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.892"/>
          <p n="312">DEM. To be sure I know.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.892"/>
          <p n="313">S. S. On purpose this fellow was anxious for it to be cheap, that you might buy and eat, and then the dicasts might kill each other2 in the Heliæa with fizzling.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="314">DEM. By Neptune, a stinkard also told this to me.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="315">S. S. Is it not the case that ye then became red with blushes with fizzling ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="316">DEM. Aye, by Jove, this device was one of Pyrrandrus's.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="317">CLE. With what ribaldry you worry met you villain !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="318">S. S. For the goddess bade me conquer you with quackery.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.900"/>
          <p n="319">CLE. But you shall not conquer me. For I promise, 0 Demus, to supply you with a bowl of pay to gulp down,4 for doing nothing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.908"/>
          <p n="320">S. S. But I give you a gallipot and ointment, to smear over the slight sores on your shins. [Presents them.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.908"/>
          <p n="321">CLE. I will pluck out your grey hairs and make you a young man.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.908"/>
          <p n="322">S. S. (offering a hare’s scut). There, take a hare’s scut5 to wipe your two little eyes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.908"/>
          <p n="323">CLE. After you have blown your nose, Demus, wipe your fingers upon my head.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.917"/>
          <p n="324">S. S. Nay rather, upon mine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.917"/>
          <p n="325">CLE. Nay rather, upon mine. [Demus bestows his dirty preference on the Sausage-seller.] I will6 cause you to be a trierarch expending your own money, with an old vessel, upon which you will never cease spending money or making repairs. And I will contrive that you get a rotten sail.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.917"/>
          <p n="326">CiO. The man is bubbling up. Stop, stop boiling over. We must drag from beneath him some of the firebrands, and skim off some of the threats with this here ladle.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.925"/>
          <p n="327">CLE. You shall give me proper satisfaction,2 being pressed down by my taxes, for I will exert myself that you may be enrolled among the rich.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.925"/>
          <p n="328">S. S. I will utter no threats; but I wish you the fol lowing: that your frying-pan of cuttle-fish may stand over the fire frizzling, and that you, about to move a decree con cerning the Milesians,4 and to gain a talent if you effect your object, may hasten to fill yourself with the5 cuttle-fish before you go to the assembly; and then, before you've eaten them, may a man come to fetch you, and may you, wishing to get the talent, be choked with eating.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.925"/>
          <p n="329">CHO. Capital! by Jove! by Apollo! by Cares!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.942"/>
          <p n="330">DEM. To me also he appears to be manifestly in other re spects, too, a good citizen, such as no man has ever been for a long time towards the three-halfpenny mobocracy.6 While you, Paphlagonian, who say you love me, have garlicked me.1 And now give me back my ring, as you shall no longer be my steward.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.942"/>
          <p n="331">OLE. Take it: but know thus much, that if you will not permit me to be overseer, some other again more villanous than I will appear.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="332">DEM. It is not possible that this ring is mine. At all events, the device appears different, unless2 I do not see dis tinctly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="333">S. S. Come, let me see. What was your device ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="334">DEM. A roasted olio of bull's fat.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="335">S. S. There is not this in it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="336">DEM. Not the olio? What then ?4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.951"/>
          <p n="337">S. S. A gaping cormorant haranguing upon a rock.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="338">DEM. Alas, miserable man !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="339">S. S. What is the matter ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="340">DEM. Take it out of the way: he had not mine, but that of Cleonymus.6 But do you receive this from me, and be my steward.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="341">CLE. Not yet, pray, 0 master, I entreat you, until you hear my oracles.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="342">S. S. And mine then.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.959"/>
          <p n="343">CLE. But if you accede to this fellow, you must become a mere hide.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="344">S. S. And if to this man, you must become completely circumcised.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="345">CLE. But mine say that you must rule over8 every country, crowned with roses.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.967"/>
          <p n="346">S. S. While mine, on the other hand, say, that with an embroidered purple robe and a diadem you shall pursue in a chariot of gold Smicythe 1 and her husband.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="347">DEM. Well now, go and bring them, that this 2 man here may hear them.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="348">DEM. And do you then bring yours.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="349">S. S. Very well, by Jove : there's nothing to hinder you.4 [Cleon and the S. S. hurry out.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="350">CHO. Most sweet will be the light of day to all those pre. sent, and to those who are5 coming, if Cleon perish. And yet I heard some very crabbed6 old fellows disputing in the Law Exchange,7 that if this fellow had not become great in the state, there would not have been two useful utensils, a pestle8 or a ladle. But this also I wonder at in his swinish musical taste; for the boys who went to school with him say that he constantly adapted his lyre to the Dorian9 mode alone, and was not willing to learn any other. And then, that the harp- master,10 being enraged, gave orders to take him away, " since this youth is not able to learn any mode, except the Bribery mode." [Re-enter Cleon and S. S., both heavily laden with papers. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.973"/>
          <p n="351">CLE. There, see ! and yet I bring not all out!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="352">S. S. Ah me, how I want to ease myself, and yet I bring not all out.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="353">DEM. What are these ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="354">CLE. Do you wonder ? By Jove, I have still a chest full.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="355">S. S. And I have an upper-room and two out-houses full.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="356">DEM. Come, let me see : why, whose in the world are the oracles ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.985"/>
          <p n="357">CLE. Mine are Bacis's.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="358">DEM. And whose are yours ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="359">S. S. Glanis's, elder brother of Bacis.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="360">DEM. What are they about ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="361">CLE. About Athens, about Pylos, about you, about me, about every thing.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="362">DEM. And what are yours about ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.997"/>
          <p n="363">S. S. About Athens, about lentil-broth, about the Lace dæmonians, about fresh mackerel, about those who measure their barley unfairly in the market-place, about you, about me.—May this here fellow tumble and tread on his nose !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1005"/>
          <p n="364">DEM. Come now, see that you read them to me, and that notable2 one about me, with which I am delighted, “ That I shall become an eagle3 in the clouds."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1005"/>
          <p n="365">CLE. Hear now, and give me your attention. [Unrolls his papers.]. “ Son of Erectheus, take heed of the way of the oracles,4 which Apollo uttered for you from the sanctuary by means of highly-prized tripods. He ordered you to preserve the sacred dog5 with jagged teeth, who by snarling in your defence and barking dreadfully in your behalf, will provide you pay; and if he do not this, he will perish. For many daws, through hatred, croak at him."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1005"/>
          <p n="366">DEM. By Ceres, I do not know what these things mean. For what has Erectheus1 to do with jackdaws and a dog ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1014"/>
          <p n="367">CLE. I am the do-, for I howl in your defence, and Phœbus ordered you to preserve me, your dog.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1022"/>
          <p n="368">S. S. The oracle does not say this, but this here dog gnaws at the oracles, as he does your door,. For I have it correctly about this dog.2</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1030"/>
          <p n="369">DEM. Read it, then: but first I'll take a stone, lest the oracle about the dog bite me.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1030"/>
          <p n="370">S. S. " Beware, son of Erectheus, of the kidnapping dog Cerberus, who, fawning upon you with his tail, watching when you are dining, will consume your victuals, whenever you gape any other way: and he will often go secretly into your kitchen4 by night, like a dog, and lick clean your plates and islands."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1030"/>
          <p n="371">DEM. Far better, 0 Glanis, by Neptune!5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1030"/>
          <p n="372">CLE. Good sir, hear, and then decide:—“ There is a wo man, and she shall bring forth a lion in sacred Athens, who in behalf of the people shall fight with many gnats, as if de fending6 his whelps. Him do thou guard, having made a wooden wall and iron towers."7 Do you know what these mean ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1041"/>
          <p n="373">DEM. By Apollo, not I.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1041"/>
          <p n="374">CLE. The god clearly ordered you to preserve me. For I am in the place of the lion to you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1041"/>
          <p n="375">DEM. Why, how have you become " lion-like ” I without my knowing it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1041"/>
          <p n="376">S. S. One part of the oracles he purposely does not inform you of, which is2 the only iron wall and wood wherein Loxias ordered you to keep this fellow.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1041"/>
          <p n="377">DEM. How then did the god declare this ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1049"/>
          <p n="378">S. S. He bade you bind this fellow here in the five-holed pillory.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1049"/>
          <p n="379">DEM. These4 oracles seem to me soon about to be accom plished.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1049"/>
          <p n="380">CLE. Do not believe him; for envious crows croak at me. But love the hawk, remembering him in your mind, who bound and brought you the young ravens of the Lacedæ monians.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1049"/>
          <p n="381">S. S. Assuredly the Paphlagonian hazarded this when he was drunk.6 0 foolish son of Cecrops, why do you consider this deed a great one ? “ Even a woman can bear a burden, when a man may put it upon her;" but she cannot fight, for she would 7 be in a fright if she were to fight.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1057"/>
          <p n="382">CLE. But take heed of this—a Pylos in front of a Pylos, which he declared to you. " There is a Pylos in front of a Pylos."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1057"/>
          <p n="383">DEM. What does this mean, " in front of a Pylos ?”8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1057"/>
          <p n="384">S. S. He says he will seize the bathing-tubs in the bath.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1057"/>
          <p n="385">DEM. And I shall be to-day unwashed, for this fellow has stolen away our bathing-tubs.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1057"/>
          <p n="386">S. S. But this oracle here is about our navy, to which you must by all means give your attention.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1065"/>
          <p n="387">DEM. I attend: but do you read, how, in the first place, their pay shall he paid to my sailors.1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1065"/>
          <p n="388">S. S. " Son of Ægens, beware of the dog-fox, lest it de ceive you, biting2 in secret, swift of foot, the crafty thief, cunning." Do you know what this is ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1065"/>
          <p n="389">DEM. Philostratus the dog-fox.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1065"/>
          <p n="390">S. S. He does not say this; but this fellow here is always asking for swift ships to levy tribute: these Loxias forbids you to 4 grant him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="391">DEM. How, pray, is a trireme a dog-fox ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="392">S. S. How ? Because your trireme and your dog are swift.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="393">DEM. How, then, was " fox " added to " clog ?"</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="394">S. S. He compared the soldiers to little foxes,5 because they eat the clusters of grapes in the farms.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="395">DEM. Well, where is the pay for these little foxes ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1073"/>
          <p n="396">S. S. I will supply it, and that too within three days.6 But further, hearken to this oracle, in which the son of Latona ordered you to beware of Cyllene,7 lest she deceive you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1082"/>
          <p n="397">S. S. He rightly represented this fellow's band as a “Cyl lene," because he says " put into ray bent hand.” 8</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1082"/>
          <p n="398">CLE. You 1 do not understand it rightly ; for in Cyllene Phœbus rightly hinted at the hand of Diopithes.2 But in deed 3 I have a winged oracle about you, " that you become an eagle, and rule over every land."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1082"/>
          <p n="399">S. S. For I also have one, which says you shall rule both over the land and the Red Sea too, and that you shall give judgment at Ecbatana, licking up seed-cakes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1090"/>
          <p n="400">CLE. But I have seen a vision, and the goddess herself ap peared to me to pour health and wealth over the people with a ladle.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1098"/>
          <p n="401">S. S. Yes, by Jove, for I also have seen one; and the god dess herself appeared to me to come from the citadel, and an owl to be sitting upon her, and then to pour upon each head with a bucket-ambrosia over thee-over this fellow garlick pickle.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1098"/>
          <p n="402">DEM. Huzza! huzza! No one then, it appears, is wiser than Glanis.5 Accordingly, now I here commit myself to you, to guide me in my dotage and educate me afresh.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1098"/>
          <p n="403">CLE. Kay, not yet, I beseech you, but stop, since I will pro vide you with barley and sustenance every day.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1098"/>
          <p n="404">DEM. I cannot bear to hear of barley : often have I been deceived by you and Thuphanes.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="405">CLE. But I will forthwith provide you with barley-meal ready prepared.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="406">S. S. And I barley-scones 7 thoroughly kneaded, and fishes which have been roasted. Do nothing else except eat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="407">DEM. Make haste, then, with what ye are going to do ; for I will deliver the reins of the Pnyx to him, whichever of you, again, confers more benefits upon me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="408">CLE. I will run in first.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1107"/>
          <p n="409">S. S. Certainly not, but I will. [ Cleon and the S. S. run off.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1111"/>
          <p n="410">CHO. 0 Demus, you possess a fine sovereignty, when all men dread you as a tqgaol Yet you are easily led by the nose, and you delight in being flattered1 and cajoled, and gape open-mouthed at whoever happens to be2 speaking, and your mind, though present, is abroad.3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1121"/>
          <p n="411">DEM. There is no sense in your locks,4 when you think me not to be in my sound senses. But I drivel thus on purpose. For I myself delight to cry for drink every day, and wish to bring up a5 thievish minister, and him, when he is glutted, I take up and strike.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1129"/>
          <p n="412">CHO. And in this way you would be doing well, if, as you say, very great prudence is in this habit of yours, if you pur posely bring up these in the Pnyx like public victims, and then, when you have no food, sacrifice and feast upon one of these, whichever 6 is fat.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1141"/>
          <p n="413">DEM. Observe me, if I cleverly overreach them, those who fancy they are wise, and that they humbug me. For I am al ways watching them while stealing, pretending not to see them; and then I compel them to disgorge again whatever they steal from me, putting the ballot-box like a probe down their throats. [ Clean and the S. S. return.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1141"/>
          <p n="414">CLE. Begone to the devil out of the way !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1141"/>
          <p n="415">S. S. Do you, you pestilent fellow !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1141"/>
          <p n="416">CLE. 0 Demus, in truth I have been sitting ready long, long ago, wishing to benefit you. 1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="417">S. S. And I ten times as long ago,2 and twelve times as long ago, and a thousand times as long ago, and very long ago, long ago, long ago.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="418">DEM. And I with waiting for you have been detesting you both thirty thousand times as long ago, and very long ago, long ago, long ago.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="419">S. S. Do you know, then, what you are to do ?3</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="420">DEll. If I do not, you shall tell me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="421">S. S. Start me and this fellow here from the starting-post, that we may confer favours on you on equal terms.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1151"/>
          <p n="422">DEM. I must do so. Begone !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <p n="423">S. S. I don't suffer bim to cut in before me. [Both run off.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <p n="424">DEM. Well, by Jove, I shall be mightily blest to-day by ray lovers, or I shall grow. conceited. [Re-enter Cleon and S. S.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <p n="425">CLE. You see, I am the first to bring out a seat for you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <p n="426">S. S. Yet not a table ;5 but I am days and days before you. [Demus sits down.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1159"/>
          <p n="427">CLE. See ! I am bringing you this barley-scone kneaded from the barley of Pylos.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="428">S. S. And I bread-spoons scooped out by the goddess with her ivory hand.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="429">DEM. (taking one up). What 6 a huge finger, then, you have, O mistress !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="430">CLE. And I pea-soup of a good colour and excellent; and Pallas fighting at the gates 1 stirred it up.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="431">S. S. Evidently the goddess watches over you, Demus, and now she holds over you a pot full of broth.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1168"/>
          <p n="432">DEM. Do you think this city could any longer be governed, if she did not evidently hold her pot 2 over us ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="433">CLE. The scarer of hosts presented you with this slice of salt-fish.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="434">S. S. And the daughter of a strong father sent you flesh boiled with broth,3 and a slice of tripe, and belly, and paunch.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="435">DEM. She did well in remembering the Peplus.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="436">CLE. She of the Gorgon crest bade you eat some of this pancake, that we may row our vessels well.5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="437">S. S. Take now these also. [Hands him the tripe.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1177"/>
          <p n="438">DEM. And what am I to do with these guts ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="439">S. S. The goddess sent them you on purpose as belly-timber for the triremes;6 for she manifestly watches over the navy. Take and drink a mixture of. three parts water and two parts wine. [He hands him a bowl of wine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="440">DEM. (drinks). 0 Jupiter, how sweet, and how well it bears the three!</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="441">S. S. For Tritogenia mixed it three to two.7</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="442">CLE. Accept now from me a slice of rich'cheese-cake.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="443">S. S. But from me the wholes of this here cheese-cake.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1185"/>
          <p n="444">CLE. (running to his basket). Well, you will have no means of giving1 hare's flesh ; but I shall.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="445">S. S. Ah me ! whence shall I have hare's flesh ? Soul of mine, now devise some low trick !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="446">CLE. (holding up the basket). Do you see this, you poor wretch ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="447">S. S. I care little. For, see ! yonder2 people are coming to me !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="448">S. S. Ambassadors with purses of money.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="449">CLE. (looking round). Where ? where ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1193"/>
          <p n="450">S. S. What's that to you? Won't you let the foreigners alone? [Steals the hare's flesh.] My little Demus, do you see the hare's flesh which I am bringing to you ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="451">CLE. Ah me, miserable! Unjustly have you filched away what was mine.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="452">S. S. Aye, by Neptune,3 for you also did so to the prison ers at Pylos.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="453">DEM. (laughing). Tell me, I entreat you; how did you contrive to steal it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="454">S. S. The device was the goddess's—the theft mine.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="455">CLE. But I ran the hazard.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1201"/>
          <p n="456">S. S. And I roasted it.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1209"/>
          <p n="457">DEM. (to Cleon). Be off! For the thanks belong to him who served it up.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1209"/>
          <p n="458">CLE. Ah me,6 unhappy! I shall be surpassed in impu dence.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1209"/>
          <p n="459">S. S. Why do you not decide, Demus, which of us two is the better man towards you and towards your belly ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1209"/>
          <p n="460">DEM. By the use of what proof, pray, shall I appear to the audience to decide between you wisely ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1209"/>
          <p n="461">S. S. I will tell you : go and seize upon my chest in silence, and examine what there is in it, and that of the Paphlago nian; and doubtless,you'll judge rightly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1217"/>
          <p n="462">DEM. Come, let me see; what, then, is there in it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1217"/>
          <p n="463">S. S. (opening the chest). Do you not see that it is empty, dear little papa ? for I have set all before you.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1217"/>
          <p n="464">DEM. This chest is a friend of the people.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1217"/>
          <p n="465">S. S. At any rate, walk this way'also to that of the Paph lagonian. [ Opens Cleon's chest.] Do you see these ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1217"/>
          <p n="466">DEAL. Ah me, the number 1 of good things with which it is filled ! What a prodigious cheese-cake he has stowed away! while he cut off and gave me only this tiny bit.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1225"/>
          <p n="467">S. S. Such things, however, he used to do aforetime also; he used to offer you a little of what he received, but used to set before himself the greater part.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1225"/>
          <p n="468">DEM. 0 abominable fellow! did you deceive me then, in stealing these? " while I crowned you and2 made you pre sents."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1225"/>
          <p n="469">CLE. I stole for the good of the stated</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1225"/>
          <p n="470">DEM. Quickly lay down the chaplet, that I may put it upon this man.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="471">S. S. Lay it down quickly, you knave !4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="472">CLE. Certainly not, since I have a Pythian oracle, which mentions by whom alone I must be conquered.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="473">S. S. Aye, which mentions my name, and very distinctly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="474">CLE. Well now, I wish to examine you by a test, if in any wise you shall agree5 with the oracles of the god. And first I will inquire of you thus much : To what teacher's school did you go when a child ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="475">S. S. I was taught with cuffs in the singeing-pits.6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1234"/>
          <p n="476">CLE. How say you? How7 the oracle affects my soul! Well-What style of wrestling did you learn in the school of the gymnastic-master ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="477">S. S. When stealing,1 to forswear and look them in the face.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="478">CLE. " 0 Phœbus,2 Lycian Apollo, what in the world will you do to me ?" W hat trade had you when come to man's estate ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="479">S. S. I sold sausages, and also3 wenched a little.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="480">CLE. Ah me, unhappy ! " No longer am I aught. Very slender is the hope upon which we ride."4 And tell me thus much: did you sell sausages, pray, in the market-place, or at the gates ? 5</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1242"/>
          <p n="481">S. S. At the gates, where the dried fish is sold.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1250"/>
          <p n="482">CLE. Ah me ! the oracle of the god is accomplished ! " Roll within this wretched man."6 My chaplet, fare thee well! albeit7 I leave thee unwillingly. Some other one will take and possess thee: a greater thief he cannot be ; more fortunate, perhaps, he may.8 [Exit Cleon.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1250"/>
          <p n="483">S. S. Hellenic Jove ! thine is the prize of victory.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1250"/>
          <p n="484">DEMOSTH. Oh hail, thou splendidly victorious! and remem ber that by my means you have become a man. And I ask you a trifling favour, that I may be your Phanus, secretary of indictments.9</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1250"/>
          <p n="485">DEM. Tell me, what is your name ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1258"/>
          <p n="486">S. S. Agoracritus, for I was maintained by litigation in the market-place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1258"/>
          <p n="487">DEM. Then I commit myself to Agoracritus, and deliver up this here Paphlagonian.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1258"/>
          <p n="488">AGOR. Well now, Demus, I will tend you excellently, so that you confess that you have seen no man better than me for the city of the Gapenians.1 [Exeunt Demus and Agora critus.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1264"/>
          <p n="489">CHO. What is more noble for people beginning, or for peo ple concluding, than to sing of the drivers of swift steeds,2- and with willing heart to give no offence to Lysistratus, or Thumantis the homeless? For this fellow, 0 dear Apollo, ever hungers, touching thy quiver with copious tears at divine Delphi, so as not to be miserably poor.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1276"/>
          <p n="490">To revile the wicked is in no wise invidious ; but it is an honour to the good, if any consider3 rightly. If there fore the man, who must hear much abuse from me, had been known himself, I would not make mention of a man my friend.4 But now every one knows5 Arignotus, who knows either white, or the Orthian strain. He has, then, a brother, not akin to him in disposition, the vile Ariphrades.1 But he even prefers this vileness. Now he is not only vilefor I should not even have heard of him, if he had been only this, nor yet most villanous, but he has also invented something besides.2 For he employs himself in committing unheard-of obscenities, composing Polymnestean poems and associating with Oionichus.3 Whoever, therefore, does not detest such a fellow exceedingly, shall never drink out of the same cup with us.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1284"/>
          <p n="491">Of a truth 4 I have oftentimes been engaged in nightly meditations, and have sought whence in the world Cleonymus feeds poorly. For they say that he,5 feeding on the property of the rich, would not come forth from the cupboard; while the others nevertheless used6 to entreat him: " Come, lord, by thy knees, come forth and pardon the table."</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1295"/>
          <p n="492">They say that the triremes came together for a conference with each other, and that one of them said, who was more advanced in years, " Have ye not heard, ye virgins, these doings in the city ? They say that a certain person requires a hundred of us for Chalcedon, a rascally citizen, sour-tem pered7 Hyperbolus." And they say that this appeared to the others to be shameful and not to be borne, and that one of them said, who had not come nigh man : " Thou averter of ill, he shall certainly never rule over me; but if I must, I will here grow old, rotted by wood-worms. Neither shall he rule over Nauphante, daughter of Nauson; certainly not, ye gods, if indeed I also was constructed of fir and timbers ! But if this content the Athenians, I move that we sail to the Theseum,l or to the august goddesses,2 and sit as suppliants. For he shall not laugh at the city by being our commander. Nay, let him sail alone by himself to the crows, if he will, having launched the trays in which he used to sell his lamps. [Re- enter Agoracritus. ]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1305"/>
          <p n="493">AGOR. You must use words of good omen, and close the mouth, and abstain from evidence, and shut up the law-courts, in which this city delights; and the audience must chaunt the paean at our new successes.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1305"/>
          <p n="494">CHO. 0 thou light of sacred Athens, and protector of the islands, with what good news have you come, at which3 we should fill the streets with the steam of burnt sacrifice ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1305"/>
          <p n="495">AGOR. I have boiled down 4 your Demus, and made him beautiful from being ugly.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1316"/>
          <p n="496">CiO. Why, where is he now, 0 thou5 who inventest won drous devices ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1316"/>
          <p n="497">AGOR. He is dwelling in the violet-crowned,6 the ancient Athens.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1316"/>
          <p n="498">CHO. Would we could see him !7 What sort of a dress has he ? What sort of a person has he become ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1316"/>
          <p n="499">AGOR. Such as when he used to mess with Aristides and Miltiades in olden time. Ye shall see him, for now there is a noise of the Propylaea getting opened. But shout aloud at the appearance of the ancient Athens, both wondrous, and much sung of, where the illustrious Demus dwells.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1324"/>
          <p n="500">CiO. 0 sleek,' and violet-crowned, and much to be envied Athens ! show to us the monarch of Greece, and of this land. [Here the folding-doors of the Acropolis are thrown open, and Demus is seen sitting upon a throne, gorgeously dressed in the fashion of the Marathonian times, and in all the bloom of youth.]</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1324"/>
          <p n="501">AGOR. Lo! there he is for you to behold, wearing the cicada,2 conspicuous in his olden garb, not smelling of shells,3 but of peace, anointed with myrrh.4</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1324"/>
          <p n="502">CHO. Hail, thou king of the Grecians! We also rejoice with thee ; for thou farest in a manner worthy of the city and of the trophy at Marathon.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1324"/>
          <p n="503">DEM. 0 dearest of men, come hither, Agoracritus ! How much good you have done me by having boiled me down !</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1335"/>
          <p n="504">AGOR. I? But, my good friend, you do not know what sort of a person you were before, nor what you did : for other wise you would consider me a god.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1335"/>
          <p n="505">DEM. What 5 did I before this, and what sort of a man was I ? tell me.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1335"/>
          <p n="506">AGOR. In the first place, whenever any one said in the as sembly, " Demus, I am your lover, and I love you, and care for you, and alone 1 provide for you ;" whenever any one used these preambles, you used to clap your wings and crow, and hold your head high.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1335"/>
          <p n="507">AGOR. And then in return for this, he cheated you and went off.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1345"/>
          <p n="508">DEM. What do you say ? Did they treat me thus, and I not perceive it ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1345"/>
          <p n="509">AGOR. Aye, by Jove, and your ears used to be opening and shutting again, just like a parasol.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1345"/>
          <p n="510">DEM. Had I become so senseless and doting ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1345"/>
          <p n="511">AGOR. And, by Jove, if two orators2 were speaking, the one recommending to build ships of war, the other, on the contrary, to spend this in paying the dicasts, the one who spoke of the pay, having outstripped the one who spoke of the triremes, used to go his way.3 Hollo you ! Why do you hang down your head ? Will you not remain in your place ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1345"/>
          <p n="512">DEM. In truth I am ashamed at my former faults.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1354"/>
          <p n="513">AGOR. You were not to blame for this,-do not be con cerned,—but those who deceived you in this. But4 now tell me: if any lick-spittle advocate should say, " You dicasts have no maintenance, if you will not decide against this suit." Tell me ; what will you do to this advocate ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1362"/>
          <p n="514">DEM. I will raise him aloft and cast him into the Pit, having hung Hyperbolus about his neck.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1362"/>
          <p n="515">AGOR. This now you speak rightly and prudently.' But in other respects, come, let me see, tell me how you will conduct the government.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1362"/>
          <p n="516">DEM. In the first place, as many as row ships of war, to these I will pay their wages in full when they come into port.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1362"/>
          <p n="517">AGOR. You 2 have bestowed a favour on many smooth-worn bottoms.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1362"/>
          <p n="518">DEM. Secondly, no hoplite who has been enrolled in the list for service, shall be transferred to another list, through inter est, but shall remain enrolled 3 as he was at first.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1372"/>
          <p n="519">AGOR. This has stung Cleonymus' buckler.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1372"/>
          <p n="520">DEM. Nor shall any beardless fellow lounge in the market- place.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1372"/>
          <p n="521">AGOR. Where then shall Clisthenes 4 and Strato lounge ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1372"/>
          <p n="522">DEM. I mean these striplings in the perfume-market, who sit and chatter in this wise :—" Phaeax5 is a clever fellow, and has learnt shrewdly. For he is cogent, and conclusive, and clever at coining maxims, and perspicuous, and forcible, and admirably adapted for checking the uproarious."6</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1381"/>
          <p n="523">AGOR. Are not you, then, adapted for7 kicking the bab bling ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1381"/>
          <p n="524">DEll. No, by Jove, but I will compel all these to go a hunt ing, having left off decrees.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1381"/>
          <p n="525">AGOR. On these conditions, then, take 8 this here folding-stool, and a stout youth who shall carry it for you. And, if any where you choose, make a folding-stool of him.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1381"/>
          <p n="526">DEM. Happy man, now I am reinstated in my pristine con stitution !1</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1381"/>
          <p n="527">AGOR. You will say so, when I give you the thirty years' peace. Come hither, peace, quickly! [Enter a beautiful girl in the character of Peace.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1390"/>
          <p n="528">DEM. Much-honoured Jove, how beautiful! By the gods,2 is it permitted to enjoy her ? Pray, how did you get her ?</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1390"/>
          <p n="529">AGOR. Did not the Paphlagonian conceal her within, that you might not get her ? Now therefore I hand her over to you, to take with you into the country.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1390"/>
          <p n="530">DEM. But tell me what mischief you will do to the Paph lagonian, who did this.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1398"/>
          <p n="531">AGOR. No great matter, except3 that he shall exercise my trade. He shall have the exclusive sale of sausages at the gates, mixing dogs' with asses' flesh; and when drunk he shall slang with the harlots, and shall drink the dirty water4 from the baths.</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="1.1398"/>
          <p n="532">DEM. You have happily devised that of which he is worthy, to contend5 in bawling with the harlots and bath-men; and in return for this I invite you to the Prytaneum, and to the seat where that villain used to be. But take this here frog green coat and follow ! And let some one carry him out to exercise his trader that the foreigners whom he maltreated may ' behold him ! [Cleon is carried out, and exeunt omnes.]</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
