<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moschus, Idylls</title>
        <author>Moschus</author>
        <editor role="translator">J. Banks</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Generated by Diodorus alignment pipeline.</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>J. Banks (1878). Public domain.</bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)\.(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:p[@n='$2'])"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0035.tlg004.perseus-eng80">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="book" n="4">
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.1"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.11"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.19"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.27"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.36"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.47"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.56"/>
          <p n="1.0">My mother, why dost thou thus wound thy spirit, being sad beyond measure, and why is the former bloom no longer preserved on thy cheeks ? Why, I pray thee, art thou vexed so much? Is it in sooth because thine illustrious son suffers countless annoyances from 1 a man of no account, even as a lion from a fawn ? Alas me I why then have the immortal gods thus so far dishonoured me ? why then did my parents beget me to a fate thus adverse ? Ill-fated am I, who, since I have come to the bed of a faultless hero, whom I did honour indeed like my own eyes, ay, even now both worship and reverence him in my heart. But than him has no other of living beings been more ill-starred, or tasted so many cares in his own thoughts ; wretched man, who with the 2bow and arrows, which Apollo himself had provided for him, dire weapons either of one of the Fates, or of Erinnys, 3 slew his own children, and robbed them of their dear life, as he raged about his house, and it was full of slaughter. Them indeed I, wretched woman, beheld with mine own eyes, stricken by their father; and this bath befallen no other even in a dream: nor was I able to succour them, though they loudly called upon their mother; for re sistless evil was nigh. 4 And even as a bird laments over her nestlings as they perish, which while still in infancy a fierce snake devours amid the thick bushes, while she, kind mother, hovers over them shrieking very shrilly, yet is not able, I ween, to succour her children ; for in truth, she herself hath a great dread of coming nigher to the ruthless monster; so I, most wretched mother, wailing for mine own offspring, with frantic feet kept running to and fro through my house fre quently. Yes, and would that dying along with my children I too had lain low, having through my heart a poisonous arrow, thou, Artemis, mighty ruler to women, the gentler beings. So, when they had mourned for us, would our parents with their own hands have placed us on a common pile with many funeral honours; and having collected into one golden urn the bones of all, would have buried us, where we first were born. But now they indeed inhabit horse-breeding Thebes, plough ing the deep rich 5 clods of the Aonian plain ; but I at Tiryns, Juno's rocky city, wretched woman that I am, am ever in the same manner wounded at heart by many griefs; and there is present to me no rest from tears. But my husband indeed I behold with mine eyes only for a brief space in our house; for a work is prepared for him of many labours, at which he toils, as he roams over land and sea, yes, for he has within his breast a strong heart of iron or stone; 6 but thou meltest away like water, weeping both at night, and as many days as come from Jove. None other, however, of my kinsfolk can stand by and comfort me; for it is not a wall between houses that shuts them in; no! but all dwell right beyond the 7piny Isthmus: nor have I to whom, having looked, as an ill-fated woman, I could unfold my heart, except at least, 'tis true, my sister Pyrrha: but she herself, too, is grieving more about her husband, thy son, 8 Iphiclus; for most woeful children of all I deem that you have borne both to a god and a mortal man. Thus in sooth spake she : and 9the warmer tears poured the more down from her eyelids on her lovely bosom, as she called to mind her children, and her own parents afterwards. And in like manner Alcmena was 10bedewing her white cheeks with tears; and deeply while she groaned even from her heart, with wise words thus did she reply to her dear daughter-in-law: 11 Unhappy in thy children, why then, I pray, bath this fallen upon thy sharp thoughts ? how is it that thou wishest to disturb us both, by speaking of our unceasing sorrows ? for not now have they been wept for the first time. Are not the woes enough, in which we are involved as they arise, ever and anon, each second day? Yes, fond indeed of laments would be the man, who 12 would wish to add to the numbei of our woes. Cheer up then! such fate as this we have met by Heaven's behest; and in truth I see thee, dear child, la bouring under unabating griefs: yet I am ready to pardon your woe; for in fact I suppose 13 even of joy there is satiety. And I very exceedingly lament and pity thee, for that thou hast partaken of our dismal destiny, which also hangs heavily over our heads. For be Proserpine and richly-robed Demeter witnesses, (by whom with great hurt to himself would any of our foes Swear wilfully a false oath,) that in mine heart I love thee not a whit less, than if thou hadst come from out my womb, and wert to me in mine house a 14late-born daughter: nor do I imagine that, for thine own part, this at any rate altogether escapes thee. Wherefore say not ever,15 my young shoot, that I care not for thee, not even if I wail more con stantly than fair-haired Niobe: for 'tis no cause of blame for a mother to weep over an afflicted son: since for ten months did I labour, before even I first beheld him, whilst I had him in my womb, and he brought me near to 16 Hell's gate-keeper Pluto; so severe throes did I endure when about to travail hard with him. But now my son is gone to accomplish a fresh toil on a foreign land, nor know I, ill-starred woman, whether I shall welcome him again having returned hither, or not. And besides also a fearful dream has scared me during sweet sleep; and I fear exceedingly, having seen a hurtful vision, lest it betide something untoward to my chil dren. For my son, stout Hercules, seemed to me to hold in both his hands a well-made spade, with which he was delving, as one that had taken the work for hire, a dyke at the outskirt of some flourishing field, stripped, without cloak, and well girdled tunic: but when he had arrived at the end of all the work, labouring at the strong fence of a levelled plot for vines, in truth, he was about, having placed his 17shovel upon the projecting raised bank, to put on the garments, in which he had been clad before; when, on a sudden, above the deep trench there blazed up a fierce fire, and a vast flame was gathering round him: but he kept ever drawing back with swift feet, desiring to escape the destructive weapon of He phaestus ; and continually in front of his person he was brand ishing, as a 18 shield, his spade: and with his eyes he kept looking around hither and thither, lest in truth the hostile fire should burn him. High-souled Iphiclus, desiring, as me thought, to lend him help, tripped and fell upon the ground, ay, before he came up to him: nor could he raise himself erect again, but lay 19 still, like a feeble old man, whom even against his will joyless age has forced to fall; and there he lies fixedly on the ground, till some passer-by maintaining 20 ancient re verence for the hoary beard, has upraised him by the hand ; so on the ground had spear-brandishing Iphiclus 21 fallen. But as I beheld my two sons in sore distress, I did weep, till sound sleep at length was dispelled from mine eyes, and forth with bright dawn came. Such dreams, dear one, have thoroughly affrighted my mind all night long : 22 but may they all turn from our house upon Eurystheus ;</p>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.65"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.75"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.83"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.91"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.99"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.107"/>
          <milestone unit="section" n="4.118"/>
          <p n="1.1">and may my spirit become a prophet to him, nor fate accomplish otherwise aught else.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
